<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19255648</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2649423</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">005700032009</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Prediction Model</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Leaving out control groups: an internal contrast analysis of gene                    expression profiles in atrial fibrillation patients &#x02010; A systems                    biology approach to clinical categorization</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vanhoutte</surname><given-names>Kurt</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Asmundis</surname><given-names>Carlo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Francesconi</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Figys1</surname><given-names>Jurgen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steurs</surname><given-names>Griet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boussy</surname><given-names>Tim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>Markus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Massimo</surname><given-names>Lucio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paparella</surname><given-names>Gaetano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Van Caelenberg</surname><given-names>Kristien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chierchia</surname><given-names>Gian Battista</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkozy</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Y Terradellas</surname><given-names>Pedro Brugada</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zizi</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Faculty of Medicine and Pharmacy, Dept of Physiology,                    Vrije Universiteit Brussel</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Heart Rhythm Management Unit, Dept of Cardiology, UZ                    Brussel</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Kurt Vanhoutte:                        <email>kurt.vanhoutte@vub.ac.be</email>Phone: 322 477 44 31;                    Fax: 322 477 45 68</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2009 Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open-access article, which permits unrestricted use, distribution,                        and reproduction in any medium, for non-commercial purposes, provided the                        original author and source are credited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p> Atrial fibrillation (AF) is a frequent chronic dysrythmia with an incidence that                    increases with age (&#x0003e;40). Because of its medical and socio-economic                    impacts it is expected to become an increasing burden on most health care                    systems. AF is a multi-factorial disease for which the identification of                    subtypes is warranted. Novel approaches based on the broad concepts of systems                    biology may overcome the blurred notion of normal and pathological phenotype,                    which is inherent to high throughput molecular arrays analysis. Here we apply an                    internal contrast algorithm on AF patient data with an analytical focus on                    potential entry pathways into the disease. We used a RMA (Robust Multichip                    Average) normalized Affymetrix micro-array data set from 10 AF patients                    (geo_accession #GSE2240). Four series of probes were selected based on                    physiopathogenic links with AF entryways: apoptosis (remodeling), MAP kinase                    (cell remodeling), OXPHOS (ability to sustain hemodynamic workload) and                    glycolysis (ischemia). Annotated probe lists were polled with Bioconductor                    packages in R (version 2.7.1). Genetic profile contrasts were analysed with                    hierarchical clustering and principal component analysis. The analysis revealed                    distinct patient groups for all probe sets. A substantial part (54%                    till 67%) of the variance is explained in the first 2 principal                    components. Genes in PC1/2 with high discriminatory value were selected and                    analyzed in detail. We aim for reliable molecular stratification of AF. We show                    that stratification is possible based on physiologically relevant gene sets.                    Genes with high contrast value are likely to give pathophysiological insight                    into permanent AF subtypes.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>atrial fibrillation</kwd><kwd>gene expression</kwd><kwd>Robust Multichip Average</kwd><kwd>genetic profile</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is a frequent chronic dysrythmia with an incidence that                increases with age (&#x0003e;40) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>]. Due to its medical and socio-economic impacts and, of the                aging European/ Western /Japanese populations, it is projected to become an                increasing burden on most health care systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>]. Besides the obvious medical emergencies, the                costs include the chronic corrective therapies (pacemakers, surgical ablations,                etc.), the severe complications (thromboembolisms, strokes e.a., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]) and various other                hospitalisation costs. Atrial fibrillation is a multi-factorial disease for which                the identification of subtypes - molecular categories - will be both useful and                needed to provide better and cost-effective therapies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>] and to improve the quality of                future clinical studies.</p><p>With the advent of high-throughput molecular analyses, the classical paradigm of a                failing gene corresponding to an altered/pathological phenotype is being lost. It is                widely accepted that an altered genotype can lead to a healthy phenotype via                numerous compensation mechanisms, but it is becoming also apparent - and much less                known - that even healthy genotypes could lead to defective/pathological phenotypes.                Indeed a given cell phenotype could be considered as a state more akin to the orbit                of a chaotic strange attractor than a definitive frozen combination of gene                expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. There                seem to exist many ways to dissociate genotypes from phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>], hence the conceptual                impossibility of a <italic>bona fide</italic> control group. In this context of a                blur between the notions of normal and pathological phenotypes, novel analytical                approaches are warranted based on the broad concepts of system biology                    [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>].</p><p>To provide evidence of robust/reliable stratification based on molecular profiles is                one of the biggest challenges in molecular medicine. Exploratory tools from                multivariate statistics and data mining offer solutions, but often miss a biological                and physiological focus, and neglect the dynamic reality of the biological system.                As part of a series of feasibility studies, we are using an internal contrast                analysis - i.e without comparison with a control population - of an existing                micro-array data-set from chronic AF patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>] in which up-regulation of metabolism was found                to be a key marker. Prior to their chronic stage where tissue remodelling acts as a                positive feedback for the phenotype, AF patients enter this pathology either via                ischemia-related, work-load and hypertension, and/or degenerative problems, each of                which can be potentially traced at a molecular level.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methodology</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Datasets</title><p>We used the RMA (Robust Multichip Average, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>]) normalized gene expression micro-array data                    set for 4 series of probes linked to either apoptosis, glycolysis, OXPHOS and                    MAP kinase pathway. Those probe sets were selected because of their potential                    physiopathogenic links with the entryways toward AF: apoptosis (remodeling), MAP                    kinase (cell and tissular differentiation), OXPHOS (ability to sustain workload                    including high tensions), glycolysis (ischemic or pre-ischemic situations). The                    data were obtained from 10 patient samples in an Affymetrix -set (geo_accession                    #GSE2240).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Gene selection</title><p>Bioconductor, version 2.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>] and R, version 2.7.1 (packages: hgu133b, KEGG, annotate,                    cluster) provided the tools to select functional category-related genes that are                    prevalent in the KEGG database (function hgu133bPATH2PROBE).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Contrast analysis</title><p>Overall similarity in genetic profiles between patients was apparent from the                    dendrograms after hierarchical clustering (HC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>] based on the                    &#x0201c;dissimilarity&#x0201d; correlation matrix. To select genes with                    high contrast value between all patients a principal component analysis (PCA)                        [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>] was                    done. Gene probes were selected based on the loadings vector of the first and                    second principal component. Selected genes were further classified according to                    absolute univariate expression levels. We found contrast mostly interpretable                    for genes with (i.) low variance in between-probe (ii.) high difference between                    patient groups and (iii.) high deviation from the over-all median patient value                    for a given gene.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Micro-array analysis is a high-throughput technique, which allows probing the                expression levels of thousands of genes simultaneously. Though at first sight arrays                provide a powerful tool, conclusions and robustness of the technique are still                heavily debated and solutions are presented to address standardization of                experimental conditions, calculation of proper sample size, pre-processing of data                and statistical inference of gene signals, to name a few. Systems biology provides a                useful framework, mainly addressing the &#x0201c;dynamics&#x0201d; and the                concepts of normality, and of modularity in biological networks. In                supra-ventricular arrhythmia, time-dependent changes for functional groups of genes                were recently investigated in canine models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>].</p><p>Barth and colleagues found that atrial tissue acquires ventricular characteristics,                up-regulation of metabolic genes was also apparent in chronic AF patients. The                multi-factorial pathophysiological patterns may come more apparent from a                patient-centric viewpoint. Therefore we applied contrast analysis within the AF                patient group, aiming at finding the genes for which divergence were maximal, and                which contributed the most to the variations in the expression signals.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, HC and PCA of AF patients based on                the apoptotic gene set is illustrated. Based on gene expression profiles,                multivariate analysis (HC and PCA) of patients revealed distinct clustering patterns                of the patients in all 4 datasets. The most striking observation is the consistent                grouping of 3 patients (patient id: 1, 2, 3) for the 4 datasets, clearly separated                from the rest, and the isolation of one patient (patient id: 10), bearing little                resemblance to all of the other AF patients. The analysis also revealed high                similarity of another group (id: 5, 6, 9) in all datasets.</p><p>For all datasets a substantial proportion of the variance (54% till                67%) in the dataset is captured in the first 2 principal components                (cumulative proportion for apoptosis: 0.53 0.67, oxphos: 0.51 0.63, glycolysis: 0.31                0.54, MAPK: 0.42 0.67). Gene probes with high discriminatory value were selected                based on high loadings in PC1/2, either positive (+) or negative (-)                (see Table 1 under <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary                    material</xref>). These probes are likely to be the most relevant in terms of                the between-patient contrast. It should be noted that genes are often mapped to                multiple probesets. Affymetrix arrays such as the hgu133b are designed to target the                600 bp at the 3' end of the transcript, not the start of the transcript. Therefore                many-to-one mappings between probesets and genes are often due to alternative                splicing, use of alternative poly (A) sites, or annotation errors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. This could add to the variations, a point we will                discuss later.</p><p>We are especially interested in genes for which the expression range for all probes                (i.e. with identical annotation), clearly differs among patients, and thus provide                unambiguous discrimination between those patients. To identify such genes, we also                explored the univariate expression levels of all probes. Doing so, we could identify                3 types of genes. The genes for which all probe levels were markedly different                between patients and displayed nearly no variance within a single patient, those                were defined as Class I, and are reliable signals. The genes, for which the                intra-patient variance of the expression levels between their various probes was                large, were identified as Class II. For those, the high contrast was more likely due                to the spread response instead of <italic>bona fide</italic> differences in                expression levels; hence these are not correct signals. Then we also identified                genes for which both a marked difference in levels between different patients could                be recorded, and at the same time a large intra-patient variance for the response of                gene expression for the various probes, those were termed Class III and could be                considered acceptable signals. Hence we evidence that we could identify and classify                36 different genes, which are reliable markers and could be used to categorize the                patients. The split per pathological entryway was: for MAPK (8 class I, 0 class II,                3 class III), for glycolysis (7, 0, 4), for OXPHOS (7,1,1) and for apoptosis (4, 2,                2).</p><p>The Class II &#x02013; i.e. the non-reliable and/or irrelevant markers &#x02013; were GAPDH (glucose                phosphate dehydrogenase), Acetyl-coA synthase 1 (whereas Acetyl-coA synthase 2 fell                into class I), ADHFE (alcohol dehydrogenase), ENO&#x003b2;3 (muscular isoform of                    &#x003b2;<sup>&#x002dc;</sup>enolase), PPP3R (protein phosphatase 3                regulatory subunit &#x003b1;), CYC (cytochrome C). Surprisingly these are all                metabolic markers.</p><p>A closer look at Class I markers reveals interesting facts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, PCA lower inset for an example). For instance, in 3                patients (id:1,2,3), MAP3K16 levels - an apoptotic effector involved in the                re-organization of actin filaments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>] - are up-regulated and, this occurs in parallel with the                marked up-regulation of the SOS1 gene - a well known guanine nucleotide exchange                protein which links mitogen- activated kinase and cytoskeletal elements like actin.                Hence these patients differ from all the others in that they are re-modelling their                heart tissue. In those 3 patients, PPP3CA (the catalytic subunit of protein                phosphatase A), (NDUFFS8) NADH-coQ reductase, and ubiquinol-cytochrome C reductase                core protein II (UQCRC2) are also up-regulated. Those would reflect an enhanced                electron transport chain activity. It is worth noticing that dehydrolipoamide                dehydrogenase (DLD), a flavoprotein linked to electron transport and the Krebs cycle                is also up-regulated. It could thus be concluded that these 3 patients are markedly                different from a metabolic standpoint. The CFLAR (caspase 8 FADD-like apoptosis                regulator and CASP8 (caspase 8 itself) are respectively up- and down regulated.                CFLAR is transducing external triggering of apoptosis; this is coupled with the fact                that effector caspases are not up-regulated and the fact that XIAP - a                post-mitochondrial inhibitor of apoptosis - is normal. In contrast within 3 other                patients (id: 5,6,8), XIAP is down-regulated, those latter patients are hence more                apoptotic and less remodelling than the 3 former ones. The patients (id: 4, 5, 6)                had marked increases in FG18 - a fibroblast growth factor isoform, important for                cell proliferation and inflammation, and whose overexpression can lead to                abnormalities - whereas patients (id: 1,2,3) had decreases. Once more, this is                consistent with those 2 groups of patients being functionally very different.                Another and potentially important marker distinguishing those two groups is the AKT3                gene, a protein kinase B isoform with some oncogenic activity but selectively                expressed in the heart [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. It promotes cell growth and is known to have some                cardioprotective effect during re-modelling, but a continuous overexpression would                lead to dysfunctional maladaptive hypertrophy. Patients (id: 1, 2, 3) are                up-regulated whereas patients (id:4,5,6) are down-regulated. The first group is                hence cardio-protected vs. the second, but could also become more dysfunctional on                the long term. At any rate AKT3 is likely to be an important follow-up marker. Two                isoforms of aldolase (ALDOA and ALDOB, a glycolytic enzyme) showed an interesting                pattern: all patients who were up for ALDOA were down for ALDOB and conversely, with                the exception of 2 of the 10 patients (id: 1, 5). Noteworthy patient 10 was markedly                different from all the other for most of the 36 markers we studied.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>We aim for a reliable patient stratification based on molecular profiles without the                use of a &#x0201c;normal&#x0201d; group. We showed that by contrast                analysis; we could identify patient clusters and individual markers. By using                objective criteria, those markers could be further appraised for their biological                reliability. Even with a small cohort (10 AF patients in total), we could identify                at least 2 markedly different sub-populations, which differed based on potential                entryway into the disease. One group (id: 1,2,3) differs metabolically and                functionally from another. While both groups have some apoptotic markers, their                molecular context is highly different as the first had more MAP-kinase activation                (hypertrophy) and effector caspases were less controlled in the second. We could                also identify an interesting prognostic follow-up marker. However we have to                highlight several caveats. There is a high variance between probes for one gene and                hence quality control is warranted. This variance can arise from actual differences                (alternate splices,&#x02026;), problems on the DNA CHIP or in annotation. In our feasibility                study, we face clear limitations, e.g. the number of patients is small and not all                apoptosis genes are included (e.g. no VDAC's). However we showed that                stratification is possible based on physiologically relevant gene sets. Genes with                high contrast value in PCA are likely to give pathophysiological insight into                &#x0201c;permanent&#x0201d; AF subtypes. It is our interest to extend this                exploratory analysis with classification approaches using independent training and                validation data sets. In a future programme we also like to contrast dynamic changes                in expression patterns with a focus on AF entry point-related molecular signatures                in a reductionist animal model.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><caption><title>Data 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="97320630003275S1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x21d6140N0x2265910" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><source>Heart Rhythm</source><year>2007</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>S1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17336876</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Value Health</source><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18657103</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Cardiovasc Hematol Disord Drug Targets</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>233</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17378769</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Sherif</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Baroudi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>224</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15028054</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://home.comcast.net/~reillyjones/order.html">                            http://home.comcast.net/~reillyjones/order.html</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suel</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>440</volume><fpage>545</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16554821</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>295</volume><fpage>1678</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11872832</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Circ Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>1022</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817885</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolstad</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Statistics for Biology and Health</source><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>13</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>R80</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15461798</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sekhon.berkeley.edu/stats/html/hclust.html">                            http://sekhon.berkeley.edu/stats/html/hclust.html</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sekhon.berkeley.edu/stats/html/princomp.html">                            http://sekhon.berkeley.edu/stats/html/princomp.html</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Circ Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>425</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17234964</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://stat.ethz.ch/pipermail/bioconductor/2008-July/023305.html">                        https://stat.ethz.ch/pipermail/bioconductor/2008-July/023305.html</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stalteri</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17224057</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zihni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>7317</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407310</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taniyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J Mol Cell Cardiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>375</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15698844</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Analysis of apoptosis gene set. HC (a) of AF patients shows 2 distinct                        clusters of patients. PCA analysis (b) corroborates clear differentiation of                        patient AF1-2-3 (dashed group). Inset: example of univariate expression                        levels within patients of CFLAR (CASP8 and FADD-like apoptosis regulator), a                        gene with highest loadings on PC1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="97320630003275F1"/></fig></floats-wrap></article>