<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">DNA Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dnares</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">dnares</journal-id><journal-title>DNA Research: An International Journal for Rapid Publication of Reports on Genes and Genomes</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1340-2838</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-1663</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2650631</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsn003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dsn003</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">Editorial</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Editorial</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oishi</surname><given-names>Michio</given-names></name><role>Editor-in-Chief</role></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2008. Kazusa DNA Research Institute</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons"><p>The online version of this article has been published under an open access model. Users are entitled to use, reproduce, disseminate, or display the open access version of this article for non-commercial purposes provided that: the original authorship is properly and fully attributed; the Journal and Oxford University Press are attributed as the original place of publication with the correct citation details given; if an article is subsequently reproduced or disseminated not in its entirety but only in part or as a derivative work this must be clearly indicated. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org</p></license></article-meta></front><body><p><italic>DNA Research</italic> was first published in 1994, at a time when our understanding of the genomic structure of various organisms was just starting to unfold. In fact, the very first issue of <italic>DNA Research</italic> published a report of genome analysis of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>. The issue also included a paper on the sequence analysis of a collection of human cDNAs. We had set the focus of our journal on this newly emerging field of research: our primary objective was to provide readers with hard-core genomic and related data from a variety of biological systems, hoping that they could be fully explored and the biological functions encoded therein efficiently exploited. Since then, papers of this category have constituted a major part, though not all, of the papers published in <italic>DNA Research</italic>, a trend that continues through to today. We believe that our journal has not only satisfied the original goals of its publication, but has exceeded our expectations, as evidenced by the fact that quite a large number of highly cited papers on genomic and other related biological resources have appeared in <italic>DNA Research</italic> (2006 Impact Factor was 3.066).</p><p>In the last decade, huge amounts of genomic sequence data have been gathered/deposited and stored in various sequence databases. Technologies allowing the accumulation and interpretation of data, particularly those involving computer software, have seen great advances. Some might say that the data accumulated to date are sufficient enough to cover every conceivable area of research as far as genomics is concerned. We believe, however, that there are still several fields of research where the current sequence data cannot be fully exploited and more pertinent information is urgently needed. One such area is of comparative studies of accumulated genomic data. For example, it is well known that the functions of a majority of the genes of many organisms, predicted from sequence data, cannot be clearly defined because similar sequences with known functions cannot be found in the databases. We therefore feel strongly that the genomic analysis of many more organisms is still needed and that the role of our journal to promote publication of genomic data has not been diminished.</p><p>At the editorial board of <italic>DNA Research</italic>, we feel it is equally important to promote publication of papers concerning newly developing technologies for more advanced analysis of genomic data from various perspectives. Furthermore, we would like to encourage researchers to submit papers exploring alternative approaches in genomics, which may complement some of the more conventional genome analyses of individual organisms. Metagenomic analysis of a mixed population of organisms in various habitats is one example of such an approach. We envision and sincerely hope that this type of research will continue in years to come, and will be very much welcome to our journal.</p><p>In January 2006, Oxford University Press became the publisher of <italic>DNA Research</italic>. Our journal is currently one of the &#x02018;open access&#x02019; journals in which all published papers are freely accessible by readers and we ask the submitting authors of papers to pay a charge for its publication. At the same time, an online submission/administration system (Scholar One) was introduced to speed up and to make transparent the process of submission, editorial handling, and publication of papers.</p><p>In 2008, in order to attract and encourage more people to read <italic>DNA Research</italic> and to submit papers of superior quality, we introduced the following measures:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Invitation of editors from foreign countries to the editorial board.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Introduction of a new section &#x02018;Current Status and Perspectives&#x02019; which deals with reviews on specific topics.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Broadening of the scope of the journal in response to the expansion as well as fusion of genomics with other research fields.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Updating of the design of the journal's cover.</p></list-item></list>We sincerely hope that these measures will be accepted favorably by the scientific community of DNA/genome research and related disciplines as we continue our service into the future with our determination to publish manuscripts ever more rapidly.</p></body></article>