<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chin Med</journal-id><journal-title>Chinese Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1749-8546</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19038060</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2631514</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1749-8546-3-15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1749-8546-3-15</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>and some other medicinal plants commonly used in South-East Asia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Lai Wah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>phaclw@nus.edu.sg</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheah</surname><given-names>Emily LC</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>emily_lc_cheah@nus.edu.sg</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>Constance LL</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>constancesaw@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>Wanyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>u0407528@nus.edu.sg</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heng</surname><given-names>Paul WS</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>phapaulh@nus.edu.sg</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Pharmacy, Faculty of Science, National University of Singapore, 18 Science Drive 4, Singapore 117543</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Center for Cancer Prevention Research, Department of Pharmaceutics, Ernest Mario School of Pharmacy, Rutgers, State University of New Jersey, 160 Frelinghuysen Road, Piscataway, New Jersey 08854, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cmjournal.org/content/3/1/15"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>2</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Chan et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chan et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Chan               Wah               Lai                              phaclw@nus.edu.sg            </dc:author><dc:title>            Antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis and some other medicinal plants commonly used in South-East Asia         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Chinese Medicine 3(1): 15-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1749-8546(2008)3:1&#x0003c;15&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1749-8546</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Eight medicinal plants were tested for their antimicrobial and antioxidant activities. Different extraction methods were also tested for their effects on the bioactivities of the medicinal plants.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Eight plants, namely <italic>Herba Polygonis Hydropiperis </italic>(<italic>Laliaocao</italic>), <italic>Folium Murraya Koenigii </italic>(<italic>Jialiye</italic>), <italic>Rhizoma Arachis Hypogea </italic>(<italic>Huashenggen</italic>), <italic>Herba Houttuyniae </italic>(<italic>Yuxingcao</italic>), <italic>Epipremnum pinnatum </italic>(<italic>Pashulong</italic>), <italic>Rhizoma Typhonium Flagelliforme </italic>(<italic>Laoshuyu</italic>), <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>(<italic>Houpo</italic>) and <italic>Rhizoma Imperatae </italic>(<italic>Baimaogen</italic>) were investigated for their potential antimicrobial and antioxidant properties.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Extracts of <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>had the strongest activities against <italic>M. Smegmatis</italic>, <italic>C. albicans</italic>, <italic>B. subtilis </italic>and <italic>S. aureus</italic>. Boiled extracts of <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis</italic>, <italic>Folium Murraya Koenigii, Herba Polygonis Hydropiperis </italic>and <italic>Herba Houttuyniae </italic>demonstrated greater antioxidant activities than other tested medicinal plants.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Among the eight tested medicinal plants, <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>showed the highest antimicrobial and antioxidant activities. Different methods of extraction yield different spectra of bioactivities.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Some medicinal plants used in traditional Chinese medicine are effective in treating various ailments caused by bacterial and oxidative stress. As new drug-resistant bacteria strains emerge, especially methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus </italic>and vancomycin-resistant enterococci, new drugs or adjuvants have been actively searched in medicinal plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. New antioxidants such as plant phenolics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] are sought for general health maintenance, anti-aging and chemoprevention.</p><p>Eight medicinal plants, namely <italic>Herba Polygonis Hydropiperis </italic>(<italic>Laliaocao</italic>), <italic>Folium Murraya Koenigii </italic>(<italic>Jialiye</italic>), <italic>Rhizoma Arachis Hypogea </italic>(<italic>Huashenggen</italic>), <italic>Herba Houttuyniae </italic>(<italic>Yuxingcao</italic>), <italic>Epipremnum pinnatum </italic>(<italic>Pashulong</italic>), <italic>Rhizoma Typhonium Flagelliforme </italic>(<italic>Laoshuyu</italic>), <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>(<italic>Houpo</italic>) and <italic>Rhizoma Imperatae </italic>(<italic>Baimaogen</italic>) were tested for their potential antimicrobial and antioxidant properties. They have been long been used in treating of various infectious diseases, e.g. skin/wound infections, fever, cough and digestive ailments (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Ethnomedicinal uses and properties of the selected plants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Latin pharmaceutical name/Plant scientific name/Family/Voucher specimen no</bold>.</td><td align="left"><bold>Vernacular/pinyin names</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Ethnomedicinal uses</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Properties</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Herba Polygonis Hydropiperis/Persicaria hydropiper </italic>(L.)<sup>a </sup>Spach/Polygonaceae/001-CS0807</td><td align="left">Laksa plant/<italic>Laliaocao</italic></td><td align="left">Used as a condiment. Also employed as a stomachic and aphrodisiac. Externally, the crushed leaves or juice are used to treat skin conditions such as ringworms, scabies, boils, abscesses, carbuncles, ulcers or bites of snakes, dogs or insects</td><td align="left">Antioxidant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Folium Murraya Koenigii/Murraya koenigii Spreng./</italic>Rutaceae/002-CS0807</td><td align="left">Curry leaves/<italic>Jialiye</italic></td><td align="left">Used as a condiment. Treatment of piles, inflammation, itching, fresh cuts, dysentery, vomiting, burses and dropsy</td><td align="left">Reducing halitosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], antioxidant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], antimicrobial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], antifungal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], antihyperglycemic and antihyperlipidemic properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rhizoma Arachis Hypogea/Arachis hypogaea <italic>L./Leguminosae/003-CS0807</italic></td><td align="left">Groundnut/<italic>Huashenggen</italic></td><td align="left">Treatment of insomnia and strengthening of bones</td><td align="left">Antifibrinolytic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Herba Houttuyniae/Houttuynia cordata </italic>Thunb./Saururaceae/004-CS0807</td><td align="left">Chinese houttuynia or chameleon plant/<italic>Yuxingcao</italic></td><td align="left">Detoxification, treatment of infection, removing toxic heat, promoting drainage of pus and urination</td><td align="left">Anti-Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Prevention of urinary infection, modulation of neutrophils and monocytes, inhibition of respiratory bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Anti-inflammatory activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Virucidal effects on herpes simplex virus type 1 and 2, influenza virus, and human immunodeficiency virus type 1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Epipremnum pinnatum </italic>(L.) Engl./Araceae/005-CS0807</td><td align="left">Dragon tail/<italic>Pashulong</italic></td><td align="left">Detoxification, removes toxic heat, tendonitis, fractures, burns, carbuncles, sores, redness</td><td align="left">Cytotoxicity against cancers cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], immuno-modulating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Rhizoma Typhonium Flagelliforme/Typhonium flagelliforme </italic>(Lodd.) Blume/006-CS0807</td><td align="left">Rodent tuber/<italic>Laoshuyu</italic></td><td align="left">Treatment of cough, asthma, nausea and cancers</td><td align="left">Relieving cough, eliminating phlegm, asthmatic, analgesia, anti-inflammation, sedation and cytotoxic activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis/Magnolia biloba </italic>(Rehder &#x00026; E. H. Wilson) Cheng/Magnoliaceae/007-CS0807</td><td align="left">Magnolia/<italic>Houpo</italic></td><td align="left">A tonic to improve general well-being, also used to treat cough, diarrhea, allergic rhinitis and phlegm</td><td align="left">Alleviateing menopausal symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], brochial asthma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], active against <italic>Propionibacterium acnes </italic>and <italic>Propionibacterium granulosum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], antimicrobial and cytotoxic activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Rhizoma Imperatae/Imperata cylidrica </italic>(L.) Beeuv. var. <italic>major </italic>(Nees) C.E. Hubb/Gramineae/008-CS0807</td><td align="left">Lalang/<italic>Baimaogen</italic></td><td align="left">Wound-healing, diuretic, anti-inflammatory and antipyretic agents</td><td align="left">Neuroprotective, immunostimulating effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup><italic>Persicaria hydropiper </italic>(L.) is synonymous with <italic>Polygonum hydropiper (L.). Persicaria hydropiper </italic>(L.) and <italic>Persicaria odoratum </italic>(L.) are commonly used interchangeably in literature while they are two distinct species. Efforts were made to identify the species of laksa plants used in the study. The plant was probably <italic>Persicaria hydropiper </italic>(L.). A specimen of the plant has been deposited in the National University of Singapore Herbarium for future reference.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The traditional method for Chinese medicine preparation is to boil the medicinal plants in water for 20 minutes to one hour. The present study aims to test the effectiveness of traditional herb preparation methods for antimicrobial and antioxidant treatments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title><sec><title>Selection of plants</title><p>The rationales behind the selection of these eight plants are as follows. (1) They are commonly used in Asia. (2) They have long been used as medicinal plants. (3) They are abundant in the market. (4) Their daily applications have not been documented (except <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis</italic> which served as a positive control for its antimicrobial activity against <italic>S. aureus</italic>). The fresh juices of some of the plants were traditionally used as fresh poultices to treat some skin conditions (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Plant materials</title><p><italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>from Zhejiang, China was purchased from WHL Ginseng &#x00026; Herbs (Singapore), while all other plants were purchased from a herbal vendor in Outram Park wet market in Singapore. <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>and <italic>Rhizoma Imperatae </italic>were authenticated by the Institute of Medicinal Plant Development of the Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences (China), while the rest were authenticated by the Herbarium of the Singapore Botanic Gardens (Singapore). The voucher specimens for each plant were preserved under the reference number 001-CS0807 to 008-CS0807 at the Herbarium of the National University of Singapore, Raffles Museum of Biodiversity Research and the Department of Biological Sciences of the National University of Singapore (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Chemicals</title><p>2,2-diphenyl-1-picryl-hydrazyl (DPPH), magnolol, honokiol (99.9%) and quercetin were purchased from Sigma Aldrich (USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Solvents</title><p>Absolute ethanol (99.9%, Far East Distiller, Singapore) was diluted with water to produce 80% (v/v) solution of ethanol for extraction. De-ionized water was used for extraction (by boiling and maceration), reconstitution and dilution where appropriate. Methanol (analytical grade, Tedia, USA) was used for reconstitution and dilution in the DPPH assay.</p></sec><sec><title>Microorganisms, growth media and standard antibiotic discs</title><p>Four strains of bacteria and one strain of yeast were used for antimicrobial tests. The test bacteria included Gram-positive <italic>Staphylococcus aureus </italic>(ATCC 6538P) and <italic>Bacillus subtilis </italic>(ATCC 6633), Gram-negative <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa </italic>(ATCC 9027) and acid-fast <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis </italic>(ATCC 14468). <italic>Candida albicans </italic>(ATCC 2091) was used as a representative of yeast. All microorganisms were purchased in the form of inoculation loops from Oxoid (UK). Nutrient broth with agar and Sabouraud dextrose agar (Acumedia, USA) were used for the cultivation of bacteria and yeast respectively. Mueller Hinton agar (France) was used in antimicrobial screening.</p><p>Standard antibiotic discs (diameter 6 mm) used in this study were: methicillin 5 &#x003bc;g, tetracycline 30 &#x003bc;g, carbenicillin 100 &#x003bc;g and streptomycin 10 &#x003bc;g. In our preliminary studies, these antibiotics were found to be active against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, Bacillus subtilis, Pseudomonas aeruginosa </italic>and <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis </italic>respectively. All standard antibiotic discs were purchased from Oxoid (UK). Disc containing chlorhexidine which was active against <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, were prepared by loading dry sterile filter paper discs (Whatman No. 54, diameter 5.5 mm) with chlorhexidine solution to give a total weight of approximately 100 &#x003bc;g of chlorhexidine per disc. The impregnated discs were dried overnight at 40&#x000b0;C and stored (less than five days) in a desiccator until use.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of plant materials prior to extraction</title><p>The fresh plants were kept in a refrigerator for no longer than three days prior to extraction. <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>was dried in a cool, dark room (room temperature 19&#x000b0;C, relative humidity 60%) and subsequently stored in a drum with silica gel desiccants until use. Before extraction, the plants were cut into 1 cm pieces with pruning scissors, except <italic>Rhizoma Imperatae </italic>and <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>which were milled into fine powder using a pulverizer mill (Christy &#x00026; Norris, UK). Triplicate preparations of each sample were carried out.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Extraction and preparation of crude extracts</title><sec><title>Boiling, maceration and blending</title><p>Two and a half grams of <italic>Folium Murraya Koenigii</italic>, <italic>Typhonium flagelliforme </italic>aerial parts and 5 g of the other plant materials, were each extracted with 200 ml of water or ethanol. Three extraction methods were employed: (1) boiling in water for 1 hour, (2) maceration for 24 hours in water or (3) 80% (v/v) ethanol at room temperature. <italic>Herba Houttuyniae </italic>was extracted using an additional extraction method that involved boiling in water for 20 minutes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. Additional extraction experiments were carried out on aqueous plant extracts that showed promising antimicrobial activities. Boiling time was limited to 20 minutes to minimize heat exposure. Blending-maceration was used as a non-heat extraction method with cell rupture mechanism. Blending was performed with a laboratory blender (Waring Commercial, USA) for one minute, followed by a pause and then blending for an additional minute. Maceration in de-ionized water for one hour was performed. Coarse particles were removed using Whatman No. 1 filter paper (Whatman International, UK) before evaporation.</p></sec><sec><title>Extraction of fresh juices</title><p>Fresh juices of <italic>Herba Houttuyniae</italic>, <italic>Epipremnum pinnatum </italic>stem and <italic>Typhonium flagelliforme </italic>aerial parts and rhizomes were prepared in a mortar, wrapped in linen cloth and squeezed for the juices. Coarse particles were removed using Whatman No. 1 filter paper before evaporation.</p></sec><sec><title>Evaporation of extracts</title><p>The plant extracts were evaporated to dryness under reduced pressure at 40&#x000b0;C for ethanol extracts and 60&#x000b0;C for water extracts and fresh juices in a rotary evaporator (Model N1000, Eyela, Japan). The solid content of the extract was weighed. The dried extracts were stored in a freezer at -20&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Characterization of plant extracts</title><p>The crude and dried extracts were characterized by their odor, appearance and texture. The weights of the dried extracts were also determined.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Determination of antimicrobial activities</title><sec><title>Preparation of extract- and standard-loaded discs</title><p>Filter paper discs (Grade 54, diameter 5.5 mm, Whatman International, UK) were autoclaved at 121&#x000b0;C for 20 minutes and oven-dried at 40&#x000b0;C overnight. Plant extracts were diluted with the same extraction solvent to 50 &#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l. Each diluted solution (2 &#x003bc;l, equivalent to 100 &#x003bc;g of the dried extract) was loaded on a sterile filter paper disc. All impregnated discs were dried in sterile glass Petri dishes placed in an oven at 40&#x000b0;C overnight. The discs were then allowed to condition to room temperature before use in the antimicrobial test. Solutions in methanol (5 &#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l) were prepared for magnolol and honokiol respectively and a 1:1 solution of the two compounds (2.5 &#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l) was made. 2 &#x003bc;l of the honokiol, magnolol or 1:1 solutions were loaded onto paper discs which were then left to air-dry. These standard-loaded discs were freshly prepared before the antimicrobial screening experiments.</p></sec><sec><title>Screening of antimicrobial activities of plant extracts</title><p>The antimicrobial activities of the extracts were determined by the Kirby-Bauer agar diffusion method according to NCCLS standards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Sterilized molten agar (20 ml) was dispensed to each sterile disposable Petri dish (diameter 9 cm) and allowed to solidify. Mueller Hinton agar was used for bacteria and Sabouraud dextrose agar for yeast. Microbial suspension (200 &#x003bc;l) containing approximately 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>CFU was spread evenly onto the surface of the solidified medium. The plates were allowed to dry for 15 minutes before the test discs were placed at equidistance from each other. Each plate consisted of one standard antibiotic disc and three other discs impregnated with various extracts.</p><p>After standing for 30 minutes, the Petri dishes were incubated in an inverted position at 37&#x000b0;C for 18 to 24 hours for bacteria and 24&#x000b0;C for 48 to 72 hours for yeasts. The diameters of the zone of inhibition (ZIH), defined by the clear area devoid of growth, was measured twice. The antimicrobial activities were determined by the ratio of the ZIH diameters of the extracts to that of the standard antibiotic in the same Petri dish, whereby a higher ratio indicates a more potent extract.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of antioxidant activity</title><p>Antioxidant activities of the extracts were determined with 2,2-diphenyl-1-picryl-hydrazyl (DPPH) assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. The free radical, DPPH, served as the model oxidizing agent to be reduced by the antioxidant present in the extracts. The amount of dried extract subject to DPPH assay was 100 &#x003bc;g, the same amount used for antimicrobial screening. The dried extract was dissolved in 1.56 ml of methanol and mixed with 40 &#x003bc;l of 2 mM DPPH dissolved in methanol to make up a total volume of 1.6 ml in each polyethylene microfuge tubes. The final solution was allowed to react in dim light for 15 minutes. It was then centrifuged (4000 rpm; 1165 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>, Kubota 2100 Centrifuge, Japan) for five minutes. The absorbance of the supernatant was measured at 517 nm with a UV spectrophotometer (Genesys 10 UV, ThermoSprectronic, USA). The tests were carried out in triplicates. The DPPH radical scavenging activity was calculated with the following formula:</p><p><disp-formula>DPPH radical scavenging activity (%) = [A<sub>0</sub>-(A<sub>1</sub>-A<sub>S</sub>)]/A<sub>0 </sub>&#x000d7; 100</disp-formula></p><p>Where A<sub>0 </sub>is the absorbance of the control solution containing only DPPH after incubation; A<sub>1 </sub>is the absorbance in the presence of plant extract in DPPH solution after incubation; and A<sub>s </sub>is the absorbance of sample extract solution without DPPH for baseline correction arising from unequal color of the sample solutions (optical blank for A<sub>1</sub>).</p></sec><sec><title>Data and statistical analysis</title><p>Data are expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD) of triplicates. Two-way ANOVA was used to analyze the effect of different plant materials and extraction methods on the extraction yields and DPPH radical scavenging activity while one-way ANOVA was performed to determine the effect of streptomycin, honokiol, magnolol and honokiol-magnolol combination on <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>. Both tests employed Bonferroni <italic>post hoc </italic>analysis. Student's t-test was used to compare antimicrobial activity of the extracts against the standard antibiotic. All statistical analyses were conducted with SPSS software (v.12, SPSS, USA) at a significance level of 0.05.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Physical characterization of herbal extracts</title><sec><title>Extraction yields</title><p>The extraction yields obtained from different extraction methods were analyzed with two-way ANOVA and Bonferroni <italic>post hoc </italic>analysis. Among the 11 experimental groups, <italic>Rhizoma Imperatae </italic>produced the highest yields (<italic>P </italic>= 0.001) regardless of extraction methods, followed by <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). These two dry herbs were processed through comminution producing fine powder prior to extraction. The reduced particle size decreases the internal mass resistance for compounds to traverse through the plant matrix and increases the specific surface area for extraction. The extraction yields obtained from boiling were higher than those from other extraction methods.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Solid content of extracts obtained by different methods*</bold>. *Error bars represent standard deviation (n = 3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1749-8546-3-15-1"/></fig><p>Boiling <italic>Herba Houttuyniae </italic>aerial parts in water for 20 minutes or one hour produced comparable yields (<italic>P </italic>= 1.000). For <italic>Herba Polygonis Hydropiperis</italic>, <italic>Folium Murraya Koenigii </italic>and <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis</italic>, a shorter boiling time of 20 minutes was shown to be comparable to a boiling time of 60 minutes (<italic>P </italic>= 0.061, 0.053 and 0.798 respectively). While results from blending/maceration varied, this method was as efficient as the boiling method in terms of solid yields (<italic>P </italic>= 0.261) of <italic>Folium murraya koenigii</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Organoleptic properties</title><p>The color, texture and odor of the plant extracts were characterized (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). The ethanolic extracts were better than corresponding aqueous extracts in retaining the natural fragrances of the plants. This may be due to the preservative ability of ethanol (i.e. reducing breakdown of organic compounds by microorganisms), its enhanced extraction capability (i.e. more fragrant components extracted) or a combination of both. Extracts obtained by boiling generally appeared darker and more turbid than those obtained by maceration. The solid content by boiling was higher than that by maceration (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Boiling is more likely to damage the plant cell membrane and cell wall which act as natural filters to keep larger extraneous compounds within the cell.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Antimicrobial activities</title><sec><title>Dried herbal extracts</title><p>Among all the extracts studied, the 100 &#x003bc;g of the ethanolic extract of <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>loaded on the filter paper disc demonstrated the most robust antimicrobial activities against <italic>S. aureus</italic>, <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, <italic>M</italic>.<italic>smegmatis </italic>and <italic>C. albicans</italic>, equivalent to at least 50% of the activities of the standard antibiotics. Among the test organisms, it was most active against <italic>M</italic>.<italic>smegmatis</italic>, 20% more than the standard antibiotic, streptomycin 10 &#x003bc;g (Student's t-test, <italic>P </italic>= 0.001) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The boiled extract of <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>had comparable antimicrobial activities to those of streptomycin 10 &#x003bc;g (Student's t-test, <italic>P </italic>= 0.279). These data suggest that <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>may be a potential agent to treat infections caused by <italic>M. smegmatis </italic>and <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. It was reported that magnolol and honokiol exhibited antibacterial activities against methicillin-resistant <italic>S. aureus </italic>and vancomycin-resistant enterococci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], <italic>Propionibacterium sp </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] and periodontal pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Therefore, disk diffusion test was carried out on magnolol and honokiol individually and in combination (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The one way ANOVA on the four treatment groups namely streptomycin, honokiol, magnolol and combination of magnolol and honokiol (1:1) demonstrated a significant difference between groups (<italic>P </italic>= 0.001). Bonferroni <italic>post-hoc </italic>test showed that honokiol and magnolol had comparable activities (<italic>P </italic>= 1.000) against <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, accounting for 83.58 &#x000b1; 3.06% (<italic>P </italic>= 0.015) and 82.09 &#x000b1; 6.51% (<italic>P </italic>= 0.006) of those of Streptomycin 10 &#x003bc;g respectively. In terms of antibacterial activities, the combination of magnolol and honokiol (1:1) was comparable to the reference antibiotic (<italic>P </italic>= 1.000) but higher than either magnolol (<italic>P </italic>= 0.007) or honokiol (<italic>P </italic>= 0.017) alone. These results suggest a new discovery of synergism between magnolol and honokiol.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Inhibition zones of Streptomycin 10 &#x003bc;g, magnolol, honokiol and a 1:1 combination of magnolol and honokiol</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Compound tested</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Inhibition zone (mm)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Percentage activity of compound in comparison to Streptomycin 10 &#x003bc;g (%)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="4"><bold><italic>P</italic>-value</bold><break/><bold>(one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni <italic>post hoc </italic>test)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Streptomycin 10 &#x003bc;g</td><td align="left">Magnolol</td><td align="left">Honokiol</td><td align="left">Magnolol and Honokiol (1:1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Streptomycin 10 &#x003bc;g</td><td align="left">34.67 &#x000b1; 1.75</td><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Magnolol 10 &#x003bc;g</td><td align="left">27.50 &#x000b1; 2.18</td><td align="left">82.09 &#x000b1; 6.51</td><td align="left">0.006</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Honokiol 10 &#x003bc;g</td><td align="left">28.42 &#x000b1; 1.04</td><td align="left">83.58 &#x000b1; 3.06</td><td align="left">0.015</td><td align="left">1.000</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Magnolol and Honokiol (1:1) 10 &#x003bc;g</td><td align="left">34.50 &#x000b1; 2.00</td><td align="left">94.52 &#x000b1; 5.48</td><td align="left">1.000</td><td align="left">0.007</td><td align="left">0.017</td><td align="left">-</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Ethanolic extract of <italic>Folium Murraya Koenigii </italic>and boiled extract of <italic>Herba Polygonis Hydropiperis </italic>showed 80% and 50% of the activities of streptomycin 10 &#x003bc;g against <italic>M. smegmatis </italic>respectively. These extracts also exhibited antimicrobial activities against <italic>S. aureus </italic>and <italic>B. subtilis</italic>. Additionally, the boiled extract of <italic>Herba Polygonis Hydropiperis </italic>was active against <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Boiling was essential for the active principles to be removed from the laksa plant, as blended and water macerated extracts showed little antimicrobial activities (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). The duration of the boiling process also affected the antimicrobial activities of laksa plant, whereby herbs boiled for 20 minutes were more active against <italic>S. aureus </italic>and <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>. The aerial parts of <italic>Herba Houttuyniae </italic>and rodent tuber were only active against <italic>B. subtilis </italic>and <italic>S. aureus </italic>respectively. The leaves and <italic>Rhizoma Arachis Hypogea, Rhizoma Imperatae</italic>, <italic>Rhizoma Typhonium Flagelliforme</italic>, and the leaves and stems <italic>of Epipremnum pinnatum </italic>did not show any antimicrobial activities.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Antimicrobial activities of various plant extracts (100 &#x003bc;g of the extract per loaded disc)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="10"><bold>Zone of inhibition (extract)/Zone of inhibition (standard)</bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="2"><bold><italic>S. aureus</italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2"><bold><italic>B. subtilis</italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2"><bold><italic>Ps. Aeruginosa</italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2"><bold><italic>M. smegmatis</italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2"><bold><italic>C. albicans</italic></bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Plant name (Latin)</td><td align="left">Plant part</td><td align="left">Code</td><td align="left">Ave</td><td align="left">SD</td><td align="left">Ave</td><td align="left">SD</td><td align="left">Ave</td><td align="left">SD</td><td align="left">Ave</td><td align="left">SD</td><td align="left">Ave</td><td align="left">SD</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Arachis hypogea</italic></td><td align="left">Leaves</td><td align="left">PLB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">PLW</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">PLE</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Rhizomes</td><td align="left">PRLB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">PRLW</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">PRLE</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Epipremnum pinnatum</italic></td><td align="left">Leaves</td><td align="left">RB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">RW</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">RE</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Stems</td><td align="left">RSB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">RSW</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">RSE</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Stems (fresh juices)</td><td align="left">RF</td><td align="left">0.29</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Periscaria hydropiper</italic></td><td align="left">Aerial parts (leaves &#x00026; stems)</td><td align="left">LB</td><td align="left">0.30</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">0.32</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">0.00</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">0.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">LW</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">LE</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">LM</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Imperata cylindrica</italic></td><td align="left">Rhizomes</td><td align="left">AB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">AW</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">AE</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic></td><td align="left">Aerial parts (leaves &#x00026; stems)</td><td align="left">FSB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">FB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">0.30</td><td align="left">0.00</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">FW</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">FE</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Aerial parts (fresh juices)</td><td align="left">FF</td><td align="left">0.29</td><td align="left">0.04</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Murraya koenigii</italic></td><td align="left">Leaves</td><td align="left">CB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">0.30</td><td align="left">0.00</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">CW</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">CE</td><td align="left">0.49</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td align="left">0.35</td><td align="left">0.03</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">0.77</td><td align="left">0.05</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">CM</td><td align="left">0.20</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Magnolia officinalis</italic></td><td align="left">Barks</td><td align="left">MB</td><td align="left">0.35</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">0.37</td><td align="left">0.00</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1.07</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">MW</td><td align="left">0.30</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td align="left">0.32</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">0.71</td><td align="left">0.05</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">ME</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td align="left">0.61</td><td align="left">0.03</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1.23</td><td align="left">0.05</td><td align="left">0.89</td><td align="left">0.06</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">MM</td><td align="left">0.19</td><td align="left">0.04</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">0.24</td><td align="left">0.08</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Typhonium flagelliforme</italic></td><td align="left">Aerial parts (leaves &#x00026; stems)</td><td align="left">YB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">YW</td><td align="left">0.22</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">YE</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Rhizomes</td><td align="left">YRB</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">YRW</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">YRE</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Leaves (fresh juices)</td><td align="left">YF</td><td align="left">0.28</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Rhizomes (fresh juices)</td><td align="left">YRF</td><td align="left">0.27</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Roots (fresh juices)</td><td align="left">YRR</td><td align="left">0.23</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>An extract with a high yield, however, does not necessarily have high antimicrobial activities. For example, <italic>Rhizoma Imperatae </italic>whose yields topped all extraction methods, did not show any antimicrobial activities (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Fresh herbal extracts</title><p>The fresh juices of <italic>Herba Houttuyniae </italic>aerial parts, <italic>Epipremnum pinnatum </italic>stems and <italic>Rhizoma Typhonium Flagelliforme </italic>were tested for their folkloric use to treat wounds and various skin ailments (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). All these fresh juices displayed some activities (less than 30% of the activity of methicillin 5 &#x003bc;g) against <italic>S. aureus</italic>. However, they were inactive against the rest of the test organisms. While the yields of fresh juices were lower than those of other extraction methods, antibacterial activities against <italic>S. aureus </italic>implied reduced degradation of the bioactive principles.</p><p>Among all extracts, only the fresh juices of <italic>Rhizoma Typhonium Flagelliforme </italic>and <italic>Epipremnum pinnatum </italic>leaves and stems possessed antimicrobial activities (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), suggesting that the antimicrobial components were unstable and destroyed by boiling and/or maceration. However, the extract of aerial parts of <italic>Rhizoma Typhonium Flagelliforme </italic>by maceration in water showed 20% of the activities of methicillin 5 &#x003bc;g against <italic>S. aureus</italic>. This finding suggests the antimicrobial potential of rodent tuber is beyond the ethnomedicinal use of the rhizomes.</p><p>The strongly aromatic plant materials, such as <italic>Herba Polygonis Hydropiperis</italic>, <italic>Folium Murraya Koeniggi </italic>and <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis</italic>, exhibited a broad spectrum of antimicrobial activities. One possible reason is the presence of essential oils and active polyphenolic compounds which possess antimicrobial activities. Among the extracts of <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis</italic>, the ethanolic extract demonstrated the strongest activities against <italic>S. aureus, B. subtilis</italic>, <italic>M. smegmatis </italic>and <italic>C. albicans</italic>. The active biphenol compounds in <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>(honokiol and magnolol) are poorly water soluble and extracted more efficiently by ethanol than water.</p><p>None of the extracts, however, inhibited <italic>Ps. aeruginosa</italic>. Both <italic>S. aureus </italic>and <italic>B. subtilis </italic>are Gram-positive, while <italic>Ps. aeruginosa </italic>is Gram-negative and has an outer lipid membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. The results suggest that the antimicrobial compounds in the extracts were unable to penetrate this lipid membrane to exert their effects inside a cell. This speculation will require further experiments to confirm.</p></sec><sec><title>Antioxidant activities</title><p>The antioxidant activities of the dried extracts and fresh juices are presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. All tested plants possessed some DPPH radical scavenging activities to a certain extent. While <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis</italic>, stems and leaves of dragon tail, laksa aerial parts, <italic>Herba Houttuyniae </italic>aerial parts and curry leaves showed high activities, rodent tuber rhizomes and aerial parts showed low activities.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Antioxidant activities of extracts tested by DPPH assay*</bold>. *Error bars represent standard deviations (n = 3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1749-8546-3-15-2"/></fig><p>The high antioxidant activities of the boiled and ethanolic extracts of the leafy materials were probably due to the extracted tannins and photosynthetic pigments. <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>is a rich source for antioxidative compounds, such as biphenols, polyphenols and tannins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Lo <italic>et al</italic>. found that the antioxidant effects of magnolol and honokiol isolated from <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>were 1000 times higher than those of alpha-tocopherol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. Earlier studies confirmed that several naturally occurring dietary phytochemicals, such as isothiocyanates, curcumin and Epigallocatechin-3-gallate, possessed cancer preventive properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>].</p><p>Boiled extracts showed greater antioxidant activities than those of other extraction methods (<italic>P </italic>= 0.001). Antioxidant compounds in leafy materials are generally located in conduit structures called the apoplast and symplast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. Maceration alone is not sufficient to extract these compounds from the structures. The application of heat, in the boiling process, facilitates cell rupture and leaching, thereby improving the mass transfer of these compounds from the storage organs into the boiling water. Ethanol may partially solubilize the membranes of the plant cells and storage organs, helping leach the chemicals away. However, maceration in 80% ethanol took over 24 hours and exposed the extracts to oxidative and hydrolytic degradation. This may explain the relatively low antioxidant activities of some ethanolic extracts.</p><p>The extracts of <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis</italic>, <italic>Herba Houttuyniae </italic>aerial parts and <italic>Folium Murraya Koenigii </italic>(ethanolic extract) had similar high DDPH radical scavenging activities (&#x0003e;85%) but markedly different antimicrobial properties (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). The results suggest that the active components for antimicrobial and antioxidant activities do not share common biochemical pathways.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The present study discovered that (a) the ethanolic extract of <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>had 20% greater antimicrobial activities against <italic>M. smegmatis </italic>than streptomycin; (b) the boiled extract of <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>demonstrated comparable activities to streptomycin (c) the synergism of magnonol and honokiol had comparable effects to those of streptomycin; (d) the aerial parts of rodent tuber had antimicrobial activities against <italic>S. aureus</italic>. Among the tested 107 extracts, <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>had (1) potent antimicrobial activities against <italic>S. aureus</italic>, <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, <italic>M. smegmatis </italic>and <italic>C. albicans </italic>and (2) highest antioxidant activities in DPPH assay regardless extraction methods. <italic>Cortex Magnoliae Officinalis </italic>is likely a potential medicinal plant resource for developing effective antimicrobials and antioxidants.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>LWC and PWSH conceived the research design and supervised the manuscript preparation. WYW, ELCC and CLLS performed all extractions, antimicrobial and antioxidant studies as well as statistical analyses. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p>Organoleptic properties of the plant extracts investigated in this study. This table is a summary of the organoleptic properties of the plant extracts investigated in this study, such as color, texture and odor.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1749-8546-3-15-S1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was funded by the Academic Research Fund (R-148-000-055-112), National University of Singapore. Our appreciation is extended to Ms Ooi Shing Ming for her assistance in experiments, Prof Baolin Guo, Herbarium of the Institute of Medicinal Plant Development (IMPLAD) of the Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences (Beijing, China) and Ms Serena Lee, Herbarium of Singapore Botanic Gardens, National Parks Board of Singapore for the authentication of plant materials. ELCC received a postgraduate research scholarship from the National University of Singapore.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahverdi</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fakhimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarrini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehghan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Iranshahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Galbanic acid from Ferula szowitsiana enhanced the antibacterial activity of penicillin G and cephalexin against Staphylococcus aureus</article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2007</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1805</fpage><lpage>1807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17827745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.30.1805</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horiuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of oleanolic acid from Salvia officinalis and related compounds on vancomycin-resistant enterococci (VRE)</article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2007</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1147</fpage><lpage>1149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17541170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.30.1147</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horiuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentiation of antimicrobial activity of aminoglycosides by carnosol from Salvia officinalis</article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2007</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17268067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.30.287</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tepe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition, antioxidant and antimicrobial properties of the essential oils of three Salvia species from Turkish flora</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2008</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>4096</fpage><lpage>4104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17936619</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>M-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>Y-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S-T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activities of ethanolic extracts from the twigs of Cinnamomum osmophloeum</article-title><source>Bioresource Tech</source><year>2008</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>1918</fpage><lpage>1925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2007.03.020</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H-B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>K-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant properties in vitro and total phenolic contents in methanol extracts from medicinal plants</article-title><source>LWT &#x02013; Food Sci Tech</source><year>2008</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2007.03.011</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soobrattee</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahorun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Neergheen</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Googoolye</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aruoma</surname><given-names>OI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the content of phenolics and antioxidant actions of the Rubiaceae, Ebenaceae, Celastraceae, Erythroxylaceae and Sterculaceae families of Mauritian endemic plants</article-title><source>Toxicology in Vitro</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17911003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tiv.2007.07.012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramaniam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant flavonoids from leaves of Polygonum hydropiper L</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12482460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(02)00504-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Haraguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Imoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidative sulphated flavonoids in leaves of polygonum hydropiper</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>1994</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(00)90632-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haraguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidative substances in leaves of polygonum hydropiper</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>1992</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf00020a011</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Math</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramaniam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curry leaves (Murraya Koenigii spreng) and halitosis</article-title><source>BMJ (South Asia ED)</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>211</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic antioxidants from herbs and spices</article-title><source>Biofactors</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11237173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/biof.5520130123</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A benzoisofuranone derivative and carbazole alkaloids from Murraya koenigii and their antimicrobial activity</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1601</fpage><lpage>1606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15955541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2005.05.001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antifungal activity of some constituents of Murraya koenigii Spreng</article-title><source>Experientia</source><year>1965</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>340</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5870511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02144703</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kesari</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Watal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the glycemic and lipidemic effect of Murraya koenigii in experimental animals</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2007</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17467937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2007.03.023</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruys</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Double-blind experiments on the effect of a peanut extract on the bleeding incidence in 92 haemophiliacs</article-title><source>Br Med J</source><year>1967</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4861744</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Layon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Symptom combinations associated with outcome and therapeutic effects in a cohort of cases with SARS</article-title><source>Am J Chin Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17163583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/S0192415X06004417</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of houttuynia cordata thunb and some other herbs on human neutrophil and monocyte chemiluminescence</article-title><source>Guangxi Yikedaxue Xuebao</source><year>1997</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in studies on houttuynia cordata</article-title><source>Zhongcaoyao</source><year>2001</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>368</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory effect of Houttuynia cordata injection</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2006</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16213118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2005.09.012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virucidal effects of the steam distillate from Houttuynia cordata and its components on HSV-1, influenza virus, and HIV</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7617766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2006-958063</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-Herpes simplex virus activity of Bidens pilosa and Houttuynia cordata</article-title><source>Am J Chin Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12943167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/S0192415X03001090</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Najimudin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulaiman</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth arrest and non-apoptotic programmed cell death associated with the up-regulation of c-myc mRNA expression in T-47D breast tumor cells following exposure to Epipremnum pinnatum (L.) Engl. hexane extract</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2005</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15619555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2004.07.005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro cytotoxicity and immunomodulating property of Rhaphidophora korthalsii</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>1996</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8733120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-8741(96)01391-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sam</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitotsuyanagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cytotoxicity and chemical constituents of the hexane fraction of Typhonium flagelliforme (Araceace)</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2001</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(01)00274-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Itokawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytotoxic activity of Typhonium flagelliforme (Araceae)</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11351365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.717</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tengku-Muhammad</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of cytotoxic activities between in vitro and field grown plants of typhonium flagelliforme (Lodd.) Blume</article-title><source>J Plant Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Study on the identification of standard and false Banxia by two-dimensional infrared correlation spectroscopy]</article-title><source>Guang Pu Xue Yu Guang Pu Fen Xi</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15766148</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carraro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadia</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Volpini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Benvenuti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soy isoflavones, lactobacilli, Magnolia bark extract, vitamin D3 and calcium. Controlled clinical study in menopause</article-title><source>Minerva Ginecol</source><year>2006</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16957676</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Homma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Niitsuma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacological effects of urinary products obtained after treatment with saiboku-to, a herbal medicine for bronchial asthma, on type IV allergic reaction</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11105563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2000-8626</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation of the BK(Ca) channel in cultured smooth muscle cells of human trachea by magnolol</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2002</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11809993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thorax.57.1.67</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antibacterial and anti-inflammatory effects of honokiol and magnolol against Propionibacterium sp</article-title><source>Eur J Pharmacol</source><year>2004</year><volume>496</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15288590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2004.05.047</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Syu</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and cytotoxic activities of neolignans from Magnolia officinalis</article-title><source>Chem Biodivers</source><year>2004</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>530</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17191867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbdv.200490046</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of honokiol and magnolol isolated from Magnolia officinalis</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11268114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.736</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinilla</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and partial characterization of immunostimulating polysaccharides from Imperata cylindrica</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10483377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-1999-14087</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>But</surname><given-names>PPH</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J-X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><collab>Eds</collab></person-group><source>International collation of traditional and folk medicine. Northeast Asia. Part I</source><year>1996</year><publisher-name>Singapore: World Scientific Publishing Co. Pte. Ltd</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DFJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality assurance of antimicrobial susceptibility testing by disc diffusion</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2001</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11420339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/48.2.219</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>NCCLS</collab></person-group><source>Performance standards for antimirobial disk susceptibility tests: Approved standard M2-A7</source><year>2000</year><edition>7</edition><publisher-name>Pennsylvania: Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maisuthisakul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Suttajit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pongsawatmanit</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assesment of phenolic content and free radical-scavenging capacity of some Thai indigenous plants</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>1409</fpage><lpage>1418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2005.11.032</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leprosy, tuberculosis, and the new genetics</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1993</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8416888</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><source>Microbiology: Principles and Explorations</source><year>1999</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-name>New York: Prentice Hall</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United States Department of Agriculture Forest Service</collab></person-group><source>Bark and Its Possible Uses</source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fpl.fs.fed.us/documnts/fplrn/fplrn091.pdf"/></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dharmananda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Magnolia Bark</source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.itmonline.org/arts/magnolia.htm"/></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnolol and honokiol isolated from Magnolia officinalis protect rat heart mitochondria against lipid peroxidation</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>1994</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8117323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-2952(94)90187-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khor</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebbar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacogenomics of cancer chemopreventive isothiocyanate compound sulforaphane in the intestinal polyps of ApcMin/+ mice</article-title><source>Biopharm Drug Dispos</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16952200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bdd.522</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khor</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Keum</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gopalakrishnan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Conney</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined inhibitory effects of curcumin and phenethyl isothiocyanate on the growth of human PC-3 prostate xenografts in immunodeficient mice</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16423986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-05-2708</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barcel&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sevilla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant Systems and O2./H2O2 Production in the Apoplast of Pea Leaves. Its Relation with Salt-Induced Necrotic Lesions in Minor Veins</article-title><source>Plant Phys</source><year>2001</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.010188</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luwe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidants in the apoplast and symplast of beech (Fagus sylvatica L.) leaves: seasonal variations and responses to changing ozone concentrations in air</article-title><source>Plant, Cell &#x00026; Environment</source><year>1996</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.1996.tb00254.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Plazaola</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Becerril</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal changes in photosynthetic pigments and antioxidants in beech <italic>Fagus sylvatica </italic>in a Mediterranean climate: implications for tree decline diagnosis</article-title><source>Funct Plant Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/PP00119</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>