<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Circadian Rhythms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Circadian Rhythms</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1740-3391</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19123938</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2631603</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1740-3391-7-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1740-3391-7-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Debate</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Is a purpose of REM sleep atonia to help regenerate intervertebral disc volumetric loss?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fryer</surname><given-names>Jerome CJ</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>drfryer@shaw.ca</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Private Practice, Nanaimo, British Columbia, V9S 3Y3, Canada </aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcircadianrhythms.com/content/7/1/1"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Fryer; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Fryer; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Fryer               CJ               Jerome                              drfryer@shaw.ca            </dc:author><dc:title>            Is a purpose of REM sleep atonia to help regenerate intervertebral disc volumetric loss?         </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Circadian Rhythms 7(1): 1-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1740-3391(2009)7:1&#x0003c;1&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1740-3391</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>The nature of atonia in sleep continues to be enigmatic. This article discusses a new hypothesis for complete core muscle relaxation in REM sleep, suggesting a bottom-up recuperative perspective. That is, does the atonia in REM sleep provide a utility to help restore the mechanobiology and respective diurnal intervertebral disc hydraulic loss? By combining the effects of gravity with current compressive concepts in spinal stability, this article looks at vertebral approximation as a deleterious experience with an intrinsic biological need to keep vertebrae separated. Methods using polysomnography and recumbent MRI are discussed.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>The goal of this article is to stimulate spine research in sleep. Specifically, I ask whether REM atonia plays a mechanical function in assisting recuperative imbibition to diurnally influenced cartilaginous structures in mammalian species. Since the discovery of REM sleep, researchers have been looking to the midbrain and surrounding parenchyma in search for answers with much progress in the neuro-mechanisms around the reticular formation. But do we know definitively the mechanical effects of REM's atonia on all diurnally influenced mammalian tissues? To the best of the author's knowledge, this relationship has not been thoroughly investigated and requires a closer look.</p><p>To appreciate the historical pursuit of REM sleep atonia's regulatory mechanisms, Michael Jouvet's study in 1962 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] warrants honorable mention. Jouvet investigated subcortical activities in sleeping decerebrate cats. He measured EMG activity of neck muscles and found that muscle tone disappeared 4&#x02013;5 times (for a period of about 6 min) over a 6 h course of sleep &#x02013; even without the cortex. He also found that, during atonia, high voltage spiky waves appeared in the pontine EEG recording electrodes and waking EEG in the cortex. This apparent paradox (atonia and waking-like EEG activity) led him to coin the term "paradoxical sleep" and the research suggested the structures responsible for REM's characteristic identification of atonia were located caudal to the transection at the midbrain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>The function of REM sleep continues to be enigmatic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], with atonia well documented in humans and animals. Some have explained this as the loss of core muscle tone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] and by others, as the total paralysis of the anti-gravity muscles of the body [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. But, to date, the best functional hypothesis for this complete pseudo-paralysis is believed to be for the purpose of not acting out our dreams. It is understood that this idea has evolved from the disturbing effects of REM sleep behavior disorders. Here, an alternative viewpoint and new hypothesis will be proposed.</p><p>If the muscles of REM sleep atonia are identified as "antigravity muscles", then it would seem reasonable to understand clearly the gravitational influences on all adjacently associated mammalian structural tissues related to these muscles across day and night. The spine plays a foundational role in mammalian motility with associated spinal muscles attached to the vertebrae, by way of origins and insertions, and crossing intervertebral discs (IVDs) (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, for example). Research on human IVDs and corresponding biomechanics has revealed a definitive nycthemeral variation of human stature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. It has been found that we lose height over the course of one day by as much as 26 mm, which is very likely due to changes in the IVDs. On average, 19.3 mm of height is lost with volumetric changes of 1300 mm<sup>3</sup> to the lumbar discs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Others have found in vivo daily variations of 16.2% in the lumbar IVDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] and 10.6% height gain over an 8 hr recumbent rest period with MRI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. In the absence of gravitational influences, some space flight studies have shown alterations in REM, suggesting a possible gravitational influence on sleep [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Example of compressive muscle stabilization of the intervertebral disc</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1740-3391-7-1-1"/></fig><p>In order to consider this new functional hypothesis for REM's atonia, it is imperative that the reader understands current concepts of spinal stability. Simplistically, muscles can either contract or relax. Under the act of spinal stabilization, muscles contract to provide a 360 degree buttressing force to prevent the IVDs from buckling (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). McGill [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] explains how the core musculature acts like guy wires of tension to create a stable platform. This concerted effort from the musculature around each spinal motion segment and across heavily water concentrated cartilaginous tissue causes a net effect of IVD compression. And, when this myotogenous spinal stability function is combined with the nycthemeral variation in the influence of gravity, the consequential pressures are thus significant on IVDs &#x02013; showing their deformation with daily variations. Therefore, there are two combined forces working against the task of maintaining hydraulic vertebral spacing: 1) stabilizing musculature and 2) gravity. In absolute terms, an anti-gravity muscle is one that must create compression with the goal of minimizing approximation to osteological structures and associated articular cartilage. In other words, it is physically impossible to have a muscle that contracts against the forces of gravity. Using the term "anti-gravity muscles" may have been misleading terminology. The reader is directed to McGill's work for a full understanding of spinal biomechanics, but the highlights, for the purposes of this paper, have been mentioned.</p><p>It is proposed here that one of the possible reasons humans and most other mammals experience atonia during REM (and possibly during NREM) is to relax the compressive stabilizing musculature around the IVD(s) to allow effective imbibition of the cartilage in a pulse-like mechano-hydraulic fashion through sleep. This would simply aid to recuperate the net diurnal IVD height and related water loss experienced as a result of the loading effects on the preceding day. Relaxation of the muscles is proposed to result in net nutrient influx to these large avascular structures in mammalian species. Recent research has shown the importance of dynamic loads vs. static loads in oxygen delivery to IVDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] with the idea that this on/off pulse of REM atonia delivers varying loads and resultant mechanobiological influences to chondrocytes (and their microenvironments) across sleep.</p></sec><sec><title>Some of what we know and what we don't know about REM and related topics</title><p>Approximately twenty-five percent of sleep is REM in the young adult [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] but interestingly, this varies with age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. We know that infants have much more REM compared to adults, as human infants typically enter REM sleep directly after the initial onset of sleep and spend approximately 50% of their total sleep time in REM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. And we also know that as we age, cartilaginous structures desiccate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. During development, infants have much more cartilaginous tissue compared to adults while they undergo the metabolic demanding task of endochondral ossification. Chondrocytes constitute the predominant cell of cartilage which is an interface tissue that is avascular, aneural and alymphatic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. These cells lay in an environment that is influenced by mechanical forces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] whereby cellular perception of mechanical stress within cartilaginous tissues is an important modulator of chondrocyte function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Recent understandings of growth plate proliferation have revealed that distraction is facilitatory while compression is inhibitory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Therefore, could the relaxation of the mechanical tension across growth plates explain to provide a function of assisting growth and perhaps explain why infants have much more REM? Endochondral ossification related to growth is complete in humans around the ages of 18&#x02013;24 yr which could possibly account for the difference in REM across the ages. The demand for micronutrients to these cellular processes in the adult may be less because there is less demand for the process of osseous growth.</p><p>Interestingly, cetaceans are the only mammals in which REM is not observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. This finding could lend support to this new hypothesis. That is, aquatic mammals are not under the same gravitational demands as are land mammals and do not require the same buttressing spinal mechanisms for stability. They may not require atonia to recuperate the disc height loss in the same way land vertebrates do because of their aquatic environment. With minimal axial gravitational compressive loads coupled with the horizontal and constantly moving nature of their life, the need for atonia during REM could not be required.</p><p>Quadruped mammals are known to experience atonic sleep. And some readers may argue that the horizontal nature of quadrupeds would not require similar atonia to unload the upright bipedal nature of a human's spinal biomechanics. Comparative differences in sleep architecture are not too obvious; except that the size of a mammal appears to be related to the quantity of sleep [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. It is believed that quadrupeds are designed with similar buttressing mechanics around the spine when compared to upright bipeds. Holding the fore limbs and hind limbs together must require similar compressive forces for stability to inhibit significant spinal bowing and vertebral approximation. And it is believed that the forces within the spine are more similar than different when comparing bipedals and quadrupeds. Unfortunately, the nycthemeral variations in the height and length of quadrupeds have not been investigated thoroughly. Perhaps, the small variations are difficult to detect. Horses, for example, can sleep standing in "stay mechanisms." But some authors have speculated that horses do not experience REM in this position but require lying down to experience REM (S McDonnell, e-mail communication, October 1, 2007). This observation would lend support to this hypothesis with horses requiring to lie down to spinally recuperate. Although unknowns regarding spinal nycthemeral variations in quadrupeds remain, further investigations may help define the physical aspects of recuperation during sleep in these mammals. Could the finding of mammal size and quantity of sleep be related to the size of the vertebrae and related hydraulic recovery?</p></sec><sec><title>Suggested methods</title><p>The testing methodology of whether spinal intervertebral disc restoration occurs significantly greater during REM sleep's atonia will likely require 3T MRI lumbar mapping and polysomnography. One method could involve obtaining three measures of lumbar IVD heights in sleep (10 pm, 2:30 am, and 7 am, for example) and correlating the changes to REM atonia. It is well known that there is a higher percentage of REM sleep in the latter half of the night and it is proposed that the atonia in REM will correlate to greater disc volume gains. Disc hydraulic recuperation has not been correlated to REM sleep. It is hypothesized that the atonia would contribute to a greater hydraulic recovery and in turn, provide insight into the diurnal hydraulic nature of spinal recuperation and its relationship to muscle tone in sleep. Aged matched controls would also be of interest, with an investigation across the full 24 hr cycle to be thorough. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> compares expected height changes under the proposed hypothesis with the height changes predicted by a linear model (as is suggested by previous work) over a bed-time cycle. Other methodological strategies could involve REM sleep deprivation and/or the use of medication to inhibit REM sleep with manipulation of independent variables. Importantly, age matched subjects who simply lie down and do not sleep (having MRI images) would prove as a useful control group. Additional tools like highly sensitive digital stadiometers could also help in revealing the answers to this new hypothesis. For other related works, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Example of lumbar disc height, believed (blue) and proposed (red), across sleep</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1740-3391-7-1-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Future directions</title><p>Because sleep is defined not as a single-state, but as a number of mixed states [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], it seems reasonable to approach the challenge of understanding <italic>why we sleep </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] through a careful dissection of all sleep's anatomy. Limiting our search to descending inhibitory neurological pathways with atonia may not allow us to step-back and look at all the requirements on Earth, including physical ones. Vertebral approximation is not a favourable situation in the spine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] and, simplistically, it seems reasonable to think that there should be an innate biological mechanism to indicate when to allow IVDs to decompress and regain hydraulic structure and associated nutrients in preparation for the following day. The IVDs are daily oscillatory hydraulic structures that undergo compression throughout the waking day, but when they specifically recuperate their hydraulic loss in sleep has not been investigated thoroughly. Unfolding the full wake/sleep story on these biological tissues should help provide us with insights into concepts of physical recovery in sleep. Importantly, understanding the relationship of sleep to many medically related mobility disorders such as narcolepsy, cataplexy, fibromyalgia, Parkinsons, restless leg syndrome, and osteoarthritis, for example, will provide large rewards. The curious nature of atonia during REM may not be as complex as once thought. Simply, this mechanobiological investigation would look at whether or not REM atonia had an influence on water flow (with its solutes) into cartilage in sleep.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author declares that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>JF contributed to all of the article's content.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Very special thanks to Jerome Siegel PhD for editing help and assisting with methodological strategies.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jouvet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recherches sur les structures nerveuses et les mechanismes responsables des differentes phases du sommeil physiologique</article-title><source>Arch Ital Biol</source><year>1962</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14452612</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurobiological mechanisms for the regulation of mammalian sleep-wake behavior: Reinterpretation of historical evidence and inclusion of contemporary cellular and molecular evidence</article-title><source>Neurosci Biobehav Reviews</source><year>2007</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2007.02.004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep: a functional enigma</article-title><source>Neuromolecular Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15001813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/NMM:5:1:059</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biopsychology</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>Boston: Allyn &#x00026; Bacon</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Mallick BN, Singh R</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Brainstem systems mediating the control of muscle tone</article-title><source>Environment and Physiology</source><year>1994</year><publisher-name>New Delhi, India: Narosa Publishing House</publisher-name><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidlinger-Wilke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurtz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maroudas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal fluid expression and activity of intervertebral disc cells</article-title><source>Biorheology</source><year>2006</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16912401</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangerfield</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative analysis of diurnal variation in volume and water content of lumbar intervertebral discs</article-title><source>Clin Anat</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9445091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-2353(1998)11:1&#x0003c;1::AID-CA1&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-Z</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botsford</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Esses</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogilvie-Harris</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo diurnal variation in intervertebral disc volume and morphology</article-title><source>Spine</source><year>1994</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8009352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-199404150-00012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malko</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fajman</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An in vivo MRI study of the changes in volume (and fluid content) of the lumbar intervertebral disc after overnight bed rest and during an 8-hour walking protocol</article-title><source>J Spinal Disord Tech</source><year>2002</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11927827</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gundel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nalishiti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Reucher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vejvoda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zulley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep and cicardian rhythm during a short space mission</article-title><source>Clin Investig</source><year>1993</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>718</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8241722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00209726</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lumbar Spine Stability: Myths and Realities</article-title><source>Low Back Disorders: Evidence-based Prevention and Rehabilitation</source><year>2002</year><publisher-name>Champaign, Ill.: Human Kinetics</publisher-name><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of mechanical compression on metabolism and distribution of oxygen and lactate in intervertebral disc</article-title><source>J Biomech</source><year>2008</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1184</fpage><lpage>1196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18374341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiomech.2008.02.002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarley</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Chokverty S</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Neurophysiology of sleep: Basic mechanisms underlying control of wakefulness and sleep</article-title><source>Sleep Disorders Medicine; Basic Science, Technical Considerations and Clinical Aspects</source><year>1994</year><publisher-name>Boston: Butterworth-Heineniann</publisher-name><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nature of spontaneous sleep across adulthood</article-title><source>J Sleep Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17309760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2007.00567.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carskadon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dement</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kryger MH, Roth T, Dement WC</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Normal Human Sleep Overview</article-title><source>Principles and Practice of Sleep Medicine</source><year>2005</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-name>Philadelphia, PA: Elsevier/Saunders</publisher-name><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botsford</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Esses</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogilvie-Harris</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo diurnal variation in intervertebral disc volume and morphology</article-title><source>Spine</source><year>1994</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8009352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-199404150-00012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoltz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wand</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Payan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mainard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurice</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Netter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of mechanical forces on cells and tissues</article-title><source>Biorheology</source><year>2000</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10912174</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grodzinsky</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Levenston</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cartilage tissue remodeling in response to mechanical forces</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biomed Eng</source><year>2000</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11701528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bioeng.2.1.691</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuscik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Di</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Keefe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of chondrogenesis and chondrocyte differentiation by stress</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2008</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18246193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI34174</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Aronsson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortright</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endochondral growth in growth plates of three species at two anatomical locations modulated by mechanical compression and tension</article-title><source>J Orthopaedic Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1327</fpage><lpage>1334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.20189</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clues to the functions of mammalian sleep</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>437</volume><fpage>1264</fpage><lpage>1271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16251951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04285</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidlinger-Wilke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurtz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maroudas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal fluid expression and activity of intervertebral disc cells</article-title><source>Bioreheology</source><year>2006</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>291</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangerfield</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative analysis of diurnal variation in volume and water content of lumbar intervertebral discs</article-title><source>Clin Anat</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9445091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-2353(1998)11:1&#x0003c;1::AID-CA1&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-Z</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botsford</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Esses</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogilvie-Harris</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo diurnal variation in intervertebral disc volume and morphology</article-title><source>Spine</source><year>1994</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8009352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-199404150-00012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malko</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fajman</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An in vivo MRI study of the changes in volume (and fluid content) of the lumbar intervertebral disc after overnight bed rest and during an 8-hour walking protocol</article-title><source>J Spinal Disord Tech</source><year>2002</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11927827</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal changes in spinal mechanics and their clinical significance</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source><year>1990</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2138156</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why we Sleep</article-title><source>Sci Am</source><year>2003</year><volume>NOV</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14564818</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnake</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Putzier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandziora</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanical concepts for disc regeneration</article-title><source>Eur Spine J</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>S354</fpage><lpage>S360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16835733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00586-006-0176-y</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>