<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19042973</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2632895</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn946</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkn946</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Chemistry and Synthetic Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chemical synthesis of oligodeoxyribonucleotides containing <italic>N</italic>3- and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-carboxymethylthymidine and their formation in DNA</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jianshuang</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yinsheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Chemistry, University of California, Riverside, CA 92521-0403, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+1 951 827 2700</phone>; Fax: <fax>+1 951 827 4713</fax>; Email: <email>yinsheng.wang@ucr.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><!--For NAR both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>37</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2008 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Humans are exposed to <italic>N</italic>-nitroso compounds from both endogenous and exogenous sources. Many <italic>N</italic>-nitroso compounds can be metabolically activated to give diazoacetate, which can result in the carboxymethylation of DNA. The remarkable similarity in <italic>p53</italic> mutations found in human gastrointestinal tumors and in shuttle vector studies, where the human <italic>p53</italic> gene-containing vector was treated with diazoacetate and propagated in yeast cells, suggests that diazoacetate might be an important etiological agent for human gastrointestinal tumors. The <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-carboxymethyl-2&#x02032;-deoxyguanosine was previously detected in isolated DNA upon exposure to diazoacetate and in blood samples of healthy human subjects. The corresponding modifications of thymidine and 2&#x02032;-deoxyadenosine have not been assessed, though significant mutations at A:T base pairs were found in the <italic>p53</italic> tumor suppressor gene in human gastrointestinal tumors and in shuttle vector studies. To understand the implications of the carboxymethylation chemistry of thymidine in the observed mutations at A:T base pairs, here we synthesized authentic <italic>N</italic>3-carboxymethylthymidine (<italic>N</italic>3-CMdT) and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-carboxymethylthymidine (<italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT), incorporated them into DNA, and demonstrated, for the first time, that they were the major carboxymethylated derivatives of thymidine formed in calf thymus DNA upon exposure to diazoacetate. The demonstration of the formation of <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT in isolated DNA upon treatment with diazoacetate, together with the preparation of authentic oligodeoxyribonucleotide substrates housing these two lesions, laid the foundation for investigating the replication and repair of these lesions and for understanding their implications in the mutations observed in human gastrointestinal tumors.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Humans are exposed to <italic>N</italic>-nitroso compounds (NOCs) from diet, tobacco smoke and other environmental sources as well as from endogenous sources, and it was estimated that the endogenous sources account for 45&#x02013;75% of the total NOC exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). The exposure to endogenous NOCs was found to be significantly associated with the risk of developing non-cardia gastric cancer in a recent large-scale epidemiological study, i.e. European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition (EPIC) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). This study included more than half a million individuals and 314 incident cases of gastric cancer that had occurred after an average of 6.6 years of follow up (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>).</p><p>Some endogenously produced NOCs are known to cause damage to DNA and they are both mutagenic and carcinogenic. Earlier studies by Wogan <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>) revealed that the treatment of male Fischer rats with nitrosated bile acid conjugates <italic>N</italic>-nitrosoglycocholic acid (NOGC) and <italic>N</italic>-nitrosotaurocholic acid (NOTC) could induce significant levels of hepatocarcinoma in 54&#x02013;70% of the treated animals, and 12&#x02013;13% of the treated rats developed gastric tumors. Forward mutation assay in <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> and in TK6 diploid human lymphoblasts showed that NOGC and NOTC are both mutagenic, with NOGC being more effective than NOTC in inducing mutations in TK6 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). In this regard, NOGC could arise from the nitrosation of glycocholic acid under simulated gastric conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Shuker <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) later demonstrated that the treatment of calf thymus DNA with NOGC can induce the formation of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-carboxymethyl-2&#x02032;-deoxyguanosine (<italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG) and, to a much lesser extent, <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-methyl-2&#x02032;-deoxyguanosine (<italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-MdG, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Scheme 1</xref>). By using immunoslot blot assay or immunoaffinity/HPLC method with antibody recognizing <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-carboxymethylguanine, Shuker <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7 B8 B9">7&#x02013;9</xref>) showed that <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG can be induced in DNA by <italic>N</italic>-nitroso glycine (NG, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Scheme 1</xref>). In addition, <italic>O</italic>-diazoacetyl-<sc>l</sc>-serine (also known as azaserine, AS, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Scheme 1</xref>), a pancreatic carcinogen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>), could induce the carboxymethylation of guanine residues in DNA in pancreatic acinar cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>).</p><p>The above carboxymethylation was thought to proceed through a common reactive intermediate, diazoacetate (DA, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Scheme 1</xref>), and it was demonstrated that potassium diazoacetate (KDA) can induce the formation of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG and, to a lesser degree (about one-sixteenth of that of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG), <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-methyl-2&#x02032;-deoxyguanosine in DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7 B8 B9">7&#x02013;9</xref>). Furthermore, it was observed that humans consuming red meat have a higher level of nitrosated compounds in feces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) and an elevated level of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG in colonic exfoliated cells than control group consuming vegetarian diet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG was also detected at a level of three to eight lesions per 10<sup>7</sup> nucleosides in the blood DNA of healthy human subjects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>).</p><p>Some initial replication and repair studies have been carried out for <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG. In this context, it was found that the azaserine-mediated cell killing cannot be rescued by the overexpression of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-methylguanine methyltransferase (MGMT) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>), which is keeping with the observation that <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG is not subjected to repair by MGMT <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). On the other hand, lymphoblastoid cells with deficiency in nucleotide excision repair (NER) were significantly more sensitive to azaserine than the control repair-proficient cells, suggesting that <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG can be repaired by NER factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>).</p><p>A very recent study by Gottschalg <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>) revealed that the passage of KDA-treated, human <italic>p53</italic> gene-containing plasmid in yeast cells could result in substantial single-base substitutions. Interestingly, KDA induced almost equal distributions of transition and transversion mutations, which differs markedly from the predominant GC&#x02192;AT transition mutation (&#x0003e;80%) induced by methylating agent methylnitrosourea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), suggesting that DNA methylation is not the major contributor to KDA-induced mutations. Moreover, the identities and frequencies of mutations induced by diazoacetate at non-CpG sites are remarkably similar to the mutations at non-CpG sites in <italic>p53</italic> gene observed in human stomach and colorectal tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), suggesting that diazoacetate may constitute an important etiological agent for the development of gastrointestinal cancer.</p><p>Gottschalg <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>) also observed a substantial frequency of single-base substitutions at A:T base pairs in <italic>p53</italic> gene from shuttle vector studies and in human gastrointestinal tumors. For instance, the percentages of mutations at A:T base pairs account for 43% and 28% of all the observed mutations while the vector was treated with KDA in PBS and Tris&#x02013;EDTA, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). The observation of a significant proportion of mutations at A:T base pairs supports that KDA can also induce promutagenic lesions at adenine and/or thymine. Although KDA has been shown to induce the formation of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG, it remains unexplored what types of lesions can be induced at adenine and thymine sites in DNA by KDA and what the mutagenic properties are for the lesions induced at these two nucleobases.</p><p>As a first step toward answering these questions, we report here the chemical syntheses of <italic>N</italic>3- and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-carboxymethylthymidine, their incorporation into oligodeoxyribonucleotides (ODNs), and the demonstration of their formation in calf thymus DNA upon treatment with diazoacetate.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Materials</title><p>All chemicals, unless otherwise specified, were from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). Common reagents for solid-phase DNA synthesis were obtained from Glen Research Co. (Sterling, VA).</p></sec><sec><title>Synthesis of standard <italic>N</italic>3-carboxymethylthymidine (<italic>N</italic>3-CMdT, 1b, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Scheme 2</xref>a)</title><p>In a flask, 242 mg of thymidine and 166 mg of potassium carbonate were dissolved in 50 ml of anhydrous methanol. To the solution was subsequently added 184 mg of methyl bromoacetate. The resulting solution was refluxed for 6 h. Evaporation of solvent under reduced pressure afforded white solid which was then purified by silica gel column chromatography with EtOAc/MeOH (85/15, v/v) as mobile phase to give 152 mg of <bold>1a</bold> as colorless viscous liquid (yield 48%). Hydrolysis of <bold>1a</bold> (152 mg) with 2.0 ml of aqueous NaOH solution (0.5 M) rendered <bold>1b</bold> in sodium salt form (119 mg; yield 84%).</p><p><bold>1a</bold>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (300 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>, 25&#x000b0;C, Figure S1): <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> 7.49 (s, 1H, H-6), 6.20 (t, 1H, H-1&#x02032;, <italic>J</italic> = 6.6 Hz), 4.69 (s, 2H, <italic>N</italic>3-CH<sub>2</sub>), 4.54 (m, 1H, H-3&#x02032;), 3.98 (m, 1H, H-4&#x02032;), 3.83&#x02013;3.80 (m, 2H, H-5&#x02032; and H-5&#x02033;), 3.75 (s, 3H, 3-OCH<sub>3</sub>), 2.35 (m, 2H, H-2&#x02032; and H-2&#x02033;), 1.94 (s, 3H, 5-CH<sub>3</sub>).</p><p>HRMS (ESI): [M + H]<sup>+</sup> calcd <italic>m/z</italic> 315.1192, found 315.1184.</p><p><bold>1b</bold>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (300 MHz, D<sub>2</sub>O, 25&#x000b0;C, Figure S2): <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> 7.72 (s, 1H, H-6), 6.34 (t, 1H, H-1&#x02032;, <italic>J</italic> = 6.6 Hz), 4.50 (m, 3H, <italic>N</italic>3-CH<sub>2</sub> and H-3&#x02032;), 4.07 (m, 1H, H-4&#x02032;), 3.93&#x02013;3.79 (m, 2H, H-5&#x02032; and H-5&#x02033;), 2.41&#x02013;2.45 (m, 2H, H-2&#x02032; and H-2&#x02033;), 1.96 (s, 3H, 5-CH<sub>3</sub>).</p><p>HRMS (ESI): [M + H]<sup>+</sup> calcd <italic>m/z</italic> 301.1025, found 301.1028.</p></sec><sec><title>Synthesis of <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-carboxymethylthymidine (<italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT, 2d, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Scheme 1</xref>b)</title><p>Compound <bold>2a</bold> was prepared following the previously published procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Compound 1,2,4-triazole (414 mg) was suspended in anhydrous acetonitrile (9.0 ml) in an ice bath, and then POCl<sub>3</sub> (110 &#x003bc;l) was slowly added with rapid stirring followed by dropwise addition of TEA (840 &#x003bc;l). Compound <bold>2a</bold> (261 mg) in &#x0223c;2.0 ml acetonitrile was subsequently added, and the solution was continuously stirred for 90 min. The reaction was terminated by adding saturated NaHCO<sub>3</sub> solution and extracted with CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>. The organic layer was washed sequentially with saturated NaHCO<sub>3</sub> and brine, dried with Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, and the solvent was evaporated under reduced pressure. Purification with silica gel column chromatography using ethyl ether as mobile phase rendered <bold>2b</bold> as white solid (154 mg; yield 63%).</p><p>Compound <bold>2b</bold> (450 mg) was dissolved in anhydrous acetonitrile (8.0 ml), and to this solution were added methyl glycolate (240 &#x003bc;l) and DBU (60 &#x003bc;l). The resulting solution was stirred at room temperature overnight and subsequently acidified by adding an equal volume of 3% trichloroacetic acid (TCA) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>. The solvent was removed under reduced pressure, and the resulting residues were subjected to purification with silica gel column chromatography by using EtOAc/MeOH (85/15, v/v) as the mobile phase. Compound <bold>2c</bold> (182 mg) was obtained as colorless viscous liquid (yield 58%). Hydrolysis of <bold>2c</bold> (150 mg) with 2.0 ml of 0.1 M aqueous NaOH solution rendered <bold>2d</bold> in sodium salt form (142 mg; yield 92%).</p><p><bold>2b</bold>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (300 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d<sub>6</sub></italic>, 25&#x000b0;C, Figure S3): <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> 9.35 (s, 1H, triazolyl H), 8.35 (s, 1H, triazolyl H), 8.27 (s, 1H, H-6), 6.80&#x02013;7.32 (m, 26H, aromatic H of DMTr), 6.22 (t, 1H, H-1&#x02032;, <italic>J</italic> = 6.2 Hz), 4.09 (m, 1H, H-3&#x02032;), 3.82 (m, 1H, H-4&#x02032;), 3.71 (m, 12H, OCH<sub>3</sub> of DMTr), 3.23&#x02013;3.04 (m, 2H, H-5&#x02032; and H-5&#x02033;), 2.23 (m, 1H, H-2&#x02032;), 1.92 (m, 1H, H-2&#x02033;), 2.04 (s, 3H, 5-CH<sub>3</sub>).</p><p>HRMS (ESI): [M + Na]<sup>+</sup> calcd <italic>m/z</italic> 920.3635, found 920.3606.</p><p><bold>2c.</bold><sup>1</sup>H NMR (300 MHz, D<sub>2</sub>O, 25&#x000b0;C, Figure S4): <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> 7.78 (s, 1H, H-6), 6.32 (t, 1H, H-1&#x02032;, <italic>J</italic> = 6.0 Hz), 4.78 (s, 2H, <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CH<sub>2</sub>), 4.51 (m, 1H, H-3&#x02032;), 3.91 (m, 1H, H-4&#x02032;), 3.87 (m, 2H, H-5&#x02032; and H-5&#x02033;), 3.82 (s, 3H, <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-OCH<sub>3</sub>), 2.41 (m, 2H, H-2&#x02032; and H-2&#x02033;), 1.96 (s, 3H, 5-CH<sub>3</sub>).</p><p>HRMS (ESI): [M + H]<sup>+</sup> calcd <italic>m/z</italic> 315.1192, found 315.1186.</p><p><bold>2d</bold>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (300 MHz, D<sub>2</sub>O, 25&#x000b0;C, Figure S5): <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> 7.71 (s, 1H, H-6), 6.34 (t, 1H, H-1&#x02032;, <italic>J</italic> = 6.0 Hz), 4.48 (m, 3H, <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CH<sub>2</sub> and H-3&#x02032;), 4.06 (m, 1H, H-4&#x02032;), 3.87 (m, 2H, H-5&#x02032; and H-5&#x02033;), 2.43 (m, 2H, H-2&#x02032; and H-2&#x02033;), 1.96 (s, 3H, 5-CH<sub>3</sub>).</p><p>HRMS (ESI): [M + H]<sup>+</sup> calcd <italic>m/z</italic> 301.1035, found 301.1034.</p></sec><sec><title>Synthesis of 5&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-(4,4&#x02032;-dimethoxytrityl)-<italic>N</italic>3-methoxycarbonylmethylthymidine (3a, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Scheme 3</xref>)</title><p>Compound <bold>3a</bold> was prepared from <bold>1a</bold> following standard procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Briefly, 450 mg of compound <bold>1a</bold> was dissolved in anhydrous pyridine (10 ml) and the solution was cooled in an ice-bath. 4-Dimethylaminopyridine (DMAP, 10 mg) and dimethoxytrityl chloride (DMTr-Cl, 340 mg) were added, and the resulting solution was stirred at room temperature for 90 min. The reaction was then quenched with methanol (0.5 ml), and the solvent was removed under reduced pressure. The product was isolated by silica gel column chromatography using 15% MeOH in EtOAc as mobile phase, and dried under reduced pressure to give a foam (565 mg; yield: 64%).</p><p><bold>3a.</bold><sup>1</sup>H NMR (300 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d<sub>6</sub></italic>, 25&#x000b0;C, Figure S6): <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> 7.65 (s, 1H, H-6), 7.45&#x02013;6.80 (m, 13H, aromatic H of DMTr), 6.25 (t, 1H, H-1&#x02032;, <italic>J</italic> = 6.3 Hz), 5.38 (s, 1H, 3&#x02032;-OH), 4.58 (s, 2H, <italic>N</italic>3-CH<sub>2</sub>), 4.36 (m, 1H, H-3&#x02032;), 4.04 (m, 1H, H-4&#x02032;), 3.72 (s, 6H, OCH<sub>3</sub> of DMTr), 3.67 (s, 3H, 3-OCH<sub>3</sub>), 3.23 (m, 2H, H-5&#x02032; and H-5&#x02033;), 2.25 (m, 2H, H-2&#x02032; and H-2&#x02033;), 1.99 (s, 3H, 5-CH<sub>3</sub>).</p><p>HRMS (ESI): [M + Na]<sup>+</sup> calcd <italic>m/z</italic> 639.2318, found 639.2300.</p></sec><sec><title>Synthesis of 5&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-(4,4&#x02032;-dimethoxytrityl)-<italic>N</italic>3-methoxycarbonylmethylthymidine-3&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-[(2-cyanoethyl)-<italic>N,N</italic>-diisopropylphosphoramidite] (3b)</title><p>To a flask, which was suspended in an ice bath and contained a solution of compound <bold>3a</bold> (92.4 mg) in dry CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (3.0 ml), was added <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-diisopropylethylamine (DIEA, 52 &#x003bc;l) followed by dropwise addition of 2-cyanoethyl-<italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-diisopropyl chlorophosphoramidite (60 &#x003bc;l). The mixture was stirred at room temperature for 30 min under an argon atmosphere. The reaction was quenched by cooling the mixture in an ice bath followed by slow addition of CH<sub>3</sub>OH (0.40 ml). The solution was quickly extracted with EtOAc (8.0 ml). The organic layer was washed with saturated NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (4.0 ml) and brine (4.0 ml), and dried with anhydrous Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. The solvent was evaporated <italic>in vacuo</italic> to yield <bold>3b</bold> in white foam that was used for ODN synthesis (101 mg; yield: 84%).</p><p><bold>3b.</bold><sup>1</sup>H NMR (300 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d<sub>6</sub></italic>, 25&#x000b0;C, Figure S7): <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> 7.70 (s, 0.5H, H-6, diastereomer 1), 7.65 (s, 0.5H, H-6, diastereomer 2), 7.39&#x02013;6.82 (m, 13H, aromatic H of DMTr), 6.43 (m, 1H, H-1&#x02032;), 4.71 (s, 2H, <italic>N</italic>3-CH<sub>2</sub>), 4.64 (m, 1H, H-3&#x02032;), 4.15 (m, 1H, H-4&#x02032;), 3.80 (s, 6H, OCH<sub>3</sub> of DMTr), 3.76 (s, 3H, 3-OCH<sub>3</sub>), 3.56&#x02013;3.34 (m, 5H, 2H from CH<sub>2</sub>CN, 2H from 2CH and 2H from H-5&#x02032;&#x00026;H-5&#x02033;), 2.59 (m, 2H, OCH<sub>2</sub>), 2.39 (m, 2H, H-2&#x02032; and H-2&#x02033;), 1.46 (s, 3H, 5-CH<sub>3</sub>), 1.15-1.04 (m, 12H, CH<sub>3</sub> from isopropyl). <sup>31</sup>P NMR: <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> 149.9, 149.8.</p><p>HRMS (ESI): [M + Na]<sup>+</sup> calcd <italic>m/z</italic> 839.3397, found 839.3379.</p></sec><sec><title>ODN synthesis</title><p>ODNs (sequences shown in the text) were synthesized on a Beckman Oligo 1000S DNA synthesizer (Fullerton, CA) at 1 &#x003bc;mol scale. The synthesized phosphoramidite building block was dissolved in anhydrous acetonitrile at a concentration of 0.07 M. Standard phosphoramidite building blocks (Glen Research Inc., Sterling, VA) of dA, dC, dG and dT were employed, and a standard ODN assembly protocol was used without any modification.</p><p>Synthesis of the ODNs containing <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT (<bold>3d</bold>) started with <bold>3b</bold> as phosphoramidite building block, after synthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Scheme 3</xref>), the ODNs containing <italic>N</italic>3-methoxycarbonylmethylthymidine were cleaved from the controlled-pore glass (CPG) support with 1.0 M NaOH (3.0 ml) at room temperature for 2 days. Under such conditions, the nucleobase protecting groups were removed and the ester was hydrolyzed to the corresponding carboxylic acid derivative to yield the ODN containing <bold>3c</bold>.</p><p>An <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-triazolyl derivative of standard dT phosphoramidite building block was used for synthesis of the ODNs containing <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT (<bold>4c</bold>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Scheme 4</xref>). After the ODN assembly, the CPG support bearing <bold>4a</bold> was first suspended in anhydrous acetonitrile (3.0 ml). To the solution were then added 50 equivalents of methyl glycolate and 15 equivalents of DBU, and the suspension was stirred at room temperature for 24 h, which offered the CPG support bearing <bold>4b</bold>. The solvent was removed by filtration. The <bold>4b</bold>-containing ODN was hydrolyzed with 0.1 M NaOH (3.0 ml) at room temperature for 3 days to afford <bold>4c</bold>, and in the mean time <bold>4c</bold> was cleaved from the CPG support and deprotected. The beads were then removed, and the solution was neutralized with 0.1 M HCl to pH 7.0 and lyophilized to dryness.</p></sec><sec><title>KDA treatment of calf thymus DNA</title><p>KDA was synthesized via alkaline hydrolysis of ethyl diazoacetate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). The concentration of KDA was estimated by assuming that the hydrolysis reaction was quantitative. Calf thymus DNA (&#x0223c;1.0 mg/ml) was treated with freshly prepared KDA (8 or 20 mM) in PBS buffer (pH 7.3) at 37&#x000b0;C for 8 h. The resulting DNA was isolated by ethanol precipitation, and the recovered pellets were taken up into doubly distilled water.</p></sec><sec><title>Enzymatic digestion of KDA-treated calf thymus DNA</title><p>One unit of nuclease P1, 0.01 unit of calf spleen phosphodiesterase, and 2.5 &#x003bc;l of buffer solution, which contained sodium acetate (300 mM, pH 5.0) and zinc acetate (10 mM), were added to a 20 &#x003bc;l solution of KDA-treated calf thymus DNA. The digestion was continued at 37&#x000b0;C for 6 h. To the digestion mixture were then added 10 units of alkaline phosphatase, 0.05 unit of snake venom phosphodiesterase, and 5 &#x003bc;l of 0.5 M Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 8.9). The digestion was continued at 37&#x000b0;C for 6 h, and the enzymes were removed by chloroform extraction. The resulting aqueous solution was lyophilized to dryness and redissolved in ultra-pure water for LC/MS analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Mass spectrometry (MS) and NMR</title><p>Electrospray ionization-MS (ESI-MS) and tandem MS (MS/MS) experiments were carried out on an LCQ Deca XP ion-trap mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, San Jose, CA). A mixture of acetonitrile and water (50:50, v/v) was used as solvent for electrospray. The spray voltage was 3.0 kV, and the temperature of the heated capillary was maintained at 275&#x000b0;C. High-resolution mass spectra (HRMS) were acquired on an Agilent 6510 Q-TOF LC/MS instrument (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA) equipped with an electrospray ionization (ESI) source. <sup>1</sup>H NMR spectra were recorded at 300 MHz on a Varian Inova 300 NMR spectrometer (Varian Inc., Palo Alto, CA), and <sup>31</sup>P NMR spectra were acquired at 80 MHz on the same instrument.</p><p>2D NMR spectra were recorded in D<sub>2</sub>O using a Varian Unity (Varian, Inc., Palo Alto, CA) spectrometer operating at 500 MHz at 25&#x000b0;C. A triple resonance 5 mm <sup>1</sup>H<sup>13</sup>C<sup>15</sup>N probe was used. Resonance assignments were made based on <sup>1</sup>H&#x02013;<sup>1</sup>H COSY and <sup>1</sup>H&#x02013;<sup>13</sup>C HMBC experiments. The HMBC spectra were acquired using sweep widths of 5006.3 Hz and 30 177.3 Hz for <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C, respectively. The first delay was set to match a 140 Hz coupling constant, and the second delay was set to match a long-range coupling constant of 8 Hz.</p></sec><sec><title>LC/MS</title><p>Coupled liquid chromatography and ESI tandem MS experiments were performed on an Agilent 1100 capillary HPLC pump (Agilent Technologies) and an LTQ linear ion trap mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, San Jose, CA). A 0.5 &#x000d7; 150 mm Zorbax SB-C18 column (5 &#x003bc;m in particle size, Agilent Technologies) was used, and a 0.1% formic acid in water (Solution A) and a 0.1% formic acid in methanol (Solution B) were employed as mobile phases. The ESI spray voltage was 3.0 kV, and the temperature of the heated capillary was maintained at 275&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>HPLC purification</title><p>The purification of ODNs was performed on a Beckman HPLC System (32 Karat software version 3.0, pump module 125) with a UV detector (module 126) monitoring at 260 nm. A 4.6 &#x000d7; 250 mm Apollo C18 column (5 &#x003bc;m in particle size and 300 &#x000c5; in pore size, Alltech Associate Inc., Deerfield, IL) was used, and a 50 mM triethylammonium acetate buffer (TEAA, pH 6.6, Solution A) and a mixture of 50 mM TEAA and acetonitrile (70/30, v/v, Solution B) were employed as mobile phases.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Chemical synthesis of <italic>N</italic>3- and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-carboxymethylthymidine</title><p>To understand the implications of carboxymethylation of thymidine in the diazoacetate-induced mutations observed at A:T base pairs in human <italic>p53</italic> tumor suppressor gene, we set out to assess the carboxyalkylation chemistry of thymidine. To this end, we first synthesized the authentic <italic>N</italic>3- and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-carboxymethylthymidine (<italic>N</italic>3- and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT).</p><p>We introduced the methyl ester derivative of the carboxymethyl functionality to the <italic>N</italic>3 position of thymidine by alkylation with methyl bromoacetate, and treated the resulting compound with 0.5 M NaOH to give the desired <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Scheme 2</xref>a).</p><p>The chemical synthesis of <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT was inspired by the previous synthesis of ODNs bearing an <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-methylthymidine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) and <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Scheme 2</xref>b). We incorporated the 1,2,4-triazolyl moiety to the C4 carbon atom of 3&#x02032;,5&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-di-DMTr-protected thymidine, which, upon treatment with methyl glycolate in the presence of DBU, renders the corresponding methyl ester of the di-DMTr-protected <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT. The DMTr groups in the latter derivative were removed by using 3% TCA in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Scheme 2</xref>b, details shown in Materials and methods section), and the resulting product was incubated with 0.1 M NaOH to give the corresponding carboxylic acid derivative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Scheme 2</xref>).</p><p>The structures of the two synthesized carboxymethylated thymidine derivatives were supported by <sup>1</sup>H NMR and 2D heteronuclear multi-bond correlation (HMBC) measurements. In particular, the two methylene protons in the carboxymethyl functionality of <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT exhibit strong correlation with the C2 and C4 of the thymine ring in the 2D HMBC spectrum, whereas the two corresponding methylene protons in <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT show correlation with the C4, but not the C2, of the thymine ring (Figures S8 and S9). These distinct spectral features support the sites of carboxymethylation in these two thymidine lesions.</p></sec><sec><title>Formation of <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT and <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT in calf thymus DNA upon treatment with KDA</title><p>The availability of the standard <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT and <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT enabled us to assess whether these two lesions can be induced in calf thymus DNA. To this end, we treated calf thymus DNA with potassium diazoacetate, removed the salts from the reaction mixture by ethanol precipitation, digested the DNA with enzymes, and subjected the resulting nucleoside mixture to LC-MS/MS analysis, where we monitored selectively the fragmentation of the [M + H]<sup>+</sup> ion (<italic>m/z</italic> 301) of carboxymethylated thymidines. The selected-ion chromatogram (SIC) for monitoring the formation of the protonated carboxymethylthymine (i.e. <italic>m/z</italic> 185) revealed two peaks with elution time at 27.8 and 29.2 min, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>c). The product-ion spectra averaged from these two peaks showed the formation of a predominant fragment ion of <italic>m/z</italic> 185 (insets in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>c&#x02013;d), which is attributed to form from the elimination of a 2-deoxyribose component. Further fragmentation of this ion (i.e. MS<sup>3</sup> experiment) leads to the facile loss of a water molecule to give the ion of <italic>m/z</italic> 167 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>c&#x02013;d).<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>LC-MS/MS for monitoring the formation of <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT in calf thymus DNA upon treatment with diazoacetate. Shown are the SICs for monitoring the <italic>m/z</italic> 301&#x02192;185 transition, corresponding to the loss of a 2-deoxyribose, from the LC-MS/MS analyses with the injection of: <bold>(a)</bold><italic>N</italic>3-CMdT standard; <bold>(b)</bold><italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT standard; <bold>(c)</bold> enzymatic digestion mixture of calf thymus (ct) DNA treated with 20 mM potassium diazoacetate (KDA, and the LC-MS/MS results from the reaction with 8 mM KDA are shown in Figure S7); <bold>(d)</bold> the sample in (c) with the addition of standard <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT; and <bold>(e)</bold> the sample in (c) with the addition of standard <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn946f1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Tandem mass spectra supporting the formation of <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT in calf thymus DNA. Shown are the MS<sup>3</sup> results, which monitors the further fragmentation of the protonated carboxymethylthymine (<italic>m/z</italic> 185), for: <bold>(a)</bold> standard <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT; <bold>(b)</bold> standard <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT; <bold>(c)</bold> the 27.8 min fraction shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>c; and <bold>(d)</bold> the 29.2 min fraction shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>c. Depicted in the insets are the corresponding MS/MS for the [M + H]<sup>+</sup> ions of the modified nucleosides. The ion of <italic>m/z</italic> 185 found in MS/MS is attributed the elimination of a 2-deoxyribose.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn946f2"/></fig></p><p>We also subjected standard <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT and <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT to LC-MS/MS analysis under the same experimental conditions. It turned out that these two modified nucleosides share the same retention times (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>a&#x02013;c) and the identical product-ion spectra (both MS/MS and MS<sup>3</sup>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) as the two components present in the enzymatic digestion mixture of KDA-treated calf thymus DNA. Moreover, doping the nucleoside mixture arising from the KDA-treated calf thymus DNA with <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT leads to increase in signal for the first peak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>d), similar doping with <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT results in a rise in signal intensity for the later-eluting peak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>e), lending further support that both <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT and <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT could be induced in calf thymus DNA upon KDA treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Incorporation of <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT and <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT into ODNs</title><p>To understand the implications of <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT and <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT in the KDA-induced mutations observed at T:A base pairs, it is important to obtain ODN substrates housing a site-specifically inserted <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT and <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT for future replication and repair studies. Therefore, we developed synthetic methods for the insertion of these two lesions into ODNs at a unique site. In this respect, the phosphoramidite building block of the methyl ester derivative of <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT was prepared from the above-described modified nucleoside following standard procedures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Scheme 3</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). After solid-phase ODN assembly, we cleaved the ODN from the resin and removed the nucleobase protecting groups by treatment with 1.0 M NaOH, which also converted the methyl ester derivative to the corresponding carboxylic acid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>).</p><p>A similar nucleoside conversion strategy as described above for the synthesis of <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT was employed for the synthesis of ODNs housing a site-specifically inserted <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Scheme 4</xref>). The 1,2,4-triazolyl-protected thymidine was incorporated into ODNs by using standard phosphoramidite chemistry, and the triazolyl functionality on thymidine was displaced with methyl glycolate while the ODN was still on the resin. The resin was subsequently treated with 0.1 M NaOH to convert the ester derivative to the corresponding carboxylic acid; such treatment also resulted in the cleavage of the ODN from the solid support and the removal of the nucleobase protecting groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Scheme 4</xref>).</p><p>It is worth noting that alkaline conditions were employed for the above conversion from methyl ester to the corresponding carboxylic acid and for the nucleobase deprotection, it is important to assess the stability of the lesion-carrying ODNs under these basic conditions. Our LC-MS/MS analyses showed that while the dodecameric ODN containing <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT is stable under the alkaline conditions (1.0 M NaOH for 24 h), the corresponding <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT-bearing ODN is not very stable under strong alkaline conditions. Thus, we treated the ODN-carrying solid support with 0.1 M NaOH for 36 h to facilitate the above ester-to-acid conversion and the nucleobase deprotection. In this context, our LC-MS analysis showed that approximately 13% of the ODN has lost the carboxymethyl group to produce the corresponding unmodified thymidine-containing ODN. The thymidine and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT-bearing ODNs, however, can be resolved by HPLC.</p><p>The ODNs obtained from the above-described procedures were characterized by ESI-MS and MS/MS to confirm their sequence and the location of carboxymethylation. Taking the characterizations of the d(ATGGCGXGCTAT) (where &#x02018;X&#x02019; represents <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT) as an example, we found that the measured <italic>m/z</italic> values for the multiply deprotonated ions are consistent with their calculated ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, inset). In addition, MS/MS of the [M &#x02013; 3H]<sup>3&#x02013;</sup> ion (<italic>m/z</italic> 1243.9, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>) gives a series of sequence ions, allowing us to establish unambiguously that there is an <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT at the seventh position in this ODN counting from the 5&#x02032; terminus. Upon collisional activation in a mass spectrometer, an ODN undergoes cleavages at the <italic>N</italic>-glycosidic bond and the 3&#x02032; C&#x02013;O bond of the same nucleoside to form [a<italic><sub>n</sub></italic> &#x02013; Base] and its complementary w<sub>n</sub> ions, which carry the 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; termini of the ODN, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Because of the low proton affinity of thymine, the <italic>N</italic>-glycosidic bond in thymidine is usually not susceptible to cleavage and, as a result, chain cleavage is often not observed at the 3&#x02032; C&#x02013;O bond of this nucleoside (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, we observed [a<sub>3</sub> &#x02013; G], [a<sub>4</sub> &#x02013; G], [a<sub>5</sub> &#x02013; C], [a<sub>6</sub> &#x02013; G], [a<sub>8</sub> &#x02013; G], [a<sub>9</sub> &#x02013; C], [a<sub>11</sub> &#x02013; A], w<sub>3</sub>, w<sub>4</sub>, w<sub>5</sub>, w<sub>6</sub>, w<sub>7</sub>, w<sub>8</sub>, w<sub>9</sub> and w<sub>11</sub> ions. The observed masses of w<sub>6</sub>, w<sub>7</sub>, w<sub>8</sub>, w<sub>9</sub> and w<sub>11</sub> ions are 58 Da higher in masses than the calculated masses of the corresponding fragments for the unmodified ODN, whereas the masses of the w<sub>3</sub>, w<sub>4</sub>, w<sub>5</sub> ions are the same the calculated masses for the corresponding fragments from the unmodified ODN, supporting the presence of an <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT at the seventh position of this ODN. The same conclusion can be drawn based on the observed masses of the [a &#x02013; Base] series fragment ions. Likewise, we characterized the synthesized <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT-containing ODN by ESI-MS and MS/MS analyses (spectra not shown).<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The product-ion spectrum of the ESI-produced [M &#x02013; 3H]<sup>3&#x02013;</sup> ions of d(ATGGCGXGCTAT), where &#x02018;X&#x02019; represents <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT. Illustrated in the insets is the negative-ion ESI-MS for the modified ODN.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn946f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Scheme 1.</label><caption><p>The formation of diazoacetate and its modification of 2&#x02032;-deoxyguanosine.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn946f4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Scheme 2.</label><caption><p>The chemical synthesis of <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn946f5"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Scheme 3.</label><caption><p>The incorporation of <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT into ODNs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn946f6"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Scheme 4.</label><caption><p>The incorporation of <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT into ODNs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn946f7"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Humans are exposed to NOCs from both endogenous and exogenous sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>), and a recent epidemiological study found a significant correlation between the human exposure toward endogenous NOCs and the risk of developing non-cardia gastric cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Endogenously induced NOCs can be metabolically activated to give diazoacetate, which can result in the alkylation of DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). An earlier study by Zurlo <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) showed that the exposure of pancreatic acinar cells to <italic>O</italic>-diazoacetyl-<sc>l</sc>-serine, which can be metabolically activated to give diazoacetate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Scheme 1</xref>), could induce the formation of 7-carboxymethylguanine in DNA. It was also observed that the treatment of calf thymus DNA with potassium diazoacetate or NOCs could result in the formation of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6 B7 B8 B9">6&#x02013;9</xref>). In addition, <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG was detected at a level of three to eight lesions per 10<sup>7</sup> nucleosides in the blood DNA of healthy human subjects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), and humans consuming red meat have elevated level of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-CMdG in colonic exfoliated cells than control group consuming vegetarian diet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Moreover, the propagation of diazoacetate-treated, human <italic>p53</italic> gene-containing shuttle vector in yeast cells gave similar mutation pattern at non-CpG sites as that found in human stomach and colon cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Together, these previous studies established a strong link between human exposure to <italic>N</italic>-nitroso compounds and the carboxymethylation of DNA and suggested that the exposure to <italic>N</italic>-nitroso compounds may constitute an important etiological factor in human cancer development.</p><p>Aside from the above two dG adducts, the diazoacetate-mediated carboxymethylation chemistry of other nucleosides in DNA has not been assessed. Shuttle vector studies revealed that diazoacetate treatment can also lead to significant mutations at T:A base pairs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), suggesting that diazoacetate can also lead to the modification of thymine and/or adenine in DNA. Here, we synthesized authentic <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT, and demonstrated, by using LC-MS/MS, that indeed these two lesions could be induced and they constitute the main thymidine products formed in calf thymus DNA upon exposure to diazoacetate. The methods for the syntheses of <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT can be readily adapted for the preparation of the corresponding stable isotope-labeled derivatives, which facilitates the future LC-MS/MS quantification of these lesions formed <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> by using the isotope dilution technique. In this context, it is worth noting LC-MS/MS also revealed the carboxymethylation of 2&#x02032;-deoxyadenosine in calf thymus DNA. The chemical nature of the carboxymethylated adenine is currently under investigation.</p><p>The formation of <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT in calf thymus DNA calls for the examination of the replication and repair of these lesions. To carry out such studies, we need to obtain ODN substrates housing a site-specifically incorporated <italic>N</italic>3-CMdT and <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-CMdT. Thus, we also developed facile synthetic methods for the site-specific incorporation of these two lesions into ODNs. In this respect, the methods facilitated the preparation of 12-mer ODNs in reasonably good yield. After HPLC separation and desalting, we were able to obtain &#x0223c;100 nmol of the lesion-bearing ODNs from a 1 &#x000b5;mol scale synthesis. Thus, the synthetic strategy facilitates the availability of sufficient ODN substrates for future NMR structural studies. The lesion-bearing substrates can also be employed to construct, by enzymatic ligation, longer lesion-bearing ODNs for <italic>in vitro</italic> DNA repair studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>) and damage-containing shuttle vectors for <italic>in vivo</italic> replication and repair studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkn946/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p></sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p>This work was supported by the <funding-source>National Institutes of Health</funding-source> (Grant No <award-id>R01 CA101864</award-id>). Funding for open access charge: <funding-source>National Institutes of Health</funding-source> (<award-id>R01 CA101864</award-id>).</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>[Supplementary Data]</title></caption><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="gkn946_index.html"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkn946_1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>The authors want to thank Dr Dan Borchardt for assistance with the HMBC experiments.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tricker</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>N-nitroso compounds and man: sources of exposure, endogenous formation and occurrence in body fluids</article-title><source>Eur. J. Cancer Prev.</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9306073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jakszyn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Agudo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Luben</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeing</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Giudice</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Palli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Saieva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endogenous versus exogenous exposure to <italic>N</italic>-nitroso compounds and gastric cancer risk in the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition (EPIC-EURGAST) study</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1497</fpage><lpage>1501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16571648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>WF</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Charnley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Newberne</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wogan</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carcinogenicity in rats of the nitrosated bile acid conjugates <italic>N</italic>-nitrosoglycocholic acid and <italic>N</italic>-nitrosotaurocholic acid</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>1985</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3971381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puju</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Falchuk</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Thilly</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutagenicity of N-nitroso bile acid conjugates in <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> and diploid human lymphoblasts</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>1982</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>2601</fpage><lpage>2604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7044521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DEG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wishnok</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>N</italic>-nitroso bile acid conjugates. 1. Synthesis, chemical reactivity and mutagenic activity</article-title><source>J. Org. Chem.</source><year>1981</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>2092</fpage><lpage>2096</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Margison</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrosated glycine derivatives as a potential source of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-methylguanine in DNA</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9012456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jukes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of concomitant formation of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-carboxymethyl- and <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-methyl-2&#x02032;-deoxyguanosine in DNA exposed to nitrosated glycine derivatives using a combined immunoaffinity/HPLC method</article-title><source>Chem. Res. Toxicol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9894025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairhurst</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Challis</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, characterization, and immunochemical detection of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-(carboxymethyl)-2'-deoxyguanosine: a DNA adduct formed by nitrosated glycine derivatives</article-title><source>Chem. Res. Toxicol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>652</fpage><lpage>659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9208171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cupid</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-carboxymethyl-2'-deoxyguanosine in DNA following reaction of nitric oxide with glycine and in human blood DNA using a quantitative immunoslot blot assay</article-title><source>Chem. Res. Toxicol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15025499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Longnecker</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Curphey</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adenocarcinoma of the pancreas in azaserine-treated rats</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>1975</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>2249</fpage><lpage>2258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1097106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zurlo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Curphey</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Longnecker</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of 7-carboxymethylguanine in DNA from pancreatic acinar cells exposed to azaserine</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>1982</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1286</fpage><lpage>1288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7060007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pignatelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malaveille</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Runswick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does increased endogenous formation of <italic>N</italic>-nitroso compounds in the human colon explain the association between red meat and colon cancer?</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>1996</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8631138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandaletova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Red meat enhances the colonic formation of the DNA adduct <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-carboxymethyl guanine: implications for colorectal cancer risk</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1859</fpage><lpage>1865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Driscoll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Macpherson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Karran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cytotoxicity of DNA carboxymethylation and methylation by the model carboxymethylating agent azaserine in human cells</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>1999</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1855</fpage><lpage>1862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10469634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottschalg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potassium diazoacetate-induced <italic>p53</italic> mutations in vitro in relation to formation of <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-carboxymethyl- and <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-methyl-2'-deoxyguanosine DNA adducts: relevance for gastrointestinal cancer</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16926174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and thermodynamic studies of oligodeoxyribonucleotides containing tandem lesions of thymidine glycol and 8-oxo-2&#x02019;-deoxyguanosine</article-title><source>Chem. Res. Toxicol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16780363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gait</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Oligonucleotide Synthesis: A Practical Approach.</source><year>1984</year><publisher-loc>Oxford, England</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IRL Press Limited</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hambly</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomasoni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of potassium diazoacetate on human peripheral lymphocytes, human adenocarcinoma colon Caco-2 cells, and rat primary colon cells in the comet assay</article-title><source>Teratog. Carcinog. Mutagen.</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10332810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Swann</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method for the solid phase synthesis of oligodeoxynucleotides containing <italic>O</italic><sup>4</sup>-alkylthymine</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1990</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>4061</fpage><lpage>4065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2377451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y-Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of DNA containing <italic>O</italic><sup>6</sup>-carboxymethylguanine</article-title><source>Tetrahedron</source><year>2000</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>6075</fpage><lpage>6081</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLuckey</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Berkel</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Glish</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tandem mass spectrometry of small, multiply charged oligonucleotides</article-title><source>J. Am. Soc. Mass Spectrom.</source><year>1992</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>KX</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramanathan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and fragmentation mechanisms of isomeric T-rich oligodeoxynucleotides: a comparison of four tandem mass spectrometric methods</article-title><source>J. Am. Soc. Mass Spectrom.</source><year>1998</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9879378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition and incision of oxidative intrastrand cross-link lesions by UvrABC nuclease</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>10739</fpage><lpage>10746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16939226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Essigmann</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assays for determining lesion bypass efficiency and mutagenicity of site-specific DNA lesions in vivo</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>408</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16793359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient and accurate bypass of <italic>N</italic><sup>2</sup>-(1-carboxyethyl)-2&#x02032;-deoxyguanosine by DinB DNA polymerase <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>8679</fpage><lpage>8684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18562283</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>