<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Evol Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Evol. Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Evolutionary Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2148</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19111070</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2632675</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2148-8-343</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-8-343</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Differential selection on gene translation efficiency between the filamentous fungus <italic>Ashbya gossypii </italic>and yeasts</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Huifeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>jianghf3@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A2"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>zhangyue@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>sunj03@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A4"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>wwang@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A5"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Zhenglong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>zg27@cornell.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Division of Nutritional Sciences, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>CAS-Max Planck Junior Research Group, State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution, Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS), Kunming, Yunnan 650223, PR China</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Graduate School of Chinese Academy Sciences, Beijing 100039, PR China</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>State Key Laboratory of Cellular and Molecular Evolution, Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming 650223, Yunnan Province, PR China</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2008 Jiang et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Jiang et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/8/343"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The filamentous fungus <italic>Ashbya gossypii </italic>grows into a multicellular mycelium that is distinct from the unicellular morphology of its closely related yeast species. It has been proposed that genes important for cell cycle regulation play central roles for such phenotypic differences. Because <italic>A. gossypii </italic>shares an almost identical set of cell cycle genes with the typical yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, the differences might occur at the level of orthologous gene regulation. Codon usage patterns were compared to identify orthologous genes with different gene regulation between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and nine closely related yeast species.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Here we identified 3,151 orthologous genes between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and nine yeast species. Two groups of genes with significant differences in codon usage (gene translation efficiency) were identified between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeasts. 333 genes (Group I) and 552 genes (Group II) have significantly higher translation efficiency in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeasts, respectively. Functional enrichment and pathway analysis show that Group I genes are significantly enriched with cell cycle functions whereas Group II genes are biased toward metabolic functions.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Because translation efficiency of a gene is closely related to its functional importance, the observed functional distributions of orthologous genes with different translation efficiency might account for phenotypic differentiation between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeast species. The results shed light on the mechanisms for pseudohyphal growth in pathogenic yeast species.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Filamentous and yeast-like growths are two ways for fungi to propagate in nature. Under normal growth conditions, filamentous fungi grow as multicellular mycelium but yeasts form unicellular colonies. Most species in the clade <italic>Saccharomycotina </italic>are yeasts. In some special environments, these species can switch to pseudohyphal growth that is morphologically similar to filamentous growth, but they can not form real hyphal filaments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. <italic>Ashbya gossypii</italic>, however, is classified as a filamentous fungus because it forms natural hyphal filaments for most of its life cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. What the nature of the molecular differences between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeasts is that led to such a phenotypic divergence remains an open question. It has been proposed that the divergence might result from a modified cell cycle processes in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. However, comparative genomics studies reveal that <italic>A. gossypii </italic>shares an almost identical set of cell cycle genes with the typical yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Although loss or gain of genes among different species often play important roles in phenotypic diversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], divergence of regulation in orthologous genes can also contribute significantly to this process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The fact that <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and its closely related yeasts share a very similar set of cell cycle genes prompts us to investigate whether these genes have unique regulation patterns in <italic>A. gossypii</italic>.</p><p>Genetic codes exhibit significant usage bias. Selection for gene translation efficiency is the most common Darwinian explanation for codon usage bias. Under this scenario, codons corresponding to abundant tRNA would be preferentially used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Natural selection biases such preferred codons so as to enhance accuracy and speed of protein synthesis in highly expressed genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Therefore, differential translation efficiency reflects protein expression difference, which in return can indicate differential functional requirements for these proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Therefore, divergence of translation efficiency could reveal orthologous gene functional differentiation across species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. By comparing codon usage patterns for orthologous genes between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and nine yeast species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], we show in this study that in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>genes with significantly higher translation efficiency are enriched in cell cycle processes, whereas genes with significantly lower translation efficiency are enriched in metabolic processes. Both these findings could account for phenotypic differentiation between multicellular <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and unicellular yeasts, and would shed light on the evolutionary processes that enable pseudohyphal growth in pathogenic yeast species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>tRNA adaptation index (tAI)</title><p>Within a genome, codon usage, which matches tRNA pool of the organism, is an important indicator for gene translational efficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. In order to detect the differences in gene translational efficiency between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeasts, a gene matrix containing 3,151 orthologous gene groups for <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and nine yeast species was constructed. Species-specific tRNA adaptation index (tAI), a measurement that evaluates translation efficiency of coding sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], was predicted for each gene based on tRNA pool in that species. Because estimation of codon usage can be affected by species-specific factors such as genome-wide GC contents (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>), in order to have cross species comparisons, we normalized the tAI value of each gene by the median tAI value of all studied orthologous genes in the same species. The tAI values from nine yeast species were used to calculate the likelihood of observing the tAI value for <italic>A. gossypii </italic>gene in each orthologous gene group.</p><p>Based on statistical significance at the 95% confidence level, we divided all orthologous genes into three categories. Group I: 333 genes showing significantly higher tAI values in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>than in yeasts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), group II: 552 genes showing significantly lower tAI values in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>than in yeasts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>) and group III: the rest of 2,266 genes that have no obviously different tAI values between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeasts (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref> for tAI values of genes in Group III). Under the assumption that translation efficiency is a selected trait, genes in group I would have higher expression and be translated more efficiently in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>than their orthologous genes in yeasts, whereas genes in group II would show the opposite pattern.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>tAI profile of orthologous gene in Group I and II</bold>. A) tAI values for orthologous genes in Group I (tAI values in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>are significantly higher than those in yeasts); B) tAI values for orthologous genes in Group II (tAI values in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>are significantly lower than those in yeasts). The scale of tAI values is shown to the right of the figure. (Agos: <italic>Ashbya gossypii</italic>; Sces: <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae; </italic>Spar:<italic>Saccharomyces paradoxus; </italic>Smik:<italic>Saccharomyces mikatae; </italic>Sbay:<italic>Saccharomyces bayanus; </italic>Cgla:<italic>Candida glabrata; </italic>Kpol:<italic>Kluyveromyces polysporus; </italic>Kwal:<italic>Kluyveromyces waltii</italic>, Sklu: <italic>Saccharomyces kluyveri; </italic>Klac:<italic>Kluyveromyces lactis</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-8-343-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>GO (Gene Ontology) functional enrichment analysis</title><p>Different tAI values for orthologous genes indicate the distinct functional importance of these genes in compared species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Using GO terms in <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>as reference, we characterized functional enrichment for Group I and Group II genes, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref> (See additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref> for the table list of these functional categories), Group I genes display significant enrichment in functions such as cell cycle regulation, mitosis and cytoskeleton organization. Interestingly, these functions have been hypothesized to be important for the unique life style in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. In addition, Group I genes also show enrichment of functions that are related with reproduction process, spore wall assembly and developmental process. By contrast, Group II genes show functional enrichment in amino acid and steroid biosynthesis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). Different from above two groups, Group III genes do not show any functional enrichment (data not shown).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Distribution of enriched GO functions for genes in Group I and II</bold>. A) Biological functions with enriched gene representation in Group I; B) Biological functions with enriched gene representation in Group II. The edges between functional categories represent their hierarchical relationships in Gene Ontology annotation database. The colour of each box denotes <italic>P</italic>-value from GO term finder software (See additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref> for the table list of these functional categories with FDR analysis).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-8-343-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>KEGG (Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes) pathway analysis</title><p>In order to further see the impact of differences in gene translational efficiency, we assigned all studied orthologous genes into identified pathways according to KEGG annotation for <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]; 897 genes (75% of all annotated genes in KEGG pathways) are included in our orthologous matrix. Among them, 79 genes belong to Group I and 219 genes belong to Group II. A Chi-square test was used to estimate distribution bias for each pathway. With a cut-off <italic>P </italic>value of 0.01, six pathways show significant distribution bias (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Consistent with gene ontology analysis, two of the three pathways enriched with Group I genes (cell cycle pathway and ubiquitin mediated proteolysis) are related to cell cycle regulation. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, cell cycle genes that belong to Group I scatter at each phase of cell division, so the enhanced translation efficiency, hence the increased importance of these genes, would influence the whole cell division process in <italic>A. gossypii</italic>. It is noteworthy that some cell cycle genes also belong to Group II. Interestingly, almost half of them are related with two protein complexes (condensin and mini-chromosome maintenance complex, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Group II genes are enriched in metabolic processes such as lysine biosynthesis, steroid biosynthesis and aminoacyl-tRNA biosynthesis. At 95% confidence level another six biosynthesis pathways are enriched with Group II genes (See additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>: Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> for the details of these pathways).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>KEGG pathways that are enriched in Group I or Group II genes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Pathway Name</th><th align="center">KEGG ID</th><th align="center">Total gene number</th><th align="center">Gene num. in Group I</th><th align="center">Gene num. in Group II</th><th align="center">Gene num. in Group III</th><th align="center"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Cell cycle &#x02013; yeast </bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td align="center">04111</td><td align="center">83</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">52</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Basal transcription factors </bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td align="center">03022</td><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Ubiquitin mediated proteolysis </bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td align="center">04120</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Lysine biosynthesis </bold><sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td align="center">00300</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Biosynthesis of steroids </bold><sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td align="center">00100</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Aminoacyl-tRNA biosynthesis </bold><sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td align="center">00970</td><td align="center">34</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>a: Enriched with Group I genes; b: Enriched with Group II genes.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Cell cycle pathways in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic></bold>. The pathway figure was downloaded from KEGG database. Genes from Group I, II and III were denoted in red, blue and light green, respectively. Genes with dark green were not included in our orthologous matrix because they might be missing from one of the studied species.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-8-343-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Comparative analysis with experimentally confirmed genes in <italic>A. gossypii</italic></title><p>The above observations are all based on functional annotations for genes in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. In order to confirm that genes with significantly higher tAI values in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>are truly enriched in cell cycle pathway genes, we identified all studied genes in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>according to NCBI database. Twenty one genes in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>were confirmed to be related with cell cycle processes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Eight of them have significantly higher tAI values in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>(Group I, 333 gene), the other 13 genes do not show significant differences of tAI values among species (Group III, 2,266 genes). Fisher's exact test indicates that these confirmed cell cycle genes in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>are also enriched in Group I (<italic>P </italic>= 0.003).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Experimentally confirmed cell cycle genes in <italic>A. gossypii</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Gene name in <italic>A. gossypii</italic></th><th align="left">Orthologous ORF name in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic></th><th align="right"><bold><italic>P</italic>-value </bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></th><th align="left">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">AgCDC16</td><td align="left">YKL022C</td><td align="right">0.000243</td><td align="left">Gladfelter et al. 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgCDC42</td><td align="left">YLR229C</td><td align="right">0.00143</td><td align="left">Wendland et al. 2001 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgCDC24</td><td align="left">YAL041W</td><td align="right">0.001578</td><td align="left">Wendland et al. 2001 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgCDC20</td><td align="left">YGL116W</td><td align="right">0.001869</td><td align="left">Gladfelter et al. 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgDOC1</td><td align="left">YGL240W</td><td align="right">0.004167</td><td align="left">Gladfelter et al. 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgRHO4</td><td align="left">YKR055W</td><td align="right">0.004777</td><td align="left">Wendland et al. 2005 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgCLB5</td><td align="left">YPR120C</td><td align="right">0.007449</td><td align="left">Hungerbuehler et al. 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgPDS1</td><td align="left">YDR113C</td><td align="right">0.048015</td><td align="left">Gladfelter et al. 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgBEM2</td><td align="left">YER155C</td><td align="right">0.07874</td><td align="left">Wendland 2000a [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgSWE1</td><td align="left">YJL187C</td><td align="right">0.117698</td><td align="left">Helfer et al. 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgBEM3</td><td align="left">YPL115C</td><td align="right">0.122939</td><td align="left">Wendland et al. 2005 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgCDH1</td><td align="left">YGL003C</td><td align="right">0.127995</td><td align="left">Gladfelter et al. 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgRSR1</td><td align="left">YGR152C</td><td align="right">0.148734</td><td align="left">Bauer et al. 2004 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgCDC23</td><td align="left">YHR166C</td><td align="right">0.198647</td><td align="left">Gladfelter et al. 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgBOI1</td><td align="left">YBL085W</td><td align="right">0.2807</td><td align="left">Knechtle et al. 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgBNI1</td><td align="left">YNL271C</td><td align="right">0.281555</td><td align="left">Schmitz et al. 2005 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgSIC1</td><td align="left">YLR079W</td><td align="right">0.787007</td><td align="left">Gladfelter et al. 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgRHO1</td><td align="left">YPR165W</td><td align="right">0.800873</td><td align="left">Walther et al. 2005 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgSPA2</td><td align="left">YLL021W</td><td align="right">0.812361</td><td align="left">Knechtle et al. 2003 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgBUD3</td><td align="left">YCL014W</td><td align="right">0.821338</td><td align="left">Wendland 2003 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AgCYK1</td><td align="left">YPL242C</td><td align="right">0.90517</td><td align="left">Wendland 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>a: Comparison of tAI values between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and other yeast species.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Codon usage bias in <italic>A. gossypii</italic></title><p>Among studied species, <italic>A. gossypii </italic>has the highest genome-wide GC content (0.53), while the GC contents in other species are from 0.35 to 0.46 (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1A</xref>). Correlation coefficients of codon usage between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and other nine species show strongly positive relationship with their GC contents, indicating that GC content might intensively shape codon usage in <italic>A. gossypii</italic>. Relationships of GC contents (estimated by GC3s: GC content at the third site of each codon) and codon usage bias (measured by Nc: effective number of codons which is a parameter measuring overall gene codon bias) on further analysis in all studies species show us that the higher GC3s is, the stronger correlation between GC3s and Nc is (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1B</xref>). For all studied orthologs in <italic>A. gossypii</italic>, GC3s is strongly correlated with Nc, but not strongly associated with tAI and CAI (codon adaptive index) (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1C</xref>), indicating that change of GC content might have a larger impact on gene Nc than on tAI and CAI values. As in Man and Piple [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], we obtained low correlations between tAI and Nc, and between CAI and Nc (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1C</xref>), which might be due to the dramatic change of GC content, thus Nc values in <italic>A. gossypii</italic>. Nevertheless, both correlations are still statistically significant, while tAI and CAI show a very strong positive correlation in this species (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1C</xref>). Because tAI values for orthologs among studied species were normalized to remove the impact caused by some factors at genome level including GC content, it would still be an accurate indicator for expression level, thus the importance of <italic>A. gossypii </italic>genes during evolution.</p></sec><sec><title>Possible effect of protein size on gene translation efficiency</title><p>Natural selection biases synonymous codon usage to enhance accuracy and speed of protein synthesis in various organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Differential gene translation efficiency reflects differences in functional requirements for proteins among organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. However, as previously reported, the negative correlation between translation efficiency and gene length indicates that translation efficiency could also be affected by protein size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. We tested if the different gene translation efficiencies observed between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeast species could be caused by protein size deviation in different species. At first, we computed correlation coefficient of the tAI difference for each orthologs between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and other nine yeasts and their protein size differences. To do this, for each orthologous gene, we calculated a protein size ratio, defined as the protein size of orthologous gene in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>(average protein size was used if two or more genes are in the same orthologous group) divided by the average protein size of orthologous genes in nine yeast species. Pearson correlation coefficient between tAI difference and protein size difference doesn't show significant association between the two (<italic>r </italic>= 0.035, <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003e; 0.05). In addition, Distributions of protein size ratio for genes in Group I and II are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>. There are no significant differences in protein size between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeast species for both Group I and Group II genes, indicating that our observations are not the results of protein size change of orthologous genes during evolution.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Protein size distribution for Group I and Group II genes</bold>. Protein size ratio for a gene was defined as the length of this gene in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>divided by the average length of its orthologous genes in nine yeast species. The solid and dashed lines represent the distributions of protein size ratio for Group I and Group II genes, respectively. Both distributions center around 1, indicating that there are no protein length differences between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and studied yeast species for both Group I and Group II genes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-8-343-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Higher translation efficiency of cell cycle genes in <italic>A. gossypii</italic></title><p>Comparison of translation efficiencies for orthologous genes should uncover regulation divergence, and thus the differential functional importance of those genes in diverged species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Here by a comparative genomic approach, we identified two groups of orthologous genes showing differential translation efficiency between the filamentous fungus <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and its closely related yeast species. Genes in Group I have significantly higher translation efficiency in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>than those in yeasts. Functional analysis indicates that these genes are significantly enriched in cell cycle processes. Subsequent analysis of known pathways and experimentally studied genes in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>support such conclusion. Because enhanced translation efficiency indicates increased functional requirement for a gene, our results suggest that the roles of cell cycle genes might be substantially different between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeasts. This suggestion is consistent with the observation that cell cycle processes, such as polar growth modes, cell cycle control and asynchronous nuclear division, are more complex in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>than those in yeast species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Further experimental investigations for regulatory changes of cell cycle genes in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>could provide more insights into this conclusion.</p><p>For most pathogenic yeasts, transition from yeast form to filamentous form (pseudohyphal growth) is a key mark for their pathogenicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. It has been reported that cell cycle genes play important roles in the morphological transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Micro-array experiment also shows that cell cycle genes are more up-regulated in <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>filamentous form than are those in yeast form [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Our results indicate that cell cycle genes possess higher translational efficiency, and thus might be functionally more important, in filamentous fungus than those in yeast. Therefore, understanding species difference between filamentous fungus and yeasts could be helpful for illustrating mechanisms underlying filamentous growth of pathogenic yeasts.</p></sec><sec><title>Higher translation efficiency for metabolic genes in yeasts</title><p>Genes in Group II have significantly lower translation efficiency in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>than those in yeasts. Functional enrichment analysis indicates that these genes are enriched for metabolic process, such as amino acid and steroid biosynthesis. This functional distribution might be associated with rapid cell growth in yeasts through fermentative life style. All yeast species studied can carry out fermentative growth under anaerobic or aerobic conditions, but <italic>A. gossypii </italic>can only conduct aerobic respiration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. The cell division rate is usually much faster for fermentative than for respiratory growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. For eukaryotic organisms, cell size is an important control at check points for cell division [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. In order to attain critical size, cells need to synthesize cellular components much more rapidly during fermentative than during respiratory growth. Therefore the metabolic processes should be in greater demand in yeasts than that in <italic>A. gossypii</italic>. The difference in metabolic rate could lead to differential translation efficiency for metabolic genes between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeasts.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Comparative studies revealed that more than 95% genes in multicellular organism <italic>A. gossypii </italic>share orthologs with unicellular organism <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. It has been proposed that different growth modes between these species were controlled by a very similar gene set [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Our studies of orthologous genes among <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and several yeast species show higher translation efficiency of cell cycle genes in <italic>A. gossypii</italic>, which is consistent with more complicated cell cycle processes in this multicellular organism. On the other hand, our results are also consistent with the faster growth of unicellular yeasts, which leads to greater demands of gene products for metabolic processes. Emergence of multicellular organisms was one of the most profound developmental transitions in the history of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Our results in this study, and further investigation for the difference between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeast species might also be important for understanding this process.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Species and sequence data</title><p>According to the phylogenetic tree in Fitzpatrick et al. (2006) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], 12 genomes have been sequenced in the clade <italic>Saccharomycotina</italic>. Among these species, only <italic>Ashbya gossypii </italic>is classified as filamentous fungus. For the remaining 11 yeast species, nine were used in our study (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae, Saccharomyces paradoxus, Saccharomyces mikatae, Saccharomyces bayanus, Candida glabrata, Kluyveromyces polysporus, Kluyveromyces waltii, Saccharomyces kluyveri</italic>, and <italic>Kluyveromyces lactis</italic>). <italic>Saccharomyces kudriavzevii </italic>and <italic>Saccharomyces castellii </italic>were not used due to their low sequencing coverage. The protein, coding and genomic sequences for recently sequenced <italic>K. polysporus </italic>are from Scannell <italic>et al </italic>2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Sequences for other species were downloaded from Fungal Comparative Genomics database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] and National Center for Biotechnology Information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Orthologous matrix</title><p>Using InParanoid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] program, orthologs between every two species were identified. According to the results from InParanoid, we used MultiParanoid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>] to generate orthologous matrix among all studied species. Each row in the matrix corresponds to an orthlogous gene shared by all studied species and each column to a species. Duplicated genes detected by InParanoid in one species were classified into the same orthologous group. Only orthologous groups which contain at least one gene for each species were used in our study. As a result, an orthologous matrix with 3,151 rows (genes) and 10 columns (species) was generated.</p></sec><sec><title>tRNA adaptation index (tAI)</title><p>First, we used tRNAscan-SE software (version 1.1) to predict copy numbers for all tRNA genes (tRNA gene pool) in each genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The tRNA pools among closely related species are conserved (See additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref> for the original data used to perform this analysis) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. For species with relatively low genome sequencing quality, we used tRNA pools from their closely related species, a same approach as in Ref 15: the predicted tRNA pool from <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>was used to replace the ones in <italic>S. byanus, S. paradoxus</italic>, <italic>S. mikatae </italic>and the tRNA pool from <italic>K. lactis </italic>was used to replace the ones in <italic>K. waltii </italic>and <italic>S. kluyveri</italic>.</p><p>Second, given coding sequence for a gene, we used a modified tAI.R program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] to estimate its tAI value in each species according to the tRNA pools (we kept all codons for methionines expect the start codons). When an orthologous group contains more than one gene in a species, the average tAI value of these genes was used for that species.</p><p>Finally, we normalized tAI value of each gene by median tAI value for all studied genes in the same species. For each orthologous group, we used the tAI values for nine yeast species to construct a normal distribution model, which was then used to estimate the probability of observing tAI value for the <italic>A. gossypii </italic>gene. Under 95% confidence level, we identified 333 (Group I) and 552 genes (Group II) for which orthologs from <italic>A. gossypii </italic>have significantly higher and lower tAI values than those from yeasts, respectively. The rest 2,266 genes without significantly different tAI values between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and yeasts were classified in Group III.</p></sec><sec><title>Functional enrichment analysis</title><p>GO (Gene Ontology) annotations of <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>genes were used for our analysis. We identified functional enrichment of genes in each group (group I, II and III) by GO term finder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. The functional enrichments were determined at <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.05. Pathway information for <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>was downloaded from KEGG database <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link>. All studied orthologous genes in <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>were mapped onto these pathways. For each pathway, a chi-square test was used to calculate the probability of gene number distribution among each group.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>HJ and ZG designed the study. HJ and YZ analyzed the data. HJ, WW and ZG wrote the manuscript. JS prepared the figures and checked the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>GC content and codon usage in <italic>A. gossypii</italic>.</bold> Figure A shows the relationship between GC content and codon usage. X axis is the GC content for each species. Y axis is the correlation of whole genomic codon usage measured by RSCU (Relative Synonymous Codon Usage) between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and other nine yeasts (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>). Figure B, using codonW <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://codonw.sourceforge.net/">http://codonw.sourceforge.net/</ext-link>, we calculated values for GC3s and Nc and obtained their correlation efficiencies in all studied species. X axis is the GC contents for each species. Y axis is the correlation coefficients between GC3s and Nc for each studied species. Figure C shows correlations among four indexes: tAI, GC3s, Nc and CAI in <italic>A. gossypii</italic>. All ribosomal protein gene sequences in <italic>A. gossypii </italic>were used as reference set for CAI calculation. Pearson correlation coefficients among these parameters were calculated. The lower triangle of table contains the Pearson's correlation coefficients and the upper triangle of table contains <italic>P</italic>-values</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-8-343-S1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>tAI values for orthologous genes in Group III.</bold> The figure shows the tAI values pattern for orthologous genes among all species in Group III (no significant tAI values between <italic>A. gossypii </italic>and other yeast species). The scale of tAI values is shown to the right of the figure. (Agos: <italic>Ashbya gossypii</italic>; Sces: <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae; </italic>Spar:<italic>Saccharomyces paradoxus; </italic>Smik:<italic>Saccharomyces mikatae; </italic>Sbay:<italic>Saccharomyces bayanus; </italic>Cgla:<italic>Candida glabrata; </italic>Kpol:<italic>Kluyveromyces polysporus; </italic>Kwal:<italic>Kluyveromyces waltii</italic>, Sklu: <italic>Saccharomyces kluyveri; </italic>Klac:<italic>Kluyveromyces lactis</italic>)</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-8-343-S2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>The GO enrichment analyses for genes in Group I and II.</bold> This table presents all functional categories defined by GO finder with <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.05 for genes in Group I and II.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-8-343-S3.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p><bold>Additional KEGG pathways that show gene enrichment in Group I and II.</bold> This table presents all pathways with <italic>P</italic>-value between 0.05 and 0.01.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-8-343-S4.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional file 5</title><p><bold>The correlation of codon usage and tRNA pools among species.</bold> The lower triangle of the table contains the Spearman's correlation coefficients of codon usage in the whole genome. RSCU (Relative Synonymous Codon Usage) values were calculated for all codons in each species. Then correlations of RSCU values were calculated for each species pairs. The upper triangle of the table is the Spearman's correlation coefficients of tRNA gene number among all species.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-8-343-S5.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Chuan Gao, Orna Man for technical assistance, Lin Xu for discussion and David Pinney for reading the manuscript. This work was supported by a NSFC key grant (No. 30430400) and a 973 Program of China (No. 2007CB815703-5) to WW and startup funds from Cornell University awarded to ZG.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prinz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Avila-Campillo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Galitski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Control of yeast filamentous-form growth by modules in an integrated molecular network</article-title><source>Genome research</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.2020604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14993204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Logue</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Stajich</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>A fungal phylogeny based on 42 complete genomes derived from supertree and combined gene analysis</article-title><source>BMC evolutionary biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>99</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-6-99</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17121679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mickelson</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><article-title>The metabolism of glucose by Ashbya gossypii</article-title><source>Journal of bacteriology</source><year>1950</year><volume>59</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15436438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Ashbya gossypii: a model for fungal developmental biology</article-title><source>Nature reviews</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Voegeli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brachat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohlmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Luedi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>The Ashbya gossypii genome as a tool for mapping the ancient Saccharomyces cerevisiae genome</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>304</volume><issue>5668</issue><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1095781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15001715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><article-title>Homologues of yeast polarity genes control the development of multinucleated hyphae in Ashbya gossypii</article-title><source>Current opinion in microbiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2005.06.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16023404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><article-title>Comparative genomics and genome evolution in yeasts</article-title><source>Philosophical transactions of the Royal Society of London</source><year>2006</year><volume>361</volume><issue>1467</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2005.1799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16524829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Orgogozo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Delon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Payre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><article-title>Morphological evolution through multiple cis-regulatory mutations at a single gene</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>448</volume><issue>7153</issue><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17632547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Correlation between the abundance of Escherichia coli transfer RNAs and the occurrence of the respective codons in its protein genes: a proposal for a synonymous codon choice that is optimal for the E. coli translational system</article-title><source>Journal of molecular biology</source><year>1981</year><volume>151</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-2836(81)90003-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6175758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Correlation between the abundance of yeast transfer RNAs and the occurrence of the respective codons in protein genes. Differences in synonymous codon choice patterns of yeast and Escherichia coli with reference to the abundance of isoaccepting transfer RNAs</article-title><source>Journal of molecular biology</source><year>1982</year><volume>158</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-2836(82)90250-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6750137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurland</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Codon usage determines translation rate in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Journal of molecular biology</source><year>1989</year><volume>207</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-2836(89)90260-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2474074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Synonymous codon usage in Drosophila melanogaster: natural selection and translational accuracy</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1994</year><volume>136</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>927</fpage><lpage>935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8005445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><article-title>The codon Adaptation Index &#x02013; a measure of directional synonymous codon usage bias, and its potential applications</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>1987</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1281</fpage><lpage>1295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/15.3.1281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3547335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Translational selection and yeast proteome evolution</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2003</year><volume>164</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>1303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12930740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilpel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Differential translation efficiency of orthologous genes is involved in phenotypic divergence of yeast species</article-title><source>Nature genetics</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17277776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Darwinian evolution of proteins</article-title><source>Science (New York, NY)</source><year>1970</year><volume>168</volume><issue>934</issue><fpage>1009</fpage><lpage>1011</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>dos Reis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Savva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wernisch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Solving the riddle of codon usage preferences: a test for translational selection</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>5036</fpage><lpage>5044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15448185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gollub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>GO::TermFinder &#x02013; open source software for accessing Gene Ontology information and finding significantly enriched Gene Ontology terms associated with a list of genes</article-title><source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>3710</fpage><lpage>3715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bth456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>KEGG</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gladfelter</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hungerbuehler</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Asynchronous nuclear division cycles in multinucleated cells</article-title><source>The Journal of cell biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>172</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200507003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16449188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gladfelter</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><article-title>Nuclear anarchy: asynchronous mitosis in multinucleated fungal hyphae</article-title><source>Current opinion in microbiology</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2006.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17045513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Naglik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hube</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Candida albicans proteinases and host/pathogen interactions</article-title><source>Cellular microbiology</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>915</fpage><lpage>926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-5822.2004.00439.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15339267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rua</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobe</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kron</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><article-title>Cell cycle control of yeast filamentous growth</article-title><source>Current opinion in microbiology</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5274(01)00274-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Merico</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Piskur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Compagno</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Fermentative lifestyle in yeasts belonging to the Saccharomyces complex</article-title><source>The FEBS journal</source><year>2007</year><volume>274</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>976</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2007.05645.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17239085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonhoeffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Cooperation and competition in the evolution of ATP-producing pathways</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>292</volume><issue>5516</issue><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1058079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calvert</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawes</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><article-title>Cell size control of development in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1984</year><volume>312</volume><issue>5989</issue><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/312061a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6387507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rupes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Checking cell size in yeast</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9525(02)02745-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12175809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Maynard Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Szathmary</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>The Major Transitions in Evolution</article-title><source>UK</source><year>1995</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scannell</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Conant</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolfit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><article-title>Independent sorting-out of thousands of duplicated gene pairs in two yeast species descended from a whole-genome duplication</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>8397</fpage><lpage>8402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0608218104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17494770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>Fungal Comparative Genomics database</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fungal.genome.duke.edu/">http://fungal.genome.duke.edu/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>The National Center for Biotechnology Information</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Remm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Storm</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><article-title>Automatic clustering of orthologs and in-paralogs from pairwise species comparisons</article-title><source>Journal of molecular biology</source><year>2001</year><volume>314</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1041</fpage><lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.2000.5197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alexeyenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><article-title>Automatic clustering of orthologs and inparalogs shared by multiple proteomes</article-title><source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>e9</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><article-title>tRNAscan-SE: a program for improved detection of transfer RNA genes in genomic sequence</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.5.955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9023104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gladfelter</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sustreanu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hungerbuehler</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Voegeli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Galati</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>The anaphase-promoting complex/cyclosome is required for anaphase progression in multinucleated Ashbya gossypii cells</article-title><source>Eukaryotic cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/EC.00364-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17158735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Cell polarity and hyphal morphogenesis are controlled by multiple rho-protein modules in the filamentous ascomycete Ashbya gossypii</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2001</year><volume>157</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11156982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hungerbuehler</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladfelter</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><article-title>Limited functional redundancy and oscillation of cyclins in multinucleated Ashbya gossypii fungal cells</article-title><source>Eukaryotic cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/EC.00273-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17122387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Determination of cell polarity in germinated spores and hyphal tips of the filamentous ascomycete Ashbya gossypii requires a rhoGAP homolog</article-title><source>Journal of cell science</source><year>2000</year><volume>113</volume><issue>Pt 9</issue><fpage>1611</fpage><lpage>1621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10751152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Helfer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladfelter</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><article-title>AgSwe1p regulates mitosis in response to morphogenesis and nutrients in multinucleated Ashbya gossypii cells</article-title><source>Molecular biology of the cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>4494</fpage><lpage>4512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E06-03-0215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16899511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Helfer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>A Ras-like GTPase is involved in hyphal growth guidance in the filamentous fungus Ashbya gossypii</article-title><source>Molecular biology of the cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>4622</fpage><lpage>4632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E04-02-0104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15282338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>The SH3/PH domain protein AgBoi1/2 collaborates with the Rho-type GTPase AgRho3 to prevent nonpolar growth at hyphal tips of Ashbya gossypii</article-title><source>Eukaryotic cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/EC.00210-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16950929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laissue</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>From function to shape: a novel role of a formin in morphogenesis of the fungus Ashbya gossypii</article-title><source>Molecular biology of the cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E05-06-0479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Initial molecular characterization of a novel Rho-type GTPase RhoH in the filamentous ascomycete Ashbya gossypii</article-title><source>Current genetics</source><year>2005</year><volume>48</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00294-005-0017-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16160833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Maximal polar growth potential depends on the polarisome component AgSpa2 in the filamentous fungus Ashbya gossypii</article-title><source>Molecular biology of the cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>4140</fpage><lpage>4154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E03-03-0167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12937275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Analysis of the landmark protein Bud3 of Ashbya gossypii reveals a novel role in septum construction</article-title><source>EMBO reports</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.embor.embor727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12612612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>An IQGAP-related protein, encoded by AgCYK1, is required for septation in the filamentous fungus Ashbya gossypii</article-title><source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1087-1845(02)00034-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>