<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2632930</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp062</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkp062</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Front-Matter/Back-Matter</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Subscriptions</article-title></title-group><!--For NAR both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>37</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>iii</fpage><lpage>iii</lpage></article-meta></front><body><p>A subscription to <italic>Nucleic Acids Research</italic> comprises 22 issues. All prices include postage, and for subscribers outside the UK delivery is by Standard Air. <italic>Nucleic Acids Research</italic> operates a model of continuous online publication, more details of which can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nar.oxfordjournals.org/">www.nar.oxfordjournals.org</ext-link></p><p>Annual Subscription Rate (Volume 37, 22 issues, 2009)</p><p>Institutional</p><p>Print only: &#x000a3;2391.00/$4782.00/&#x020ac;3587.00</p><p>Institutional membership online only: &#x000a3;2195.00/$4390.00/&#x020ac;3293.00</p><p>Personal</p><p>Print: &#x000a3;458.00/$916.00/&#x020ac;687.00</p><p>Please note: US$ rate applies to US and Canada, Euros applies to Europe, UK&#x000a3; applies to UK and Rest of World.</p><p>Online access will be completely free of charge in 2007. A print subscription or institutional membership provides discounted publication charges for corresponding authors based at the member institution. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nar.oxfordjournals/">www.nar.oxfordjournals</ext-link>.org/openaccess. There may be other subscription rates available, for a complete listing please visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oxfordjournals.org/nar/access_purchase/price_list">www.oxfordjournals.org/nar/access_purchase/price_list</ext-link>.</p><p>Full prepayment, in the correct currency, is required for all orders. Orders are regarded as firm and payments are not refundable. Subscriptions are accepted and entered on a complete volume basis. Claims cannot be considered more than FOUR months after publication or date of order, whichever is later. All subscriptions in Canada are subject to GST. Subscriptions in the EU may be subject to European VAT. If registered, please supply details to avoid unnecessary charges. For subscriptions that include online versions, a proportion of the subscription price may be subject to UK VAT. Personal rate subscriptions are only available if payment is made by personal cheque or credit card and delivery is to a private address.</p><p>The current year and two previous years&#x02019; issues are available from Oxford University Press. Previous volumes can be obtained from the Periodicals Service Company, 11 Main Street, Germantown, NY 12526, USA. Email: <email>psc@periodicals.com</email>. Tel: +1 (518) 537 4700. Fax: +1 (518) 537 5899. Back volumes of this journal are available in 16&#x02009;mm microfilm, 35&#x02009;mm microfilm and 105 microfiche from University Microfilms International, 300 North Zeeb Road, Ann Arbor, MI 48106-1346, USA. Copies of articles published are also available from UMI.</p><p><bold>For further information, please contact:</bold> Journals Customer Service Department, Oxford University Press, Great Clarendon Street, Oxford OX2 6DP, UK. Email: <email>jnls.cust.serv@oxfordjournals.org</email>. Tel (and answerphone outside normal working hours): +44 (0)1865 353907. Fax: +44 (0)1865 353485. <bold>In the US, please contact:</bold> Journals Customer Service Department, Oxford University Press, 2001 Evans Road, Cary, NC 27513, USA. Email: <email>jnlorders@oxfordjournals.org</email>. Tel (and answerphone outside normal working hours): 800 852 7323 (toll-free in USA/Canada). Fax: 919 677 1714. <bold>In Japan, please contact:</bold> Journals Customer Services, Oxford University Press, 1-1-17-5F, Mukogaoka, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, 113-0023, Japan. Email: <email>oupjnl@po.iijnet.or.jp</email>. Tel: (03) 3813 1461. Fax: (03) 3818 1522.</p><p><bold>Methods of payment</bold>. (i) Cheque (payable to Oxford University Press, to Oxford University Press, Cashiers Office, Great Clarendon Street, Oxford OX2 6DP, UK) in GB&#x000a3; Sterling (drawn on a UK bank), US$ Dollars (drawn on a US bank), or EU&#x02019;Euros. (ii) Bank transfer to Barclays Bank Plc, Oxford Group Office, Oxford (bank sort code 20-65-18) (UK), overseas only Swift code BARC GB 22 (GB&#x000a3; Sterling to account no. 70299332, IBAN GB89BARC20651870299332; US$ Dollars to account no. 66014600, IBAN GB27BARC20651866014600; EU&#x02019;Euros to account no. 78923655, IBAN GB16BARC20651878923655). (iii) Credit card (Mastercard, Visa, Switch or American Express).</p><p><italic>Nucleic Acids Research</italic> is published twice monthly by Oxford University Press, Oxford, UK. Annual subscription price is &#x000a3;2391.00/$4782.00/&#x020ac;3587.00. <italic>Nucleic Acids Research</italic> is distributed by Mercury International, 365 Blair Road, Avenel, NJ 07001, USA. Periodicals postage paid at Rahway, NJ and at additional entry points. Issue Date: <bold>January 30, 2009</bold>.</p><p>US Postmaster: send address changes to <italic>Nucleic Acids Research</italic> (ISSN 0305-1048), c/o Mercury International, 365 Blair Road, Avenel, NJ 07001, USA.</p><p>For information about DOIs and to resolve them, please visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/">http://dx.doi.org/</ext-link></p><p>Oxford Journals Environmental and Ethical Policies</p><p>Oxford Journals is committed to working with the global community to bring the highest quality research to the widest possible audience. Oxford Journals will protect the environment by implementing environmentally friendly policies and practices wherever possible. Please see http://www.oxfordjournals.org/ethicalpolicies.html for further information on Oxford Journals' environmental and ethical policies.</p><p><bold>Permissions</bold></p><p>For information on how to request permissions to reproduce articles/information from this journal, please visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oxfordjournals.org/jnls/permissions/">http://www.oxfordjournals.org/jnls/permissions/</ext-link>.</p><p><bold>Advertising</bold></p><p>Advertising, inserts and artwork enquiries should be addressed to Advertising and Special Sales, Oxford Journals, Oxford University Press, Great Clarendon Street, Oxford OX2 6DP, UK. Tel: +44 (0)1865 354767; Email: <email>jnlsadvertising@oxfordjournals.org</email>.</p><p>&#x000a9; Oxford University Press 2009</p><p>All rights reserved; no part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording, or otherwise without prior written permission of the Publishers, or a licence permitting restricted copying issued in the UK by the Copyright Licensing Agency Ltd, 90 Tottenham Court Road, London W1P 9HE, or in the USA by the Copyright Clearance Center, 222 Rosewood Drive, Danvers, MA 01923.</p><p>Typeset by Cepha Imaging Pvt. Ltd., Bangalore, India.</p><p>Printed by C.O.S. Printers Pte Ltd, Singapore.</p><p><table-wrap id="T1" position="anchor"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cover</italic>: 2009 marks the 200th anniversary of Charles Darwin's birth (12th February) and the 150th anniversary of the publication of &#x02018;On the Origin of Species&#x02019;. Following his five-year voyage on the Beagle, Darwin formulated his theory on evolution through natural selection. To this day, Darwin's theory remains the cornerstone of modern biology and is constantly reinforced by molecular and genomic studies. The Beagle's voyage map is reproduced with permission from John van Wyhe ed., The Complete Work of Charles Darwin Online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://darwin-online.org.uk/">http://darwin-online.org.uk/</ext-link>). The cover figure was designed by Cheryl Ryan.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></body></article>