<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Pharmacology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2210</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19000313</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2632638</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2210-8-19</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2210-8-19</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes can inhibit or enhance the TPA-induced up-regulation of activator protein-1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deck</surname><given-names>Lorraine M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ldeck@unm.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hunsaker</surname><given-names>Lucy A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>lhunsaker@salud.unm.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>Amanda M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>amgonzales@salud.unm.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Orlando</surname><given-names>Robert A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>rorlando@salud.unm.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vander Jagt</surname><given-names>David L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>dlvanderjagt@salud.unm.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Chemistry, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM 87131, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of New Mexico School of Medicine, Albuquerque, NM 87131, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2210/8/19"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Deck et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Deck et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Deck               M               Lorraine                              ldeck@unm.edu            </dc:author><dc:title>            Substituted trans-stilbenes can inhibit or enhance the TPA-induced up-regulation of activator protein-1         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Pharmacology 8(1): 19-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2210(2008)8:1&#x0003c;19&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2210</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The activator protein-1 (AP-1) family of transcription factors contributes to regulation of numerous genes involved in proliferation, apoptosis, and tumorigenesis. A wide array of stimuli can activate AP-1, including pro-inflammatory cytokines, growth factors, tumor promoters and stress. Numerous plant polyphenols have been shown to inhibit the activation of AP-1, which often is ascribed to the anti-oxidant properties of these natural products.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>In the present study, a library of substituted <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes, including polyphenols, was screened for activity against the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 using the Panomics AP-1 Reporter 293 Stable Cell Line, which is designed for screening potential inhibitors or activators.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Several <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes were identified that inhibit TPA-induced activation of AP-1, with IC<sub>50 </sub>values as low as 0.5 &#x003bc;M. Moreover, some other <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes were able to enhance the effects of TPA 2 to 3-fold. Many of the <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes identified as inhibitors or enhancers are devoid of anti-oxidant properties.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The ability of <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes to inhibit or enhance the effects of TPA does not depend upon their anti-oxidant properties.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Activator protein-1 (AP-1) transcription factors are homo- or heterodimers of members of the Jun (c-Jun, JunB, JunC), Fos (c-Fos, FosB, Fra-1, Fra-2), ATF (ATF2, ATF3, B-ATF, JDP1, JDP2) and Maf (c-Maf, MafB, MafA, MafG/F/K, Nrl) families of proteins, all of which are bZIP proteins. AP-1 dimers contribute to regulation of many cellular processes including proliferation, cell cycle regulation, differentiation, and apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Active AP-1 dimers can bind to TPA-responsive elements (TREs) in the promoters of AP-1 responsive genes. AP-1 binding to TREs also is induced by growth factors, cytokines and oncoproteins, leading to the general view that activation of AP-1 is oncogenic by contributing to proliferation, survival and transformation of cells. Several AP-1 proteins, including c-Jun and c-Fos, can transform cells in culture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Development of inhibitors of activation of AP-1 may be a promising approach to development of new anti-cancer therapeutics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. However, certain AP-1 dimers can be anti-oncogenic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Whether or not AP-1 is oncogenic depends upon cell type, genetic background, nature of the stimulus and state of differentiation. AP-1 is also an important family of transcription factors involved in gene regulation in inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>Activation of AP-1 can be inhibited by numerous natural product polyphenols such as resveratrol, curcumin, epigallocatechin gallate and theaflavins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. For example, resveratrol suppressed TNF-induced activation of AP-1 in a variety of cells through inhibition of activation of MAP kinases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Resveratrol inhibited the TPA-induced expression of c-Fos and c-Jun in mouse skin, also by inhibiting MAP kinases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. In other studies, resveratrol inhibited anchorage-independent growth of melanoma cells by altering the dimeric composition of AP-1[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><p>Resveratrol is a stilbene derivative. Both <italic>cis</italic>- and <italic>trans-</italic>resveratrol exist as natural products and both are biologically active [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. It is often assumed that the biological properties of resveratrol and other natural product polyphenols are derived from their anti-oxidant properties. In the present study, a library of substituted <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes was examined for activity as inhibitors or activators of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 in the Panomics AP-1 Reporter 293 Stable Cell Line, which is the HEK293 cell transfected with an AP-1-dependent luciferase construct. We report here that substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes devoid of anti-oxidant activity can function as inhibitors of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1. Moreover, some <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes can function as enhancers of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Synthesis of trans-stilbenes</title><p>The synthesis of a library of substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes was reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Assay of the anti-oxidant activities of trans-stilbenes</title><p>The anti-oxidant activities of the library of substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes were determined using two standard assays [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. The <italic>total radical-trapping anti-oxidant parameter </italic>(TRAP) assay measures the ability of an analog to react with the pre-formed radical monocation of 2,2'-azinobis-(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) (ABTS<sup>.+</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. ABTS was reacted with potassium persulfate in the dark, overnight, to generate the colored ABTS<sup>.+ </sup>radical cation, which has an absorption maximum at 734 nm. The activities of the <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes were determined by their abilities to quench the color of the radical cation. The <italic>ferric reducing/anti-oxidant power </italic>(FRAP) assay measures the ability of an analog to reduce a ferric tripyridyltriazine complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The ferric complex of 2,4,6-tripyridyl-<italic>s</italic>-triazine was prepared at acidic pH, and the anti-oxidant activities of the <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes were determined by their abilities to reduce the ferric complex to the ferrous complex, monitored by formation of ferrous complex at 593 nm. In both colorimetric assays, the vitamin E analog Trolox was used as a control.</p></sec><sec><title>Culturing of AP-1 reporter cells</title><p>An AP-1 reporter stable cell line derived from human 293T embryonic kidney cells transfected with a luciferase reporter construct containing three AP-1 binding sites in the promoter (293T/AP-1-luc, Panomics, Inc., Redwood City, CA, USA) was grown in a humidified atmosphere at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>/95% air. The cells were maintained in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium (DMEM &#x02013; high glucose containing 4 mM glutamine) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 100 units/ml penicillin, 100 &#x003bc;g/ml streptomycin and 100 &#x003bc;g/ml hygromycin (Gibco/Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) to maintain cell selection.</p></sec><sec><title>Assay of the activities of substituted trans-stilbeness as inhibitors of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1</title><p>One day prior to treatment, the 293T/AP-1-luc cells were plated into 24-well cell culture plates (Costar, Cambridge, MA, USA) in the above media without hygromycin. The following day, the cells, which were at approximately 60% confluency, were fed fresh media with or without TPA, 10 ng/ml, (Calbiochem, USA) and immediately treated with resveratrol or a <italic>trans-</italic>stilbene prepared in DMSO stock solutions. The cells were placed again in a humidified atmosphere at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>/95% air for 24 hours. Plate wells were gently washed with phosphate buffered saline, pH 7.4, and lysed with 1&#x000d7; passive lysis buffer (Promega, Madison, WI). The subsequent lysates were analyzed with the Luciferase Assay System (Promega, USA) utilizing a TD-20/20 luminometer (Turner Designs, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). The firefly luciferase relative light units were normalized to protein (mg/ml) with BCA&#x02122; Protein Assay Kit (Pierce, Rockford, IL, USA) and standardized to percent of control (TPA control).</p></sec><sec><title>Culturing of murine macrophage cells</title><p>Murine macrophage cells (BV-2) were kindly provided by Dr. Paul M. Stemmer (Institute of Environmental Health Sciences, Wayne State University, Detroit, MI, USA). Cells were cultured in RPMI-1640 (Cellgro, Herndon, VA, USA) supplemented with 10% FBS, 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 2 mM L-glutamine, 100 &#x003bc;g/ml streptomycin sulfate and 100 units/ml penicillin. Cells were grown on culture plates, pre-treated with 1% gelatin for 30 min at 37&#x000b0;C, and passaged twice weekly.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurement of secreted prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) levels</title><p>BV-2 cells were incubated without or with 10 ng/ml TPA. Those cells that were treated with TPA were incubated in parallel with resveratrol or analogs <bold><underline>1</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>29</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>46</underline></bold>or <bold><underline>48</underline></bold>at the indicated concentrations or with vehicle alone (dimethylsulfoxide, 0.1% final concentration). After 24 h incubation, culture media was removed and secreted PGE2 levels were quantified by competitive ELISA according to directions provided by the manufacturer (R&#x00026;D Systems, Inc., Minneapolis, MN, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistics</title><p>Error bars in figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> represent standard deviations from triplicate measurements. The &#x000b1; values in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> indicate standard deviations from triplicate measures of IC<sub>50 </sub>from dose-response curves.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Inhibition or enhancement of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by resveratrol and phenolic <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes</bold>. Screening with the 293T/AP-1-luc cell for the effects of resveratrol and phenolic <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes on TPA-induced activation of AP-1 demonstrated that resveratrol and <bold><underline>7</underline></bold>were enhancers, <bold><underline>1</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>2</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>3</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>4</underline></bold>were inhibitors, and <bold><underline>5</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>6</underline></bold>were inactive. These phenolic compounds retain anti-oxidant activity. Each value represents the average of triplicate points. Error bars show standard deviations. The * notation indicates p &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Inhibition or enhancement of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by methoxy-substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes</bold>. Screening with the 293/AP-1-luc cell of methoxy-substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes, which do not retain anti-oxidant activity, demonstrated that some derivatives inhibit, some enhance and others have no effects on the TPA-induced activation of AP-1. The * notation indicates p &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Inhibition or enhancement of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes devoid of hydroxy or methoxy functional groups</bold>. Screening with the 293/AP-1-luc cell of a range of substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes, which do not have hydroxyl or methoxy functional groups, demonstrated that some derivatives inhibit, some enhance and others have no effects on the TPA-induced activation of AP-1. The * notation indicates p &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Inhibition of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by <italic>para</italic>-methoxy-substituted trans-stilbenes</bold>. Screening with the 293/AP-1-luc cell of a range of substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes, all of which have a <italic>para</italic>-methoxy functional group on one ring, demonstrated numerous inhibitors but no enhancers of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1. Analog <bold><underline>46</underline></bold>, with an IC<sub>50 </sub>= 0.5 &#x003bc;M, was the most potent inhibitor observed in this study. The * notation indicates p &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Inhibition or enhancement of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by analogs of <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes</bold>. Screening with the 293/AP-1-luc cell of a range of analogs of stilbenes that retain the <italic>trans </italic>double bond demonstrated that inhibitors or enhancers of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 can deviate considerably from the <italic>trans-</italic>stilbene scaffold. The * notation indicates p &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Secreted PGE2 levels after treatment of TPA-activated murine macrophage cells with substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes</bold>. BV-2 cells were activated with TPA and co-incubated with resveratrol, <bold><underline>1</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>29</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>46</underline></bold>, or <bold><underline>48</underline></bold>. Secreted PGE2 levels were quantified by competitive ELISA. Basal levels of secreted PGE2 were established using non-stimulated BV-2 cells (125 pg/ml). Maximal PGE2 levels were determined by treating BV-2 cells with TPA alone and no inhibitor (230 pg/ml). Analog <bold><underline>29</underline></bold>was the most potent inhibitor of PGE2 secretion. The * notation indicates p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>IC<sub>50 </sub>values of substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes as inhibitors of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Number</td><td align="center">Structure</td><td align="center">IC<sub>50 </sub>(&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="center">TRAP</td><td align="center">FRAP</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>1</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i1.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>0.8 &#x000b1; 0.05</bold></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>8</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i2.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>0.7 &#x000b1; 0.04</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>9</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i3.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>2.4 &#x000b1; 0.7</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>10</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i4.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>3.8 &#x000b1; 1.1</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>11</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i5.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>1.3 &#x000b1; 0.03</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>29</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i6.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>1.1 &#x000b1; 0.1</bold></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>30</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i7.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>0.8 &#x000b1; 0.1</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>31</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i8.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>1.6 &#x000b1; 0.6</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>46</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i9.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>0.5 &#x000b1; 0.1</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>47</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i10.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>0.8 &#x000b1; 0.1</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>48</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i11.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>0.8 &#x000b1; 0.03</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>49</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i12.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>1.0 &#x000b1; 0.12</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>50</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i13.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>0.8 &#x000b1; 0.15</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>62</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i14.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>2.5 &#x000b1; 0.5</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>63</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i15.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>2.1 &#x000b1; 0.4</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Anti-oxidant Activity</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Anti-oxidant activities of <italic>trans</italic>-stilbene that enhance the TPA-induced activation of AP-1</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Number</td><td align="center">Structure</td><td align="center">% Enhancement</td><td align="center">TRAP</td><td align="center">FRAP</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><bold>Resveratrol</bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i16.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>262 &#x000b1; 12</bold></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>7</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i17.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>230 &#x000b1; 11</bold></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>25</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i18.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>158 &#x000b1; 0.1</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>26</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i19.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>182 &#x000b1; 21</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>27</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i20.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>248 &#x000b1; 0.5</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>28</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i21.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>172 &#x000b1; 12</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>41</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i22.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>160 &#x000b1; 16</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>42</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i23.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>203 &#x000b1; 14</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>43</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i24.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>220 &#x000b1; 6</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>44</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i25.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>251 &#x000b1; 2</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>45</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i26.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>267 &#x000b1; 15</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>68</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i27.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>143 &#x000b1; 3</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>69</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i28.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>164 &#x000b1; 13</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>70</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i29.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>167 &#x000b1; 4</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>71</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i30.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>213 &#x000b1; 29</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><underline>72</underline></bold></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1471-2210-8-19-i31.gif"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><bold>243 &#x000b1; 12</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Anti-oxidant Activity</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Inhibition or enhancement of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by resveratrol and phenolic trans-stilbenes</title><p>Resveratrol and 7 <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes that contained one or more phenolic substituents were compared for their effects on the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 in an initial screening at 15 &#x003bc;M concentration of the compounds (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Some of the compounds were strong inhibitors of the activation of AP-1. Analog <bold><underline>1</underline></bold>, which contains hydroxy and methoxy functional groups ortho to each other on one of the two aromatic rings, was the strongest inhibitor. From dose-response measurements, the IC<sub>50 </sub>for <bold><underline>1</underline></bold>was 0.8 &#x003bc;M (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). By comparison, <bold><underline>7</underline></bold>, which is isomeric with <bold><underline>1</underline></bold>, enhanced the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 2.5-fold. Clearly, small changes in structure can dictate whether a <italic>trans-</italic>stilbene inhibits or enhances the effects of TPA. Surprisingly, in this screening assay, resveratrol enhanced the effects of TPA almost 3-fold. Other compounds in this series, such as <bold><underline>5</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>6</underline></bold>, had no effect. All of the <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> retain anti-oxidant activity both in the TRAP and FRAP assays.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition or enhancement of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by methoxy-substituted trans-stilbenes</title><p>A series of 21 methoxy-substituted <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes containing one to four methoxy functional groups was screened at 15 &#x003bc;M, as above (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). A wide range of effects was observed. Some of these <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes, such as <bold><underline>8</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>9</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>10</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>11</underline></bold>, were strong inhibitors of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 with IC<sub>50 </sub>values in the range 0.7 to 3.8 &#x003bc;M (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Others, such as <bold><underline>26</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>27</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>28</underline></bold>, gave 2 to 3-fold enhancements, comparable to resveratrol. Analogs <bold><underline>18</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>19</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>20</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>21</underline></bold>were inactive. Methoxy-substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes, including <bold><underline>8</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>9</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>10</underline></bold>, which were among the most potent inhibitors, were generally devoid of anti-oxidant activity in the TRAP and FRAP assays, indicating that anti-oxidant activity is not essential.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition or enhancement of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by substituted trans-stilbenes devoid of hydroxy or methoxy functional groups</title><p>A series of 17 substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes that did not contain hydroxy or methoxy functional groups was screened at 15 &#x003bc;M as above (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Several of these, such as <bold><underline>44</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>45</underline></bold>, which contained methyl of trifluoromethyl groups on one of the aromatic rings, were effective enhancers of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1, comparable to resveratrol. Several others, such as <bold><underline>29</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>30</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>31</underline></bold>, which contained a single dimethylamino, ethoxy or methyl functional group, were strong inhibitors (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Many of the compounds in this series were weak inhibitors or weak activators.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition or enhancement of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by para-methoxy-substituted trans-stilbenes</title><p>A series of 16 substituted <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes that contained a <italic>para</italic>-methoxy substituent on one ring and a variety of substituents on the second ring was screened at 15 &#x003bc;M (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). In this series, many compounds were strong inhibitors of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1, such as <bold><underline>46</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>47</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>48</underline></bold>, <bold><underline>49</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>51</underline></bold>(Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Others were weak inhibitors or showed no activity. None of the <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes in this group enhanced the TPA-induced activation of AP-1. Thus minor changes in the nature or location of a single substituent markedly affects activity. Analog <bold><underline>46</underline></bold>, with an IC<sub>50 </sub>= 0.5 &#x003bc;M, was the most potent inhibitor observed in this study (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition or enhancement of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 by analogs of trans-stilbenes</title><p>A series of 11 analogs of <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes was evaluated. This group retained a <italic>trans </italic>double bond as in <italic>trans-</italic>stilbene. One of the aromatic benzene rings was replaced by a different ring. As with the other series, a range of activities was observed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Some compounds, such as <bold><underline>62</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>63</underline></bold>, were strong inhibitors (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) while others, such as <bold><underline>71</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>72</underline></bold>, gave enhancements comparable to resveratrol. Clearly, structures of inhibitors or enhancers of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 can differ considerable from a strict <italic>trans-</italic>stilbene scaffold.</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of substituted trans-stilbenes on secreted prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) levels</title><p>To determine whether the AP-1 inhibitory effects of substituted <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes extend beyond the 293/AP-1-luc reporter cell line used for screening, several compounds were selected from Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and examined for capacity to reduce levels of secreted PGE2 by a TPA-activated murine macrophage cell line (BV-2). PGE2 is a potent inflammatory mediator and product of cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) activity. Since COX-2 activity is an important target for traditional anti-inflammatory reagents, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, quantifying secreted PGE2 can provide a direct measurement of COX-2 expression levels. When BV-2 cells were stimulated with TPA, levels of secreted PGE2 were elevated by ~2-fold (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). All compounds tested, except resveratrol, demonstrated a dose-dependent inhibitory effect on levels of PGE2. Analog <bold><underline>29</underline></bold>was the most potent inhibitor as 0.1 &#x003bc;M was sufficient to reduce PGE2 levels to those measured for unstimulated cells. Analogs <bold><underline>1</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>46</underline></bold>were also able to reduce PGE2 levels to baseline, but required doses of 10 &#x003bc;M, making <bold><underline>29</underline></bold>~100-fold more potent that these other <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes. It was assumed that the measurement of secreted PGE2 in response to treatment with resveratrol or analogs reflects the effects of these compounds on COX-2 gene expression. It is possible that the compounds are inhibitors of COX-2 enzyme. However, we demonstrated previously in similar studies that focused on NF-&#x003ba;B-dependent expression of COX-2 in response to LPS stimulation that the inhibitory effects of resveratrol and analogs were at the level of gene expression as determined by mRNA measurements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Anti-oxidant activities of enhancers and inhibitors of TPA-induced activation of AP-1</title><p>As mentioned above and shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes that inhibit the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 need not retain anti-oxidant activity, as determined by the TRAP and FRAP assays. This same property was observed with enhancers of the TPA-induced activation of AP-1. As shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, most of the compounds that enhance activity are devoid of antioxidant activity.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The ability of resveratrol to inhibit the stress-induced activation of AP-1 has been reported in a number of studies. In addition to suppressing TNF-induced activation of AP-1 in a variety of cells, inhibiting TPA-induced expression of c-Fos and c-Jun in mouse skin, and inhibiting anchorage-independent growth of melanoma cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], resveratrol suppressed TPA-induced expression of MMP-9 by inhibition of AP-1 activation through c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) and PKC-delta pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] and protected against 4-hydroxynonenal-induced apoptosis by blocking AP-1 signaling through JNK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. These and other studies of the effects of resveratrol generally support the idea that resveratrol prevents AP-1 activation by inhibiting upstream kinases. However, in other studies, resveratrol and closely related polyphenols, such as isorhapontigenin, inhibited AP-1 activation through suppression of ROS-induced activation of MAP kinases by preventing the accumulation of ROS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. In some studies, resveratrol induced rather than inhibited protein expression; resveratrol induced COX-2 expression and nuclear accumulation in breast cancer cells through activation of MAP kinases and AP-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. In HT-29 cancer cells transfected with an AP-1 reporter, resveratrol enhanced AP-1 activity induced by TPA, similar to the present study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. It is apparent, therefore, that the effects of resveratrol and related compounds with respect to AP-1 signaling are cell specific, although generally resulting in inhibition of the activation of AP-1.</p><p>These multiple studies of the biological activities of resveratrol generally do not address the question whether anti-oxidant activity of resveratrol is required for the reported biological activity. AP-1 is one of a number of redox-sensitive transcription factors. AP-1 activity is regulated either directly or indirectly through reversible oxidation-reduction of critical cysteine residues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. c-Jun and c-fos have single conserved cysteine residues in their DNA-binding domains that undergo reversible redox reactions that alter their DNA-binding properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. There also are a number of AP-1-associated proteins, such as thioredoxin, jun activation domain-binding protein 1 (Jab1), and redox factor-1 (Ref-1), that contribute to regulation of the redox state of AP-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. The present study addressed this question through evaluation of the effects of <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes, many of which did not retain anti-oxidant activity, on AP-1 expression in response to TPA. Numerous <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes devoid of anti-oxidant activity in the TRAP and FRAP assays were able to suppress the TPA-induced activation of AP-1, including many of the more potent compounds (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Clearly, anti-oxidant activity is not essential for the ability of these <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes to affect activation of AP-1.</p><p>The question of the role of anti-oxidant activity in those substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes that enhance the TPA-induced activation of AP-1 was also addressed (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). As is the case with <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes that inhibit the TPA-induced activation of AP-1, there is no required role for anti-oxidant activity. In fact, most of the compounds that either suppressed or enhanced TPA-induced AP-1 activity in this study are devoid of anti-oxidant activity.</p><p>This study did not address the question of the actual targets of resveratrol and other <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes that result in either inhibition or enhancement of AP-1 activity in response to TPA-induced activation of the 293T/AP-1-luc cells. As mentioned above, the reports in the literature on AP-1 activation suggest that numerous upstream targets, especially protein kinases, might be involved in signaling pathways that control the expression of AP-1. Interestingly, a number of the most active analogs identified in the current study (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) were also identified in our earlier study of the inhibition of expression of pro-inflammatory transcription factor NF-&#x003ba;B in response to exposure to LPS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], suggesting that there may be common targets for both the AP-1 and NF-&#x003ba;B pathways that are inhibited by some of these <italic>trans-</italic>stilbenes. These targets remain to be identified.</p><p>The possibility should be considered that the substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes used in this study, especially those that inhibit both AP-1 and NF-&#x003ba;B pathways, may target multiple sites in the AP-1 and NF-&#x003ba;B pathways and that interactions between the AP-1 and NF-&#x003ba;B pathways may provide additional complexity that contributes to cell specific effects of these compounds. Recent studies support the complexity of the interactions between AP-1 and NF-&#x003ba;B. It was reported recently that the natural product curcumin, which like resveratrol is a polyphenolic compounds with multiple biological activities, is able to reduce expression of matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) in breast cancer cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. This was shown to involve both NF-&#x003ba;B and AP-1 pathways; silencing of the p65 subunit of NF-&#x003ba;B was sufficient to downregulate expression of AP-1 (c-jun) and MMPs, which suggests signaling was from the NF-&#x003ba;B pathway to the AP-1 pathway. It is often assumed that the site(s) of regulation of signaling through these pathways involves one or more of the numerous upstream kinases, such as MAP kinases, that control the activity of AP-1 and NF-&#x003ba;B. However, another recent study demonstrated that AP-1 and NF-&#x003ba;B can form nuclear complexes with each other [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>].</p><p>The results shown in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> for the effects of resveratrol and several of the <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes on expression of COX-2, as determined by measurement of secreted PGE2, raise a number of issues. Resveratrol did not significantly inhibit the TPA-induced activation of COX-2 (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>) in a macrophage cell line. In a number of studies, COX-2 induction by TPA in various cell types has been shown to involve signaling through AP-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>] and sometimes to involve both the AP-1 and NF-&#x003ba;B pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. In addition, resveratrol is reported to inhibit TPA-induced COX-2 expression in mouse skin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. However, resveratrol has been reported to induce COX-2 expression and nuclear accumulation in breast cancer cells through an AP-1-dependent pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Thus, the effects of resveratrol are context-dependent. This raises the question of the usefulness of reporter assays for screening compounds that may inhibit signaling pathways. It may be preferable to screen in a disease-specific manner by selecting cells that are appropriate models for a given disease and conducting phenotypic screens in which the appropriate disease-related genes are monitored, such as using macrophage cells to screen libraries for abilities to inhibit stress-induced induction of pro-inflammatory genes and using breast epithelial cells to screen for abilities to inhibit stress-induced induction of pro-growth, pro-metastatic genes.</p><p>The data in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> also demonstrate that, for the few compounds selected from Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, quantitatively different results are obtained from a reporter assay compared with a cell-specific assay. For example, analog <bold><underline>29</underline></bold>is much more effective than <bold><underline>46</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>48</underline></bold>in preventing TPA-induced COX-2 expression (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>) whereas <bold><underline>29</underline></bold>is less active than <bold><underline>46</underline></bold>and <bold><underline>48</underline></bold>in a reporter assay (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Studies are underway to address this issue of screening in a cell-specific manner and evaluating the usefulness of reporter assays.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes represent a class of compounds that can inhibit or enhance the TPA-induced activation of AP-1. Small changes in structure can convert an inhibitor into an enhancer. The ability of <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes to inhibit or enhance the effects of TPA does not depend upon their anti-oxidant properties.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>AP-1: activator protein-1; TPA: 12-O-tetradecanoylphorbol-13-acetate; TRE: TPA-responsive element.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>LMD directed the synthetic chemistry and helped design the study; LAH and AMG collected the data related to the effects of substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes on TPA-induced activation of AP-1; RAO designed and directed studies involving use of macrophage cells; and DLVJ helped design the study and wrote the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by grant BC043125 from the US Army/DOD Breast Cancer Program.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaulian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AP-1 in cell proliferation and survival</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2390</fpage><lpage>2400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402335</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chinenov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerppola</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Close encounters of many kinds: Fos-Jun interactions that mediate transcription regulatory specificity</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2438</fpage><lpage>2452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402339</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fortuitous convergences: the beginnings of JUN</article-title><source>Nature Rev Cancer</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12189388</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eferl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AP-1: a double-edged sword in tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Nature Rev Cancer</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14668816</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Angel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schorpp-Kistner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AP-1 subunits: quarrel and harmony among siblings</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>5965</fpage><lpage>5973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15564374</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>W-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>A-NT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of Nrf2, NF-&#x003ba;B, and AP-1 signaling pathways by chemopreventive agents</article-title><source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source><year>2005</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1648</fpage><lpage>1663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16356127</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jochum</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Passegue</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AP-1 in mouse development and tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2401</fpage><lpage>2412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402336</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigoriadis</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohle-Steinlein</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel target cell for c-fos-induced oncogenesis: development of chondrogenic tumours in embryonic stem cell chimeras</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1991</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2437</fpage><lpage>2450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1714376</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutberg</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppenheim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Smoluk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuspa</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>c-Fos is required for malignant progression of skin tumors</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7545543</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From JNK to pay dirt. Jun kinases, their biochemistry, physiology and clinical importance</article-title><source>IUBMB Life</source><year>2005</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16036612</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bogoyevitch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ketterman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting the JNK MAPK cascade for inhibition: basic science and therapeutic potential</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2004</year><volume>1697</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15023353</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>JunB differs from c-Jun in its DNA-binding and dimerization domains, and represses c-Jun by formation of inactive heterodimers</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1993</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8383624</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szremska</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Passegue</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Artwohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Freissmuth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoxreiter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Theussl</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Parzer</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Moriggl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sexl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>JunB inhibits proliferation and transformation in B-lymphoid cells</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2003</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>4159</fpage><lpage>4165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12907453</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Bosscher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Berghe</surname><given-names>W Vanden</given-names></name><name><surname>Haegeman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The interplay between the glucocorticoid receptor and nuclear factor-kappaB or activator protein-1: molecular mechanisms for gene repression</article-title><source>Endocr Rev</source><year>2003</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>488</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12920152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of signal transduction by tea catechins and related phytochemicals</article-title><source>Mut Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>591</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15992833</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gescher</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin: the story so far</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>2005</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1955</fpage><lpage>1968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081279</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resveratrol suppresses TNF-induced activation of nuclear transcription factors NF-kappaB, activator protein-1, and apoptosis: potential role of reactive oxygen intermediates and lipid peroxidation</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>6509</fpage><lpage>6519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10843709</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pezzuto</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of resveratrol on 12-tetradecanoylphorbol-13-acetate-induced oxidative stress and gene expression in mouse skin</article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10381133</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Surh</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resveratrol modulates phorbol ester-induced pro-inflammatory signal transduction pathways in mouse skin in vivo: NF-&#x003ba;B and AP-1 as prime targets</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1506</fpage><lpage>1515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16999939</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyskens</surname><given-names>FL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Alterations in activating protein 1 composition correlate with phenotypic differentiation changes induced by resveratrol in human melanoma</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>2005</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15492115</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>KPL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosmeder</surname><given-names>JW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Pezzuto</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological effects of resveratrol</article-title><source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1041</fpage><lpage>1064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11813979</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heynekamp</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunsaker</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlando</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Deck</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagt</surname><given-names>DL Vander</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substituted <italic>trans</italic>-stilbenes, including analogues of the natural product resveratrol, inhibit the human tumor necrosis factor alpha-induced activation of transcription factor nuclear factor kappaB</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>7182</fpage><lpage>7189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17125270</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlesier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Harwat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohm</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitsch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of antioxidant activity by using different in vitro methods</article-title><source>Free Rad Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11999386</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Re</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Proteggente</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pannala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice-Evans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity applying an improved ABTS radical cation decolorization assay</article-title><source>Free Rad Biol Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10381194</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benzie</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferric reducing/antioxidant power assay: direct measure of total antioxidant activity of biological fluids and modified version for simultaneous measurement of total antioxidant power and ascorbic acid concentrations</article-title><source>Meth Enzymol</source><year>1999</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9916193</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resveratrol inhibits phorbol myristate acetate-induced matrix metalloproteinase-9 expression by inhibiting JNK and PKC-delta signal transduction</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1845</fpage><lpage>1853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14661062</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kutuk</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Poli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Basaga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resveratrol protects against 4-hydroxynonenal-induced apoptosis by blocking JNK and cJUN/AP-1 signaling</article-title><source>Toxicol Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16322078</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isorhapontigenin and resveratrol suppress oxLDL-induced proliferation and activation of ERK1/2 mitogen-activated protein kinases of bovine aortic smooth muscle cells</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2004</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14757178</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resveratrol-induced cyclooxygenase-2 facilitates p53-dependent apoptosis in breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Ther</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>2034</fpage><lpage>2042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16928824</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of AP-1 by natural chemopreventive compounds in human colon HT-29 cancer cell line</article-title><source>Pharm Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15139522</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Surh</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>H-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J-S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redox-sensitive transcription factors as prime targets for chemoprevention with anti-inflammatory and antioxidative phytochemicals</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2005</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>2993S</fpage><lpage>3001S</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16317160</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Colavitti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rovira</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redox-dependent transcriptional regulation</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>974</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16284189</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauscher</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redox regulation of fos and jun DNA-binding activity in vitro</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1990</year><volume>249</volume><fpage>1157</fpage><lpage>1161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2118682</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thioredoxin modulates activator protein (AP-1) activity and p27Kip1 degradation through direct interaction with Jab1</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>8868</fpage><lpage>8875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15480426</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chyu</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimayuga</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cercek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altered AP-1/Ref-1 redox pathway and reduced proliferative response in iNOS-deficient vascular smooth muscle cells</article-title><source>Vasc Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15675181</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bachmeier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nerlich</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Iancu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cilli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleicher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vene</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dell'Eva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jochum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Albini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chemoprotective polyphenol curcumin prevents hematogenous breast cancer metastases in immunodeficient mice</article-title><source>Cell Physiol Biochem</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17310108</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shyu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visualization of AP-1 NF-kappaB ternary complexes in living cells by using a BIFC-based FRET</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18172215</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Goa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A JNK1/AP-1-dependent, COX-2 induction is implicated in 12-O-tetreadecanoylphorbol-13-acetate-induced cell transformation through regulating cell cycle progression</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18234971</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Surh</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KG-135 inhibits COX-2 expression by blocking the activation of JNK and AP-1 in phorbol ester-stimulated human breast epithelial cells</article-title><source>Ann NY Acad Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>1095</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><comment><bold>6</bold>:165&#x02013;174</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17404068</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Surh</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Humulone inhibits phorbol ester-induced COX-2 expression in mouse skin by blocking activation of NF-&#x003ba;B and AP-1: IkappaB kinase and c-Jun-N-terminal kinase as respective potential upstream targets</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>1498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17372274</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>