<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cases J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cases Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1757-1626</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19161627</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2633326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1757-1626-2-80</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1757-1626-2-80</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Capillary hemangioma of cauda equina: a case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Miri</surname><given-names>Seyed M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Dr_m_miri@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A2"><name><surname>Habibi</surname><given-names>Zohreh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>zohreh_h56@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>hashemi@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Meybodi</surname><given-names>Ali T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tayebi_a77@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Tabatabai</surname><given-names>Seyed Ali F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>fakhrtab@sina.tums.ac.ir</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Imam Khomeini Hospital, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2009 Miri et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Miri et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.casesjournal.com/content/2/1/80"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Capillary hemangiomas of spinal nerve root, mostly affecting the cauda equina, are extremely rare.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 20-year old man was presented with back pain, radiculopathy, and urogenital symptoms. Magnetic resonance images revealed an intradural extramedullary mass, isointense in T1-weighted and hyperintense in T2-weighted images, with noticeable post injection enhancement. The clinical and radiological findings simulated neurinoma.</p><p>However, a pinkish lesion was removed surgically and histopathological examination revealed lobules of capillary vessels separated by fibrous tissue, suggesting capillary hemangioma.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Although rare and sometimes indistinguishable from more common lesion, capillary hemangioma should be in differential diagnosis of any enhancing intradural extramedullary mass at the level of cauda equina or conus medullaris.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Tumors of cauda equina account for only 6% of all spinal tumors.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] The differential diagnosis for enhancing intradural extramedullary lesions in this region includes meningioma, hemangioma, schwannoma, hemangioblastoma, and paraganglioma. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] Primary hemangiomas of spinal nerve root, mostly affecting the cauda equina, are extremely rare. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]</p><p>In this report, a case of capillary hemangioma of cauda equina is described and different aspects regarding diagnosis, treatment and pathophysiology of the lesion, and differentiation from more common intradural extramedullary conditions are discussed.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 20-year old man presented with three months history of low back pain radiating to the legs. He also complained of urinary retention, impotence, and retrograde ejaculation of recent onset. He had bilateral weakness in knee flexion and extension of 3/5. There was also parasthesia of both feet and asymmetrical diminished deep tendon reflexes in both lower extremities, which was worse in right side.</p><p>On plain radiography, evidence of vertebral scalloping and widened foramen at the level of L3 was considered probable (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) revealed an intradural, well circumscribed mass at the level of L3, isointense to spinal cord on T1-weighted and isointense to hyperintense on T2-weighted sequences (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Post gadolinium injection images showed remarkable homogenous enhancement (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Plain radiography of lumbar area showing bony erosion and widening of the canal (scalloping) at the level of L3 vertebra (arrow)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1626-2-80-1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Sagital magnetic resonance images showing an intradural mass at the level of L3, isointense to spinal cord on T1-weighted (A) and iso-hyperintense on T2-weighted sequences (B)</bold>. T1-weihted axial image demonstrating the intradural mass pushing the caudal roots to the side of the canal <bold>(C)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1626-2-80-2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Post-gadolinium enhancement revealed in sagital (A), coronal (B), and axial (C) magnetic resonance images of this lesion</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1626-2-80-3"/></fig><p>Regarding its location and MR appearance, the lesion was considered a cauda equina scwhanoma. Surgical resection was performed through a midline posterior approach. Following a one-level laminectomy at L3, midline duratomy was performed and a pinkish intradural mass was identified. The tumor was attached tightly to one of the rootlets, albeit there was no dural attachment. The adjacent radicular vessels seemed to be enlarged. The mass had squishy consistency with high bleeding tendency. Enbloc resection was performed to reduce blood loss.</p><p>Histopathological assessment revealed encapsulated mass with lobular components containing small size capillary vessels lined by a single layer of flattened endothelial cells (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). There was no evidence of atypia, and the lobules were septated by connective tissue. A large vessel with structured endothelial components was seen in the middle of the sample, most likely to be the feeder vessel (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Photomicrograph of the lesion demonstrating a lobule composing of small capillary vessels lined by a layer of endothelial cells</bold>. The fibrous capsule (arrow), interlobular septa (right-pointing arrowhead), and a capillary lumen (left-pointing arrowhead) are disclosed in the picture. H &#x00026; E, original magnification, &#x000d7;4 <bold>(A) </bold>and &#x000d7;40 <bold>(B)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1626-2-80-4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>A large vessel with endothelialized wall in the middle of the specimen, probable to be the feeder vessel. H &#x00026; E, original magnification, &#x000d7;20</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1626-2-80-5"/></fig><p>Following surgery, the patient's motor symptoms were entirely alleviated, and urogenital problems improved marginally. During 1 year follow-up, there was no clinical or radiological evidence of recurrent disease.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Vascular tumors account for about 2% to 7% of all intraspinal tumors. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] Amongst these lesions, capillary hemangioma in the boundaries of the spinal dura mater is extremely rare, and usually presents distally at the conus medullaris or attached to nerve roots of the cauda equina. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] Instead, majority of spinal angiomas in these locations are histopatholigically cavernomas. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] Capillary hemangioma most frequently occurs in cutaneous, subcutaneous, or mucosal tissues as reddish-purple lesions and is more common in children. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] The uncommon intradural condition at the cauda equina occurs in older patients, with equal frequency in men and women. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</p><p>Haemangiomas of the cauda equina may present with intermittent low back pain, intermittent radicular symptoms, sensory deficits, saddle anaesthesia, paraplegia, sphincter dysfunction, symptoms of hydrocephalus, and subarachnoidal hemorrhage. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] Indeed, both capillary and cavernous hemangiomas usually behave as space-occupying masses, producing chronic progressive myelopathy or radiculopathy, which may deteriorate acutely following a hemorrhagic episode.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] This sudden deterioration more often occurs in cavernous angioma, while capillary variant has a slow progressive course.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] Unusual presentation with increased intracranial pressure, elevated cerebrospinal fluid protein level, and papilledema has been reported in a capillary hemangioma of cauda equina as well.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]</p><p>The diagnosis can be established by MRI. The mass usually appears isointense relative to the spinal cord on T1-weighted, and iso- or hyperintense on T2-weighted MR images. Gadolinium administration results in uniform intense enhancement of the lesion. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] After a hemorrhagic insult, heterogeneous hyperintensity on T1-weighted images and homogeneous hypointensity on T2-weighted images may correspond with the hemorrhagic focus. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] The appearance of the enlarged perimedullary draining veins associated with an intraspinal mass on MR images can imply the possibility of an extremely vascular tumor. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]</p><p>The signal characteristics may help differentiate hemangioma from more common intradural extramedullary tumors.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] Meningioma displays isointensity or slight hypointensity on T1-weighted images and isointensity or slight hyperintensity on T2-weighted images, with the mass showing considerable enhancement following gadolinium injection. These signal intensities could assist in differentiation from hemangioma, but the dural tail sign is not useful to distinguish meningioma, since the hemangioma may arise from the inner surface of the dura mater.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] In intradural extramedullary neurinomas, the signal characteristics are similar to those of intradural hemangioma.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] Cystic changes or necrosis could be found within neurinomas. In the absence of these features, it is difficult to differentiate neurinoma from hemangioma, as seen in our case. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] Arteriovenous malformations can be diagnosed through MRI by demonstrating a vascular flow void. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]</p><p>In the spinal intradural extramedullary space, hemangiomas may arise from the blood vessels of the nerve roots in the cauda equina, the inner surface of the dura, or the pial surface of the spinal cord. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] Two hypotheses have been proposed regarding the pathogenesis of the disease. The lesion may evolve during the early somitic differentiation, at the time of angioblastic differentiation (days 21&#x02013;24 of embryogenesis), due to impaired movement and differentiation of primitive mesoderm from the embryonic mesodermal plate. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] Another school of thought claims the origin from vascular structures within the epineurium of the nerve roots affected during individual ontogenesis. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</p><p>Surgery is the treatment of choice for spinal intradural capillary hemangioma, and most of the symptoms would be reversed postoperatively. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</p><p>On histopathological specimens, capillary hemangiomas usually are of lobulated structures of capillary-sized vessels lined with flattened endothelium, with the lobules being separated by a collagenous stroma. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] The lesions are surrounded by a thin fibrous pseudocapsule, and there may be a mild lymphocytic infiltrate. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] Immunohistochemical tests have been positive against neuron-specific enolase and S-100 protein. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] The tumor cells were shown to stain strongly positively for endothelial markers CD31 and CD34, which are compatible with the diagnosis of capillary hemangioma. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] These new methods could be of great value in identification of the disease in future.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Although intradural capillary hemangioma is a rare entity and may be clinically or radiologically indistinguishable from other lesions, it should be considered as the differential diagnosis of any intradural extramedullary mass at the level of conus medullaris or cauda equina.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient and his parents for publication of this case report and accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>SMM made contribution to conception and analyzed the patient data. ZH made contribution in collecting data and drafting the manuscript. MH was contributor in drafting the manuscript. ATM was contributor in revising the manuscript critically.</p><p>SAFT has given the final approval for the version to be submitted.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyakoshi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasukawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hongo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Clinical features of cauda equina tumors requiring surgical treatment</article-title><source>Tohoku J Exp Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>209</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1620/tjem.209.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16636516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghuram</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jane</surname><given-names>JA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Thoracic intradural extramedullary capillary hemangioma</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1294</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15313728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roncaroli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheithauer</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><article-title>Hemangioma of spinal nerve root</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>1999</year><volume>91</volume><issue>2 Suppl</issue><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10505501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumprecht</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000f6;lzle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumenta</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><article-title>Intraneural growth of a capillary haemangioma of the cauda equina</article-title><source>Acta Neurochir</source><year>2000</year><volume>142</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s007010050458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Widenka</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><article-title>Spinal intradural capillary haemangioma: a review</article-title><source>Eur Spine J</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s005860100296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11806386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><article-title>Spinal intradural extramedullary capillary hemangioma: MR imaging findings</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11290503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><article-title>Spinal intradural capillary hemangioma: MR findings</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>954</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10815676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ghazi</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jane</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><article-title>Capillary hemangioma of the cauda equina presenting with radiculopathy and papilledema</article-title><source>J Neuroophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16845308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>