<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genet</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Genetics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2156</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19146678</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2633016</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2156-10-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-10-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mapping of five candidate sex-determining loci in rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alfaqih</surname><given-names>Mahmoud A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>dr_faqih@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brunelli</surname><given-names>Joseph P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>brunelli@wsu.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>Robert E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>rdrew@uidaho.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>Gary H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>thorglab@wsu.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>School of Molecular Biosciences, Washington State University, Pullman WA 99164-4234, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Pharmacology and Physiology, Mutah University, Karak 61710, Jordan</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>School of Biological Sciences and Center for Reproductive Biology, Washington State University, Pullman WA 99164-4236, USA</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>University of Idaho, Department of Biological Sciences, Moscow, ID 83844-3051, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2156/10/2"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Alfaqih et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Alfaqih et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Alfaqih               A               Mahmoud                                             dr_faqih@yahoo.com            </dc:author><dc:title>            Mapping of five candidate sex-determining loci in rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss)         </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Genetics 10(1): 2-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2156(2009)10:1&#x0003c;2&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2156</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Rainbow trout have an XX/XY genetic mechanism of sex determination where males are the heterogametic sex. The homology of the sex-determining gene (SDG) in medaka to <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>suggested that SDGs evolve from downstream genes by gene duplication. Orthologous sequences of the major genes of the mammalian sex determination pathway have been reported in the rainbow trout but the map position for the majority of these genes has not been assigned.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Five loci of four candidate genes (<italic>Amh</italic>, <italic>Dax1</italic>, <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>and <italic>Sox6</italic>) were tested for linkage to the Y chromosome of rainbow trout. We exclude the role of all these loci as candidates for the primary SDG in this species. <italic>Sox6i </italic>and <italic>Sox6ii</italic>, duplicated copies of <italic>Sox6</italic>, mapped to homeologous linkage groups 10 and 18 respectively. Genotyping fishes of the OSU &#x000d7; Arlee mapping family for <italic>Sox6i </italic>and <italic>Sox6ii </italic>alleles indicated that <italic>Sox6i </italic>locus might be deleted in the Arlee lineage.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Additional candidate genes should be tested for their linkage to the Y chromosome. Mapping data of duplicated <italic>Sox6 </italic>loci supports previously suggested homeology between linkage groups 10 and 18. Enrichment of the rainbow trout genomic map with known gene markers allows map comparisons with other salmonids. Mapping of candidate sex-determining loci is important for analyses of potential autosomal modifiers of sex-determination in rainbow trout.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Teleost fishes have a variety of evolutionarily labile sex-determination systems and relatively undifferentiated sex chromosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], and thus are interesting research models for the exploration of how sex-determining mechanisms evolve. The current view of the sex-determination cascade describes it as a gene hierarchy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Genes that reside on top of this hierarchy have been recruited only relatively recently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] and are only found in specific branches of the phylogenetic tree. Downstream genes are conserved between the different phyla, regardless of the sex-determination mechanism, and thus seem to have been present for a much longer time. The recent discovery that the sex-determining gene of the medaka, <italic>Dmy</italic>, is a homologue of a downstream gene of the pathway in mammalian species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] led researchers to propose that downstream genes can be recruited to the top of the hierarchy by gene duplication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. This model of evolution of the sex-determining gene cascade is further supported in the tilapia model (<italic>Oreochromis </italic>spp) where the two downstream genes in mammals, <italic>Amh </italic>and <italic>Dmrta2</italic>, map within quantitative trait loci, QTL, regions for sex determination in that genus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>The salmonid fish, rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) has several parallels to the medaka. Both have an XX-XY genetic sex-determination system with the male being the heterogametic sex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] and in both species the sex chromosomes are at an early stage of evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The sex-determining mechanism in the rainbow trout is believed to function via a 'dominant' factor located on the Y chromosome as evidenced by the production of XXY triploid males [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. <italic>Dmy</italic>, the sex-determining gene in the medaka, also appears to function as a dominant factor. This is supported by male phenotypic development of genetically female (XX) medaka fish injected with a genomic clone containing the <italic>Dmy </italic>sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>Based on the proposed model for evolution of sex-determining gene cascades, we hypothesized that in a tetraploid-derived organism like the rainbow trout [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] which has a high repertoire of duplicated genes, any gene in the sex differentiation cascade, or its' homologue, could potentially have evolved as a sex- determining gene. Based on what we currently know from the two sex-determining genes discovered to date in vertebrates, <italic>Sry </italic>in mammals and <italic>Dmy</italic>, in the medaka, a sex-determining gene (1) has an upstream position in the cascade, (2) shows stronger expression in male gonads as compared to female, (3) is expressed before sexual differentiation of the gonad and (4) is linked to the Y chromosome. We investigated several candidate genes for sex determination in the rainbow trout model by testing for Y-linkage.</p><p>Orthologous sequences of the major genes of the mammalian sex determination pathway have been reported in the rainbow trout; including <italic>Wt1</italic>, <italic>Sox9</italic>, <italic>Dmrt1</italic>, <italic>Amh </italic>and <italic>Dax1</italic>. Three <italic>Wt1 </italic>loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], and three <italic>Sox9 </italic>loci (Alfaqih et al. Submitted) have been previously mapped by our laboratory, but none of the loci were linked to the Y chromosome. In the present study, we tested for linkage of four additional candidate genes for sex determination (<italic>Sox6</italic>, <italic>Dmrt1, Dax1 and Amh</italic>) to the Y chromosome of rainbow trout. As we will show, our results have eliminated these loci as candidates for the primary sex-determining gene in the rainbow trout. We also identified a duplication of <italic>Sox6 </italic>and discuss the inheritance of the duplicated <italic>Sox6 </italic>loci in our mapping families. In addition, we report the complete genomic sequence of <italic>Dax1 </italic>and a promoter subsequence analysis of <italic>Dax1 </italic>and <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>that implicates the role of <italic>Pax2 </italic>in trout testicular differentiation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Linkage analysis of <italic>Amh</italic>, <italic>Dax1 </italic>and <italic>Dmrt1</italic></title><p>Through comparison of rainbow trout <italic>Amh </italic>cDNA sequence with zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) orthologous genomic sequences, it was determined that the <italic>Amh </italic>gene of rainbow trout and zebrafish both have six tentative introns. We amplified, cloned and sequenced a 1.35 kb genomic fragment that contained the 3<sup>rd</sup>, 4<sup>th</sup>, 5<sup>th </sup>and 6<sup>th </sup>introns of <italic>Amh </italic>from the OSU and Arlee rainbow trout clonal lines (the presence of the 1<sup>st </sup>and 2<sup>nd </sup>introns remains tentative and still requires experimental verification). Intron sizes were 337 bp, 87 bp, 105 bp and 91 bp respectively. Comparison of OSU and Arlee intron sequences indicated the presence of a SNP in the 5<sup>th </sup>intron of OSU in a <italic>Tsp509I </italic>restriction site (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). PCR-RFLP with <italic>Tsp509I </italic>was used to genotype doubled haploids of the O &#x000d7; A mapping family for receiving either allele. Linkage analysis assigned <italic>Amh </italic>to linkage group 8 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), which corresponds to the short arm of chromosome 5 in the karyotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Typing of <italic>Amh, Dax1 </italic>and <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>genes and alleles by sequence polymorphisms in rainbow trout crosses.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Gene</td><td align="left">Accession numbers</td><td align="left">Parent</td><td align="left">Site of polymorphism</td><td align="left">Polymorphism</td><td align="left">Method of genotyping</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Amh</italic></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="FJ609190">FJ609190</ext-link></td><td align="left">Arlee</td><td align="left">82&#x02013;85 of fifth intron</td><td align="left">AAT(T)</td><td align="left">PCR-RFLP <italic>Tsp509I</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="FJ609189">FJ609189</ext-link></td><td align="left">OSU</td><td align="left">82&#x02013;85 of fourth intron</td><td align="left">AAT(G)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Dax1</italic></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="FJ617280">FJ617280</ext-link></td><td align="left">HC</td><td align="left">-10 of 5' UTR</td><td align="left"><bold>G</bold></td><td align="left">Taqman assay</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="FJ617279">FJ617279</ext-link></td><td align="left">OSU</td><td align="left">-10 of 5' UTR</td><td align="left"><bold>A</bold></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Dmrt1</italic></td><td align="left">--</td><td align="left">HC</td><td align="left">743 of first intron</td><td align="left">GTA<bold>(C)</bold></td><td align="left">PCR-RFLP <italic>Rsa1</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="FJ617281">FJ617281</ext-link></td><td align="left">OSU</td><td align="left">743 of first intron</td><td align="left">GTA<bold>(A)</bold></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Genetic map of rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) candidate sex-determining loci</bold>. Numbers on the left indicate distances in centimorgans. Marker names are indicated on the right. The linkage group number and the mapping family used for linkage analysis are indicated on top of each linkage group. Candidate sex-determining loci are underlined.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2156-10-2-1"/></fig><p>Prior to this study, the sequence of the first exon and part of the sequence of the second exon of rainbow trout <italic>Dax1 </italic>was deposited in nucleotide databases as an expressed sequence tag, EST [Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="BX298095">BX298095</ext-link>]. In order to look for sequence polymorphisms, more likely to be found in non-coding regions of the gene, we isolated and sequenced a complete genomic clone of the <italic>Dax1 </italic>gene [Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="FJ617278">FJ617278</ext-link>]. Tentative locations of the start codon, stop codon and exon-intron boundaries were inferred based on sequence alignment with cDNA sequences of <italic>Dax1 </italic>from <italic>Dicentrarchus labrax </italic>[Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AJ633646">AJ633646</ext-link>] and <italic>Oreochromis niloticus </italic>[Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AY135397">AY135397</ext-link>] and were not experimentally verified. Our sequence alignment indicated that the coding region of <italic>Dax1 </italic>contains an ORF of 909 bp and is organized into two exons (670 and 239 bp in size respectively) separated by a 560 bp intron. A 303 amino acid polypeptide was deduced from the inferred cDNA sequence.</p><p>No polymorphism between parental lines of our mapping family was detected in the intron, thus a 1.1 kb fragment of the genomic region located upstream to the putative coding sequence of <italic>Dax1 </italic>was amplified and sequenced to look for sequence polymorphisms. An (A/G) SNP between OSU and HC parental lines was found in the sequenced region (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Doubled haploids of the O &#x000d7; H mapping family were genotyped for either allele. Genotyping doubled haploids mapped <italic>Dax1 </italic>to linkage group 5 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), which corresponds to the long arm of chromosome 22 on the physical map [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>Sequence analysis revealed the presence of a SNP between OSU and HC that resulted in the loss of an <italic>RsaI </italic>site in the HC allele in a 1.89 Kb genomic fragment containing the first intron of <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>(Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). PCR-RFLP using <italic>Rsa1 </italic>restriction was used to genotype doubled haploids of the O &#x000d7; H mapping family for receiving either <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>allele but linkage analysis was unable to assign <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>to any linkage group in the O &#x000d7; H map. Chi-square analysis did not support linkage of the HC (YY) <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>allele with the Y chromosome of rainbow trout as indicated by phenotypic sex of the doubled haploid fish (&#x003c7;2 = 5.241, d.f. = 3, &#x003b1; = 0.05). One explanation for the failure to map <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>is the absence of markers closely linked with <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>in the genetic map. A second explanation would be that a duplicate of this gene may have also been amplified and interfered with accurate genotyping. However, a chi-square test (&#x003c7;2 = 2.572, d.f. = 1, &#x003b1;= 0.05) did not detect deviation from Mendelian ratios which would likely occur in such a situation.</p></sec><sec><title>Promoter Subsequence Analysis of <italic>Dax1 </italic>and <italic>Dmrt1</italic></title><p>Subsequence analysis of an upstream 1.2 Kb promoter sequence of <italic>Dax1 </italic>[Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="FJ617278">FJ617278</ext-link>] and a 649 bp promoter sequence of <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>[Genbank: <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="FJ617281">FJ617281</ext-link>] identified a number of transcription factor binding sites or <italic>cis </italic>regulatory elements (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Some of these elements are binding sites for products of genes known to be involved in the sex differentiation cascade of mammals including elements for SF1 (steroidegenic factor 1), WT1 (Wilms' tumor suppressor), COUP-TF (chicken ovalbumin upstream promoter-transcription factor), HMGA (high mobility group A) and PAX (paired domain box). Experiments in mammalian systems have demonstrated the interaction of the <italic>Dax1 </italic>gene product with SF1, WT1, and COUP-TF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Promoter sequence analysis of rainbow trout <italic>Dax1</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Element</td><td align="left">Sequence</td><td align="left">Location (bp)</td><td align="center">Strand</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">PAX5</td><td align="left">CTGTAGCACTGAAATGCAGTGCCTTAGAC</td><td align="left">-1096/-1124</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SF1</td><td align="left">ATCTCAAGGCCAT</td><td align="left">-816/-828</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">COUP-TF</td><td align="left">CCGAGTGGGGCAGCGGTCTAAGGCA</td><td align="left">-1082/-1105</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMGA</td><td align="left">ACAAATTCACAACTCCC</td><td align="left">-523/-539</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TATA box</td><td align="left">TAATATAAATGTGCTGC</td><td align="left">-123/-139</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">WT1</td><td align="left">TTGCGCGGGGGTATCAG</td><td align="left">-104/-119</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PAX 2/5/8</td><td align="left">CTTTGAAGAGTTG</td><td align="left">-52/-63</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SOX-5</td><td align="left">TTCTGACAATGCAGTAA</td><td align="left">-488/-504</td><td align="center">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Nucleotide positions correspond to the start codon.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Promoter sequence analysis of rainbow trout <italic>Dmrt1</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Element</td><td align="left">Sequence</td><td align="left">Location (bp)</td><td align="center">Strand</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SF1</td><td align="left">CCTACAAGGTTAC</td><td align="left">-176/-188</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SF1</td><td align="left">TTTGCAAGGCCAC</td><td align="left">-438/-450</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PAX2</td><td align="left">CAACTTCTCGCGACATTAAACAC</td><td align="left">-138/-160</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PAX3</td><td align="left">ACTGTCCCACGTGTACTCT</td><td align="left">-187/-205</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PAX6</td><td align="left">ATTAAACACTTCAATAAGA</td><td align="left">-128/-146</td><td align="center">+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Nucleotide positions correspond to the start codon.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Duplication and linkage analysis of <italic>Sox6</italic></title><p>Boundaries of eight putative introns were identified in <italic>Sox6 </italic>of rainbow trout by comparing the cDNA sequence from rainbow trout to genomic sequences of zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) and fugu (<italic>Takifugu rubripes</italic>). PCR amplification of the fourth intron of <italic>Sox6 </italic>from OSU and HC produced two products of differing size in each of the clonal lines. Following cloning and sequencing of all four products, OSU products were determined to be 984 and 1067 bp in size, while the sizes of the recovered products in HC were 984 and 1097 bp (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). Using the BLASTN algorithm, all four sequences were verified to be that of <italic>Sox6</italic>. The larger-sized OSU and HC alleles were named <italic>Sox6i </italic>while the smaller-sized alleles were named <italic>Sox6ii</italic>. Sequence analysis of the four different <italic>Sox6 </italic>alleles in OSU and HC revealed the presence of a microsatellite repeat nested in the 4<sup>th </sup>intron. The size difference between <italic>Sox6i </italic>and <italic>Sox6ii </italic>is due to an expansion in the size of the repeat (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). The size difference between the HC and OSU alleles at <italic>Sox6i </italic>is due to a 30 bp expansion of the microsatellite repeat in HC. No size or sequence polymorphisms were detected between OSU and HC at <italic>Sox6ii</italic>. The presence of two <italic>Sox6 </italic>products in each of the homozygous clonal lines (OSU and HC) indicated that <italic>Sox6 </italic>is duplicated in the rainbow trout.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Typing of <italic>Sox6 </italic>genes and alleles by sequence polymorphisms in rainbow trout crosses.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Gene</td><td align="left">Accession numbers</td><td align="left">parent</td><td align="left">Site of polymorphism</td><td align="left">Polymorphism</td><td align="left">Method of genotyping</td><td align="left">Size of marker</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Sox6ii</italic></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="EU848567">EU848567</ext-link></td><td align="left">Arlee</td><td align="left">725&#x02013;729 of fourth intron</td><td align="left">G<bold>(G)</bold>ACC</td><td align="left">PCR-RFLP <italic>Ava II</italic></td><td align="left">984 bp</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Sox6i</italic></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="EU848564">EU848564</ext-link></td><td align="left">OSU</td><td align="left">806&#x02013;810 of fourth intron</td><td align="left">G<bold>(G)</bold>ACC</td><td></td><td align="left">1067 bp</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Sox6ii</italic></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="EU848565">EU848565</ext-link></td><td align="left">OSU</td><td align="left">725 of fourth intron</td><td align="left">G<bold>(A)</bold>ACC</td><td></td><td align="left">984 bp</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Sox6i</italic></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="EU848568">EU848568</ext-link></td><td align="left">HC</td><td align="left">Size of fourth intron</td><td align="left">30 bp expansion</td><td align="left">Size polymorphism</td><td align="left">1097 bp</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Sox6ii</italic></td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="EU848569">EU848569</ext-link></td><td align="left">HC</td><td align="left">No polymorphism with <italic>Sox6ii </italic>of OSU</td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">984 bp</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>PCR amplification of the same intron from Arlee produced only one product 984 bp in size. Cloning and sequencing of the product did not show any sequence variants supporting the presence of a second <italic>Sox6 </italic>allele in Arlee. Sequence comparison revealed a polymorphism between OSU and Arlee parental lines that resulted in the loss of an <italic>AvaII </italic>restriction site in <italic>Sox6ii </italic>of OSU (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2(A)</xref>). PCR-RFLP with <italic>AvaII </italic>was used to genotype doubled haploids of the O &#x000d7; A mapping family (refer to Materials and Methods under linkage mapping for details on genotyping doubled haploids).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Inheritance of <italic>Sox6 </italic>alleles in the rainbow trout OSU &#x000d7; Arlee mapping family</bold>. (A) A schematic diagram showing the different <italic>Sox6 </italic>alleles in OSU and Arlee parental lines and the different genotype classes that were observed in doubled haploids of the OSU &#x000d7; Arlee mapping family. The OSU alleles are shown in solid lines while the Arlee alleles are shown in dashed lines. Restriction sites of <italic>AvaII </italic>enzyme are indicated by an inverted triangle on each respective <italic>Sox6 </italic>allele. The distance of each restriction site away from the 5' end of each respective allele is indicated above the triangle. Sizes of the different <italic>Sox6 </italic>alleles before their digestion with <italic>AvaII </italic>and the sizes observed in the mapping family following <italic>AvaII </italic>digestion are indicated with arrows. (B) A 2% agarose gel image of the different <italic>Sox6 </italic>alleles in OSU and Arlee parental lines and the different genotype classes observed in doubled haploids created by androgenesis from an OSU &#x000d7; Arlee hybrid. Look at part (A) for details.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2156-10-2-2"/></fig><p>In the O &#x000d7; A mapping family, linkage analysis assigned <italic>Sox6i </italic>to linkage group 18 (acrocentric chromosome 26) and <italic>Sox6ii </italic>to linkage group 10 (long arm of chromosome 6) supporting their homeology (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). This relationship was previously suggested by linkage analysis of duplicated microsatellites and by physical mapping of bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) clones of duplicated loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Since there were no polymorphisms in the recovered <italic>Sox6ii </italic>sequences between OSU and HC, this allele could not be mapped in the O &#x000d7; H cross. The size polymorphism in <italic>Sox6i </italic>between OSU and HC allowed us to map this gene to linkage group 18, in agreement with results from the O &#x000d7; A cross.</p></sec><sec><title>Inheritance of <italic>Sox6 </italic>alleles in the O &#x000d7; A family</title><p>Two models are considered here to explain the inheritance pattern of <italic>Sox6 </italic>loci in individuals of the O &#x000d7; A mapping family.</p><sec><title>1. Simple disomic inheritance with identical <italic>Sox6 </italic>Arlee alleles</title><p>If we assume that Arlee (A) has two identical <italic>Sox6 </italic>alleles and assume independent assortment and random segregation of OSU and Arlee alleles, four genotype classes should be observed: (1) OSU &#x02013; <italic>Sox6i</italic>/OSU &#x02013; <italic>Sox6ii </italic>(Genotype 1 in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) A &#x02013; <italic>Sox6i</italic>/A &#x02013; <italic>Sox6ii </italic>(Genotype 2) (3) OSU &#x02013; <italic>Sox6i</italic>/A &#x02013; <italic>Sox6ii </italic>(Genotype 3) (4) A &#x02013; <italic>Sox6i</italic>/OSU &#x02013; <italic>Sox6ii</italic>. This last genotype was not observed in the O &#x000d7; A family (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) which raises questions regarding validity of the model.</p></sec><sec><title>2. Simple disomic inheritance with failure to amplify <italic>Sox6i </italic>allele from Arlee</title><p>If we assume that primer combination used to amplify different <italic>Sox6 </italic>loci failed to amplify <italic>Sox6i </italic>allele in Arlee because of a mismatch in the primer sequence, or because of deletion of <italic>Sox6i </italic>in the Arlee lineage, <italic>Sox6i </italic>allele in Arlee can be genotyped as a null allele. Four genotype classes are expected in the O &#x000d7; A progeny if <italic>Sox6i </italic>is genotyped as a null allele: (1) OSU &#x02013; <italic>Sox6i</italic>/OSU &#x02013; <italic>Sox6ii </italic>(Genotype 1 in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) A &#x02013; <italic>null</italic>/A &#x02013; <italic>Sox6ii </italic>(Genotype 2) (3) OSU &#x02013; <italic>Sox6i</italic>/A &#x02013; <italic>Sox6ii </italic>(Genotype 3) (4) A -<italic>null</italic>/OSU &#x02013; <italic>Sox6ii </italic>(Genotype 4). Genotype analysis of the O &#x000d7; A mapping family showed that 23 out of 73 doubled haploids were of genotype 1, 20 doubled haploids were of genotype 2, another 20 doubled haploids were of genotype 3 and only 9 were of genotype 4. Chi-square analysis did not show significant deviation of the observed proportions for the different genotype classes from the theoretical proportions expected under this model (&#x003c7;2 = 6.2603, d.f. = 3, &#x003b1; = 0.05).</p><p>The (A -<italic>null</italic>/OSU &#x02013; <italic>Sox6ii</italic>) genotype can also be explained by failure of the <italic>AvaII </italic>restriction assays. Genotyping was however confirmed by digestion with <italic>NlaIII </italic>which also produces a distinctive restriction profile for each of the four genotype classes of the mapping family and thus ruling out this possibility (data not shown).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Additional candidate genes for sex-determination</title><p>We tested five loci for their linkage to the Y chromosome of rainbow trout in this study. In addition, three <italic>Sox9 </italic>loci (Alfaqih et al. Submitted) and three <italic>WT1 </italic>loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] have also been mapped in rainbow trout. This brings the total number of candidate genes of rainbow trout sex determination tested for linkage to the Y chromosome to eleven. All of the loci tested were chosen based on their role in sex determination in mammals and on expression during testicular differentiation of rainbow trout [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>].</p><p>A number of candidate genes can still be tested for their linkage to the sex locus of rainbow trout. In mammalian species, ten out of the 30 genes discovered so far in the <italic>Sox </italic>gene (<italic>Sry</italic>-related HMG box) family have been shown to be involved in the sex differentiation pathway or expressed in embryonic testes or ovaries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Rainbow trout orthologs of five of those genes have been deposited in GENBANK or the TIGR Rainbow Trout Gene Index. Genes of the DM domain (Doublesex and MAB-3 related) family are also strong candidates for sex determination in rainbow trout. There are at least six DM domain genes in fishes, most of them with unknown functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. In addition to <italic>Dmrt1</italic>, orthologous sequences of <italic>Dmrt2 </italic>and <italic>Dmrt4 </italic>have been isolated from rainbow trout [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Studying the gene expression profile of 102 genes involved in gonadal differentiation of rainbow trout, Baron et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] identified <italic>Pax2a </italic>as a gene that is expressed early in gonadal development and displays a testis-specific expression profile. Our study identified potential binding sites of <italic>Pax2 </italic>in the promoter sequences of <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>and <italic>Dax1 </italic>suggesting that members of this gene family should be explored in future analyses. Although our analysis focused on candidate genes that already have sequences deposited in public databases, paralogous loci might still be isolated and would also be strong candidates for sex-determination based on the model presented for evolution of sex-determining systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>It is largely accepted that the sex-determining system in rainbow trout is genetic with male heterogamety. Nonetheless, Quillet et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] reported an equal ratio of males and females in a mitotic gynogenetic family. Studying the transmission of maleness of XX gynogenetic fish across the next three generations, the authors concluded that unexpected maleness might be caused by a recessive mutation of a sex-influencing factor carried on an autosomal pair of chromosomes. This conclusion however was not accompanied by any genetic mapping of the causative mutation. Our mapping data of the candidate genes will thus be of great value in analysis of the inheritance of such an autosomal sex-determining factor.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Using linkage analysis, we excluded the role of five candidate loci as the primary sex-determining gene in rainbow trout. We also identified a duplication of the <italic>Sox6 </italic>locus. Inheritance pattern of <italic>Sox6 </italic>loci in O &#x000d7; A mapping family indicated possible deletion of <italic>Sox6i </italic>locus in the Arlee lineage. Our mapping data supports previously suggested homeology between linkage groups 10 and 18 in rainbow trout, and adds four known genes to its genomic map. Enrichment of the rainbow trout genomic map with type I markers allows the identification of conserved syntenic blocks between rainbow trout and other salmonid species, which would eventually allow for understanding the molecular organization of genomes following genome duplication. Although we did not find the primary sex-determining gene in this study, our data is of importance for analyses of potential autosomal modifiers of sex-determination in rainbow trout.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Mapping families and linkage maps</title><p>Two mapping families and their respective linkage maps have been used for this study. Mapping families are doubled haploid fish generated from F1 hybrids between two clonal lines using androgenesis. Clonal lines were produced by androgenesis and gynogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Each clonal line is homozygous at all loci and its isogenecity has been confirmed by multilocus DNA fingerprinting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p><sec><title>OSU &#x000d7; HC mapping family (O &#x000d7; H)</title><p>This family was produced from the F1 hybrid of the Oregon State University (OSU: XX female) and Hot Creek (HC: YY male) clonal lines. The family was previously described in Zimmerman et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] where it was used to identify a single major QTL affecting natural killer cell-like activity. In our study, 85 doubled haploid fish from the original mapping family were genotyped for polymorphisms in non-coding regions of the candidate genes <italic>Sox6</italic>, <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>and <italic>Dax1</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>OSU &#x000d7; Arlee mapping family (O &#x000d7; A)</title><p>This family was produced by androgenesis from a cross between the OSU (XX) and Arlee (AR; YY) clonal lines, previously used to generate a dense linkage map and is described in Young et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>] and Nichols et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. In our study, 76 doubled haploid fish of the original mapping family were genotyped for polymorphisms in non-coding regions of the candidate genes <italic>Sox6 </italic>and <italic>Amh</italic>. Synteny between the O &#x000d7; H and O &#x000d7; A linkage maps has been established [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Identification of polymorphisms in non-coding regions of candidate genes</title><sec><title>Primer design</title><p>In order to amplify genomic DNA fragments of non-coding regions of candidate genes, primers were designed to anneal within exons flanking tentative introns. Boundaries between exons and introns were predicted for <italic>Sox6</italic>, <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>and <italic>Amh </italic>through comparisons of their cDNA sequences from Genbank (<italic>Dmrt1</italic>; <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF209095">AF209095</ext-link> and <italic>Sox6</italic>; D61688) or TIGR gene index (<italic>Amh</italic>; <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="TC103383">TC103383</ext-link>) with genomic sequences of <italic>Takifugu rubripes </italic>and <italic>Danio rerio</italic>. Primer sequences are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Primer sequences for amplifying non-coding regions of candidate sex-determining genes in rainbow trout. </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Gene</td><td align="left">Cloning/Library screening primers</td><td align="left">Marker position</td><td align="left">Mapping primers</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Sox6</italic></td><td align="left">F: TTCACAGGCAGCAAGACCAG<break/>R: AACAGCGCTGTGGAGTTCAG</td><td align="left">4<sup>th </sup>intron</td><td align="left">MF: TTCACAGGCAGCAAGACCAG<break/>MR: AACAGCGCTGTGGAGTTCAG</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">SF: CTAGAGCTGCGGATGTTGTAAC<break/>SR: TGAGCCCACTGGCAGGTGTTC</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Amh</italic></td><td align="left">F: CATCACTTTCACCAGTCACTC<break/>R: TCGGTACTGCGTCTCACTG</td><td align="left">4<sup>th </sup>intron</td><td align="left">MF: CATCACTTTCACCAGTCACTC<break/>MR: TCGGTACTGCGTCTCACTG</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D</italic>ax1</td><td align="left">LF: CTCCGGTCACCGCAGGTTAC<break/>LR: AGGATCCGTTGCAACATGC</td><td align="left">5' UTR</td><td align="left">TF: CGAGCAGCACCCGATGTAG<break/>TR: CCTCGCGAGTGGCCAT</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">F: ACCTACAGCACCGAATATCAC<break/>R: GTTGTTGCCTTAGCTCAAGC</td><td></td><td align="left">P: CACGTGGTGCGCG<break/>P: CACGTGGCGCGCG</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Dmrt1</italic></td><td align="left">F: AGGAACCACGGCTACGTGT<break/>R: CAACCTCCTGACTGGACAG</td><td align="left">1<sup>st </sup>intron</td><td align="left">MF: CAGAAATGCAAACTGATCGC<break/>MR: CAACCTCCTGACTGGACAG</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>F and R, forward and reverse primers used for amplifying genomic fragments that were later cloned and sequenced; LF and LR, forward and reverse primers used for library screening; MF and MR, forward and reverse primers used for mapping each respective fragment; SF and SR; forward and reverse primers used for genotyping by size polymorphisms; TF and TR: forward and reverse primers used for genotyping by Taqman assay. P: Sequences of the probes used for genotyping by Taqman assay.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>PCR reactions</title><p>All PCR reactions were performed using a Thermolyne Amplitron II thermocycler. PCR reaction conditions began with denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 2 minutes, followed by 30 cycles of 94&#x000b0;C for 45 seconds, 60&#x000b0;C for 45 seconds and 72&#x000b0;C for 45 seconds. The reaction ended with a final extension step of 72&#x000b0;C for 2 minutes. All reactions were 20 &#x003bc;l in volume containing: 50 ng DNA template, 1&#x000d7; PCR buffer (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 pmoles of each primer, 0.25 mM dNTPs (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) and 1.5 U of Taq DNA Polymerase (Promega, Madison, WI).</p><sec><title>Cloning, sequencing and sequence alignments</title><p>Following the amplification of non-coding regions of candidate genes, PCR amplification products were resolved in a 2% agarose gel stained with ethidium bromide. Desired DNA fragments were gel-purified using Gene Clean (Bio 101, Vista, California), cloned into the pGEM-T Easy plasmid system (Promega, Madison, WI) and then sequenced at the Washington State University Laboratory for Biotechnology and Bioanalysis. Target gene sequence verification was performed using the BLASTN and BLASTX algorithms of the NCBI website. Sequence polymorphisms between parental alleles were identified by aligning them using Sequencher 3.11 software (version 3.1.1; Gene Codes, Ann Arbor, MI). Because cloning can introduce artifact sequence differences, polymorphisms were confirmed by direct sequencing of genomic DNA amplification products using a nested primer (nested primer sequences are not shown).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Isolation of Dax1 and Dmrt1 genomic sequences</title><p>A PCR-based approach (Brunelli et al. In press) was used to isolate lambda clones of <italic>Dax1 </italic>and <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>from a &#x003bb; Zap II (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA) genomic library created from an O &#x000d7; H F1 hybrid. Following sequencing of the <italic>Dax1 </italic>and <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>lambda library clones by PCR walking, the structure of the <italic>Dax1 </italic>gene was deduced based on sequence alignment with the relevant sequences of <italic>Dicentrarchus labrax </italic>and <italic>Oreochromis niloticus</italic>. Intron and promoter sequences of <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>were identified based on alignment of the recovered genomic clone with rainbow trout <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>published cDNA sequence.</p></sec><sec><title>Genotyping of doubled haploid populations</title><sec><title>PCR-RFLP</title><p>Non-coding sequences of the candidate genes <italic>Sox6, Dmrt1 and Amh </italic>have sequence substitutions between alleles of the different parental lines that alter recognition sequences of restriction enzymes (RE). Utilizing these differences, doubled haploid fish of the mapping family were genotyped for the parental allele containing the polymorphic restriction site by PCR amplification, followed by RE digestion. Products of the RE-digest were size-fractionated in 1.5% agarose gels. Appropriate restriction enzyme digestions were done in 20 &#x003bc;l volume reactions according to the manufacturer's directions (New England Bio-labs, Ipswich, MA). Gene-specific primers utilized in RFLP-genotyping are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>. Polymorphic RE-sites are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Taqman assay</title><p>A single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) was detected between OSU and HC in the deduced promoter region of <italic>Dax1</italic>. The polymorphism did not change any published recognition sequence of a RE. A Taqman assay (Applied Biosystems, Foster city, CA) was used to score doubled haploids of the O &#x000d7; H mapping family for having either OSU or HC alleles. Primers and probe sequences used in the Taqman assay are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Microsatellites</title><p>A microsatellite repeat nested in the <italic>Sox6 </italic>fourth intron was found to have a different size among the different <italic>Sox6 </italic>alleles (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). Size differences were large enough to be analyzed in a 2.5% agarose gel stained by ethidium bromide and viewed under UV light. Primer sequences used for amplifying the microsatellite are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>. Default PCR reaction conditions were used for the amplification.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Linkage mapping</title><p>Prior to linkage analysis, segregation data of all loci was checked for deviations from expected Mendelian ratios using a chi-square test (&#x003b1; = 0.05). Genotyping data of candidate genes was incorporated into the pre-constructed O &#x000d7; H and O &#x000d7; A linkage maps using Map Maker 3.0/EXP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Marker orders were retained from the previous publications using these families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. For <italic>Sox6</italic>, doubled haploids were genotyped for receiving OSU <italic>Sox6i </italic>or <italic>Sox6ii </italic>alleles, while the Arlee <italic>Sox6i </italic>allele was genotyped as a null allele. The locations of newly-genotyped loci were determined using the "try" command, with the Kosambi map function, a minimum LOD score of 3.0 and a maximum theta of 0.45.</p></sec><sec><title>Promoter sub-sequence analysis</title><p>A 2.2 Kb region upstream of <italic>Dax1 </italic>and 0.6 kb region upstream of <italic>Dmrt1 </italic>coding regions were sequenced from the isolated lambda clones. The promoter sequences were analyzed for the presence of putative regulatory elements for transcription factors known to be involved in sex differentiation using MatInspector software (Genomatix Software GmbH, Munich, Germany).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>MA drafted the manuscript, assisted in designing the study, recovered genomic sequences and genotyped doubled haploid fish of reference families. JB assisted in genotyping analyses and provided technical assistance. RD conducted linkage analysis on the reference families. GT conceived the study, participated in its design and coordinated the roles of the authors. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported in part by National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences grant ES012446 to James Nagler and by National Research Initiative grant 2006-35205-16728 from the USDA CSREES to Gary Thorgaard and Hubert Schwabl.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagahama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex determination and sex differentiation in fish: an overview of genetic, physiological, and environmental influences</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2002</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0044-8486(02)00057-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moving up the hierarchy: a hypothesis on the evolution of a genetic sex determination pathway</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><year>1995</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7702596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.950170113</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolutionary dynamics of sex determination</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>1990</fpage><lpage>1994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9748152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.281.5385.1990</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagahama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinomiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrey</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>DMY is a Y-specific DM-domain gene required for male development in the medaka fish</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>417</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12037570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature751</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schartl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex chromosome evolution in non-mammalian vertebrates</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15531158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gde.2004.09.005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seroussi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cnaani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Domokhovsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilberman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kocher</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulata</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amh and Dmrta2 genes map to tilapia (Oreochromis spp.) linkage group 23 within quantitative trait locus regions for sex determination</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>1573</fpage><lpage>1581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16951079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.106.059030</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex control in fish with particular reference to salmonids</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences</source><year>1982</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/f82-012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Haaf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>A duplicated copy of DMRT1 in the sex-determining region of the Y chromosome of the medaka, Oryzias latipes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>11778</fpage><lpage>11783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12193652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.182314699</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heteromorphic sex chromosomes in male rainbow trout</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1977</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>900</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">860122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.860122</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felip</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Noakes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphism and differentiation of rainbow trout Y chromosomes</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2004</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>1113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15644968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g04-059</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iturra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Imbert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and characterization of DNA sequence OmyP9 associated with the sex chromosomes in rainbow trout</article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>2001</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11520341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2540.2001.00845.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal differences among rainbow trout populations</article-title><source>Copeia</source><year>1983</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>650</fpage><lpage>662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1444329</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>GAE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adult triploids in a rainbow trout family</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1979</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>961</fpage><lpage>973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">546676</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinomiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul-Prasanth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>E-l</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaizumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagahama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DMY gene induces male development in genetically female (XX) medaka fish</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>3865</fpage><lpage>3870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0611707104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allendorf</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tetraploidy and the evolution of salmonid fishes</article-title><source>The Evolutionary Genetics of Fishes</source><year>1984</year><publisher-name>New York: Plenum publishing</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunelli</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Robison</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ancient and recent duplications of the rainbow trout Wilms' tumor gene</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2001</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11444705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/gen-44-3-455</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeKoning</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Morasch</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Keatley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rexroad</surname><given-names>C</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Gahr</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Danzmann</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assignment of rainbow trout linkage groups to specific chromosomes</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>1661</fpage><lpage>1670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16951085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.105.055269</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burris</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>ERB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a Putative Steroidogenic Factor-1 Response Element in the DAX-1 Promoter</article-title><source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications</source><year>1995</year><volume>214</volume><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7677767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1995.2324</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Prawitt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardeesy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Torban</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicaner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Wilms' Tumor Suppressor Gene (wt1) Product Regulates Dax-1 Gene Expression during Gonadal Differentiation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2289</fpage><lpage>2299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10022915</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jameson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Murine Dax-1 Promoter Is Stimulated by SF-1 (Steroidogenic Factor-1) and Inhibited by COUP-TF (Chicken Ovalbumin Upstream Promoter-Transcription Factor) via a Composite Nuclear Receptor-Regulatory Element</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1010</fpage><lpage>1022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9658405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/me.12.7.1010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guyomard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabet-Canale</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Martineau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Genet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Quillet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A type I and type II microsatellite linkage map of rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) with presumptive coverage of all chromosome arms</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>302</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17137492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-7-302</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Danzmann</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Robison</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rexroad</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Noakes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentzen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Spies</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>A consolidated linkage map for rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss)</article-title><source>Anim Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12648093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2052.2003.00957.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Houlgatte</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fostier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiguen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-scale temporal gene expression profiling during gonadal differentiation and early gametogenesis in rainbow trout</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>2005</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16014816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1095/biolreprod.105.041830</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schepers</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Koopman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny of the SOX family of developmental transcription factors based on sequence and structural indicators</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11071752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/dbio.2000.9883</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koopman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Origin and possible roles of the SOX8 transcription factor gene during sexual development</article-title><source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000074339</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schartl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary dynamics of the DM domain gene family in metazoans</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>2003</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>S241</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15008421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00239-003-0033-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Govoroun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Cotta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>McMeel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lareyre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Laudet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiguen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DMRT1 expression during gonadal differentiation and spermatogenesis in the rainbow trout, Oncorhynchus mykiss</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2000</year><volume>1493</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10978520</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quillet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Queau</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutation in a sex-determining gene in rainbow trout: detection and genetic analysis</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>2002</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12140268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/93.2.91</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of androgenetic diploid rainbow trout</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1985</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3998440</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheerer</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Allendorf</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of androgenetic rainbow trout</article-title><source>J Exp Zool</source><year>1991</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1744618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jez.1402600312</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheleer</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA fingerprinting confirms isogenecity of androgenetically derived rainbow trout lines</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1996</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8742822</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Evenhuis</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ristow</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single major chromosomal region controls natural killer cell-like activity in rainbow trout</article-title><source>Immunogenetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14968267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00251-004-0645-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coryell</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorgaard</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A detailed linkage map of rainbow trout produced using doubled haploids</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1998</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9504929</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrahamson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Newburg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MAPMAKER: An interactive computer package for constructing primary genetic linkage maps of experimental and natural populations</article-title><source>Genomics</source><year>1987</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3692487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0888-7543(87)90010-3</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>