<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Case Reports</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Medical Case Reports</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1752-1947</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19063741</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2633360</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1752-1947-2-379</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-1947-2-379</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Takotsubo cardiomyopathy in a patient with esophageal cancer: a case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gangadhar</surname><given-names>Tara C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>taracg@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Von der Lohe</surname><given-names>Elisabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>evonderl@iupui.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>Stephen G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>ssawada@iupui.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Helft</surname><given-names>Paul R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>phelft@iupui.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Medicine, Indiana University Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN 46202, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Indiana University School of Medicine Indiana University Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN 46202, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Division of Cardiology, Indiana University Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN 46202, USA</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Division of Hematology/Oncology, Indiana University Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN 46202, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmedicalcasereports.com/content/2/1/379"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Gangadhar et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gangadhar et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Gangadhar               C               Tara                                             taracg@gmail.com            </dc:author><dc:title>            Takotsubo cardiomyopathy in a patient with esophageal cancer: a case report         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Medical Case Reports 2(1): 379-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1752-1947(2008)2:1&#x0003c;379&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1752-1947</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Takotsubo cardiomyopathy has increasingly been reported in the medical literature in recent years. Much is still unknown regarding risk factors and clinical relationships. We contribute this case report to the growing set of literature on the topic.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p>We report the case of a 64-year-old woman with esophageal cancer who developed takotsubo cardiomyopathy, a form of reversible heart failure, and we present a review of the literature. Patients present with symptoms similar to an acute coronary syndrome; however, cardiac catheterization reveals patent coronary arteries, and symptoms of heart failure resolve completely within weeks.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>It is important that clinicians consider takotsubo cardiomyopathy in the differential diagnosis of heart failure and gain a basic understanding of the clinical presentation and diagnosis.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Takotsubo cardiomyopathy, also known as stress-induced cardiomyopathy, has increasingly been reported in the medical literature in recent years. While case series outlining the clinical features of the disease have now been published, much is still unknown regarding risk factors and clinical relationships. We contribute this case report to the growing set of literature on the topic.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 64-year-old woman with unresectable squamous cell carcinoma of the mid esophagus was treated with definitive chemoradiotherapy, including 4500 cGy of external beam radiotherapy and two cycles of cisplatin and a continuous venous infusion of 5-fluorouracil. Three months later, she was admitted to the hospital with new onset of choking with both solid and liquid foods. Her past medical history included generalized anxiety disorder and hypercholesterolemia. She had an extensive smoking history, but no known history of cardiac disease. A barium esophagram on admission revealed a tracheo-esophageal fistula for which she underwent a successful endoscopic stent placement with a self-expanding metallic stent.</p><p>One day after the procedure, the patient developed substernal chest pain. Serial electrocardiograms revealed ST elevation in the anterior and lateral leads. Troponin measurements rose to 12.3 ng/ml; serum creatine kinase MB peaked at 10.6 ng/ml. Echocardiography revealed severely reduced global left ventricular systolic function and normal basal systolic function. Regional wall motion abnormalities were noted in the left anterior descending, left circumflex and right coronary artery distributions. The patient developed clinical signs of left-sided heart failure, including acute hypoxemic respiratory failure, and required intubation and mechanical ventilation. An emergency cardiac catheterization revealed normal, patent coronary arteries. A left ventriculogram revealed apical dilation of the left ventricle with akinesis of the whole ventricle except for the anterior and posterior base (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Cardiology consultants felt that the patient's clinical and echocardiographic features met the diagnostic criteria for takotsubo cardiomyopathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The patient was managed conservatively with diuresis and had a rapid clinical improvement; she was extubated after 2 days. She was found to have marked improvement in regional wall motion and left ventricular systolic function on a repeat echocardiogram 6 days later (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). She had no clinical signs of congestive heart failure during follow-up 2.5 weeks later, making an ischemic or radiation induced irreversible cardiomyopathy unlikely.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Left ventriculography during systole showing apical ballooning akinesis with basal hyperkinesis in a characteristic takotsubo ventricle</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-1947-2-379-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Echocardiograph showing dilatation of the left ventricle in the acute phase</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-1947-2-379-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Resolution of left ventricular function on repeat echocardiograph 6 days later</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-1947-2-379-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Takotsubo cardiomyopathy is a rare form of reversible heart failure that has been reported primarily in Japan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] and, more recently, in Europe and the United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Several cases have been described previously but, to the best of the authors' knowledge, this is the first full case report in a patient with cancer. The name of the syndrome derives from the classic appearance of the left ventricle, with an akinetic apex and hyperkinetic base, which takes the shape of a Japanese octopus fishing pot, or <italic>takotsubo</italic>. Also known as an apical ballooning syndrome, this cardiomyopathy occurs primarily in women in the seventh and eighth decades of life and is often associated with an acute physiological or emotional stress.</p><p>Patients present clinically with an acute coronary syndrome, frequently with chest pain at rest. ST elevations are present in electrocardiograms, most often in the precordial leads with evolutionary T wave inversions and corrected QT interval prolongation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Serum laboratory studies reveal a moderate rise in cardiac enzymes. Unlike patients with acute coronary syndrome, coronary angiography usually reveals patent coronary arteries with no significant luminal stenosis or thrombosis. As in our patient, left ventriculography demonstrates an akinetic apex and hyperkinetic left ventricular base. According to proposed criteria for diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], takotsubo cardiomyopathy is characterized by presentation and electrocardiographic changes similar to those caused by myocardial infarction; however, atherosclerotic coronary artery disease is usually absent and the transient left ventricular apical akinesis is usually beyond the distribution of a single coronary artery. An emotional or physiological stressor is identified in almost all cases. These findings are followed by a prompt resolution of symptoms with complete echocardiographic and clinical recovery of cardiac pump function within 2 to 3 weeks of presentation.</p><p>The etiology of takotsubo cardiomyopathy is not well understood, but is thought to be related to stress. Ueyama et al. have demonstrated reversible left ventricle apical ballooning in an animal model of emotional stress, rat immobilization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In line with a stress-related mechanism, catecholamine-induced myocardial injury has been proposed, with elevated norepinephrine levels noted in many patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Others have proposed microcirculatory dysfunction as a possible mechanism of disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>Treatment for takotsubo cardiomyopathy consists of supportive care of the patient during the period of reversible heart failure with hemodynamic support and appropriate treatment of complications, most commonly left ventricular dysfunction and arrhythmias. The prognosis of patients with takotsubo cardiomyopathy is good, with low in-hospital mortality and no reported increased risk of cardiac or other long-term morbidity or mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Although takotsubo cardiomyopathy has increasingly been reported in recent years, the prevalence is likely underestimated because of the low level of awareness and infrequent diagnosis. While suspicion of stress-induced cardiomyopathy does not justify withholding reperfusion therapy when indicated, increasing awareness among physicians will improve recognition and clinical management. Furthermore, adding to the literature provides a broader reference for studying clinical relationships in this illness and highlights its underestimated prevalence.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient's next-of-kin for publication of this case report and accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>TG and PH conceived of the case report and drafted the manuscript. EV and SS performed and interpreted diagnostic studies, provided images for figures, and critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bybee</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barsness</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rihal</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic review: transient left ventricular apical ballooning: a syndrome that mimics ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>858</fpage><lpage>865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15583228</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of clinical features in transient left ventricular apical ballooning</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12628715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0735-1097(02)02925-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The clinical features of takotsubo cardiomyopathy</article-title><source>QJM</source><year>2003</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12897341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/qjmed/hcg096</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuchihashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueshima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh-mura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Owa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haze</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transient left ventricular apical ballooning without coronary artery stenosis: a novel heart syndrome mimicking acute myocardial infarction. Angina pectoris-myocardial infarction investigations in Japan</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11451258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0735-1097(01)01316-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Aurigemma</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasnow</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tighe</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Untereker</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A syndrome of transient left ventricular apical wall motion abnormality in the absence of coronary disease: a perspective from the United States</article-title><source>Cardiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14557691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000073040</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desmet</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adriaenssens</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dens</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apical ballooning of the left ventricle: first series in white patients</article-title><source>Heart</source><year>2003</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12923018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/heart.89.9.1027</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasamatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuruo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishio</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emotional stress induces transient left ventricular hypocontraction in the rat via activation of cardiac adrenoceptors: a possible animal model of 'tako-tsubo' cardiomyopathy</article-title><source>Circ J</source><year>2002</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>712</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12135146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1253/circj.66.712</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Senba</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasamatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishio</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuruo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanism of emotional stress-induced and catecholamine-induced heart attack</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Pharmacol</source><year>2003</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>S115</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12688407</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gianni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dentali</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiralal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apical ballooning syndrome or takotsubo cardiomyopathy: a systematic review</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16720686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehl032</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bybee</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barsness</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rihal</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics and thrombolysis in myocardial infarction frame counts in women with transient left ventricular apical ballooning syndrome</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15276100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjcard.2004.04.030</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>