<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Adv Urol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AU</journal-id><journal-title>Advances in Urology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1687-6369</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1687-6377</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19197375</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2633451</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2009/978038</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Novel Use for the Rigid Cystoscope: The Removal of  Sacral Tacks after a Coloanal Anastamosis Dehiscence</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmalji</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chopada</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raza</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Urology, Ealing Hospital NHS Trust, Middlesex UB1 3HW, UK</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Colo-Rectal Surgery, Ealing Hospital NHS Trust, Middlesex UB1 3HW, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*W. Mahmalji: <email>dr_wasim@hotmail.co.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Recommended by Douglas Scherr</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>2009</volume><elocation-id>978038</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 W. Mahmalji et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A 69-year-old female presented as an emergency with atrial fibrillation, which was treated with warfarin. She subsequently developed fresh rectal bleeding and after further investigations a Dukes B adenocarcinoma of the rectum was found. She subsequently underwent a low anterior resection, coloanal anastamosis and a defunctioning ileostomy. Three sterile surgical metallic tacks (pins) were inserted into the sacrum to stop brisk bleeding from the presacral venous plexus. Following discharge, she was readmitted with septic shock and a CT scan revealed a presacral fluid collection in the area surrounding the sacral tacks (pins) and an anastamotic dehiscence. The patient was not fit for further pelvic surgery to remove the tacks, so an alternative minimally invasive cystoscopic procedure was performed. The sacral tacks (pins) were removed by the urologist using a rigid cystoscope and cold cup biopsy forceps. To our knowledge, this is the first reported case in the literature.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="section" id="sec1"><title>1. Case Report</title><p>A 69-year-old Caucasian female presented as an emergency in November2006 with atrial fibrillation, which was treated with warfarin. Within onemonth, she developed fresh rectal bleeding. Her international normalised ratio  (INR) was 2.4. Her past medical historyincluded, type 2 diabetes, left renal calculi, and an anterior myocardialinfarction in 2001 (followed by a coronary angio-bypass graft). Subsequentinpatient investigations revealed a Dukes B adenocarcinoma of the rectum 5 cmfrom the anal verge. She underwent a low anterior resection, coloanalanastamosis and a defunctioning ileostomy. The procedure was complicated by presacral venous plexus haemorrhage. Attemptsto control the bleeding with packing and suturing were unsuccessful; threesterile surgical metallic tacks (pins) were inserted into the sacrum tocompress the veins and stop the bleeding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). This successfullycontrolled the haemorrhage and no transfusion was required.</p><p>After dischargeshe was referred back to the surgical team with hypotension and a temperature of37.8&#x000b0;C. Her systolic bloodpressure was consistently below 90 mmHg, and she was tachycardic with a pulserate of 96 bpm. Examination revealed a purulent, foul smelling discharge oozingfrom the drain site wound. The patient was oliguric. Initial blood tests showedthe following: white cell count, 22.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>9</sup>/L  (3&#x02013;10 &#x000d7; 10<sup>9</sup>/L);CRP, 16 mg/L (0&#x02013;5 mg/L); sodium,131 mmol/L (135&#x02013;145 mmoL/L); Potassium,8.8 mmoL/L (3.5&#x02013;5.1 mmoL/L); ureaof 38.3 mmol/L (1.7&#x02013;8.3 mmoL/L); creatinineof 986 umoL/L (49&#x02013;92 umoL/L). Arterialblood gas sampling on room air revealed the following: pH, 7.197 (7.35&#x02013;7.45); PCO<sub>2</sub>, 2.82 kPam; PaO2, 16.1 kPa; base excess &#x02212;18.2 (&#x02212;2 to 2); cHCO3 8.0.</p><p>She was admittedto the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) for haemofiltration for acute renal failureand management of her septic shock. Intravenous cefuroxime and metronidazole antibioticswere started. A CT of her abdomen and pelvis revealed a large 9.0 cm by 3.5 cm presacralcollection with flecks of gas. Her abdominal drain wound swab cultured methicillin-resistantstaphylococcus aureus (MRSA); linozolid was added to her antibiotic regimen.</p><p>Her discharge fromICU was followed by a transfer to the Coronary Care Unit (CCU) for palpitationsand increasing shortness of breath. An echocardiogram showed moderate to severeleft ventricular function and mitral regurgitation.</p><p>She continued tobe treated conservatively for her pelvic collection and sepsis in CCU. Withinone month she became hypotensive and was readmitted to ICU for inotropicsupport. Her worsening sepsis wastreated with tazocin, ciprofloxacin, and metronidazole, and the presacralcollection was drained under CT guidance. A rigid sigmoidoscopy showed pusaround the anastamosis, and a gastrografin enema revealed an anastamoticleak. A colostomy was considered butcancelled due to her poor cardiac function and breathlessness on minimalexertion. Other contraindications to invasive surgery and a general anaestheticincluded a weight loss of 3.5 stone (24.5 Kg), ongoing sepsis and recurrent urinarytract infections (UTI's). A CT Urogram (CT-IVU) was organised to investigateher renal tract and recurrent urinary tract infections, this revealed left-sidedhydronephrosis and 3 cm by 1 cm presacral thick-walled collection around theregion of the surgical tacks (pins) in the sacrum. Attempts were made tooptimise her nutritional status and improve her sepsis prior to surgicalremoval of the tacks, as it was felt they may be the underlying cause of hersepsis.</p><p>After a month shewas still unfit for major invasive surgery or a general anaesthetic. A decisionwas made to remove the tacks through the rectum by passing a rigid cystoscope throughthe anastamotic defect and removing these from the sacrum. She underwent anexamination under spinal anaesthesia. The sacral tacks (pins) were removed bythe urologist using a Storz 22 French standard rigid cystoscope with a 30&#x000b0; lens. Normalsaline was used as irrigation fluid although the view was still slightlyrestricted by the inflammatory tissue and some bleeding as the tacks (pins)were removed. The tacks (pins) were identified by their gold colour. The tacks (pins)were removed using a standard cold cup biopsy forceps. The edge of the circulartack (pin) was difficult to pick up with the biopsy forceps and the pin had tobe levered of the sacrum by applying counter pressure on the sacrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). All 3 tacks were successfully removed although the patient did feel somediscomfort during the procedure due to pressure on the sacrum during pinremoval. There was moderate oozing from the sacrum after the tacks were removedand further haemostasis was achieved using a single strip of surgicell whichwas left in the cavity.</p><p>The patient made anexcellent recovery postprocedure, with improving infective and inflammatorymarkers confirming resolution of the inflammatory response. The patient had afollow-up CT scan of her abdomen on 24/10/2007 and although the presacral collectionimprovement was minimal from a previous CT scan 4 months earlier (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>),clinically the patient was much improved.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec2"><title>2. Discussion</title><p>The use of therigid cystoscope in the anus and rectum has been described previously for closureof genitourinary fistulae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] and the resection of rectal villousadenomas or adenocarcinomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. However this case is unique and isthe first reported case in the literature. The use of a rigid cystoscope toremove the sacral tacks was possible using the cold cup biopsy forceps butcould have been made easier in retrospect if a Collins knife or perhaps a steelwire basket had been used. This would have allowed the edge of the drawing pin(tack) to be lifted of the sacrum more readily as the tack was well embeddedinto the sacral bone. This case demonstrates how close cross surgical specialtyreferral and team work can help solve an unusual problem in a patient not fitfor a general anaesthetic.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrentschuk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Precise application of fibrin glue into a fistula between the rectal stump and urinary bladder&#x02014;a new technique</article-title><source><italic>The American Journal of Case Reports</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>CR178</fpage><lpage>CR181</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvert</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic transanal resection of rectal tumours using a urological resectoscope&#x02014;still has a role in selected patients</article-title><source><italic>Colorectal Disease</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15606584</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuech</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pessaux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Regenet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ollier</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnaud</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic transanal resection using the urological resectoscope in the management of patients with rectal villous adenomas</article-title><source><italic>International Journal of Colorectal Disease</italic></source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15103489</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Computerised tomography (CT) scout film showing the placement ofthe surgical tacks in the sacrum.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="AU2009-978038.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>This is an illustration of the cold cut biopsy forceps passingthrough the anastamotic defect, and removing the tacks in the sacrum.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="AU2009-978038.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(a) CT precystoscopic tack removal. Note the thickwalled presacral collection. (b) CT post cystoscopic tack removal. Although the improvementin pre-sacral soft tissue thickening and fluid collection is minimal, thepatient was clinically much improved.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="AU2009-978038.003"/></fig></floats-wrap></article>