<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19099577</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2635384</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2164-9-618</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-9-618</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of microsatellite markers from the olive fly, <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic>, and their cross-species amplification in the Tephritidae family</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Augustinos</surname><given-names>Antonios A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>augustin@upatras.gr</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stratikopoulos</surname><given-names>Elias E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>is2193@columbia.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drosopoulou</surname><given-names>Eleni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>edrosopo@bio.auth.gr</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kakani</surname><given-names>Evdoxia G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>evkakani@bio.uth.gr</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mavragani-Tsipidou</surname><given-names>Penelope</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>mavragan@bio.auth.gr</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zacharopoulou</surname><given-names>Antigone</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>zacharop@upatras.gr</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mathiopoulos</surname><given-names>Kostas D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>kmathiop@bio.uth.gr</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Biology, University of Patras, Patras, Greece</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Biochemistry and Biotechnology, University of Thessaly, Thessaly, Greece</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Biology, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Greece</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Genetics and Development, Columbia University, New York, NY 10032, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><fpage>618</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/9/618"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Augustinos et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Augustinos et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Augustinos               A               Antonios                                             augustin@upatras.gr            </dc:author><dc:title>            Isolation and characterization of microsatellite markers from the olive fly, Bactrocera oleae, and their cross-species amplification in the Tephritidae family         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Genomics 9(1): 618-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2164(2008)9:1&#x0003c;618&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2164</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The Tephritidae family of insects includes the most important agricultural pests of fruits and vegetables, belonging mainly to four genera (<italic>Bactrocera, Ceratitis, Anastrepha </italic>and <italic>Rhagoletis</italic>). The olive fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic>, is the major pest of the olive fruit. Currently, its control is based on chemical insecticides. Environmentally friendlier methods have been attempted in the past (Sterile Insect Technique), albeit with limited success. This was mainly attributed to the lack of knowledge on the insect's behaviour, ecology and genetic structure of natural populations. The development of molecular markers could facilitate the access in the genome and contribute to the solution of the aforementioned problems. We chose to focus on microsatellite markers due to their abundance in the genome, high degree of polymorphism and easiness of isolation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Fifty-eight microsatellite-containing clones were isolated from the olive fly, <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic>, bearing a total of sixty-two discrete microsatellite motifs. Forty-two primer pairs were designed on the unique sequences flanking the microsatellite motif and thirty-one of them amplified a PCR product of the expected size. The level of polymorphism was evaluated against wild and laboratory flies and the majority of the markers (93.5%) proved highly polymorphic. Thirteen of them presented a unique position on the olive fly polytene chromosomes by <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization, which can serve as anchors to correlate future genetic and cytological maps of the species, as well as entry points to the genome. Cross-species amplification of these markers to eleven Tephritidae species and sequencing of thirty-one of the amplified products revealed a varying degree of conservation that declines outside the <italic>Bactrocera </italic>genus.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Microsatellite markers are very powerful tools for genetic and population analyses, particularly in species deprived of any other means of genetic analysis. The presented set of microsatellite markers possesses all features that would render them useful in such analyses. This could also prove helpful for species where SIT is a desired outcome, since the development of effective SIT can be aided by detailed knowledge at the genetic and molecular level. Furthermore, their presented efficacy in several other species of the Tephritidae family not only makes them useful for their analysis but also provides tools for phylogenetic comparisons among them.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>The Tephritidae family of insects includes the most important agricultural pests of fruits and vegetables. Most of them belong to four genera: <italic>Bactrocera</italic>, <italic>Ceratitis</italic>, <italic>Anastrepha </italic>and <italic>Rhagoletis</italic>. <italic>Ceratitis </italic>includes 89 different species. Among them, the Medfly, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic>, is the best so far studied member of the family and attacks over 350 different fruits and vegetables in tropical and sub-tropical regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], causing damages of hundreds of billions $ per year. <italic>Anastrepha </italic>is the most economically important genus of pests in the American tropics and subtropics and includes more than fifteen economically important pests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. <italic>Rhagoletis </italic>includes more than 60 described species distributed in Eurasia and the New World, several of which are important pests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. <italic>Bactrocera </italic>is among the largest genera in Tephritidae including about 500 species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Many of them are serious pests of fruits and vegetables in different parts of the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The only member of this genus present in Europe is the olive fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic>, the major pest of the olive fruit, with estimated damages of 5&#x02013;30% of the global olive production, resulting in economic losses of about 800 million $ per year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Quarantine orders against non-indigenous Tephritidae exist in all countries, demonstrating the appreciation of these species' destructive abilities and invasiveness success [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p><p>Currently, control of these insects is based on chemical insecticides. The Sterile Insect Technique (SIT) is the most promising, environmentally friendly method, based on the mass production and release of sterile insects into field populations. When the released males mate with the field females no progeny are produced and the field population may finally be suppressed. The appreciation of the negative effect of the released females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] lead to the development of genetic sexing strains (GSS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Successful development of such approaches, however, presupposes an understanding of the species at the genetic, molecular and population level. Additionally, new molecular and genetic tools, such as genetic transformation, could prove very helpful since they can improve mass rearing of effective male insects. Such knowledge developed in the Medfly lead to successful SIT protocols (for a review, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]), whereas respective lack in the olive fly lead to fruitless attempts. In the early '70s, efforts to employ the SIT against the olive fly were unsuccessful [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], principally due to the low competitiveness of the sterile mass-reared males compared to the wild ones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Several molecular and genetic studies have changed <italic>B. oleae</italic>'s research landscape in recent years. Among them we mention studies on population genetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], cytogenetics (for a review see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]), sex-determining cascades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] and, most notably, the successful genetic transformation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], an achievement that gives new perspectives towards the efficient use of the SIT.</p><p>Microsatellites constitute very powerful genetic and molecular markers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. In the Medfly they have been used to identify sources of origin, invasion phenomena, to design control strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], as well as in the genetic mapping of the species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. This last possibility renders microsatellite markers particularly useful in the olive fly, since several years of efforts have provided no morphological markers and therefore the development of classical genetics has been entirely hindered (Mavragani, unpublished; Zacharopoulou, unpublished). In addition, such markers can also be helpful in SIT development. For example, they have been successfully used in the analysis of mating systems in <italic>B. dorsalis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>] and <italic>C. capitata </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] and they can be used to detect the degree of differentiation between laboratory and wild flies, the main reason of SIT failure in the olive fly.</p><p>The present study enriches a previously described set of 15 microsatellite markers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] with 16 new ones. Most of these markers were proven polymorphic, some of them were localized in the polytene chromosomes of the species and many of them were successfully cross-amplified in other Tephritidae species. Their utility in genetic studies and evolutionary comparisons is considered.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Isolation and characterization of microsatellites from small-insert genomic libraries and enriched libraries</title><p>Thirty-four microsatellite containing clones were isolated from small-insert genomic libraries and 24 from enriched libraries, yielding a total of 36 and 26 discrete microsatellite motifs, respectively, since a few of them contained more than one microsatellite motif (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Despite the use of an equal mix of (GT)<sub>15 </sub>and (CT)<sub>15 </sub>as probes, there was a clear predominance of GT over CT repeats obtained from the small-insert library. This most likely reflects a difference in the abundance of these sequences in the genome, as has been the case in other Diptera, such as <italic>D. melanogaster </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>], <italic>D. simulans </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>], <italic>A. gambiae </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] and <italic>C. capitata </italic>(Stratikopoulos et al., submitted) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. In hymenoptera, CT repeats seem to be more abundant than GT repeats, as studies in <italic>Apis mellifera </italic>and <italic>Bombus terrestris </italic>reveal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Microsatellite loci motif and <italic>in situ </italic>localization to polytene chromosomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Accession number</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Locus name</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Motif</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Map position</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>T (&#x000b0;C)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">EU489746</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms1</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>13</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">AF467831</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms2</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>8</sub>TA(CA)<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center">4 (IL)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">EU489747</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms3</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>14</sub><break/>(CAA)<sub>3</sub>CAG(CAA)<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center">no specific signal</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">EU489748</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms4</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>15</sub>GC(GT)<sub>3</sub>GC(GT)<sub>13</sub>GA(GT)<sub>4</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">EU489749</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms5</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>10</sub>TA(CA)<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">95 (VR)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">EU489750</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms6</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>9</sub><break/>(GT)<sub>3</sub>GG(GT)<sub>11</sub>TT(GT)<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">EU489751</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms7</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>7</sub>CC(CA)<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">EU489752</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms8</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>7</sub>CG(CA)<sub>5</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">EU489753</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms9</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>10</sub>CTGA(GT)<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">AF467830</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms10</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>10</sub>GA(CA)<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">no specific signal</td><td align="center">55&#x02013;62</td></tr><tr><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">AF467832</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms11 (Bo-D37)</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>7</sub>CG(CA)<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">EU489754</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms12</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>10</sub>AACA</td><td align="center">26 (IIL)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">EU489755</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms13</italic></td><td align="center">GTGA(GT)<sub>10</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">EU489756</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms14</italic></td><td align="center">(AT)<sub>2</sub>GT(AT)<sub>11</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">EU489757</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms15</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>11</sub>GA(GT)<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">no specific signal</td><td align="center">55&#x02013;62</td></tr><tr><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">AF467829</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms16 (Bo-D46)</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>10</sub></td><td align="center">42(IIR)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">EU489758</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms17</italic></td><td align="center">(TG)<sub>13</sub></td><td align="center">44(IIR)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">AF467828</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms18</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>13</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">EU489759</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms19</italic></td><td align="center">CAAA(CA)<sub>10</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">EU489760</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms20</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>13+</sub></td><td align="center">8(IL) 2 signals</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">21</td><td align="center">AF467827</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms21</italic></td><td align="center">GTGG(GT)<sub>13</sub>ATGT</td><td align="center">73(IVL)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">DQ078248</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms22</italic></td><td align="center">CAT(CA)<sub>7</sub>(TA)<sub>3</sub>TT(TA)<sub>5</sub></td><td align="center">5(IL)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">EU489761</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms23</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>12</sub></td><td align="center">3(IL)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">EU489762</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms24</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>12</sub></td><td align="center">64(IIIR)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">AF467826</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms25</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>12</sub></td><td align="center">30(IIL), 97&#x00026;100(VR)</td><td align="center">58/62</td></tr><tr><td align="center">26</td><td align="center">EU489763</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms26</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>8</sub>AT(GT)<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">26(IIL)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">27</td><td align="center">AF467825</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms27 (Bo-D52)</italic></td><td align="center">(GA)<sub>14</sub></td><td align="center">83(IVR)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">28</td><td align="center">EU489764</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms28</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>12</sub>CT(CA)<sub>5 </sub>(GA)<sub>12</sub>GG(GA)<sub>11</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">29</td><td align="center">AF467824</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms29</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>10</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">30</td><td align="center">AF467823</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms30</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>17</sub></td><td align="center">5&#x02013;6(IL)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">31</td><td align="center">DQ078249</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms31</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>4</sub>GC(GT)<sub>6</sub>GC(GT)<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">63&#x00026;65(IIIR)</td><td align="center">58,62</td></tr><tr><td align="center">32</td><td align="center">EU489765</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms32</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>14</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">33</td><td align="center">EU489766</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms33</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>2</sub>TA(CA)<sub>9</sub></td><td align="center">no signal</td><td align="center">55&#x02013;58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">34</td><td align="center">EU489767</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms34</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>3</sub>CTA(CA)<sub>8</sub></td><td align="center">86(IVR)</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="center">35</td><td align="center">EU489768</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms35</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>48</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">36</td><td align="center">EU489769</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms36</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>24</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">37</td><td align="center">EU489770</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms37</italic></td><td align="center">(TG)<sub>4</sub>G(TG)<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">38</td><td align="center">EU489771</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms38</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>10</sub>AT(GT)<sub>6</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">39</td><td align="center">EU489772</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms41</italic></td><td align="center">GTAT(GT)<sub>8</sub>GCGTGA(GT)<sub>4</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">40</td><td align="center">EU489773</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms42</italic></td><td align="center">(AT)<sub>3</sub>CC(GT)<sub>3</sub>(AT)<sub>3</sub>(GT)<sub>14</sub>GAGT</td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">41</td><td align="center">EU489774</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms43</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>18</sub>C(CA)<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">42</td><td align="center">EU489775</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms45</italic></td><td align="center">TAA(CAA)<sub>6</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">43</td><td align="center">EU489776</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms47</italic></td><td align="center">(AG)<sub>12</sub>TG(AG)<sub>8</sub>(TG)<sub>3</sub>(AG)<sub>10</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">44</td><td align="center">EU489777</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms48</italic></td><td align="center">(TC)<sub>5</sub>C<sub>8</sub>G(CT)<sub>4</sub>C<sub>5</sub>G(CT)<sub>5</sub>C<sub>5</sub>G(CT)<sub>6</sub>CCTCG(CT)<sub>8</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">45</td><td align="center">EU489778</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms49</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>3</sub>CT(CA)<sub>3</sub>CT(CA)<sub>3</sub>CT(CA)<sub>9</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">46</td><td align="center">EU489779</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms50</italic></td><td align="center">(GA)<sub>18</sub>N<sub>4</sub>(GA)<sub>2</sub>G<sub>4</sub>(GA)<sub>2</sub>G<sub>4</sub>(GA)<sub>14</sub>CA(GA)<sub>2</sub>TA(GA)<sub>5</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">47</td><td align="center">EU489780</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms53</italic></td><td align="center">T<sub>8</sub>GT<sub>10</sub>GT<sub>7</sub>CGT<sub>9</sub>GT<sub>6</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">48</td><td align="center">EU489781</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms55</italic></td><td align="center">(AG)<sub>13</sub>GG(AG)<sub>3</sub>GC(AG)<sub>8</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">49</td><td align="center">EU489782</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms58</italic></td><td align="center">A<sub>6</sub>CA<sub>3</sub>GCA<sub>6</sub>TA<sub>5</sub>CA<sub>5</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">DQ078250</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms59</italic></td><td align="center">TGTA(TG)<sub>10</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">51</td><td align="center">DQ078251</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms60</italic></td><td align="center">(CAAA)<sub>2</sub><break/>A<sub>6</sub>CA<sub>3</sub>GCA<sub>6</sub>TA<sub>5</sub>CA<sub>4</sub>N<sub>26</sub>A<sub>2</sub>GA<sub>9</sub>CGA<sub>4</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">52</td><td align="center">DQ078252</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms61</italic></td><td align="center">T<sub>23</sub>G<sub>2</sub>T<sub>3</sub>GT<sub>3</sub>GT<sub>2</sub>GTAAT<sub>4</sub>C<sub>2</sub>T<sub>5</sub>CTGT<sub>5</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">53</td><td align="center">EU489783</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms62</italic></td><td align="center">A<sub>11</sub>CA<sub>11</sub>CATCACA<sub>4</sub>GA<sub>2</sub>GA<sub>8</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">54</td><td align="center">EU489784</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms63</italic></td><td align="center">A<sub>3</sub>CA<sub>3</sub>CCA<sub>18</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">EU489785</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms64</italic></td><td align="center">CAGA(CA)<sub>2</sub>C(CA)<sub>4</sub>N<sub>12</sub>(CA)<sub>4</sub>C(CA)<sub>2</sub><break/>(CA)<sub>5</sub>C(CA)<sub>4</sub>C(CA)<sub>4</sub>ACACC(CA)<sub>3</sub>C(CA)<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">56</td><td align="center">EU489786</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms68</italic></td><td align="center">T<sub>8</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">57</td><td align="center">EU489787</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms69</italic></td><td align="center">(A/G TT)<sub>4</sub>N<sub>4</sub>T<sub>7</sub>(CTT)<sub>2</sub>AGT<sub>4</sub>CA<sub>2</sub>T<sub>4</sub>GT<sub>4</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">58</td><td align="center">EU489788</td><td align="center"><italic>Boms70</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)-rich</td><td align="center">-</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Boms1&#x02013;34</italic>: Microsatellite loci isolated from total, small-insert DNA libraries</p><p><italic>Boms35&#x02013;70</italic>: Microsatellite loci isolated from enriched libraries</p><p>T: annealing temperature for <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization</p><p>(-): not tested</p><p>N: bases that do not present any motif</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A significant predominance of interrupted (60.5%) over perfect motifs (34.2%) was observed in both isolation approaches, while only a few (5.2%) were compound. These percentages are quite similar to those observed in <italic>C. capitata </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] and <italic>B. terrestris </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. On the other hand, they are not in agreement with results from <italic>B. tryoni </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>], <italic>B. morii </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>], <italic>D. pseudoobscura </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] and a recent study in <italic>C. capitata </italic>(Stratikopoulos et al., submitted). Therefore, it is unclear whether these results represent the actual structure of microsatellites in the olive fly genome, since data from closely related species are conflicting. Possibly these results can be attributed to differences in isolation strategies.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In situ </italic>hybridization to polytene chromosomes</title><p>Cytological analysis of <italic>B. oleae </italic>has revealed five chromosomes (10 polytene arms) and a heterochromatic mass, corresponding to the five autosomes and the sex chromosomes, respectively (for a review see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]). Well-defined polytene maps have been produced, providing the opportunity for a cytologic localization of molecular markers on the chromosomes.</p><p>Twenty of the isolated microsatellite clones were <italic>in situ </italic>hybridised to the salivary gland polytene chromosomes of <italic>B. oleae</italic>, in order to identify their chromosomal localization. At hybridisation temperature of 58&#x000b0;C, sixteen of the microsatellite probes gave specific signals (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) and 13 of them mapped to unique chromosome loci. Clone <italic>Boms20 </italic>hybridised to two neighbouring bands of the same chromosome region, <italic>Boms31 </italic>hybridised to two regions on the same chromosome arm, while <italic>Boms25 </italic>mapped to three regions on two chromosome arms (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) [Note that microsatellite loci and clones' names are written in italics whereas microsatellite markers' names are written in regular font]. These microsatellite clones gave the same multiple hybridisation pattern even at the higher hybridisation temperature of 62&#x000b0;C. Chromosome localization was not possible for four of the microsatellite probes, although tested at several hybridisation temperatures. Lack of hybridization signal can be attributed either to insufficient hybridization due to small probe length or to the fact that these clones may lie in heterochromatic regions (such as sex chromosomes or centromeric regions). <italic>Boms33 </italic>gave no detectable signal, while the remaining three gave multiple signals.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Schematic representation of the <italic>in situ </italic>localization of microsatellite markers on the polytene chromosomes of <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic></bold>. Arrows that originate from numbers in bold stand for the Boms microsatellite markers. Underlined numbers refer to microsatellite markers that give multiple signals. All other arrows refer to previously mapped loci [Zambetaki et al 1999].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-9-618-1"/></fig><p>The thirteen microsatellites that uniquely mapped to the polytene chromosomes of <italic>B. oleae </italic>are dispersed on seven polytene arms, establishing genetic markers for all five autosomes. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> summarizes the microsatellite hybridization sites and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> schematically presents the relative positions of the hybridization signals to the polytene chromosome arms of <italic>B. oleae </italic>together with previously described markers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Hybridization signals are presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold><italic>In situ </italic>hybridization of several microsatellite probes on the salivary gland polytene chromosomes of <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic></bold>. a: Boms23; b: Boms2; c: Boms17; d: Boms31; e: Boms24; f: Boms34. Arrows indicate the hybridization signals.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-9-618-2"/></fig><p>Although their number is small, they enrich the already existing cytological map and are the basis for a low-resolution cytogenetic map that will facilitate future genome projects of the species. It is encouraging that these thirteen markers are dispersed in seven of the ten chromosome arms (except IR, IIIL, VL). However, our <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization data are still limited to support a claim of a uniform distribution of microsatellite loci in the olive fly genome.</p></sec><sec><title>Development of microsatellite markers</title><p>Unique sequences flanking each repeat array were used to design PCR primer pairs for the amplification of 42 microsatellites. Thirty-one primer pairs amplified a product of the expected size, as revealed by agarose gel electrophoresis (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Subsequently, all primer pairs that amplified a specific band were used for the genotyping of 20 individual wild flies (from Greece and Cyprus) and/or up to 37 individuals of a laboratory strain. In addition, 19 <italic>C. capitata </italic>microsatellite markers (Stratikopoulos et al., submitted) that cross-amplified in the olive fly were used, raising the total number of functional primer pairs to 50 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In total, 37 primer pairs (29 designed for the olive fly and eight for the medfly) amplified a polymorphic and easily scorable PCR product, while eight pairs amplified a monomorphic one. The five remaining primer pairs generated PCR products that were not easily scored (shuttered or multiple bands or faint signal).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Microsatellite markers' characteristics and genetic variability</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><bold>Marker</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Primer pairs</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>E.S</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Tm</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Samples</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>N</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>n<sub>a</sub></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>n<sub>e</sub></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Ho</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>He</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>HWEG</bold><sup>2</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Boms2</td><td align="center">F: GCTGTTTTGAATGTCAGCATC<break/>R: TGTATGCGTGACTGTTTACG</td><td align="center">128</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>13</td><td align="center">3<break/>3</td><td align="center">1.75<break/>2.15</td><td align="center">0.45<break/>0.54</td><td align="center">0.44<break/>0.56</td><td align="center">-<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms3a</td><td align="center">F: CAGTCGCCCTTTAATTTGC<break/>R: GGGTCCTTTTGTTCTCAGG</td><td align="center">176</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">laboratory</td><td align="center">32</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2.39</td><td align="center">0.63</td><td align="center">0.59</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms3b</td><td align="center">F: AGGACCCTGGCACAATTCG<break/>R: TATGGCATGGCAAGCAGC</td><td align="center">171</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">laboratory</td><td align="center">32</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2.26</td><td align="center">0.59</td><td align="center">0.57</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms5</td><td align="center">F: TCTCGCCCCAATTACCAC<break/>R: GAATTTTGGCAACATCCAAGC</td><td align="center">105</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">laboratory</td><td align="center">34</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3.25</td><td align="center">0.79</td><td align="center">0.70</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms6a</td><td align="center">F: TCACTAAAAGGAGTCCGCAC<break/>R: GAGCAGGTCAGAGGCAAAAG</td><td align="center">173</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">laboratory</td><td align="center">35</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1.64</td><td align="center">0.43</td><td align="center">0.39</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms6b</td><td align="center">F: AAACCTTACCCTTTTGCCTC<break/>R: AGTGCCAACTGAATGCTG</td><td align="center">118</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">laboratory</td><td align="center">35</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2.10</td><td align="center">0.49</td><td align="center">0.53</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms8</td><td align="center">F: TGACATACATGCCTTCATTCAC<break/>R: CAGAAAAGCTTAAAACTAGCGG</td><td align="center">75</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>9</td><td align="center">6<break/>3</td><td align="center">3.10<break/>2.66</td><td align="center">0.85<break/>0.56</td><td align="center">0.69<break/>0.66</td><td align="center">-<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms10</td><td align="center">F: CAGAGCATCTCGCTTTGG<break/>R: TCAACAATCCCAGCAAAATC</td><td align="center">172</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>33</td><td align="center">5<break/>2</td><td align="center">3.33<break/>1.27</td><td align="center">0.70<break/>0.12</td><td align="center">0.72<break/>0.22</td><td align="center">-<break/>+</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms11</td><td align="center">F: ATAGGCATTGGCAGCGAAG<break/>R: CACAGTGGGCCGAAATCAC</td><td align="center">185</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>25</td><td align="center">4<break/>2</td><td align="center">1.88<break/>1.68</td><td align="center">0.50<break/>0.32</td><td align="center">0.48<break/>0.41</td><td align="center">-<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms12</td><td align="center">F: CGCGTTTTCATACTTTAACACC<break/>R: TTCATTTGGCCTTTGTGC</td><td align="center">158</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1.17</td><td align="center">0.16</td><td align="center">0.15</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms14</td><td align="center">F: TTTGTAATTCGCAGAAGGCAC<break/>R: AGGAGGACTGACAGAAGGACAC</td><td align="center">147</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2.72</td><td align="center">0.38</td><td align="center">0.68</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms16</td><td align="center">F: CAGACAATGGATGGATACATGC<break/>R: GGAGAAGTCAAATTGTGACAGC</td><td align="center">109</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1.72</td><td align="center">0.50</td><td align="center">0.43</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms17</td><td align="center">F: ATTAGACCATAGTGTTCTCAC<break/>R: AAGATGTTGAGTGCCGTTG</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>31</td><td align="center">7<break/>5</td><td align="center">5.76<break/>1.41</td><td align="center">0.35<break/>0.19</td><td align="center">0.85<break/>0.29</td><td align="center">+<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms18</td><td align="center">F: GCCATGAATGCAGACCAC<break/>R: CCTATTCAAATGCACGCAAAAC</td><td align="center">171</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>33</td><td align="center">6<break/>3</td><td align="center">2.56<break/>1.94</td><td align="center">0.80<break/>0.39</td><td align="center">0.63<break/>0.49</td><td align="center">-<break/>+</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms21</td><td align="center">F: TCGCCTCTTACCTCACAACC<break/>R: ACCATCCTTAGTCAGCACAGTC</td><td align="center">188</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>28</td><td align="center">6<break/>4</td><td align="center">3.77<break/>1.16</td><td align="center">0.75<break/>0.14</td><td align="center">0.75<break/>0.14</td><td align="center">-<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms22</td><td align="center">F: GTAAAGCACACGGAAGCG<break/>R: TGAGGTCAAAAAGGATGCTAAG</td><td align="center">211</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">18<break/>7</td><td align="center">2<break/>2</td><td align="center">1.06<break/>1.32</td><td align="center">0.06<break/>0.29</td><td align="center">0.06<break/>0.26</td><td align="center">-<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms24</td><td align="center">F: ATTTCGCTTGCCACAAAC<break/>R: CGCCCAAGCACTTAAAAC</td><td align="center">215</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">laboratory</td><td align="center">33</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1.77</td><td align="center">0.39</td><td align="center">0.44</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms25</td><td align="center">F: TGGAATGCGCTATTTTGTTG<break/>R: ACTCGTATATACGTACATGG</td><td align="center">167</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20 33</td><td align="center">5<break/>3</td><td align="center">3.49<break/>2.16</td><td align="center">0.80<break/>0.55</td><td align="center">0.73<break/>0.55</td><td align="center">-<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms27</td><td align="center">F: CGACTTGAAGGACAATTGG<break/>R: GGCGTGAGTAGTTTCTATAAGC</td><td align="center">129</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>10</td><td align="center">5<break/>3</td><td align="center">2.02<break/>2.41</td><td align="center">0.55<break/>0.50</td><td align="center">0.52<break/>0.62</td><td align="center">-<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms29</td><td align="center">TGAAGGTGATGAATGAAAGC<break/>GGAATGACTGTGAGCAAGC</td><td align="center">118</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>13</td><td align="center">5<break/>1</td><td align="center">2.57<break/>1.00</td><td align="center">0.60<break/>0.00</td><td align="center">0.63<break/>0.00</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms30</td><td align="center">F: CTGACTTCTTGCTTTACACG<break/>R: CAGCTTATCTGCTTTAAGTGC</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>9</td><td align="center">4<break/>4</td><td align="center">2.12<break/>2.19</td><td align="center">0.70<break/>0.78</td><td align="center">0.54<break/>0.58</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms31</td><td align="center">F: TGCTTGAGTTGCTCGTTGG<break/>R: GCCGCATGACATAAAGAATCG</td><td align="center">173</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>30</td><td align="center">4<break/>2</td><td align="center">3.27<break/>1.03</td><td align="center">0.75<break/>0.03</td><td align="center">0.71<break/>0.03</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms32</td><td align="center">F: TGTATGTATTTGTGCGTCG<break/>R: GCTTAGACCATTTGCTCC</td><td align="center">125</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">3.96</td><td align="center">0.55</td><td align="center">0.77</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms34</td><td align="center">F: ACGCCGCACACTTCTTAAAC<break/>R: CACCCAACTTTTGTAGTTTCC</td><td align="center">219</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">laboratory</td><td align="center">34</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2.08</td><td align="center">0.65</td><td align="center">0.53</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms47</td><td align="center">F: CAAACACACGCTAAAACG<break/>R: TTTAACCCAGAGGCTTGC</td><td align="center">158</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">3.15</td><td align="center">0.61</td><td align="center">0.70</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms58</td><td align="center">F: AGTTGGACGCGCACATATC<break/>R: AGCGCGTACGAGCTTTAGC</td><td align="center">181</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">18<break/>30</td><td align="center">7<break/>3</td><td align="center">5.02<break/>1.15</td><td align="center">0.72<break/>0.13</td><td align="center">0.82<break/>0.13</td><td align="center">-<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms59</td><td align="center">F: AGCGCTTACATAAATATAGCTAC<break/>R: TCCCCGTAAAGCCATAAAGTC</td><td align="center">171</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2.27</td><td align="center">0.50</td><td align="center">0.57</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms60</td><td align="center">F: TGGACGCGCACATATCAG<break/>R: ACGACGTTTAGCGGAAATGAG</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild<break/>laboratory</td><td align="center">20<break/>37</td><td align="center">6<break/>3</td><td align="center">3.14<break/>1.21</td><td align="center">0.70<break/>0.19</td><td align="center">0.70<break/>0.18</td><td align="center">-<break/>-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms62</td><td align="center">F: CTTTCGCTGCCTCCATTTG<break/>R: CAAAACCCCTCTGCAATCC</td><td align="center">174</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2.00</td><td align="center">0.55</td><td align="center">0.51</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms64a</td><td align="center">F: TGCTAGGCTGAACATTCG<break/>R: TGTTTTGCTGTTTCCAGG</td><td align="center">129</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center" colspan="4">Multiple bands</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms64b</td><td align="center">F: TGGAAACAGCAAAACACC<break/>R: AGCGAATCAAGAGACAGC</td><td align="center">137</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center" colspan="4">Multiple bands</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic9</td><td align="center" colspan="2">Stratikopoulos et al., submitted</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2.42</td><td align="center">0.88</td><td align="center">0.63</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic142</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center" colspan="4">monomorphic</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic149</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center" colspan="4">monomorphic</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic150</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2.03</td><td align="center">0.50</td><td align="center">0.54</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic151</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2.66</td><td align="center">0.35</td><td align="center">0.64</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic152</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">5.00</td><td align="center">0.40</td><td align="center">0.82</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic153</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2.24</td><td align="center">0.40</td><td align="center">0.57</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic154</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center" colspan="4">monomorphic</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic157</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center" colspan="4">monomorphic</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic158</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2.25</td><td align="center">0.63</td><td align="center">0.59</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic163</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center" colspan="4">monomorphic</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic22</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center" colspan="4">Multiple bands</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic23</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center" colspan="4">monomorphic</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic29</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center" colspan="4">Multiple bands</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic40</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center" colspan="4">Multiple bands</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic61</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2.32</td><td align="center">0.45</td><td align="center">0.58</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic64</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center" colspan="4">monomorphic</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic72</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center" colspan="4">monomorphic</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Medflymic109</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x0003e;&#x0003e;</td><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">wild</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1.05</td><td align="center">0.05</td><td align="center">0.05</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="11"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="3">Mean wild (monomorphic excluded)<break/>Mean laboratory (monomorphic excluded)</td><td></td><td align="center">19.5<break/>26.5</td><td align="center">4.63<break/>3.14</td><td align="center">2.74<break/>1.90</td><td align="center">0.53<break/>0.44</td><td align="center">0.57<break/>0.44</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>E.S: Expected size</p><p>Tm: PCR annealing temperature</p><p>N: sample size</p><p>n<sub>a</sub>: actual number of alleles; n<sub>e</sub>: effective number of alleles</p><p>Ho: heterozygosity observed; He: heterozygosity expected</p><p>(-): in HWE; (+): out of HWE</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The mean allele number per locus was 4.63 for natural populations and 3.14 for laboratory strains (monomorphic loci excluded), demonstrating their usefulness in population analyses of the species. Conformation to HWE was tested for 26 loci for natural populations and 19 loci for laboratory strains, according to G<sup>2 </sup>criterion, at a significance level of 5%. Only five deviations were observed due to homozygosity excess, which can be attributed to small sample size or to the presence of null alleles (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Cross &#x02013; species amplification in Tephritidae</title><p>The 29 primer pairs designed for the olive fly and proved polymorphic were tested in a pooled mix of five flies from each one of 11 Tephritidae species. Twenty-six of them amplified a specific DNA fragment, at least in one of the species examined. Four species belong to <italic>Bactrocera </italic>(<italic>B. correcta, B. cucurbitae, B. dorsalis </italic>and <italic>B. tryoni</italic>), four to <italic>Anastrepha </italic>(<italic>A. fraterculus, A. ludens, A. serpetina </italic>and <italic>A. striata</italic>), two to <italic>Ceratitis </italic>(<italic>C. capitata </italic>and <italic>C. fasciventris</italic>) and one belongs to <italic>Rhagoletis </italic>(<italic>R. cerasi</italic>) (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Cross-species amplification of <italic>Bactrocera oleae </italic>microsatellite markers in other Tephritidae species</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="right"><bold>Species</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="5"><bold>Bactrocera</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="4"><bold>Anastrepha</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><bold>Ceratitis</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Rhagoletis</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Markers</bold></td><td align="center"><italic>Bo</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Bcu</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Bco</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Bd</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Bt</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Af</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Al</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Astr</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Aser</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Cc</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Cf</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Rc</italic></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Boms2</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">400</td><td align="center">400</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">450/<break/>Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">200</td><td align="center">200f</td><td align="center">Sm</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms3a</td><td align="center">210</td><td align="center">210</td><td align="center">210</td><td align="center">210</td><td align="center">230</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">190</td><td align="center">190</td><td align="center">500</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms3b</td><td align="center">200</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">220</td><td align="center">200</td><td align="center">210</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">150</td><td></td><td align="center">200</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms5</td><td align="center">110</td><td align="center">500</td><td></td><td align="center">700</td><td align="center">130</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">300</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms6a</td><td align="center">150/<break/>400</td><td align="center">350/<break/>Sm</td><td></td><td align="center">350</td><td align="center">300/<break/>500</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td></td><td align="center">600</td><td align="center">200/<break/>300</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms6b</td><td align="center">150</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">150f/<break/>200</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms8</td><td align="center">75</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">200</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms10</td><td align="center">200</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">180</td><td align="center">200</td><td></td><td align="center">180/<break/>Sm</td><td></td><td align="center">120f/<break/>150f</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">200/<break/>300</td><td align="center">300</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms11</td><td align="center">200</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">220</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">500</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms12</td><td align="center">200</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms14</td><td align="center">150</td><td></td><td align="center">150</td><td></td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">300</td><td></td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms16</td><td align="center">100</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">100</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms18</td><td align="center">171</td><td></td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">190</td><td align="center">Mb</td><td align="center">Mb</td><td align="center">Mb</td><td align="center">Mb</td><td align="center">300</td><td align="center">300</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms21</td><td align="center">188</td><td align="center">190</td><td align="center">180</td><td></td><td align="center">180</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms22</td><td align="center">210</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">500f</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms24</td><td align="center">200</td><td></td><td align="center">250</td><td align="center">250</td><td align="center">250</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms27</td><td align="center">130</td><td></td><td align="center">130</td><td align="center">130</td><td align="center">130</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">150/<break/>Mb</td><td align="center">Sm</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms29</td><td align="center">120</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms30</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">150</td><td></td><td align="center">Mb</td><td align="center">130</td><td align="center">130</td><td align="center">110</td><td align="center">110</td><td align="center">110</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms31</td><td align="center">170</td><td></td><td align="center">120</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">500</td><td align="center">120f/<break/>300/<break/>500/<break/>600</td><td align="center">120f</td><td align="center">120f/<break/>400/<break/>500/<break/>700</td><td></td><td align="center">800</td><td align="center">450f</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms32</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">150</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms34</td><td align="center">200</td><td></td><td align="center">200</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">200</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms58</td><td align="center">180</td><td></td><td align="center">400</td><td align="center">150f/<break/>180f</td><td align="center">150f/<break/>180f</td><td align="center">400</td><td align="center">400/<break/>500</td><td align="center">500</td><td align="center">400</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td><td align="center">Sm</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms60</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">150f</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">170</td><td align="center">250/<break/>Mb</td><td align="center">150</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms62</td><td align="center">174</td><td align="center">200</td><td align="center">160</td><td align="center">200</td><td align="center">180</td><td align="center">160/<break/>Mb</td><td align="center">160/<break/>Mb</td><td align="center">160/<break/>Mb</td><td align="center">160/<break/>Mb</td><td align="center">200</td><td align="center">160</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Boms64a</td><td align="center">150</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">300/<break/>450</td><td align="center">500</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Numbers in columns indicate PCR product size, as revealed by agarose gel electrophoresis</p><p>Sm: smear; f: faint band; Mb: multiple bands</p><p>Bo: B. oleae; Bco: B. correcta; Bcu: B. cucurbitae; Bd: B. dorsalis; Bt: B. tryoni; Cc: C. capitata; Cf: C. fasciventris; Af: A. fraterculus; Al: A. ludens; Aser: A. serpentina; Astr: A. striata; Rc: R. cerasi</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Conservation of <italic>Bactrocera oleae </italic>microsatellite markers in Tephritidae</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Species/<break/><bold>Genera</bold></td><td align="center">Functional primer pairs</td><td align="center">Expected size</td><td align="center">Presence of SSR motif</td><td align="center">Presence of the expected motif</td><td align="center">Mean number of uninterrupted repeats</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><italic>B. oleae</italic></td><td align="center">29</td><td align="center">29</td><td align="center">29</td><td align="center">29</td><td align="center">100%</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>B. correcta</italic></td><td align="center">15/29 (51.7%)</td><td align="center">13/15 (86.7%)<break/>13/29 (44.8%)</td><td align="center">6/7 (85.7%)</td><td align="center">5/6 (83.3%)<break/>5/7 (71.5%)</td><td align="center">20/50 (40%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>B. cucurbitae</italic></td><td align="center">9/29 (31%)</td><td align="center">6/9 (66.7%)<break/>6/29 (20.7%)</td><td align="center">2/2 (100%)</td><td align="center">2/2 (100%)<break/>2/2 (100%)</td><td align="center">11/27 (40%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>B. dorsalis</italic></td><td align="center">14/29 (48.3%)</td><td align="center">12/14 (85.7%)<break/>12/29 (41.4%)</td><td align="center">4/4 (100%)</td><td align="center">4/4 (100%)<break/>4/4 (100%)</td><td align="center">29/36 (80.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>B. tryoni</italic></td><td align="center">19/29 (65.5%)</td><td align="center">17/19 (89.5%)<break/>17/29 (58.6%)</td><td align="center">5/6 (83.3%)</td><td align="center">5/5 (100%)<break/>5/6 (83.3%)</td><td align="center">32/53 (60%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Bactrocera</bold><break/><bold>genus</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>57/116 (49.1%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>48/57 (84.2%)</bold><break/><bold>48/116 (41.4%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>17/19 (89.5%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>16/17 (94.1%)</bold><break/><bold>16/19 (84.2%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>92/166 (55.4%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>A. fraterculus</italic></td><td align="center">5/29 (17.2%)</td><td align="center">2/5 (40%)<break/>2/29 (6.9%)</td><td align="center">2/2 (100%)</td><td align="center">1/2 (50%)<break/>1/2 (50%)</td><td align="center">8/9 (88.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>A. ludens</italic></td><td align="center">7/29 (24.1%)</td><td align="center">5/7 (71.5%)<break/>5/29 (17.2%)</td><td align="center">1/1 (100%)</td><td align="center">1/1 (100%)<break/>1/1 (100%)</td><td align="center">11/9 (122%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>A. serpentina</italic></td><td align="center">9/29 (31%)</td><td align="center">6/9 (66.7%)<break/>6/29(20.7%)</td><td align="center">1/1 (100%)</td><td align="center">1/1 (100%)<break/>1/1 (100%)</td><td align="center">8/9 (88.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>A. striata</italic></td><td align="center">7/29 (24.1%)</td><td align="center">5/7 (71.5%)<break/>5/29 (17.2%)</td><td align="center">1/1 (100%)</td><td align="center">1/1 (100%)<break/>1/1 (100%)</td><td align="center">12/9 (133%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Anastrepha genus</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>28/116 (24.1%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>18/28 (64.3%)</bold><break/><bold>18/116 (15.5%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>5/5 (100%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>4/5 (80%)</bold><break/><bold>4/5 (80%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>39/36 (108.3%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>C. capitata</italic></td><td align="center">8/29 (27.6%)</td><td align="center">7/8 (87.5%)<break/>7/29 (24.1%)</td><td align="center">1/2 (50%)</td><td align="center">1/1 (100%)<break/>1/2 (50%)</td><td align="center">2/3 (66.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>C. fasciventris</italic></td><td align="center">12/29 (41.4%)</td><td align="center">9/12 (75%)<break/>9/29 (31%)</td><td align="center">2/2 (100%)</td><td align="center">2/2 (100%)<break/>2/2 (100%)</td><td align="center">12/24 (50%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Ceratitis genus</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>20/58 (34.5%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>16/20 (80%)</bold><break/><bold>16/58 (27.6%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>3/4 (75%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>3/3 (100%)</bold><break/><bold>3/4 (75%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>15/27 (55.5%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold><italic>R. cerasi</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>8/29 (27.6%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>4/8 (50%)</bold><break/><bold>13.8%</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>1/3 (33.3%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>1/1 (100%)</bold><break/><bold>1/3 (33.3%)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>2/3 (66.7%)</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic><underline>Functional primer pairs</underline></italic>: number of primer pairs that cross-amplified successfully; <italic><underline>Expected size</underline></italic>: number of primer pairs that cross-amplified and produced fragment of the expected size (calculated either in regard to total available primer pairs or in regard to primer pairs that successfully cross-amplified); <italic><underline>Presence of SSR motif</underline></italic>: number of cross-species amplification products that harboured a microsatellite motif; <italic><underline>Presence of the expected motif</underline></italic>: number of cross-species amplification products that harboured the expected microsatellite motif (calculated either in regard to total sequencing reactions or in regard to cross-species amplification products that harboured a microsatellite motif); <italic><underline>Mean number of uninterrupted repeats</underline></italic>: sum and comparison of the number of uninterrupted repeats for primer pairs that cross-amplified and harboured the expected motif. Dividend represents repeats in the new species, while divider stands for number of repeats in <italic>B. oleae</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A total of 113 PCR products were amplified. The species with the highest degree of amplification was <italic>B. tryoni </italic>(19/29), while with the lowest was <italic>Rhagoletis cerasi </italic>(8/29). As expected, the highest percentage of amplification was inside <italic>Bactrocera</italic>, with a mean of 49.1%. <italic>Ceratitis </italic>presented the next higher amplification degree (34.5%), followed by <italic>Rhagoletis </italic>and <italic>Anastrepha </italic>(27.6% and 24.1%, respectively) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3-1</xref>). It is worth mentioning that <italic>B. cucurbitae </italic>exhibited very low amplification rate, similar to that of <italic>Anastrepha</italic>. Finally, <italic>C. capitata </italic>presented substantially lower degree of amplification than <italic>C. fasciventris</italic>.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Cross-species amplification of <italic>Bactrocera oleae </italic>microsatellites in four Tephritidae genera</bold>. 1: Percentage of cross-amplified primer pairs. 2: Percentage of primer pairs that produced a fragment of the expected size.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-9-618-3"/></fig><p>The majority of PCR products had similar size (less than ~50 bp difference, as estimated by agarose gel electrophoresis) with those obtained in <italic>B. oleae </italic>(about 76%). Still, the highest degree of PCR product size conservation was inside <italic>Bactrocera </italic>(84.2%), although <italic>Ceratitis </italic>showed a comparable percentage (80%). <italic>Anastrepha </italic>and <italic>Rhagoletis </italic>presented significantly lower values (64.3% and 50%, respectively) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3-2</xref>). Surprisingly, <italic>B. cucurbitae </italic>showed very low size conservation (66.7%), comparable to that of <italic>Anastrepha</italic>, implying that the low amplification value mentioned before may not be a PCR artefact. This in not the case in <italic>C. capitata</italic>, since size conservation is very high (87.5%). This value is higher than that of <italic>C. fasciventris </italic>and comparable to that of <italic>Bactrocera</italic>, suggesting that medfly's low amplification value is more likely a PCR artefact.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of cross-species amplification products</title><p>Amplification of a band of expected size does not necessarily mean that the expected microsatellite motif is also present. To evaluate the degree of motif conservation, 31 of the reactions that produced a specific band were subcloned and sequenced. We focused on PCR products of similar to the expected size and distributed in as many species as possible. Twenty-seven of the amplification products harboured a repeat motif, 25 of which contained the same as that of <italic>B. oleae</italic>. Six of the products harboured new motifs (instead of or in addition to the expected ones) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Microsatellite loci obtained through cross-species amplification</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Locus</td><td align="center"><italic>B. oleae </italic>motif</td><td align="left">Motif of other Tephritidae</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><italic>Boms3a</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)<sub>14</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>Bt</italic>: (AT)G<sub>2</sub>(AT)<sub>3</sub>AC(AT)A<sub>2</sub>(AT)<bold>(GT)</bold><sub>2</sub>(AT)/<bold>(TG)</bold><sub>2</sub>(TA)<sub>2</sub><bold>(TG)</bold><sub>8</sub><break/><italic>Bco</italic>: <bold>(TG)</bold><sub>2</sub>TA(GT)N<sub>7</sub><bold>(TG)</bold><sub>2</sub>(TA)/<bold>(TG)</bold>(GA)<bold>(TG)</bold><sub>2</sub>(TA)<sub>2</sub><bold>(TG)</bold>(TA)<sub>3</sub>(TA<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub><bold>(TG)</bold><sub>3</sub>C<bold>(GT)</bold><sub>3</sub><break/><italic>Bcu</italic>: (TA)<sub>3</sub>A(TA)CA<sub>2</sub><bold>(GT)</bold><sub>4</sub><break/><italic>Bd</italic>: (TA)<sub>2</sub><bold>TG</bold>(TA)CA(TA)<sub>3</sub>A<sub>2</sub><bold>(TG)</bold><sub>5</sub>CA<bold>(TG)</bold>(TC)<sub>2</sub>(TA)<sub>2</sub><bold>(TG)</bold><sub>7</sub><break/><italic>Cf</italic>:<bold>(TG)</bold><sub>4</sub>T<sub>2</sub><bold>(TG)</bold><sub>8</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Boms3b</italic></td><td align="center">(CAA)<sub>3</sub>CAG(CAA)<sub>3</sub>/<break/>(CAA)<sub>2</sub>CAG(CAA)</td><td align="left"><italic>Bco</italic>: <bold>(CAA)</bold><sub>2</sub>AAA<bold>(CAA)/(CAA)</bold><sub>3</sub><break/><italic>Bd</italic>: <bold>(CAA)</bold><sub>2</sub>AA<bold>(CAA)/(CAA)</bold><sub>5</sub><break/><italic>Bt</italic><bold>: (CAA)</bold><sub>2</sub>A<bold>(CAA)</bold>/<bold>(CAA)</bold><sub>3</sub><break/><italic>Cc</italic>:/<bold>(CAA)</bold>A<sub>3</sub><bold>(CAA)</bold><sub>2</sub><break/><italic>Rc</italic>: A<sub>4</sub>CA<sub>2</sub>CGATACA<sub>5</sub>N<sub>9</sub><italic>A</italic><sub>5</sub>/<bold>(CAA)</bold>G<bold>(CAA)</bold><sub>2</sub>(CAG)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Boms10</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>10</sub>GA(CA)<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>Cc</italic>: -<break/><italic>Cf</italic>: <bold>(CA)</bold>GAC<bold>(CA)</bold><sub>4</sub><break/><italic>Rc</italic>: -</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Boms11</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>7</sub>CG(CA)<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>Bco</italic>: -<break/><italic>Rc</italic>: -</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Boms14</italic></td><td align="center">(AT)<sub>2</sub>GT(AT)<sub>11</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>Bco</italic>:<bold>(TA)</bold><sub>2</sub>G<bold>(TA)</bold>CA<bold>(TA)</bold><sub>3</sub>A<sub>2</sub><break/><italic>Af</italic>: <italic>G</italic><sub>6</sub>N<sub>7</sub>(GT)<sub>3</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Boms16</italic></td><td align="center">(CA)<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>Bco</italic>: <italic>T</italic><sub>5</sub>ATCA<sub>4</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>5</sub>TCA<sub>2</sub>A<sub>2</sub><break/><italic>Bd</italic>: <bold>(CA)</bold>TG<bold>(CA)</bold><sub>4</sub><break/><italic>Bt</italic>: <bold>(CA)</bold>TA<bold>(CA)</bold><sub>4</sub>CG<bold>(CA)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Boms21</italic></td><td align="center">(GT)GG(GT)<sub>13</sub>AT(GT)</td><td align="left"><italic>Bco</italic>: (GA)<sub>3</sub><bold>(GT)</bold><sub>6</sub><break/><italic>Bcu</italic>: (AT)<sub>3</sub><bold>(GT)</bold>(AT)<bold>(GT)</bold><sub>7</sub><break/><italic>Bt</italic>: (GA)<sub>3</sub><bold>(GT)</bold><sub>3</sub>AT<bold>(GT)</bold><sub>5</sub>AT<bold>(GT)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Boms60</italic></td><td align="center">CACA<sub>2</sub>(CA<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub><break/>A<sub>6</sub>CA<sub>3</sub>GCA<sub>6</sub>TA<sub>5</sub>CA<sub>4</sub>N<sub>26</sub>A<sub>2</sub>G<bold>A</bold><sub>9</sub>CGA<sub>4</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>Bco</italic>: CACA<sub>2</sub>(CA<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>/A<sub>5</sub>C<sub>2</sub>A<sub>3</sub>(GT)<sub>2</sub>A<sub>4</sub>G<sub>2</sub><bold>A</bold><sub>5</sub>N<sub>7</sub>A<sub>5</sub>N<sub>5</sub>A<sub>3</sub>CA<sub>3</sub>CA<sub>2</sub>CA<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>A<sub>3</sub>N<sub>3</sub>A<sub>2</sub>N<sub>3</sub><bold>A</bold><sub>5</sub>GA<sub>2</sub>CGA<sub>4</sub><break/><italic>Bd</italic>: CACA<sub>2</sub>(CA<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>/<bold>A</bold><sub>13</sub>CA<sub>6</sub>TA<sub>4</sub>N<sub>4</sub>A<sub>3</sub>CA<sub>2</sub>TA<sub>2</sub>CA<sub>5</sub><break/><italic>Bt</italic>: CACA<sub>2</sub>(CA<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>/A<sub>6</sub>CA<sub>3</sub>GCA<sub>6</sub>TA<sub>5</sub>CA<sub>5</sub>N<sub>28</sub>A<sub>2</sub>G<bold>A</bold><sub>9</sub>CGA<sub>4</sub><break/><italic>Af</italic>: CACA<sub>2</sub>(CA<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>/<italic>(GA)</italic><sub>4</sub>A<sub>3</sub>G<bold>A</bold><sub>8</sub>GA<sub>4</sub>N<sub>9</sub>GA<sub>3</sub>GATA<sub>4</sub>T<bold>A</bold><sub>8</sub>GACA<sub>5</sub>CA<sub>4</sub><break/><italic>Al</italic>: CACA<sub>2</sub>(CA<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>/<italic>(GA)</italic><sub>4</sub>A<sub>3</sub>GA<sub>9</sub>GA<sub>4</sub>N<sub>9</sub>CA<sub>3</sub>GATA<sub>4</sub>T<bold>A</bold><sub>11</sub>CA<sub>5</sub>CA<sub>5</sub><break/><italic>Aser</italic>: CACA<sub>2</sub>(CA<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>/CA<sub>5</sub>GA<sub>5</sub>GA<sub>4</sub>TACA<sub>4</sub>TACA<sub>2</sub>TCA<sub>2</sub>CA<sub>3 </sub>GATA<sub>4</sub>TA<sub>4</sub>TACA<sub>5</sub>C<bold>A</bold><sub>8</sub><break/><italic>Astr</italic>: CACA<sub>2</sub>(CA<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>/<italic>(GA)</italic><sub>4</sub>A<sub>3</sub>GA<sub>6</sub>C<sub>2</sub>A<sub>3 </sub>TACA<sub>2</sub>TCA<sub>2</sub>CA<sub>3 </sub>GATA<sub>4</sub>TA<sub>9</sub>C<bold>A</bold><sub>12</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Boms64a</italic></td><td align="center">CAGA(CA)<sub>2</sub>C(CA)<sub>4</sub>N<sub>12</sub>(CA)<sub>4</sub>C(CA)<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>Bt</italic>: <bold>(CA)</bold><sub>2</sub>A<bold>(CA)</bold><sub>2</sub>C(CA)T<sub>2</sub><bold>(CA)</bold><sub>2</sub></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>In bold: cases of preservation of the expected motif</p><p>N: non-motif bases</p><p>Bco: B. correcta; Bcu: B. cucurbitae; Bd: B. dorsalis; Bt: B. tryoni; Cc: C. capitata; Cf: C. fasciventris; Af: A. fraterculus; Al: A. ludens; Aser: A. serpentina; Astr: A. striata; Rc: R. cerasi</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Nineteen (of the 31) sequencing reactions were performed in <italic>Bactrocera</italic>. The presence of a microsatellite motif in 18 of them (16 of which had the expected motif), demonstrates their potential in the analysis of other <italic>Bactrocera </italic>species. Results from other genera are encouraging, although preliminary. In <italic>Ceratitis</italic>, for example, four sequencing reactions were performed, three of which exhibited the expected motif. In <italic>Anastrepha</italic>, five sequencing reactions were performed, all of which exhibited a microsatellite motif with four cases possessing the expected one (however, they all refer to the same locus in four different species). Finally, in <italic>Rhagoletis</italic>, three sequencing reactions were performed, one of which exhibited a microsatellite repeat of the expected motif. These results are summarized in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref> and demonstrate the potential utility of these markers in the analysis of Tephritidae genera other than <italic>Bactrocera</italic>.</p><p>Mean number of uninterrupted repeats was measured only in cases where the expected motif was present in cross-species amplification products (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). In seventeen cases within <italic>Bactrocera </italic>(regarding seven microsatellite loci), the mean number of uninterrupted repeats was 9.8 for <italic>B. oleae </italic>and 5.4 for the other <italic>Bactrocera </italic>species. Same analysis for three PCR products (regarding three microsatellites) in <italic>Ceratitis </italic>gave a mean of 9.0 and 5.0 uninterrupted repeats for <italic>B. oleae </italic>and <italic>Ceratitis</italic>, respectively. Although sequencing data are still limited, it is obvious that microsatellites tend to present longer arrays in the species in which they were isolated from. This has been described in a variety of species, such as <italic>Drosophila </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] and primates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], and has been attributed to the fact that microsatellites can evolve directionally and at different rates in closely related species.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequencing analysis and phylogenetic comparisons</title><p>Although we did not perform a phylogenetic analysis, it seems that measures of cross-species amplification (e.g., percentages of functional primers and expected size of PCR products) are indicative of the phylogenetic history of these species. Our results support the notion that three of the Bactrocera species are very close to <italic>B. oleae</italic>, while the fourth (<italic>B. cucurbitae</italic>) seems to be more distant (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Also, <italic>Ceratitis </italic>seems to be more closely related to <italic>Bactrocera </italic>than <italic>Anastrepha </italic>and <italic>Rhagoletis </italic>seems to be the most distantly related genus to <italic>Bactrocera</italic>. These results perfectly replicate the exact same relationships observed in the most recent phylogenetic analysis of these species based on mtDNA sequencing data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Secondarily, they are also supported by several other studies from different insect species based on alignment of mitochondrial 16S rDNA sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] and 18S rDNA sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], which show that <italic>Bactrocera </italic>is more closely related to <italic>Ceratitis</italic>, and closer to <italic>Anastrepha </italic>than it is to <italic>Rhagoletis</italic>. In addition, we also performed sequencing alignments of a few cross-species amplification products of some of our markers (data not shown). In all cases, the different species were clustered to their respective genera with high bootstrap values. Although these data are very limited, they come from dispersed regions of nuclear DNA which gives significant value to phylogenetic analyses. There are studies supporting that microsatellite data can shed light to phylogenetic relationships among closely related taxa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>]. Sequencing analysis of more microsatellite markers can probably reveal complex phylogenetic relationships among different Tephritidae species, especially in cases of species complexes.</p></sec><sec><title>Polymorphism of cross-species microsatellite markers</title><p>Presence of a microsatellite motif does not necessarily mean that these loci can be used as genetic markers. Nineteen microsatellite markers developed in the medfly cross-amplified in the olive fly (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The fact that eight of them were polymorphic in a relative small sample (twenty wild flies) confirms the possible utility of the markers presented here in the analysis of other Tephritidae species.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Since their discovery, microsatellite markers have been particularly useful in population and genetic analyses, mainly due to their high degree of polymorphism. Their significance is even greater in organisms like the olive fly, where the lack of morphological markers makes classical genetic analysis practically impossible. The interest in olive fly's genetics is not only theoretical, since modern genetic and molecular tools have benefited several operational SIT programmes, particularly those where GSSs are involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. The observed polymorphism of the developed microsatellite markers (both in laboratory and natural populations) guarantees their utility in genetic and population analyses. A subset of these markers has already been successfully used in previous population studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. The existence of well-described polytene chromosomes in the olive fly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and the possibility of cytological localization of molecular markers by <italic>in situ </italic>hybridisation provide a powerful method to link the genetic and molecular information of an organism. The existence of defined polytene chromosomes in other Diptera [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] also offers the opportunity to establish syntenic linkages and to study the evolutionary relationships of separate chromosomal segments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Cross-species amplification of the developed markers to other Tephritidae demonstrates their potential utility in those species. Sequencing analysis of several cross-amplified products revealed a varying degree of conservation that declines outside the <italic>Bactrocera </italic>genus. Such sequencing analyses can also assist the clarification of phylogenetic relationships among different species, particularly in cases of species complexes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Fly culture and stocks</title><p>Field-collected samples: Olive fruits were collected and kept in the laboratory until adult flies emerged. These flies were preserved individually at -20&#x000b0;C until DNA extraction.</p><sec><title>Laboratory strain</title><p><italic>B. oleae </italic>flies used for <italic>in situ </italic>hybridisation and polymorphism analysis were obtained from the Department of Biology, "Demokritos" Nuclear Research Center, Athens, Greece. In our laboratory the stock was reared on an artificial medium based on yeast hydrolysate, sucrose, egg yolk and water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>] at 25 &#x000b1; 1&#x000b0;C and a 12 h light: 12 h dark cycle.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Construction and screening of total small insert genomic libraries</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from adult flies of the laboratory strain as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. Approximately 3 &#x003bc;g of genomic DNA were digested to completion with <italic>Mbo</italic>I and digestion products were electrophoresed in 1% agarose gel (Seakem GTG). Restriction fragments that ranged between 500 bp and 1200 bp were isolated from the gel (Jetquick gel extraction kit, Genomed) and cloned into the <italic>BamHI </italic>site of plasmid vector pBlueskript II SK (Stratagene). About 10<sup>4 </sup>recombinant clones were transferred onto nylon membranes (Hybond-N, Amersham), screened with a mix of radioactively labeled (CT)<sub>15 </sub>and (GT)<sub>15 </sub>oligonucleotides. Labelling was performed with terminal transferase (Promega), under the conditions suggested by the manufacturer. Hybridisation was performed at 48&#x000b0;C in standard hybridisation solution (6&#x000d7; SSC, 0.5% SDS, 5&#x000d7; Denhardt's) for at least 16 hours. Membranes were then washed twice for 5 min in 2&#x000d7; SSC/0.1% SDS at 25&#x000b0;C and once for 15 min in 1&#x000d7; SSC/0.1% SDS at 37&#x000b0;C and subsequently exposed with film. Positive colonies underwent a secondary screening and plasmid DNA was then purified by the alkaline lysis method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>] and electrophoresed. Clones of convenient size inserts (i.e., 500&#x02013;1000 bp) were sequenced (Thermo Sequenase core Sequencing kit, Amersham). Sequencing reactions were analysed in an automatic sequenator and the microsatellite repeat motif was determined.</p></sec><sec><title>Construction of microsatellite-enriched genomic libraries</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted as above. Enriched libraries were prepared according to [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Seven libraries were constructed using different oligonucleotide probes [(GA)<sub>15</sub>, (CA)<sub>15</sub>, (GT)<sub>15</sub>, (CT)<sub>15</sub>, (AT)<sub>15</sub>, (GC)<sub>15 </sub>and (GAC)<sub>10</sub>]. Two rounds of enrichment were performed for each library. Enriched products were cloned either in plasmid vector pBlueskript SKII digested with <italic>EcoRI</italic>, (without removal of the amplification linkers), or into the <italic>BamHI </italic>site of the pUC18 vector (Ready-To-Go&#x02122; pUC18/<italic>BamHI</italic>, Amersham), (after linker removal). Insert size of recombinant clones was estimated on agarose gels and selected clones were sequenced as above. Selection was done either at random, or after Southern transfer and hybridization with (GT)<sub>15 </sub>and (CT)<sub>15 </sub>radiolabelled probes.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In situ </italic>hybridization procedures</title><p>Squash preparations of salivary gland chromosomes were made from 10&#x02013;12 day-old third instar larvae and 1&#x02013;2 day old pupae, as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. Microsatellite containing clones were labelled with digoxigenated dUTP (Dig-11dUTP) using the random priming method and <italic>in situ </italic>hybridized to polytene chromosomes according to [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. Hybridization temperature was 55&#x02013;62&#x000b0;C (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Signals were detected with specific antibodies (ROCHE Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany). Five or more chromosomal preparations were hybridized with each probe and at least ten well-spread polytene nuclei per preparation were examined to identify the hybridization signals.</p></sec><sec><title>Genotyping</title><p>PCR amplification was performed in a 10 &#x003bc;l volume that contained ~10 ng of DNA, 1.6 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1&#x000d7; reaction buffer [Promega: 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 9.0), 50 mM KCl, 0.1% Triton X-100], 0.2 U Taq polymerase (Promega), 0.2 mM of each dNTP, 3 pmol of each primer. PCR products were subsequently separated in 1.5% agarose gels. For genotyping, PCRs were performed as above with the only difference that one fifth of one of the primers of each pair was end-labeled with [&#x003b3;<sup>32</sup>P]-ATP, using T4 polynucleotide kinase (MBI, Fermentas) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>]. Amplification was performed on a PTC-100 thermocycler (MJ Research Inc) for 30 cycles of 1 min at 95&#x000b0;C, 1 min at 50&#x000b0;C and 1 min at 72&#x000b0;C. PCR products were electrophoresed on 5% denaturing polyacrylamide gels and visualized by autoradiography.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>Genetic variability was measured as the mean number of alleles per locus, effective number of alleles and observed and expected heterozygosity. Conformation to HWE was tested at a significance level of 5%, according to G<sup>2 </sup>criterion. All computations were performed with POPGENE version 1.31 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>].</p><sec><title>Sequencing of cross-species amplification products</title><p>PCR products were electrophoresed, isolated from gel with the 'PCR Clean up and Gel extraction' kit (Nucleospin) and subsequently ligated to the pCR2.1-TOPO vector with the TOPO TA cloning kit (Invitrogen). Recombinant vectors were used to transform <italic>E. coli </italic>competent cells of the XL-1 strain. Plasmid DNA was extracted with the alkaline lysis method, as above and sequence analysis was performed by Macrogen Inc (Korea).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>AAA isolated the microsatellite markers, performed most of the analysis described in the manuscript and drafted the largest part of the manuscript. EES participated in the isolation of the microsatellite markers and developed the <italic>C. capitata </italic>markers. ED carried out the <italic>in situ </italic>hybridisations and helped to draft the manuscript. EGK participated in the cross-species analysis. PMT analysed the <italic>in situ </italic>hybridisation results and helped to draft the manuscript. AZ participated in the design of the study, hosted most of the research performed in her laboratory and helped to draft the manuscript. KDM participated in its design and coordination and helped to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was supported by a grant of the Hellenic General Secretariat of Research and Technology (99 E&#x00394;529). AAA and EES were supported by a Fellowship from the National Fellowship Foundation (Greece). We would like to thank Dr Alan Robinson for providing <italic>C. fasciventris, A. ludens, B. dorsalis, B. correcta</italic>, <italic>B. cucurbitae </italic>samples, Dr M. Frommer for <italic>B. tryoni </italic>and the Campa&#x000f1;a Nacional Contra Moscas de la Fruta, Tapachula, Chiapas, Mexico, for providing <italic>A. oblique, A. serpentine</italic>, <italic>A. striata </italic>and <italic>A. fraterculus</italic>.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Robinson AS, Hooper G</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Life history strategies of tephritid fruit flies</article-title><source>Fruit flies, their biology, natural enemies and control</source><year>1989</year><volume>3B</volume><publisher-name>Amsterdam: Elsevier Science Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>208</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elson-Harris</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fruit Flies of Economic Significance: Their Identification and Bionomics</source><year>1994</year><publisher-name>CAB International &#x00026; ACIAR, Wallingford</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny of the genus Rhagoletis (diptera: tephritidae) inferred from DNA sequences of mitochondrial cytochrome oxidase II</article-title><source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9007018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/mpev.1996.0374</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>RAI</given-names></name></person-group><source>The tropical fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae: Dacinae) of the Australasian and Oceanian regions</source><year>1989</year><publisher-name>Memoirs &#x02013; Queensland Museum</publisher-name><fpage>26</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>RAI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Aluja M, Norrbom AL</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny of the tribe Dacini (Dacinae) based on morphological, distributional, and biological data</article-title><source>Fruit Flies (Tephritidae): Phylogeny and Evolution of Behavior</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press</publisher-name><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>504</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazomenos</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Robinson AS, Hooper G</surname></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Dacus oleae</italic></article-title><source>World crop pests</source><year>1989</year><volume>3B</volume><publisher-name>Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam</publisher-name><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>177</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montiel-Bueno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative methods for controlling the olive fly, <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic>, involving semio-chemicals</article-title><source>IOBC Wprs Bull</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aketarawong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thanaphum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomulski</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Malacrida</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gugliemino</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferences on the population structure and colonization process of the invasive oriental fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis </italic>(Hendel)</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3522</fpage><lpage>3532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17845427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2007.03409.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baliraine</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guglielmino</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Osir</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lux</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulaa</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomulski</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Quilici</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Malacrida</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population genetics of the potentially invasive African fruit fly species, <italic>Ceratitis rosa </italic>and <italic>Ceratitis fasciventris </italic>(Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14871371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-294X.2004.02105.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duyck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Junod</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Quilici</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of competition mechanisms in successive invasions by polyphagous tephritids in La R&#x000e9;union</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2006</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1770</fpage><lpage>1780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16922326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/0012-9658(2006)87[1770:IOCMIS]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malacrida</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomulski</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guglielmino</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Globalization and fruitfly invasion and expansion: The medfly paradigm</article-title><source>Genetica</source><year>2007</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17111234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10709-006-9117-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hot peppers as a host for the Mexican fruit fly <italic>Anastrepha ludens </italic>(Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title><source>Florida Entomologist</source><year>2004</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1653/0015-4040(2004)087[0603:HPAAHF]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrewartha</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some recent contributions to the study of the distribution and abundance of insects</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>1960</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.en.05.010160.001251</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitten</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated sexing of pupae and its usefulness in control by sterile insects</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>1969</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>273</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic sexing strains in Medfly, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic>, Sterile Insect Technique Programmes</article-title><source>Genetica</source><year>2002</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12484522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1020951407069</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Economopoulos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Avtzis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zervas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsitsipis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haniotakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsiropoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Manoukas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experiments on control of olive fly, <italic>Dacus oleae </italic>(Gmelin), by combined effect of insecticides and releases of gamma-ray sterilized insects</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Entomology</source><year>1977</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>215</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Economopoulos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zervas</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sterile insect technique and radiation in insect control</article-title><source>IAEA-SM-255/39</source><year>1982</year><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>368</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zouros</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Loukas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Robinson AS, Hooper G</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and colonization genetics of <italic>Dacus oleae </italic>(Gmelin)</article-title><source>Fruit flies, their biology, natural enemies and control</source><year>1989</year><volume>3B</volume><publisher-name>Amsterdam: Elsevier Science Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>87</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Augustinos</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamuris</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratikopoulos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Amelio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacharopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathiopoulos</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite analysis of olive fly populations in the mediterranean indicates a westward expansion of the species</article-title><source>Genetica</source><year>2005</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16247695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10709-005-8692-y</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nardi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Carapelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dallai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roderick</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Frati</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population structure and colonization history of the olive fly, <italic>Bactrocera oleae </italic>(Diptera, Tephritidae)</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2005</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2729</fpage><lpage>2738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16029474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2005.02610.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mavragani-Tsipidou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and cytogenetic analysis of the olive fruit fly <italic>Bactrocera oleae </italic>(Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title><source>Genetica</source><year>2002</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12484525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1020907624816</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Koukidou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Savakis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Komitopoulou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The transformer gene in <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic>: The genetic switch that determines its sex fate</article-title><source>Insect Molecular Biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17298554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2583.2006.00717.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sa&#x000ec;nchez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Komitopoulou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of the <italic>Bactrocera oleae </italic>genes orthologous to the sex determining Sex-lethal and doublesex genes of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2005</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15777677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2004.12.053</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koukidou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klinakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reboulakis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagoraiou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavernarakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Livadaras</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Economopoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Savakis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Germ line transformation of the olive fly <italic>Bactrocera oleae </italic>using a versatile transgenesis marker</article-title><source>Insect Molecular Biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2583.2006.00613.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruford</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wayne</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellites and their application to population genetic studies</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Genetics and Development</source><year>1993</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8118220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0959-437X(93)90017-J</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schl&#x000f6;tterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pemberton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of microsatellites for genetic analysis of natural populations</article-title><source>EXS</source><year>1994</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7994107</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tautz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schl&#x000f6;tterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simple sequences</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><year>1994</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7888752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0959-437X(94)90067-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Malacrida</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Guglielmino</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomulski</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite polymorphism in the mediterranean fruit fly, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic></article-title><source>Insect Molecular Biology</source><year>2000</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10886408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2583.2000.00184.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guglielmino</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Haymer</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomulski</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Malacrida</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite analysis of medfly bioinfestations in California</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2515</fpage><lpage>2524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0962-1083.2001.01376.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guglielmino</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Smallridge</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomulski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Malacrida</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the origins of medfly invasion and expansion in Australia</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>3845</fpage><lpage>3855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15548296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2004.02371.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomulski</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Murelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Torti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Malacrida</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Guglielmino</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic differentiation, gene flow and the origin of infestations of the medfly, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic></article-title><source>Genetica</source><year>2002</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12484532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1020971911612</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stratikopoulos</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustinos</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Petalas</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrahatis</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintzas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathiopoulos</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacharopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrated genetic and cytogenetic map for the Mediterranean fruit fly, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic>, based on microsatellite and morphological markers</article-title><source>Genetica</source><year>2008</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17786564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10709-007-9195-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>RAI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple paternity in a natural population of a wild tobacco fly, <italic>Bactrocera cacuminata </italic>(Diptera: Tephritidae), assessed by microsatellite DNA markers</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2353</fpage><lpage>2361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17561896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2007.03277.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsoyannos</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>Marguerie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Guglielmino</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Malacrida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite analysis reveals remating by wild Mediterranean fruit fly females, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic></article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2002</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1915</fpage><lpage>1921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12296936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-294X.2002.01602.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kraaijeveld</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsoyannos</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>Stavrinides</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouloussis</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remating in wild females of the Mediterranean fruit fly, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic></article-title><source>Animal Behaviour</source><year>2005</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anbehav.2004.06.015</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Augustinos</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratikopoulos</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacharopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathiopoulos</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphic microsatellite markers in the olive fly, <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic></article-title><source>Molecular Ecology Notes</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-8286.2002.00222.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bachtrog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zangerl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brem</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schl&#x000f6;tterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of dinucleotide microsatellites in the <italic>Drosophila melanogaster </italic>genome</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1999</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10335653</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katti</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranjekar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential distribution of simple sequence repeats in eukaryotic genome sequences</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2001</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1161</fpage><lpage>1167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11420357</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schug</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetterstrand</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudette</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutter</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquadro</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The distribution and frequency of microsatellite loci in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9465417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-294x.1998.00304.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutter</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schug</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquadro</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite variation in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster </italic>and <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic>: A reciprocal test of the ascertainment bias hypothesis</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1998</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1620</fpage><lpage>1636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9866198</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedict</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornel</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kafatos</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrated genetic map of the African human malaria vector mosquito, <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1996</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>941</fpage><lpage>952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8725240</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Estoup</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Solignac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornuet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of (GT)(n) and (CT)(n) microsatellites in two insect species: <italic>Apis mellifera </italic>and <italic>Bombus terrestris</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><year>1993</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1427</fpage><lpage>1431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8464734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/21.6.1427</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinnear</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bariana</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sved</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Frommer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphic microsatellite markers for population analysis of a tephritid pest species, <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic></article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1489</fpage><lpage>1495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9819903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-294x.1998.00480.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraju</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellites in the silkworm, <italic>Bombyx mori</italic>: Abundance, polymorphism, and strain characterization</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>1999</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1057</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10659770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/gen-42-6-1057</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>MAF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schug</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquadro</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite variation in populations of <italic>Drosophila pseudoobscura </italic>and <italic>Drosophila persimilis</italic></article-title><source>Genetical Research</source><year>2000</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10740918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0016672399004024</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harr</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schl&#x000f6;tterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of microsatellite variability in the <italic>Drosophila melanogaster </italic>complex</article-title><source>Genetica</source><year>2004</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15088648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:GENE.0000017631.00820.49</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubinsztein</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Amos</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Leggo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodburn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite evolution &#x02013; Evidence for directionality and variation in rate between species</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><year>1995</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7670473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0795-337</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Callejas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferna&#x000ec;ndez</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochando</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New contributions towards the understanding of the phylogenetic relationships among economically important fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title><source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source><year>2006</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16768816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/BER2006425</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular phylogenetic study of the tribe Trypetini (Diptera: Tephritidae), using mitochondrial 16S ribosomal DNA sequences</article-title><source>Biochemical systematics and Ecology</source><year>2000</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10793251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0305-1978(99)00097-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>McPheron</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular phylogenetic study of tephritidae (insecta: diptera) using partial sequences of the mitochondrial 16S ribosomal DNA</article-title><source>Molecular phylogenetics and Evolution</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9007017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/mpev.1996.0370</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>McPheron</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic study of selected Tephritid flies (Insecta: Diptera: Tephritidae) using partial sequences of the nuclear 18s ribosomal DNA</article-title><source>Biochemical systematics and Ecology</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0305-1978(94)90040-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chirhart</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Honeycutt</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenbaum</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite variation and evolution in the Peromyscus maniculatus species group</article-title><source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source><year>2005</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15619451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2004.10.018</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Launching microsatellites: A review of mutation processes and methods of phylogenetic inference</article-title><source>Journal of Heredity</source><year>1997</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9378905</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schl&#x000f6;tterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genealogical inference of closely related species based on microsatellites</article-title><source>Genetical Research</source><year>2001</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11865709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0016672301005444</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kounatidis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourtzis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavragani-Tsipidou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and cytogenetic analysis of the fruit fly <italic>Rhagoletis cerasi </italic>(Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2008</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18545272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/G08-032</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zacharopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polytene chromosome maps in the Medfly <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic></article-title><source>Genome</source><year>1990</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zacharopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frisardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Savakis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolias</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Konsolaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Komitopoulou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kafatos</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genome of the Mediterranean fruit fly <italic>C. capitat </italic>a: Localization of molecular markers by <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization to salivary gland polytene chromosomes</article-title><source>Chromosoma</source><year>1992</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1618026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00582839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsitsipis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An improved method for the mass rearing of the olive fruit fly, <italic>Dacus oleae </italic>(Gmel.) (Diptera, Tephritidae)</article-title><source>Z Angrew Entomol</source><year>1977</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>426</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsitsipis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a caging and egging system for mass rearing the olive fruit fly, <italic>Dacus oleae </italic>(Gmel.) (Diptera, Tephritidae)</article-title><source>Ann Zool Ecol Anim</source><year>1977</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>139</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzanakakis</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Economopoulos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsitsipis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The importance of conditions during the adult stage in evaluating an artificial food for larvae of <italic>Dacus oleae </italic>(Gmel.) (Diptera, Tephritidae)</article-title><source>Z Angew Entomol</source><year>1967</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Drosophila: A Laboratory Manual</source><year>1989</year><publisher-name>New York: Cold Spring Harbour Laboratory Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritch</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual</source><year>1989</year><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor, NY. 21: Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schl&#x000f6;tterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hoelzel AR</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellites</article-title><source>Molecular Genetic Analysis of Populations: a practical approach</source><year>1998</year><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>245</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zambetaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacharopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scouras</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavragani-Tsipidou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genome of the olive fruit fly <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic>: Localization of molecular markers by <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization to the salivary gland polytene chromosomes</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>1999</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/gen-42-4-744</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Crampton JM, Beard CB, Louis C</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite mapping of insect genomes</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of Insect Disease Vectors: A methods manual</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Chapman &#x00026; Hall</publisher-name><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>329</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B66"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>TBJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name></person-group><source>POPGENE, the user-friendly shareware for population genetic analysis</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Molecular Biology and Biotechnology Centre, University of Alberta, Canada</publisher-name></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>