<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xml:lang="EN" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Nanomedicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">International Journal of Nanomedicine</journal-id><journal-title>International Journal of Nanomedicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1176-9114</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1178-2013</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Medical Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19337419</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636583</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijn-3-505</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reversible pH-controlled DNA-binding peptide nanotweezers: An                    in-silico study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Gaurav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijn-3-505">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rege</surname><given-names>Kaushal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijn-3-505">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijn-3-505">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Budil</surname><given-names>David E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-ijn-3-505">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yarmush</surname><given-names>Martin L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijn-3-505">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5-ijn-3-505">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mavroidis</surname><given-names>Constantinos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijn-3-505">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-ijn-3-505"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijn-3-505"><label>1</label> Department of Mechanical and Industrial Engineering</aff><aff id="af2-ijn-3-505"><label>2</label> The Center for Engineering in Medicine (CEM), Massachusetts General                Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="af3-ijn-3-505"><label>3</label> Department of Chemical Engineering, Arizona State University,                Tempe, AZ, USA</aff><aff id="af4-ijn-3-505"><label>4</label> Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, Northeastern                University, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="af5-ijn-3-505"><label>5</label> Department of Biomedical Engineering, Rutgers University, NJ, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijn-3-505">Correspondence: Constantinos Mavroidis, Department of                    Mechanical and Industrial Engineering, 360 Huntington Avenue, Northeastern                    University, Boston, MA, 02115, USA, Tel +1 617 373 4121, Fax                    +1 617 373 2921, Email <email>mavro@coe.neu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2008 Dove Medical Press Limited. All rights reserved</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><abstract><p>We describe the molecular dynamics (MD)-aided engineering design of mutant                    peptides based on the &#x003b1;-helical coiled-coil GCN4 leucine zipper                    peptide (GCN4-p1) in order to obtain environmentally-responsive nanotweezers.                    The actuation mechanism of the nanotweezers depends on the modification of                    electrostatic charges on the residues along the length of the coiled coil.                    Modulating the solution pH between neutral and acidic values results in the                    reversible movement of helices toward and away from each other and creates a                    complete closed-open-closed transition cycle between the helices. Our results                    indicate that the mutants show a reversible opening of up to 15 &#x000c5;                    (1.5 nm; approximately 150% of the initial separation) upon pH                    actuation. Investigation on the physicochemical phenomena that influence                    conformational properties, structural stability, and reversibility of the                    coiled-coil peptide-based nanotweezers revealed that a rationale- and                    design-based approach is needed to engineer stable peptide or macromolecules                    into stimuli-responsive devices. The efficacy of the mutant that demonstrated                    the most significant reversible actuation for environmentally responsive                    modulation of DNA-binding activity was also demonstrated. Our results have                    significant implications in bioseparations and in the engineering of novel                    transcription factors.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>bionanotechnology</kwd><kwd>nanotweezers</kwd><kwd>coiled-coil</kwd><kwd>GCN4</kwd><kwd>leucine zipper</kwd><kwd>molecular dynamics</kwd><kwd>environmentally responsive peptides</kwd><kwd>transcription factor engineering</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The development of environmentally-responsive functional                &#x02018;nanodevices&#x02019;, capable of performing complex tasks at                nanoscale, will require the assembly of individual nanoscale components. Most                reports in the literature have focused on inorganic nanoparticles including                buckyball fullerenes and carbon nanotubes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55-ijn-3-505">Tenne 2006</xref>), and various metal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28-ijn-3-505">Hirsch et al 2006</xref>) and semiconductor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-ijn-3-505">Biju et al 2008</xref>) nanoparticles. These                systems can have significant implications in a variety of applications including                molecular electronics, sensors, and drug delivery. In nature, many manipulations at                the nanoscale are carried out by proteins and peptides that serve a variety of                structural (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-ijn-3-505">Bella et al 1994</xref>) and                mechanical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34-ijn-3-505">Lee et al 2006</xref>)                functions. Therefore, it is of great interest to engineer naturally-occurring                peptides and proteins as functional components that can be eventually assembled as                novel nanodevices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ijn-3-505">Banta et al 2007</xref>)                in combination with other environmentally responsive nanomaterials.</p><p>A number of tools are already in place to manipulate the vast repertoire of naturally                occurring proteins and peptides. Structural information, obtained by techniques such                as X-ray crystallography and nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), has provided an                intricate picture of the conformational attributes of proteins. Coupling this                information with data obtained by dynamic molecular simulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31-ijn-3-505">Karplus and McCammon 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54-ijn-3-505">Tama and Brooks 2006</xref>) and nanoscale                manipulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56-ijn-3-505">Tinoco and Bustamante                2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ijn-3-505">Bao and Suresh 2003</xref>;                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-ijn-3-505">Bustamante 2004</xref>) has enabled                the correlation of protein structure and function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41-ijn-3-505">Mizoue and Chazin 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16-ijn-3-505">Daggett and Fersht 2003</xref>). The breadth of structure                and function in proteins and peptides has been enhanced by protein engineering,                which provides the capability to modify existing proteins or generate new ones                    (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-ijn-3-505">Brannigan and Wilkinson 2002</xref>;                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-ijn-3-505">Bloom et al 2005</xref>).</p><p>Transcription factors are proteins that bind to specific DNA sequences in the                promoter and enhancer regions thereby regulating gene transcription. The basic                leucine-zipper (bZIP) motif of the yeast transcription factor GCN4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20-ijn-3-505">Ellenberger et al 1992</xref>) is a                56-residue peptide (residues 225&#x02013;281) which consists of two sub-domains:                the leucine zipper (GCN4-LZ) dimerization domain and the basic DNA-binding domain                    (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-3-505">Figure 1a</xref>). The leucine zipper                region forms a stable, two-stranded, parallel coiled-coil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46-ijn-3-505">O&#x02019;Shea et al 1991</xref>) in which individual                residues follow a heptad repeat pattern                    (<bold>a</bold>&#x02022;<bold>b</bold>&#x02022;<bold>c</bold>&#x02022;<bold>d</bold>&#x02022;<bold>e</bold>&#x02022;<bold>f</bold>&#x02022;<bold>g</bold>)<sub>n</sub>;                residues in the <bold><italic>a</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>d</italic></bold> position are primarily hydrophobic, and residues in the <bold><italic>e</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>g</italic></bold> position are predominantly charged or polar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-3-505">Figure 1c</xref>). The coiled-coil structure is highly stable                largely due the hydrophobic interactions at the interface of the two helices and the                complementary electrostatic interactions between individual amino acids that                stabilize the structure as a knobs-in-hole model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-ijn-3-505">Crick 1953</xref>). GCN4-LZ consists of two identical                33-residue polypeptide chains/helices and is ~4.5 nm long and ~3 nm wide. The                helices wrap around each other to form approximately &#x000bc; turn of a                left-handed supercoil. The pitch of the supercoil averages 181 &#x000c5;, and                the average distance between the helix axes is 9.3 &#x000c5; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46-ijn-3-505">O&#x02019;Shea et al 1991</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-3-505">Figure 1b</xref> shows the enlarged view of                the leucine zipper with the corresponding dimensions.</p><p>Coiled-coil proteins play an important role as transcriptional activators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ijn-3-505">Barbara et al 2007</xref>) and in membrane                fusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25-ijn-3-505">Harbury 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61-ijn-3-505">Weis and Scheller 1998</xref>). The                simplicity and regularity in their structure make them excellent candidates for                protein design and engineering studies. For example, folding pathways in coiled-coil                proteins have been studied as model systems for quaternary structure formation in                proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39-ijn-3-505">Mason and Arndt 2004</xref>).                Coiled-coil motif-based dimers and trimers of &#x003b1;-helices have been                designed to act as functional protein receptors for molecular recognition of ligands                    (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18-ijn-3-505">Doerr et al 2004</xref>) and                heterodimerizing leucine zipper coiled-coils have been designed to deliver                radionuclides to the surface of cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44-ijn-3-505">Moll et al 2001</xref>). Coiled-coil proteins have been                extensively investigated using various experimental techniques such as NMR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45-ijn-3-505">Nikolaev and Pervushin 2007</xref>), X-ray                diffraction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46-ijn-3-505">O&#x02019;Shea et al                1991</xref>), circular dichroism (CD) and fluorescence spectroscopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53-ijn-3-505">Suzuki et al 1998</xref>), differential                scanning calorimetry (DSC) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b64-ijn-3-505">Yu et al                1996</xref>) and electron spin resonance (ESR) spectroscopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14-ijn-3-505">Columbus and Hubbell 2004</xref>) as well as theoretical and                computational approaches using molecular dynamics (MD) simulation techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42-ijn-3-505">Mohanty et al 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40-ijn-3-505">Missimer et al 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48-ijn-3-505">Pineiro et al 2005</xref>). MD simulations                provide a means to understand the structural and dynamic behavior of coiled-coil at                the atomic level which is often inaccessible to experimental tools.</p><p>In the present work, we describe the molecular dynamics-aided design, concept                evolution and biophysical characterization of an engineered peptide nanotweezer                based on the coiled-coil GCN4-LZ. The simplicity, regularity in structural                organization, and availability of the peptide crystal structure allows the                engineering of GCN4-LZ to develop functional nanoscale elements. The GCN4-LZ was                engineered to obtain pH-dependent nanotweezers involving the lateral displacement of                the two helices relative to each other. The reversible actuation mechanism depends                on the generation of similar electrostatic charges along the peptide chain which                forces the two coils to repel each other, creating a closed-to-open transition.                Neutralizing these charges leads to an open-to-closed transition and restitution of                the original structure stabilized primarily by hydrophobic interactions. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ijn-3-505">Figure 2a</xref> shows a schematic of the                nanotweezer operating principle. A broader impact of this study was the analysis of                coiled-coil stability under different pH conditions in addition to an in-depth                investigation into the effect of point mutations and electrostatic forces on                coiled-coil secondary structure. Based on these studies, we propose the design of a                DNA-binding modulator element based on the pH-driven nanotweezer architecture and                show preliminary simulation results to support our hypothesis. The development of                such a DNA-binding modulator has implications in transcription factor engineering                wherein one of the focuses is the construction of designer transcription factors for                various therapeutic and research applications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ijn-3-505">Beerli and Barbas 2002</xref>). We also describe the                development of key design principles required for incorporating flexibility in rigid                peptide motifs which can have implications in computational drug design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-ijn-3-505">Carlson and McCammon 2000</xref>), design of                protein-based biosensors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24-ijn-3-505">Gooding et al                    2003</xref>) and molecular motors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52-ijn-3-505">Sun                    et al 2003</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Peptide design</title><p>The X-ray crystallographic structure of the native GCN4 (PDB entry: 1YSA),                    complexed with AP-1 yeast DNA, was obtained from the Protein Data Bank (see                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-3-505">Figure 1a</xref>). The DNA was                    removed by deleting the coordinates from the PDB structure and the two peptide                    chains (A and B) were truncated to contain 33 residues numbered 249 to 281                    corresponding to the coiled-coil portion of the peptide (henceforth referred to                    as GCN4-LZ); an arginine residue, missing at position 281 of chain B in the                    original crystal structure was added. A cysteine residue was also introduced at                    position 248 in both chains in order to enable interhelical bonding and                    dimerization.</p><p>Three different nanotweezer mutants (M1, M2, and M3) were designed using GCN4-LZ                    as template. First, a pentaglycine tag was added at the N-terminus of GCN4-LZ;                    the glycine (Gly) residues were added in order to maintain the same number of                    residues as those in the nanotweezer mutants described below. The resulting                    structure is referred to as the wild-type (WT) peptide in subsequent                    discussions. Mutant M1 consists of a pentahistidine tag (His-tag) aligned with                    the &#x003b1;-helix at the N-terminus of the wild-type. Mutant M2 consists                    of four mutations (L261H, S262H, N264H, and Y265H) in each of the two helical                    chains in addition to the N-terminal His-tags present in M1. Mutant M3 consists                    of five mutations (L253H, K256H, E259H, L261H, and Y265H) in each of the helical                    chains in addition to the His-tag. Finally, in mutant M3CT we replaced the                    His-tag of mutant M3 with a pentaglycine tag. These mutation sites were chosen                    based on the MultiCoil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62-ijn-3-505">Wolf et al                        1997</xref>) predictions for the coiled-coil formation probability of each                    of the mutants; a probability greater than 0.8 was seen for all engineered                    mutants. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="f10-ijn-3-505">Figure                    S-1</xref> shows the MultiCoil score for the mutants; the probability cut-off                    for coiled coil formation is 0.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62-ijn-3-505">Wolf                        et al 1997</xref>). <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1-ijn-3-505">Table 1</xref>                    shows the single-letter amino acid sequences of the wild-type and the mutant                    peptides with the residue positions shown against the coiled-coil heptad repeat                    sequence. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ijn-3-505">Figure 2b</xref> shows the                    architecture of different nanotweezer mutants with the position of His-tags and                    histidine residues shown.</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular dynamics</title><p>The protonation states of histidine (His), glutamic acid (Glu), and asparatic                    acid (Asp) residues were modified appropriately to model neutral and low pH. His                    residues are unprotonated at neutral pH whereas Glu and Asp are negatively                    charged. At low pH, His are protonated and therefore, positively charged,                    whereas Asp and Glu are considered neutral. N&#x0025b;2H and                    N&#x003b4;1H + N&#x0025b;2H(+) tautomeric states                    of His were considered to model neutral and low pH, respectively. For Glu                    O&#x0025b;2(&#x02212;) and O&#x0025b;2H tautomeric states were                    considered to model neutral and low pH, respectively. For Asp                    O&#x003b4;2(&#x02212;) and O&#x003b4;2H tatutomeric states were                    considered to model neutral and low pH, respectively.</p><p>The Nanoscale Molecular Dynamics (NAMD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47-ijn-3-505">Phillips et al 2005</xref>) program was used to perform                    MD simulations in this study. The protein was modeled with an all-atom CHARMM27                    force field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37-ijn-3-505">MacKerell et al                    1998</xref>). The protein was solvated by placing it at the center of a box of                    water with approximate edge lengths of 50 &#x000d7; 50 &#x000d7; 70                    &#x000c5; and subtracting all water molecules within 2.4 &#x000c5; of                    any protein atom. Water molecules were described by the TIP3P model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30-ijn-3-505">Jorgensen 1983</xref>). The system being                    studied carries excess charge at low pH due to the protonation of amino acids in                    the peptide. To represent a typical biological environment which is electrically                    neutral, salt (NaCl, 2 mM) was added by placing ions in water to make the system                    neutral. Electrostatic interactions were computed using the particle mesh Ewald                    (PME) method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17-ijn-3-505">Darden et al                    1993</xref>). Van der Waals interactions were truncated at a cutoff distance of                    12 &#x000c5; and a smooth switching function was used at a switching                    distance of 10 &#x000c5;. The ShakeH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58-ijn-3-505">van Gunsteren and Berendsen 1977</xref>) algorithm was                    used to fix the bond between each hydrogen and its mother atom to the nominal                    bond length with a relative tolerance of 1.0 &#x000d7;                    10&#x02212;<sup>8</sup> &#x000c5; and the timestep for integration was 2                    fs. The temperature was regulated by coupling the system to an external bath                    with a damping coefficient of 5. An isobaric (P = 1 atm) and                    isothermal (T = 298 K) with constant number of atoms (the so-called                    NPT) ensemble was created using the approach developed by Nose and Hoover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38-ijn-3-505">Martyna et al 1994</xref>).</p><p>Each MD simulation consisted of four individual steps. In the first, the system                    was minimized for 2000 steps using the conjugate gradient method with the                    protein fixed in space. This allowed the water to relax and absorb around the                    protein. The constraints on the protein were then removed in the second step and                    the entire system was minimized for 2000 steps. In the third step, the system                    was heated to the desired temperature within 10 ps and then allowed to                    equilibrate for another 10 ps at the target temperature with the protein                    constrained through a harmonic potential. The constraints were then removed and                    the system was allowed to evolve for 4&#x02013;5 ns of production run. The                    trajectory was saved every 2 ps. The evolution of the secondary structure during                    MD trajectories was calculated using the STRIDE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21-ijn-3-505">Frishman and Argos 1995</xref>) program.</p></sec><sec><title>MD methods for DNA-binding simulation</title><p>Steered Molecular Dynamics (SMD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29-ijn-3-505">Isralewitz et al 2001</xref>) technique was used for DNA-binding modulation                    simulation. This technique has been used extensively to study the mechanical                    properties of proteins and biopolymers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35-ijn-3-505">Lu and Schulten 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-ijn-3-505">Cheng et al 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23-ijn-3-505">Gao et al 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36-ijn-3-505">Lu and Long 2005</xref>). The DNA molecule was pulled                    out of the protein-binding site using a constant velocity SMD simulation in                    which a constant velocity is imparted to the DNA atoms in a predefined                    direction. This is done by attaching the center-of-mass (COM) of DNA atoms                    (called SMD atom) to a dummy atom and pulling the dummy atom with a virtual                    spring of known stiffness. This dummy atom is moved at constant velocity and                    then the force between both is measured using:</p><disp-formula><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02207;</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x02009;&#x0200a;&#x0200a;</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>U</italic> is the potential energy, <italic>k</italic> is spring                    constant, <italic>v</italic> is the pulling velocity, <italic>t</italic> is                    time, <italic>r</italic> is the actual position of the pulling atom,                        <italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub> is the initial position of the pulling atom,                    and <italic>n</italic> is the pulling direction. A harmonic spring of stiffness,                        <italic>k</italic> = 0.2 kcal/mol/&#x000c5;<sup>2</sup>, was                    used and the DNA molecule was pulled along the longitudinal axis of the GCN4                    peptide with a constant velocity <italic>v</italic> = 10                    &#x000c5;/ns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ijn-3-505">Figure 3</xref>). At                    low pH, the N<sub>1</sub> atom of A nucleoside (pK<sub>a</sub>~3.8) and N atom                    of C nucleoside (pK<sub>a</sub>~4.5) are know to accept a proton, thereby                    neutralizing the charge on the entire nucleotide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49-ijn-3-505">Saenger 1984</xref>). At moderate pH (3&#x02013;5)                    range only a fraction of the A and C nucleosides can be expected to be                    protonated. We therefore chose to protonate all of A nucleosides which could                    effectively correspond to a simulation carried out at pH 4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27-ijn-3-505">Heng et al 2006</xref>). Partial charges                    for the N<sub>1</sub>-protonated A nucleoside were used as reported in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27-ijn-3-505">Heng et al 2006</xref>) and were kindly                    provided by Dr. Aleksei Aksimentiev. The entire GCN4&#x02013;DNA system was                    solvated in a water box and neutralized using NaCl salt at 20 mM concentration.                    All the other simulation parameters are the same as described previously.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results|discussion"><title>Results and discussion</title><p>We designed GCN4-LZ mutants with His residues at different positions in the peptide                sequence in order to enable the pH-dependent actuation mechanism. At neutral pH, His                residues (histidine pKa ~6.1) are unprotonated and the coiled-coil peptide maintains                a &#x02018;closed&#x02019; structure. At low pH, interhelical repulsion                induced by His protonation results in the actuation motion of the two helices of the                peptide away from each other.</p><sec><title>Wild-type structure and mutant M1 are stable</title><p>From previous experimental (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33-ijn-3-505">Kohn et al                        1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b64-ijn-3-505">Yu et al 1996</xref>;                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26-ijn-3-505">Hendsch and Tidor 1999</xref>) and                    computational studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42-ijn-3-505">Mohanty et al                        1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40-ijn-3-505">Missimer et al                    2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48-ijn-3-505">Pineiro et al                    2005</xref>), we expect that the wild-type GCN4-LZ will be stable at both                    neutral and low pH. To address this, we performed simulations starting with the                    GCN4-LZ crystal structure immersed in a box of water molecules. The backbone                    C&#x003b1; root mean square deviation (RMSD) for residues                    248&#x02013;281 does indeed remain low (1.5 &#x000c5;) over the course                    of simulation at both neutral and low pH (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="f11-ijn-3-505">Figure S-2a</xref>).                    This value agrees well with the previously reported range of RMSD values from MD                    simulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59-ijn-3-505">Vieth et al 1994</xref>;                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42-ijn-3-505">Mohanty et al 1999</xref>) of                    GCN4-LZ. These results are expected since the presence of at least six sites of                    strong hydrophobic interactions along the helical chain makes the WT peptide                    highly stable and resistant to any pH perturbation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="f11-ijn-3-505">Figure S-2b</xref>).                    Previous reports in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33-ijn-3-505">Kohn et al 1995</xref>) also indicate that the GCN4-LZ is stable under                    conditions of low pH due to the stabilization by increased hydrophobicity of the                    unionized glutamic acid residues compared to the ionized glutamic acid                    side-chain at neutral pH. Our results on the stability of GCN4-LZ under acidic                    pH are in agreement with these studies.</p><p>The pH-dependent actuation of mutant M1, which contains a 5-histidine tag at the                    N-terminus of each helical chain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ijn-3-505">Figure                        2b</xref>), was evaluated at both neutral and low pH. It was hypothesized                    that the protonation of histidine residues in the N-terminal tags at low pH                    would result in significant electrostatic repulsive forces and                    &#x02018;push&#x02019; the two helices apart, thus generating the                    closed-to-open mechanochemical actuation in the mutant peptide. Two atoms                    (C&#x003b1; atoms of the His247 residues) were selected near the N-terminal                    of the individual chains in order to measure the opening between the helices and                    the distance between the two was measured as a function of simulation time. No                    significant opening was observed after a 4 ns simulation; the initial distance                    of 13 &#x000c5; between the two atoms remained constant during the first                    nanosecond of simulation after which it increased to 16 &#x000c5; and                    remained stable at this separation for the rest of the simulation. The increase                    of 3 &#x000c5; is not significant and can be attributed to atomic                    fluctuations or the perturbation in the histidine residues due to repulsive                    forces rather than the overall displacement of the two chains. This implies that                    the electrostatic repulsive forces generated by the positively charged                    N-terminal histidines are not sufficient to overcome the strong hydrophobic                    interactions that stabilize the coiled-coil core of M1 mutant. In order to                    offset the attractive hydrophobic interactions in the core, we designed                    subsequent mutants that possess histidine residues along the length of                    coiled-coil.</p></sec><sec><title>Additional repulsive forces are needed to trigger a conformational change in                    the coiled-coil</title><p>Mutant M2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ijn-3-505">Figure 2b</xref>) was designed                    next with four histidine residues incorporated within the helical chains in                    addition to the N-terminal histidine-tag. It was hypothesized that the presence                    of these additional histidine residues will create a second region of repulsive                    forces along the interface of the two helices at low pH and trigger                    conformational displacement between the helices.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ijn-3-505">Figure 4a</xref> shows the snapshots of a                    4 ns simulation of M2 at low pH. Mutant M2 was not stable during the course of                    the simulation as indicated by the disruption of the &#x003b1;-helix in                    chain B. Moreover, no significant opening was observed in the mutant, implying                    that either the electrostatic forces were not sufficient or the mutation sites                    were not well-selected. To gain further insight into the stability of the                    structure we plotted the evolution of the secondary structure elements of M2                    over the simulation time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ijn-3-505">Figure                    4b</xref>). Unfolding of the &#x003b1;-helix begins during the first                    nanosecond of the simulation itself, implying that these mutations were                    inherently destabilizing to the secondary structure. One explanation for the                    unfolding of the &#x003b1;-helix lies in the nature of the N264H mutation.                    The location of the two asparagines (Asn264A and Asn264B) is unique in that they                    are the only polar residues in the core positions (<bold><italic>a</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>d</italic></bold>) of the GCN4-LZ. The Asn264A&#x02013;Asn264B interhelical                    interaction is the strongest favorable interaction between individual groups in                    the GCN4-LZ and stabilizes the coiled-coil structure by contributing                    &#x02212;2.1 kcal/mole towards the free energy of the structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26-ijn-3-505">Hendsch and Tidor 1999</xref>). This                    strong interaction arises from the fact that the two Asn residues are buried and                    packed in the &#x02018;knobs-into-holes&#x02019; pattern described by                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-ijn-3-505">Crick (1953)</xref>. The N264H                    mutation replaces this stabilizing interaction of Asn residues with the                    destabilizing ionic repulsions of the charged His residues thereby disrupting                    the coiled-coil structure. The resulting structural instability obviates the use                    of M2 as a potential design since maintaining structural rigidity during the                    course of operation is an important design requirement for the nanotweezer.</p></sec><sec><title>Evolved design of the coiled-coil nanotweezer (mutant M3): Low pH triggers                    the actuation motion while maintaining the structural integrity</title><p>Mutant M3 was designed next with the following point mutations in addition to the                    N-terminal histidine tag: L253H, K256H, E259H, L261H, Y265H. These mutation                    sites correspond to the <bold><italic>d</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>g</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>c</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>e</italic></bold>, and <bold><italic>b</italic></bold> positions respectively on the helical wheel diagram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-3-505">Figure 1c</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ijn-3-505">Figure 5a</xref> shows the starting structure of M3 with                    the His mutation sites shown as spheres. M3 has a uniform distribution of His                    residues along the helical chain which results in a spatial distribution of                    electrostatic charges in addition to the concentrated charges from the distal                    His-tags. Further, the L253H, L261H, and Y265H mutations replace the hydrophobic                    leucine and tyrosine residues with polar His residues thereby significantly                    reducing the strength of the hydrophobic interactions towards the N-terminal and                    &#x02018;middle&#x02019; regions of the coiled-coil core while                    maintaining the strong hydrophobic core in the C-terminal region. This evolved                    design was therefore a balance between repulsive forces that can induce the                    actuation mechanism at low pH and strong hydrophobic interactions that can (i)                    maintain the coiled-coil structure and (ii) serve as the restoring force for the                    &#x02018;hinge&#x02019; action in order to restore the original                    conformation of the peptide at neutral pH. We verified, as predicted from its                    MultiCoil score (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62-ijn-3-505">Wolf et al                    1997</xref>), that these mutations do not destabilize the coiled-coil formation                    propensity of the individual helices. Interestingly, of all the mutants                    evaluated, M3 demonstrated the highest probability (0.9) of dimer formation in                    solution (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="f10-ijn-3-505">Figure                    S-1</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ijn-3-505">Figure 5b</xref> shows the snapshots of a                    4 ns simulation of M3. Large conformational changes were observed in the M3                    system leading to a significant net opening between the two helices. The helices                    rapidly moved apart within the first nanosecond and continued to move apart                    steadily until three nanoseconds (ns) before adopting a final stable                    conformation. The distance between the C&#x003b1; atoms of the His246                    residues in both chains was plotted as a function of the simulation time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ijn-3-505">Figure 5c</xref>). The initial distance                    between the two atoms was 11 &#x000c5; which gradually increased to 28                    &#x000c5; at the 2.5 ns stage. The distance then fluctuated due to the                    dynamic nature of the electrostatic forces but stayed near the 27 &#x000c5;                    separation during the rest of the simulation (4 ns). Thus, a net opening of 16                    &#x000c5; which is approximately 150% of the initial separation                    (11 &#x000c5;) was observed for M3 at low pH.</p><p>We plotted the evolution of the secondary structure of the simulated system to                    characterize the effects of electrostatic forces on the structural stability of                    M3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ijn-3-505">Figure 5d</xref>). The main                    structural features of mutant are largely retained, ie, the                    &#x003b1;-helices of the two chains are preserved throughout the simulation.                    The last three residues at the C-terminal in both chains remain in their native                    random coil conformation throughout the simulation and do not affect the                    stability of the overall structure. This result, in conjunction with the                    MultiCoil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62-ijn-3-505">Wolf et al 1997</xref>)                    prediction (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="f10-ijn-3-505">Figure                        S-1</xref>), verifies the hypothesis that selective mutations can be                    performed in the native GCN4-LZ, inducing large conformational changes without                    compromising its structural stability. The conformational change is, however,                    not uniform along the length of the &#x003b1;-helical chains as is evident                    from the helix&#x02013;helix contact map (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="f12-ijn-3-505">Figure S-3</xref>).                    The closed-to-open conformational change in M3 results in a loss of                    helix&#x02013;helix contacts in residues 243&#x02013;261 while contacts                    are largely preserved in residues 262&#x02013;281. The &#x003b1;-helices                    appear to &#x02018;bend&#x02019; near the His-261 region as a result of                    the electrostatic forces. The bending, while maintaining the overall secondary                    structure, creates elastic forces in &#x003b1;-helices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50-ijn-3-505">Seungho and Sean 2005</xref>) which tend                    to bring the helices back to their initial &#x02018;relaxed&#x02019;                    structure. Thus the &#x02018;open&#x02019; conformation of mutant M3 at                    low pH is in a state of dynamic equilibrium between the electrostatic repulsive                    forces from charged residues and the restituting forces created by helix                    elasticity and coiled-coil hydrophobic interactions.</p><p>In order to gain insights into the mechanisms of action of M3, we designed a                    control mutant, M3CT, by replacing the N-terminal histidines in M3 by an                    equivalent number of glycine residues. This design enables an investigation into                    the contribution of the five histidine residues within the coiled-coil core                    towards the conformational dynamics of the resulting GCN4-LZ mutant, without                    additional contributions from the distal His-tags. Glycine was chosen since it                    is a neutral, &#x003b1;-helix breaking amino acid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ijn-3-505">Aurora et al 1994</xref>) and therefore, has no secondary                    structural or charge contributions to the resulting M3CT mutant. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ijn-3-505">Figure 6</xref> compares the actuation                    dynamics of all five mutants plotted against time. Mutant M3 shows the most                    significant actuation followed by the M3CT mutant, further reinforcing the                    observation that while the N-terminal His-tag contributes towards the actuation,                    the His mutations in the parent GCN4-LZ structure play the critical role. These                    results are consistent with the lack of closed-to-open transition for M1. The WT                    and M2 mutants did not show any transition during the simulation as discussed                    earlier.</p></sec><sec><title>Mutant M3 demonstrates reversible pH-dependent actuation</title><p>One of the key design goals of a nanotweezer is reversibility of mechanochemical                    actuation. We therefore investigated whether the mutant M3 demonstrated a                    reversible open-to-closed transition when the pH reverts back to neutral from                    acidic. The initial structure (the &#x02018;open&#x02019; state) for                    this simulation was taken from the final conformation generated from the                    previous 4-ns closed-to-open simulation at low pH. Histidine, glutamic acid, and                    aspartic acid residues in M3 were unprotonated to simulate neutral pH.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ijn-3-505">Figure 7a</xref> shows snapshots of a 5                    ns-long reversible-motion simulation of M3. Increasing the pH back to neutral                    triggered the reversible transition of the mutant and the final conformation                    generated by this simulation resembles the initial starting structure from the                    closed-to-open simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ijn-3-505">Figure                    5b</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ijn-3-505">Figure 7b</xref> shows the                    dynamics of the reversible motion of M3 over the simulation time. As mentioned                    in the previous section, the &#x02018;open&#x02019; state generated at                    the end of the close-to-open simulation of M3 at low pH was in a state of                    dynamic equilibrium. This means that the peptide was in a                    &#x02018;tensed&#x02019; state wherein the restituting forces due to                    helices elasticity and the hydrophobic attractions near the C-terminal of the                    peptide chains balanced the repulsive electrostatic forces of the ionized                    histidine residues. At neutral pH, the force-generating capability vanished due                    to histidine neutralization, leading to the restitution of the                    &#x02018;relaxed&#x02019; state. The reversible transition of the mutant                    at neutral pH was exactly as hypothesized and verifies the concept of designing                    a nanotweezer element whose actuation can be modulated by pH.</p></sec><sec><title>Physicochemical contributions to the nanotweezer motion in M3</title><p>In order to probe the physicochemical contributions to the actuation mechanism,                    we first examined the closed-to-open actuation behavior of M3 at three different                    pH values: neutral, intermediate, and low. The objective of these simulations                    was to ascertain if the nanotweezer design based on M3 mutant is sensitive to                    smaller changes in pH. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-3-505">Figure 8a</xref>                    shows the plots of opening dynamics of M3 at three pH values. As expected, no                    opening was observed in the mutant at neutral pH due the absence of ionic                    repulsions in the chains as the His residues are not ionized at neutral pH. The                    distance between the two helices at the end of closed-to-open simulation at                    neutral pH is 7 &#x000c5; which is in good agreement with the distance                    observed between the helices at the end of the open-to-closed simulation of M3                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ijn-3-505">Figure 7</xref>). At intermediate                    pH, where the Glu and Asp residues are assumed to be unprotonated and the His                    residues protonated, the transition closely followed the low pH trajectory until                    approximately 2.2 ns, at which point the distance between the two chains was 24                    &#x000c5;. From 2.2&#x02013;3 ns the separation reduced by 4                    &#x000c5; and the two chains finally stabilized at a distance of 20                    &#x000c5; during the last nanosecond. Thus, at intermediate pH the final                    inter-helical opening was 9 &#x000c5;, in contrast to the separation of 16                    &#x000c5; seen at low pH. Each chain of mutant M3 has five glutamic acids                    (Glu254, Glu258, Glu268, Glu270, Glu280) and one aspartic acid (Asp255) residue.                    These residues are negatively charged at intermediate pH and can be expected to                    contribute to the overall ionic repulsion, resulting in increased separation                    between the two chains. However, the opening of M3 at intermediate pH was less                    than that at low pH by 7 &#x000c5;. One explanation for this reduced opening                    lies in the location of the Glu and Asp residues along the protein chain. The                    Asp255 and Glu280 residues are at the <bold><italic>f</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>c</italic></bold> position respectively on the helical wheel diagram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-3-505">Figure 1c</xref>) of the protein. The <bold><italic>f</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>c</italic></bold> positions are at the outer periphery of the protein and thus these                    residues are not expected to participate in any interhelical ionic interactions.                    On the other hand, three salt-pairs (Glu268A&#x02013;Lys263B,                    Lys275A&#x02013;Glu270B, Lys275B&#x02013;Glu270A) contribute to                    interhelical ionic attractions at the intermediate pH thereby significantly                    reducing the total ionic repulsions between the two chains resulting in a                    reduced separation between the chains. These salt-pairs are absent at low pH due                    to the protonation of Glu residues which permits greater opening between the                    helices. This qualitative explanation neglects the fact that the Glu, Asp, and                    His residues are most likely only partially protonated at intermediate pH                    values, and also neglects possible cooperative effects in the acid-base                    equilibria of adjacent residues. Nevertheless, these approximations do not alter                    the overall conclusion that the results at intermediate and low pH support our                    hypothesis that the opening of the nanotweezer can be modulated simply by                    varying the pH of its environment.</p><p>We next compared the variation of solvent accessible surface area (SASA) of                    mutant M3 under neutral and low pH conditions. The SASA is calculated by rolling                    a sphere of solvent (water) molecule with a probe radius of 1.4 &#x000c5;                    over the protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51-ijn-3-505">Shrake and Rupley                        1973</xref>). Changes in the SASA of the residues located in the region                    between residues His243 and His261 were computed as a function of time (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="f13-ijn-3-505">Figure S-4</xref>).                    Under low pH conditions the SASA value increased from 4250                    &#x000c5;<sup>2</sup> to approximately 4700 &#x000c5;<sup>2</sup>                    indicating increasing solvent exposure of buried residues due to pH-induced                    actuation. The residues near the C-terminus remained protected from the solvent                    due to the strong hydrophobic binding between the residues in this region of the                    peptide (&#x02018;hydrophobic core&#x02019;, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="f11-ijn-3-505">Figure S-2</xref>). As                    expected for a pH change from low to neutral, the SASA value decreased due to                    the reduction in solvent exposure during the open-to-close transition of the                    mutant.</p><p>In order to investigate the contributions from individual residues further, we                    identified the flexible region of the peptide that contributes to the opening                    dynamics. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-3-505">Figure 8b</xref> shows the                    plot of the total RMSD for each residue during the close-to-open (low pH) and                    open-to-close (neutral pH) transitions. The region of the peptide lying between                    residues 243 and 260 is significantly flexible and shows a per-residue RMSD                    greater than 3 &#x000c5;. Also, the His261 and His265 residues were not                    involved in electrostatic interactions in the peptide since the charge-carrying                    nitrogen atoms are further than the 13.5 &#x000c5; cut-off set during MD                    simulations for calculating possible electrostatic interactions. Nevertheless,                    these mutations play an important part by reducing the hydrophobic binding and                    increasing the flexibility of the peptide when compared with the parent                    residues. Residues 262&#x02013;279 remained strongly associated with                    significantly low RMSD values due to stabilizing hydrophobic interactions. The                    higher RMSD value for residues 280 and 281 near the C-terminus is explained by                    their random coil structure as a consequence of which these residues undergo                    high thermal fluctuations resulting in increased RMSD values.</p><p>Another interesting feature of the per-residue RMSD plot is the periodicity                    observed in the curve. The periodicity in the RMSD values of the residues                    follows the same trend during both the <italic>opening</italic> and                        <italic>closing</italic> mechanism of the nanotweezer. Further investigation                    revealed that the &#x02018;peaks&#x02019; in the RMSD curve correspond                    to His247, Lys251, Glu254, Glu258, His261, and Glu268 residues occupying the <bold><italic>e</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>b</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>e</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>b</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>e</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>e</italic></bold> positions respectively along the heptad repeat (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-3-505">Figure 1c</xref> for helical wheel diagram showing the                    heptad repeat positions). Given that histidine, lysine, and glutamic acids are                    polar residues and the <bold><italic>e</italic></bold> position in the heptad repeat is involved in electrostatic interactions,                    it may be surmised that the presence of polar residues in this position plays an                    important role in the overall flexibility of the peptide.</p></sec><sec><title>Modulation of DNA-binding activity</title><p>The pH dependent conformational change of the nanotweezer can be employed for                    modulating the DNA-binding affinity of the parent GCN4 transcription activator                    protein. The design principle can also be employed to generate proteins with                    distinct DNA-binding specificities and different physiological targets thereby                    having implications in engineering of novel transcription factors and ligand                    design for DNA purification. To demonstrate the DNA-binding modulation                    capability of the nanotweezer a new peptide was designed in which the                    DNA-binding basic region of the parent GCN4 peptide was grafted at the end of                    the N-terminus of the nanotweezer based on the M3 mutant design (henceforth                    called GCN4mT). The residue sequence of the resulting GCN4mT peptide is shown in                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ijn-3-505">Figure 9a</xref>.</p><p>Two simulations were carried out to study the GCN4mT&#x02013;DNA complex at                    low and neutral pH respectively. It was hypothesized that the conformational                    opening in the GCN4mT and protonation (and hence neutralization) of charges on                    the adenosine nucleotides at low pH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ijn-3-505">Aksimentiev et al 2004</xref>) would result in the reduction of the                    GCN4mT-DNA-binding activity in turn resulting in the release and diffusion of                    DNA molecule away from the GCN4mT-binding site. However, diffusion is an                    extremely slow process governed mostly by random Brownian motions and hence is                    difficult to simulate in typical MD timescales. In order to                    &#x02018;accelerate&#x02019; the diffusion process and therefore, obtain                    quantitative data on the strength of GCN4mT&#x02013;DNA binding, we employed                    the SMD technique. The DNA molecule was pulled out of the GCN4mT-binding site                    using a constant velocity SMD simulation and the force required for this pull                    was computed and plotted. Each simulation was further divided into two runs: In                    the first run a normal 4-ns MD simulation (without applying SMD) was carried out                    on the GCN4mT&#x02013;DNA complex to let the system evolve naturally and                    change conformation. A second 4-ns long MD simulation was then started from the                    end point of the first simulation but this time the C-terminal residues of the                    peptide were held fixed while the DNA atoms were pulled out with a constant                    velocity.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ijn-3-505">Figure 9b</xref>,c shows the simulation                    snapshots of the GCN4mT&#x02013;DNA complex at neutral and low pH values. No                    major conformational changes were observed in the GCN4mT&#x02013;DNA system                    at neutral pH during the first 4 ns of simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ijn-3-505">Figure 9b</xref>). This was expected, firstly because at                    neutral pH there are no electrostatic repulsive forces                    &#x02018;pushing&#x02019; the peptide chains since the histidine                    residues are unionized. Secondly, the DNA bases as well as phosphate backbone is                    negatively charged at neutral pH and hence binds electrostatically with the                    positively charged residues in the DNA-binding region of the peptide. For the                    next 4 ns the C-terminal residues (Arg281) in both peptide chains were held                    fixed and the DNA atoms were pulled with a constant velocity in the direction of                    the vector joining the center-of-mass (COM) of DNA atoms and the COM of the                    fixed Arg281 residues in the peptide chains. This effectively pulls out the DNA                    along the longitudinal axis of the peptide. There was no reduction of the                    DNA-binding capability of the GCN4mT at neutral pH which is evident from the                    4&#x02013;8 ns simulation snapshots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ijn-3-505">Figure 9b</xref>. The strength of the                    GCN4mT&#x02013;DNA binding at neutral pH was such that instead of the DNA                    molecule being released from the GCN4mT-binding pocket, the force applied on the                    DNA atoms was transferred to peptide chains and the &#x003b1;-helices                    started to unfold under its influence.</p><p>At low pH, a significant nanotweezer actuation mechanism was observed in the                    GCN4mT peptide during the initial 4 ns of simulation; the actuation was a result                    of the electrostatic repulsive forces in the M3 coiled-coil portion. The average                    RMSD of the C&#x003b1; atoms was 4.3 &#x000c5; at low pH which is                    significantly higher when compared to 2.2 &#x000c5; RMSD at neutral pH. At                    low pH, the system was initially simulated till the C&#x003b1; RMSD for the                    peptide stabilized at a constant value (4.3 &#x000c5;) signifying that the                    peptide had achieved a stable &#x02018;open&#x02019; state. This                    corresponds to the 3.2 ns mark in the simulation timeline. At this stage the                    C-terminal residues (Arg281) were fixed and the DNA molecule was                    &#x02018;pulled&#x02019; using a constant velocity. As can be seen from                    the simulation snapshots shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ijn-3-505">Figure                        9c</xref>, the DNA molecule was rapidly released from the GCN4mT-binding                    cavity without destabilizing the protein secondary structure. The force required                    to pull the DNA was computed using Eq. 1 and plotted. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ijn-3-505">Figure 9d</xref> shows the plot of this force at both the                    neutral and low pH values. The force required to pull the DNA from the                    GCN4mT-binding cavity is much weaker at low pH then at neutral pH. At low pH a                    40 nN force was being applied to the DNA molecule to overcome the peptide-DNA                    interactions. At the 3.9 ns stage, the DNA molecule started to break free from                    the peptide which resulted in a weaker &#x02018;pulling&#x02019; force                    from this point on. At the 4.4 ns stage, the DNA molecule is completely free                    from the peptide-binding cavity and the only force required is the friction                    force to drag it through the water box which is signified by the flattening of                    the force curve at a low (35 nN) value. At neutral pH, however, due to no                    initial conformational &#x02018;opening&#x02019; in the GCN4mT peptide                    maintain strong peptide-DNA interactions as indicated by a higher value of force                    (58 nN) initially being applied on the DNA,. This applied force increases with                    simulation time due to the additional work is being performed upon unfolding of                    the coiled-coil &#x003b1;-helices.</p><p>Taken together, the SMD simulation results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ijn-3-505">Figure 9b</xref>,c) in conjunction with the force                    profiles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ijn-3-505">Figure 9d</xref>) suggests a                    reduced DNA-binding of the GCN4mT peptide at low pH when compared to neutral pH                    and confirms our hypothesis that DNA-binding activity of the GCN4 peptide can be                    engineered in order to obtain environmentally-responsive mutants as exemplified                    by the pH-activated nanotweezer in this case. Environmentally responsive                    DNA-binding protein systems can lead to practical tools for the studying                    cellular chemistry and controlling transcription process. Several groups have                    reported techniques for controlling DNA-binding ability of basic zipper domains                    and cross-linked peptide constructs with applications in drug delivery either                    independently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b60-ijn-3-505">Walensky et al                    2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22-ijn-3-505">Futaki 2005</xref>) or in                    conjunction with cell-penetrating peptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32-ijn-3-505">Kawamura et al 2006</xref>). Examples of these                    techniques include the reversible photocontrol of designed GCN4-bZIP proteins                    using a azobenzene chromophore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b63-ijn-3-505">Woolley et al 2006</xref>) and the design of a negative vitellogenin                    promoter-binding protein (VBP) leucine zipper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43-ijn-3-505">Moll et al 2000</xref>). In a similar fashion, we                    propose that our nanotweezer construct may also have applications in drug                    delivery; drug-binding domains may be grafted at the N-terminus of the tweezer                    which can be employed for releasing the bound drug by inducing repulsions in the                    helices of the coiled-coil upon pH activation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We have described the design, evolution, and evaluation of a pH-dependent coiled-coil                nanotweezer using molecular dynamics simulations. We designed four mutants based on                the parent coiled-coil GCN4-LZ protein containing histidine tags (five histidines)                and up to five point histidine mutations along the helical chains. One of the                mutants, M3, showed optimal performance characteristics while maintaining its                structural integrity during the entire operation. Upon pH actuation, M3 opened up to                27 &#x000c5;, which is a significant displacement considering the initial                separation between the two chains was only 11 &#x000c5;. Importantly, this                actuation behavior was reversible upon restoration of initial pH conditions. Our                results shed significant light on molecular interactions involved in coiled-coil                stability and the role of molecular interactions in incorporating flexibility in                rigid peptide motifs. Accommodating protein flexibility has implications in                computational drug design wherein one of the goals is to design a receptor that is                flexible enough to accommodate multiple binding modes of the same ligand. The                ability to incorporate flexibility in protein receptor domains can therefore lead to                novel drug design and/or to properly predict the activity of existing inhibitors                    (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-ijn-3-505">Carlson and McCammon 2000</xref>). In                addition to the observation that electrostatic interactions in a protein motif are                sensitive to the location, orientation and neighborhood of electrostatic charges and                that these charges can be modified by modulating the pH, our results highlight the                utility of computational modeling for protein design and stability analysis. Our                preliminary computational results show that engineering of novel transcription                factor is a potential application of the nanotweezer wherein pH-dependent                DNA-binding modulation can be achieved by grafting a DNA-binding domain at the                N-terminus of the peptide chains.</p><p>We have recently experimentally demonstrated the reversible opening and closing of a                truncated version of the M1 peptide by electron spin resonance (Gull&#x000e0;                SV, pers comm. 2008). Briefly, a sequence with a trihistidine tag and the TOAC                    (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57-ijn-3-505">Toniolo et al 1995</xref>) amino acid                spin label immediately N-terminal to the leucine zipper region was synthesized. The                distance between the labels in the dimer measured by double electron-electron                resonance (DEER) spectroscopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19-ijn-3-505">Eaton and                    Eaton 2000</xref>) at low and neutral pH. At pH 7, the spin-spin distance                exhibits a tight distribution around 23 &#x000c5;, identical to the distance                predicted from the crystal structure of GCN4. At pH 4, a broad distribution around                36 &#x000c5; is observed, consistent with the predictions of the MD                calculations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="f10-ijn-3-505"><label>Figure S-1</label><caption><p>MultiCoil score for different molecular tweezer mutants. The coiled-coil                        probability cut-off is 0.5.</p></caption><media xlink:href="ijn-3-505f10.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x1cd8fc0N0x3e29710" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="f11-ijn-3-505"><label>Figure S-2</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>) Time dependence of the root mean squared deviation (RMSD),                        measured with respect to the initial (t = 0) structure of the                        wild-type (WT) peptide, for all backbone atoms at neutral and low pH. The                        value agrees well with the reported range of RMSD values from previously MD                        simulations and also shows that the WT peptide is stable at both low and                        neutral pH; <bold>b</bold>) Location of the binding hydrophobic cores along                        the WT structure.</p></caption><media xlink:href="ijn-3-505f11.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x1cd8fc0N0x3e297d0" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="f12-ijn-3-505"><label>Figure S-3</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>) Helix contacts by residue for wild-type GCN4 after 4-ns                        simulation at low pH; <bold>b</bold>) Helix contacts for mutant M3 after                        4-ns simulation at low pH shows that only residues 243&#x02013;261 in                        both chains moved during the simulation. The C&#x003b1;                        -to-C&#x003b1; distance for each pair is shown as a square colored by                        linear grayscale between 0 and 10.0 &#x000c5;, and white when                        &#x02265; 10.0 &#x000c5;.</p></caption><media xlink:href="ijn-3-505f12.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x1cd8fc0N0x3e29890" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="f13-ijn-3-505"><label>Figure S-4</label><caption><p>Solvent accessible surface area (SASA) as a function of time for residues                        His243 to His261 during the opening and closing mechanism of the                        nanotweezer. Residues which are initially buried become exposed to the                        solvent during the opening mechanism. SASA representation of the                        &#x02018;closed&#x02019; (<italic>Bottom Inset</italic>) state and                        &#x02018;open&#x02019; state (<italic>Top Inset</italic>) for the                        nanotweezer showing the increased surface area.</p></caption><media xlink:href="ijn-3-505f13.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x1cd8fc0N0x3e29950" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank the NASA Institute for Advanced Concepts (NIAC) Phase II grant and                the National Science Foundation (grant DMI-0422724) for the financial support of                this research. The authors thank Prof. Alexei Aksimentiev at University of Illinois                at Urbana-Champaign for providing the parameters of protonated adenosine nucleotide                and Dr Zaki E Megeed and Dr Monica Casali at the Center for Engineering in Medicine                (CEM) for helpful technical discussions.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aksimentiev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heng</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Timp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Microscopic kinetics of DNA translocation through synthetic                        nanopores</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>2086</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15345583</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b2-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aurora</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Rules for alpha-helix termination by glycine</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>264</volume><fpage>1126</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8178170</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b3-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Megeed</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Casali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Engineering protein and peptide building blocks for                        nanotechnology</article-title><source>J Nanosci Nanotechnol</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17450770</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b4-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Cell and molecular mechanics of biological. materials</article-title><source>Nat Mater</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14593396</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b5-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Coiled coil structures and transcription: an analysis of the S.                        cerevisiae coilome</article-title><source>Mol Genet Genomics</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17476531</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b6-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beerli</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbas</surname><given-names>CF</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Engineering polydactyl zinc-finger transcription factors</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11821858</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b7-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bella</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodsky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Crystal and molecular structure of a collagen-like peptide at 1.9                        A resolution</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>266</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7695699</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b8-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biju</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Anas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Semiconductor quantum dots and metal nanoparticles: syntheses,                        optical properties, and biological applications</article-title><source>Anal Bioanal Chem</source><volume>391</volume><fpage>2469</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18548237</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b9-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinhold</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Evolving strategies for enzyme engineering</article-title><source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16006119</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b10-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brannigan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Protein engineering twenty years on</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>964</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12461562</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b11-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Of torques, forces, and protein machines</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>3061</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15498944</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b12-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Accommodating protein flexibility in computational drug design</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10648630</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b13-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Steered molecular dynamics simulations on the &#x0201c;tail                        helix latch&#x0201d; hypothesis in the gelsolin activation process</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12124262</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b14-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Columbus</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbell</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Mapping backbone dynamics in solution with site-directed spin                        labeling: GCN4-58 bZip free and bound to DNA</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>7273</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15182173</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b15-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crick</surname><given-names>FHC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1953</year><article-title>The packing of &#x003b1;-helices: simple coiled-coils</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b16-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daggett</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fersht</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>The present view of the mechanics of protein folding</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12778129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b17-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>York</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Particle mesh Ewald. An Nlog(N) method for Ewald sums in large                        systems</article-title><source>J Chem Phys</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>10089</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b18-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doerr</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelczer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Design of a functional protein for molecular recognition:                        specificity of ligand binding in a metal-assembled protein cavity probed by                        19f NMR</article-title><source>J Am Chem Soc</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>4192</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15053608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b19-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><source>Distance measurements in biological systems by EPR</source><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic/Plenum Pub</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="b20-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandl</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Struhl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>The GCN4 basic region leucine zipper binds DNA as a dimer of                        uninterrupted alpha helices: crystal structure of the protein-DNA complex</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>71</volume><fpage>1223</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1473154</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b21-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frishman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Argos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Knowledge-based protein secondary structure assignment</article-title><source>Proteins</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8749853</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b22-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Futaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Membrane-permeable arginine-rich peptides and the translocation                        mechanisms</article-title><source>Adv Drug Deliv Rev</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15722163</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b23-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Identifying unfolding intermediates of FN-III(10) by steered                        molecular dynamics</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>323</volume><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12417205</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b24-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gooding</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Biosensors for detecting metal ions: New trends</article-title><source>Aus J Chem</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b25-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harbury</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Springs and zippers: coiled coils in SNARE-mediated membrane                        fusion</article-title><source>Structure</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1487</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9862813</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b26-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hendsch</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tidor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Electrostatic interactions in the GCN4 leucine zipper:                        substantial contributions arise from intramolecular interactions enhanced on                        binding</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>1381</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10422826</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b27-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heng</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Aksimentiev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The electromechanics of DNA in a synthetic nanopore</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>1098</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16284270</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b28-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gobin</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowery</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Metal nanoshells</article-title><source>Ann Biomed Eng</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16528617</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b29-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isralewitz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Baudry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gullingsrud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Steered molecular dynamics investigations of protein function</article-title><source>J Mol Graph Model</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11381523</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b30-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Madura</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>Comparison of simple potential functions for simulating liquid                        water</article-title><source>J Chem Phys</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>926</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b31-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Molecular dynamics simulations of biomolecules</article-title><source>Nat Struct Biol</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12198485</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b32-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolewska-Pedyczak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Probing the impact of valency on the routing of arginine-rich                        peptides into eukaryotic cells</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>1116</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16430208</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b33-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Protein destabilization by electrostatic repulsions in the                        two-stranded alpha-helical coiled-coil/ leucine zipper</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7757012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b34-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinotsis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Mechanical strength of the titin Z1Z2-telethonin complex</article-title><source>Structure</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16531234</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b35-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Steered molecular dynamics simulations of force-induced protein                        domain unfolding</article-title><source>Proteins</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10382673</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b36-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Forced dissociation of selectin-ligand complexes using steered                        molecular dynamics simulation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biomech</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16705863</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b37-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacKerell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bashford</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>All-atom empirical potential for molecular modeling and dynamics                        studies of proteins</article-title><source>J Phys Chem</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>3586</fpage><lpage>616</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b38-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martyna</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobias</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Constant pressure molecular dynamics algorithms</article-title><source>J Chem Phys</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>4177</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b39-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Coiled coil domains: stability, specificity, and biological                        implications</article-title><source>Chembiochem</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14760737</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b40-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Missimer</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahnke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Molecular-dynamics simulations of C- and N-terminal peptide                        derivatives of GCN4-p1 in aqueous solution</article-title><source>Chem Biodivers</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>1086</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17193192</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b41-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizoue</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chazin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Engineering and design of ligand-induced conformational change in                        proteins</article-title><source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12163068</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b42-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolinski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skolnick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>De novo simulations of the folding thermodynamics of the GCN4                        leucine zipper</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10388740</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b43-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Olive</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Attractive interhelical electrostatic interactions in the                        proline- and acidic-rich region (PAR) leucine zipper subfamily preclude                        heterodimerization with other basic leucine zipper subfamilies</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>275</volume><fpage>34826</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10942764</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b44-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvinov</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Designed heterodimerizing leucine zippers with a ranger of pIs                        and stabilities up to 10(&#x02212;15) M</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11344333</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b45-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pervushin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>NMR spin state exchange spectroscopy reveals equilibrium of two                        distinct conformations of leucine zipper GCN4 in solution</article-title><volume>129</volume><fpage>6461</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b46-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Shea</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Klemm</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>X-ray structure of the GCN4 leucine zipper, a two-stranded,                        parallel coiled coil</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>254</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1948029</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b47-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Scalable molecular dynamics with NAMD</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>1781</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16222654</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b48-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pineiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vagt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>A molecular dynamics study of the formation, stability, and                        oligomerization state of two designed coiled coils: possibilities and                        limitations</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>3701</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16150975</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b49-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saenger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><source>Principles of Nucleic Acid Structure</source><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="b50-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seungho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sean</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The elasticity of alpha-helices</article-title><source>J Chem Physics</source><volume>122</volume><fpage>244912</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="b51-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shrake</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1973</year><article-title>Environment and exposure to solvent of protein atoms. Lysozyme                        and insulin</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4760134</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b52-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinner</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Elastic energy storage in beta-sheets with application to                        F1-ATPase</article-title><source>Eur Biophys J</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12955360</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b53-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>An isoleucine zipper peptide forms a native-like triple stranded                        coiled coil in solution</article-title><source>Protein Eng</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9876926</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b54-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tama</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Symmetry, form, and shape: guiding principles for robustness in                        macromolecular machines</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biophys Biomol Struct</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16689630</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b55-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tenne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Inorganic nanotubes and fullerene-like nanoparticles</article-title><source>Nat Nano</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b56-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tinoco</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The effect of force on thermodynamics and kinetics of single                        molecule reactions</article-title><source>Biophys Chem</source><volume>101&#x02013;102</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>33</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b57-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toniolo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Formaggio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Synthesis and conformational studies of peptides containing TOAC,                        a spin-labelled C alpha, alpha-disubstituted glycine</article-title><source>J Pept Sci</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9222983</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b58-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Gunsteren</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Berendsen</surname><given-names>HJC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1977</year><article-title>Algorithms for macromolecular dynamics and constraint dynamics</article-title><source>Mol Phys</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>1311</fpage><lpage>27</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b59-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolinski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>CL</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><etal/></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Prediction of the folding pathways and structure of the GCN4                        leucine zipper</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>237</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8151697</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b60-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walensky</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Escher</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Activation of apoptosis in vivo by a hydrocarbon-stapled BH3                        helix</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>305</volume><fpage>1466</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15353804</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b61-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheller</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Membrane fusion. SNARE the rod, coil the complex</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>395</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9759719</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b62-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>MultiCoil: A program for predicting two- and three-stranded                        coiled coils</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9194178</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b63-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolley</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaikaran</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Berezovski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Reversible photocontrol of DNA binding by a designed GCN4-bZIP                        protein</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>6075</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16681380</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b64-ijn-3-505"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Monera</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Investigation of electrostatic interactions in two-stranded                        coiled-coils through residue shuffling</article-title><source>Biophys Chem</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8672718</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="f1-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>) Coiled-coil GCN4 bound to DNA showing the basic and the                        leucine zipper regions; <bold>b</bold>) Enlarged view of the leucine zipper                        region showing the side (<italic>Left</italic>) and top                        (<italic>Right</italic>) views and the corresponding dimensions;                        <bold>c</bold>) Helical wheel diagram of the leucine zipper motif showing                        the positions of the residues and the interactions stabilizing the                        coiled-coil motif. Shaded arrows in the middle indicate hydrophobic                        interactions. Letters indicate residues at each position according to their                        type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijn-3-505f1"/></fig><fig id="f2-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>) Schematic of the operating principle of nanotweezer. Initial                        &#x02018;closed&#x02019; state at neutral pH                        (<italic>Left</italic>). Final &#x02018;open&#x02019; state                        generated at low pH (<italic>Right</italic>). The <italic>plus</italic>                        signs in the &#x02018;open&#x02019; state represent the location of                        engineered histidine residues which becomes positively charged at low pH                        thereby creating electrostatic repulsive forces; <bold>b</bold>) Nanotweezer                        mutants; Wild-Type (WT), Mutants M1, M2, M3, and the M3 control (M3CT). The                        position of glycine tag in WT and M3CT is shown in                        &#x02018;bond&#x02019; representation. Position of His-tags and                        histidine mutations in other mutants is shown in dark shades.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijn-3-505f2"/></fig><fig id="f3-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>System for studying the DNA-binding modulation of the molecular                    nanotweezer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijn-3-505f3"/></fig><fig id="f4-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>) Snapshots of a 4 ns simulation of mutant M2 at various time                        instances. The position of histidine residues are shown in dark shades. The                        &#x003b1;-helical structure in chain B was disrupted during the                        simulation implying that some of the mutations are inherently destabilizing                        for its secondary structure; <bold>b</bold>) Evolution of the secondary                        structure elements of M2 as a function of time. The coloring scheme is                        indicated at the top right. The upper and lower halves corresponds to chain                        A and B respectively while the Y-axis denotes the residue number. The early                        disruption of the &#x003b1;-helical structure in chain B is evident from                        the figure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijn-3-505f4"/></fig><fig id="f5-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>) Structural details of the M3 mutant. The position of                        histidine mutations are shown as spheres. Hydrophobic interactions are shown                        as gray dotted spheres. Note the strong hydrophobic core in the lower half                        of the protein which serves as a &#x02018;hinge&#x02019; for the                        nanotweezer design; <bold>b</bold>) Snapshots of mutant M3 at various time                        instances during a 4 ns simulation. Location of the His246 residue between                        which the opening is measured is shown as a sphere; <bold>c</bold>) Opening                        dynamics of M3 at low pH. The initial separation between the two chains was                        11 &#x000c5; which gradually increased to 27 &#x000c5; at the 2.5 ns                        stage and then stabilized for the rest of the simulation giving a net                        opening of 16 &#x000c5;; <bold>d</bold>) Evolution of the secondary                        structure elements of M3 mutant as a function of time. The structural                        features of the two chains were conserved throughout the simulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijn-3-505f5"/></fig><fig id="f6-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Comparison of opening dynamics for various mutants at low pH. M3 showed the                        maximum opening of 1.6 nm during the simulation time. The control mutant                        M3CT initially followed a similar dynamics but lags the net opening of M3 by                        0.4 nm. The dynamics of wild-type (WT) and mutants M1, M2 are explained                        previously.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijn-3-505f6"/></fig><fig id="f7-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>) Snapshots of a 5 ns simulation of open-to-close transition to                        show the reversible motion of mutant M3. For reversible motion the His, Glu                        and Asp residues were unprotonated to simulate neutral pH. Due to lack of                        ionic repulsions at neutral pH and also due to the attractive hydrophobic                        interactions the actuator chains rapidly reclosed. The final state closely                        resembles the initial NMR structure; <bold>b</bold>) Reversible motion                        dynamics for mutant M3 at neutral pH. The distance between the two chains                        after 5 ns simulation time was 10 &#x000c5; which is in good agreement                        with the separation between the helices in the initial NMR structure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijn-3-505f7"/></fig><fig id="f8-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>) Opening dynamics of M3 at varying pH. The trajectories                        plotted at each pH are the average values for two separate MD runs with                        different initial random seed. The opening at intermediate pH lags that at                        low pH by 5 &#x000c5; thereby suggesting the potential use of the                        nanotweezer as a pH sensor; <bold>b</bold>) Root mean squared deviations                        (RMSD) of individual residues of the M3 mutant during the opening and                        closing mechanism. The plot helps to identify the more flexible region of                        the protein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijn-3-505f8"/></fig><fig id="f9-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>) Residue sequence of the GCN4mT peptide. The basic DNA-binding                        region is grafted at the N-terminus of the mutant M3 design; Snapshots of                        the SMD simulation to study DNA-binding modulation; <bold>b</bold>) at                        neutral pH the DNA molecule is tightly bound to the peptide chains and                        cannot break free when pulled using an external force; <bold>c</bold>) At                        low pH the conformational changes in the GCN4mT peptide reduces the strength                        of DNA-binding and when pulled the DNA molecule is rapidly released from the                        peptide-binding cavity; <bold>d</bold>) Force required pulling the DNA out                        of the GCN4mT-binding cavity. The Left and Bottom axis are for data at low                        pH while the Top and Right axis are for neutral pH data. As hypothesized the                        force required to pull the DNA is considerably smaller at low pH.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijn-3-505f9"/></fig><table-wrap id="t1-ijn-3-505" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Naming convention and residue sequence for nanotweezer mutants. The top row                        shows the haptad repeat sequence of a coiled-coil protein. In the bottom                        rows the residue sequence of individual mutants is arranged in group of                        seven to highlight their consensus with the coiled-coil heptad repeat                        pattern.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant name</th><th colspan="6" align="center" rowspan="1">Sequence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Coiled-coil</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a b c d e f g</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a b c d e f g</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a b c d e f g</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a b c d e f g</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>243</sup><bold>GGGGG</bold>CR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MKQLEDK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VEELLSK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NYHLENE</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VARLKKL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VGER<sup>281</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HHHHH</bold>CR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MKQLEDK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VEELLSK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NYHLENE</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VARLKKL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VGER</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HHHHH</bold>CR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MKQLEDK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VEEL<bold>HH</bold>K</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HH</bold>HLENE</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VARLKKL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VGER</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HHHHH</bold>CR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MKQ<bold>H</bold>ED<bold>H</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VE<bold>H</bold>L<bold>H</bold>SK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<bold>H</bold>HLENE</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VARLKKL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VGER</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M3CT</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GGGGG</bold>CR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MKQ<bold>H</bold>ED<bold>H</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VE<bold>H</bold>L<bold>H</bold>SK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<bold>H</bold>HLENE</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VARLKKL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VGER</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-wrap></article>