<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417823</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636124</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_3_221_40361</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417823 </article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Symposium</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>First aid for complications of infectious keratitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>Vinaykumar</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Clear Vision Eye Center, Santacruz (W), Mumbai - 400 054, Maharashtra, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Vinaykumar Agrawal, Clear Vision Eye Center, 1A,Ashoka, 15, S.V.Road, Santacruz (W), Mumbai - 400 054, Maharashtra,India. Email: <email>drvinay.agrawal@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Infectious keratitis is a fairly common entity in India. However while paying attention to the primary entity,the associated events may be overlooked. Enhanced pain usually suggests a worsening of the condition ordevelopment of associated problems like secondary glaucoma. However, contrary to logic, a sudden decreasein pain is also liley to suggest a worsening, e.g. perforation of the corneal ulcer. Various such problems withtheir management are outlined.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Complications</kwd><kwd>emergency</kwd><kwd>infectious keratitis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>A patient with corneal ulcer will usually be monitored for hisprimary condition. However, there are certain signs that theclinician should be aware and watch out for. These are findingsthat would usually denote a change in the status, usually forthe worse. The problems that we frequently encounter are:</p><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Pain - sudden increase and decrease</p></list-item><list-item><p>Corneal thinning/melting</p></list-item><list-item><p>Severe anterior chamber reaction</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sudden increase in the ocular surface reaction despite medications</p></list-item></list></p><sec sec-type=""><title>Pain</title><p>This is a normal protective mechanism associated with anylesion anywhere in the body. The corneal ulcer is no exception.Usually the patients complain of a localized pain in the oculararea of the affected cornea. This is due to the ciliary spasmsecondary to the corneal neuronal reflex arc. Ciliary spasmcan be effectively relieved by use of cycloplegics such ashomatropine eye drops. In addition, the pain is usually wellcontrolled once the topical medication brings the cornealinfiltrates under control.</p><sec><title>Secondary glaucoma</title><p>However, if a patient complains of a sudden or severe increasein pain, one needs to consider secondary glaucoma. This isusually due to the secondary changes in the anterior chamber.They include hypopyon and exudates on the endothelialsurfaces causing a block of the trabecular meshwork orsecondary trabeculitis in some cases of viral keratitis.</p><p>Secondary glaucoma needs aggressive medical managementin the form of topical beta blockers and carbonic anhydraseinhibitors (dorzolamide) with or without systemic carbonicanhydrase inhibitors (acetazolamide). We prefer systemiccarbonic anhydrase inhibitors due to the potential toxicity oftopical inhibitors to the damaged corneal endothelium.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></p></sec><sec><title>Perforation</title><p>Sudden reduction of pain in a patient with an activeuncontrolled keratitis should be looked upon with suspicionrather than relief. Many a times due to the extensive exudationand/or accumulation of the medications (especially antifungal),the underlying wound is hidden. This can lead to a false senseof security and the underlying thinning may be missed. Amicro-perforation in the area of the corneal ulcer can lead tonatural drainage of the aqueous and relieve the intraocularpressure. This will relieve the pain induced by the secondaryglaucoma. However, the collapse of the anterior chamberwill lead to the formation of an adherent leukoma as well asclosure of the angle of the anterior chamber. This will leadto irreversible secondary angle closure glaucoma with poorchances of visual rehabilitation. Perforations larger than 2 mmalso have a significant risk of choroidal detachment.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Corneal Thinning</title><p>The most common effect of a microbial infection of the corneais the necrotic changes of the stromal fibers. This is due to thevarious actions of the microbe. It can be the direct action of themicrobe in breakdown of the stromal fibers. It can be indirectaction due to the endotoxins released due to the destruction ofthe microbial cell wall by the antibiotics or the body defensemechanisms. It can also be due to autolysis induced by varioushuman enzymes like matrix metalloproteinase&#x02032;s (MMPs) thatare released due to an uncontrolled activation of the tissuedestruction mechanisms.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>The end result of all these mechanisms is the necrosis of thetissue in the infected area. If this is seen only due to the directaction of the microbes, then the control of the infection willlimit the thinning. Thus, a regular watch on the corneal ulcer(we usually recommend a follow-up visit at least 48 h apart inulcers &#x0003c; 3 mm and every 24 h in larger ulcers) is necessary toprevent such mishaps (V Agrawal, unpublished data).</p><p>In infections due to Gram-negative bacteria such as<italic>pseudomonas</italic>, the risk of rapid corneal melt is unusually high.These patients need to be seen as frequently as twice a day tillthe ulcer begins to heal.</p><p>The reason to watch for a corneal melt is that an early meltmay respond to treatment and advanced melt is unlikely torespond well (V Agrawal, unpublished data).</p><p>In case of early melt, use of topical and systemic tetracyclineis believed to help.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> In addition, the use of tissueglue and bandage contact lens can also be useful. If the perforation islarger than 2 mm, then the use of tissue glue is unlikely tobe adequate. We have successfully used preserved amnioticmembrane as a multilayered application with tissue glue atthe wound edges to close such wounds. This is a modificationof the method of Hick <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Amniotic membrane also hasanti-collagenolytic properties and may help in stabilizing theocular surface.</p><p>Perforations larger than 4 mm and up to 6 mm may need acorneal patch graft to close the fistula. The important point inthese cases is to avoid undersizing the graft. The wound edgesof a melting area are also likely to be weak. This can lead tocheese wiring of the sutures and wound leaks.</p><p>Total corneal melts have been managed with sclerokeratoplasty withguarded results.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></p><p>In summary, corneal melts are best avoided by rigorousobservation and aggressive medical management.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Severe Anterior Chamber Reaction</title><p>In severe fungal infection, the descemet&#x02032;s membrane can failto limit the infection to the corneal stroma. Alternatively, thesevere anterior chamber reaction secondary to the toxic effectsof the microbe can lead to a complete organized hypopyonformation in the anterior chamber. The use of cycloplegics hasbeen advocated but in our experience it may not be adequate.In such cases, we have used the concept of anterior chamberlavage to debulk the chamber and also reduce the infectiousload to help the medications act better. Along with the lavagewith Ringer&#x02032;s lactate, there may be a need to remove theorganized fibrinoid material from the chamber. The use of asuitable antibiotic or antifungal agent in the lavage fluid isacceptable.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Ocular Surface Condition</title><p>Many a times one sees that the corneal ulcer is respondingto the medications for first 24-48 h. After this period, theeye becomes significantly redder, there is lid edema and theconjunctival surface too starts to stain with fluorescein. Thismay be a sign of spreading infection. However, it is more likelyto either be an allergic reaction to one of the medications beingused or the occurrence due to keratitis medicamentosa. Thisis differentiated from spreading infection by the fact that theprimary lesion size remains constant or shows improvementdespite all the adnexal changes.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Source of Support: Nil</p></fn><fn><p>Conflict of Interest: None declared</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konowal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdier</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Irreversible corneal decompensation in patients treated with topical dorzolamide</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>1999</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10218692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Umapathy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abedin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eatamadi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maharajan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dua</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Choroidal detachment in perforated corneal ulcers</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1111</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16723362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelmus</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of matrix metalloproteinases 2 and 9 in experimental corneal injury and fungal keratitis</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17525657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McChellan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Burrett</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lighwani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Riechiert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Matrix mettaloproteinase 9 amplifies the immune response to pseudomonas aeruginosa corneal infection</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16384971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Doxycycline: A role in ocular surface repair</article-title><source>Br J Ophthlamol</source><year>2004</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McEvanney</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Doxycycline in the management of pseudomonas corneal melting: Two cases and review of literature</article-title><source>Eye Contact Lens</source><year>2003</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Demers</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunette</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>La</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mabon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Duchesne</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amniotic membrane transplantation and fibrin glue in the management of corneal ulcers and perforations: A review of 33cases</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rant</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tectonic sclerokeratoplasty and tectonic penetrating keratoplasty as treatment for perforated or predescemetal cornealulcers</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2001</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name><name><surname>IM</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic effect of intracameral amphotericin B in the treatment of fungal keratitis</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>814</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17667615</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>