<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18580001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636172</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_4_338_41423</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intracanalicular antibiotics may obviatethe need for surgical management ofchronic suppurative canaliculitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>E Ravindra</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FRCS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kabra</surname><given-names>Sachin</given-names></name><degrees>DNB</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Udhay</surname><given-names>Priti</given-names></name><degrees>MS, FRCS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>H N</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Medical and Vision Research Foundation, Chennai, Tamil Nadu,India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. E Ravindra Mohan, Oculoplasty and OrbitService, Sankara Nethralaya, 18, College Road, Chennai - 600 006,Tamil Nadu, India. Email: <email>drerm@snmail.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Aug</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>3</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Chronic suppurative lacrimal canaliculitis is an important causeof ocular surface discomfort. Treatment with topical antibioticsis often inadequate and surgical treatment by canaliculotomyand canalicular curettage has been the mainstay of treatmentin the past. The role of canalicular antibiotic irrigation hasbeen inadequately studied. We report the clinical features,microbiological profile and treatment outcome in a series of12 patients with suppurative lacrimal canaliculitis. Two patientshad <italic>Actinomyces</italic> infection, five had <italic>Nocardia</italic> infection andseven patients had polymicrobial infection. Three patients hadresolution of canaliculitis on combination broad-spectrum topicalantibiotic therapy using ciprofloxacin and fortified cefazolin.In nine patients, topical antibiotic therapy was combined withcanalicular irrigation using fortified cefazolin. All patients hadexcellent resolution of canaliculitis without the need for surgicaltreatment. Availability of broad-spectrum antibiotics andcanalicular irrigation may offer an alternative to surgery in themanagement of suppurative lacrimal canaliculitis.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Canaliculitis</kwd><kwd>microbiological analysis</kwd><kwd>treatment</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Canaliculitis, inflammation of the lacrimal canaliculi, resultsfrom suppurative infection or non-suppurative causes includinga variety of viral infections,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> inflammatoryconditions, following use of topical medications<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> and following injuries.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> Suppurative canaliculitis is an important cause of recurrentconjunctivitis, epiphora and ocular surface discomfort.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> However, since it is uncommon, it may go unrecognized<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> and is often misdiagnosed as chronic conjunctivitis or chalazion.<italic>Actinomyces</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> (called &#x02033;streptothrix&#x02033; in early literature) and<italic>Nocardia</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> are regarded as common organisms responsible forsuppurative canaliculitis.</p><p>Conservative therapy is reported to be ineffective.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>Intracanalicular antibiotic irrigation has been reported,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> buthas not been studied for its effectiveness. Previous studies havedocumented the effectiveness of canalicular curettage and/orcanaliculotomy in the management of chronic canaliculitis,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>but these modalities have the potential to cause damage andscarring of the lacrimal drainage system. The role of topicalantibiotics and canalicular irrigation with antibiotic solutionhas not been evaluated in detail.</p><p>We evaluated the clinical features, causative microorganisms,treatment and outcome of chronic suppurative lacrimalcanaliculitis.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>This study was a retrospective analysis of all patients oflacrimal canaliculitis managed at Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai;during the period of January 1988 to May 2002. Only thosepatients with microbiologically proven chronic canaliculitisof more than three months duration and a minimum of threeweeks post-treatment follow-up were included in this study.Expressed material from the canaliculus was collected withthe help of cotton-tipped applicator in all the patients underaseptic precautions after instilling one drop of sterile 0.5%proparacaine hydrochloride (Paracaine 0.5%, Sunways) or4% lignocaine hydrochloride (lidocaine, Xylocaine 4%,AstraIDL) eye drop as a local anesthetic agent. The specimen wassubjected to microbiological analysis and antibiotic sensitivitystudy. All patients were treated with canalicular expression ofpus and topical antibiotic drops (fortified cefazolin 50 mg/ml +ciprofloxacin 0.3%) eight to ten times a day either alone or incombination with canalicular irrigation with two milliliters offortified cefazolin solution (50 mg/ml).The line of treatment wasdecided by the clinical judgment of severity of the condition.The irrigation was repeated after 48 h if clinical improvementwas not evident.</p><p>Fortified cefazolin solution (50 mg/ml) was prepared byinjecting 10 ml of water for injection into the commerciallyavailable vial of cefazolin, containing 500 mg of the drugin powder form. The clinical outcome of various treatmentmodalities was analyzed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Patient details are summarized in the <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. All the patientshad unilateral single canaliculus involvement. Lower canaliculus(eight out of 12) was more commonly involved than the uppercanaliculus (four out of 12). Epiphora, discharge, irritation andrecurrent or chronic conjunctivitis were the common symptoms.All patients had symptoms for more than three months duration(range: 3 to 24 months, mean:13.25 months). All patients had apouting punctum and erythema as well as thickening of medialeyelid [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>]. Eight patients had punctal regurgitation, whichcould be induced by pressure over the involved canaliculus[<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>]. Syringing was done in all patients through the involvedcanaliculus and was patent in all of them.</p><p><italic>In vitro</italic> resistance to ciprofloxacin was detected in twopatients (Patient nos. 3 and 5). However, resistance to cefazolinwas not detected in any of the patients.</p><p>Canalicular expression of pus and topical antibiotic dropsalone was the initial treatment in five patients (Patient nos. 4,7, 9, 10, 11) while canalicular expression, topical antibioticdrops and antibiotic irrigation was performed in the remainingseven patients.</p><p>Of the five patients treated with topical antibiotics alone,good clinical improvement was seen in three patients while intwo patients (Patient nos. 4 and 9), the condition was persistentat the end of three weeks. Canalicular irrigation with fortifiedcefazolin was performed subsequently in these two patientswith good response.</p><p>All patients who initially received canalicular antibioticirrigation in addition to topical antibiotics showed goodresponse to treatment. The average number of irrigationsrequired per patient was 4.5 (range 1-8).</p><p>All patients were symptom-free with complete resolutionand none needed canalicular curettage or canaliculotomy.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Canaliculitis should be suspected in any patient withunexplained epiphora, recurrent conjunctivitis, eyelid swellingand pain. Pouting punctum, peripunctal erythema, thickeningof medial eyelid and punctal regurgitation are the importantsigns of canaliculitis. Usually, it is localized to a single punctum,as in all the cases in our series.</p><p>In our study, polymicrobial infection was common incontrast to earlier studies, where <italic>Actinomyces</italic> or <italic>Nocardia</italic> wasfound to be the commonest organism.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> Since all theorganisms isolated were sensitive to either cefazolin or ciprofloxacin orboth, our patients were treated with canalicular expression andtopical antibiotic (ciprofloxacin 0.3% and fortified cefazolin50 mg/ml) with or without canalicular irrigation with fortifiedcefazolin solution.</p><p>Two of our patients did not respond to topical antibioticalone. Polymicrobial infection including <italic>Nocardia</italic> was detectedin both of them. These patients were subsequently treatedsuccessfully with antibiotic irrigation. Increased bioavailabilityof the drug at the site of infection may have been responsiblefor the excellent therapeutic response in this &#x02033;cross-over&#x02033;group. None of the patients treated with canalicular irrigationwith antibiotic solution had any recurrence or persistence ofthe disease.</p><p>In our series, canalicular expression followed by topicalantibiotic drops and canalicular irrigation with antibioticsolution according to the sensitivity pattern of the microorganismwas found to be effective in all cases. Based on our study, werecommend use of fortified cefazolin, both in the form oftopical eye drops and for syringing the affected canaliculusalong with topical ciprofloxacin eye drops. This treatment hasthe advantage of eliminating the risk of iatrogenic canalicularscarring with preservation of lacrimal pump function. In thepresent age, due to availability of potent, bactericidal, broad-spectrum antibiotics like ciprofloxacin and cefazolin, invasiveprocedures like canalicular curettage and canaliculotomymay not be required. However, we feel a prospective studycomparing these modalities of treatment will be needed toreassess the role of canalicular curettage and canaliculotomyin the management of suppurative lacrimal canaliculitis.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyndiuk</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Taugher</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herpetic canalicularobstruction</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>1981</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7469865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanke</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Welham</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lacrimal canalicular obstruction followingchickenpox</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>1982</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7055547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Olver</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scalloping canaliculitis after5-fluorouracil breast cancer chemotherapy</article-title><source>Eye</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9775228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rumelt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Remulla</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicone punctal plug migrationresulting in dacryocystitis and canaliculitis</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9143816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vecsei</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber-Spitzy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Arocker-Mettinger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinkogler</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canaliculitis: Difficulties in diagnosis, differential diagnosisand comparison between conservative and surgical treatment</article-title><source>Ophthalmologica</source><year>1994</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7845646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>SmartPlug Study Group</collab><article-title>Management of complications afterinsertion of SmartPlug punctual plug: A study of 28 patients</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2006</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>1859</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16920195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavilack</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Frueh</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thorough curettage in the treatment ofchronic canaliculitis</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>1992</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1736867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actinomycotic lacrimal canaliculitis</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>1973</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4684262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penikett</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nocardia asteroides infection of the nasallacrimal system</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>1962</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1006</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14038260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canalicular diseases</article-title><source>The lacrimal system</source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott-Raven Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>47</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Slit-lamp photograph showing thickening of medial eyelid</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-338-g002"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Slit-lamp photograph showing punctal regurgitation, inducedby pressure over the involved canaliculus</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-338-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient profile, microbiological analysis and treatment of patients with suppurative lacrimal canaliculitis</p></caption><alt-text>Table 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-338-g001"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>