<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417840</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636113</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_3_259_40380</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter to the Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intravitreal bevacizumab (Avastin) for the treatment of proliferative sickle retinopathy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>Saad</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Central Florida Retina Consultants, University of Central Florida, School of Medicine, Orlando, Florida, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Saad Shaikh, 44 Lake Beauty Drive Suite 300,Orlando, Florida 32806, USA. Email: <email>sshaikhmd@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>Dear Editor,</p><p>A 32-year-old African-American female with type SC sicklecell disease presented with vitreous hemorrhage in her righteye of 2 weeks&#x02032; duration. Her visual acuity was 20/25 in theright eye and 20/20 in the left eye. An active area of sea fanneovascularization was noted in the superotemporal peripheryof the right eye. Vitreous hemorrhage emanating from thelesion precluded adequate visualization of the retinal peripheryand administration of laser therapy. Over the following week,the patient&#x02032;s vision decreased to 20/40. She was offered aconservative course of observation until sufficient clarity couldbe obtained for laser therapy, but she had become severelyanxious over perceived loss of vision and had requiredpsychiatric counseling.</p><p>After a discussion of the potential risks and benefits ofoff-label bevacizumab (Avastin) use, the patient signed acomprehensive consent form and underwent pars planainjection of 1.25 mg of bevacizumab. Two weeks later, her visualacuity had returned to 20/25 and the vitreous hemorrhagehad near-completely cleared with incipient fibrosis of theneovascular lesion. A month later, her vision was 20/20 andexamination demonstrated complete resolution of vitreoushemorrhage with fibrous involution of the neovascularcomplex. Angiography demonstrated diffuse peripheralcapillary ischemia but no areas of active neovascularization.Laser photocoagulation was not performed. She remainedwithout recurrent hemorrhage or neovascularization at lastfollow-up 6 months postinjection.</p><p>The use of anti-vascular endothelial growth factor (anti-VEGF) therapy significantly altered the acute history ofproliferative sickle retinopathy in our patient. We mighthave anticipated the progression of neovascularization or atleast the persistence of vitreous hemorrhage without surgicalintervention in the form of laser therapy or vitrectomy. Ourexperience here, and a similar case reported previously,demonstrate that intravitreal bevacizumab can induce rapidregression of neovascularization and resolution of vitreoushemorrhage secondary to proliferative sickle retinopathy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>Although we are unable to state whether anti-VEGF therapychanges the long-term history and prognosis of the disease andincidence of future complications, intravitreal bevacizumabinjection may have a role in the primary and/or adjunct therapyof neovascular complications of sickle cell retinopathy. Furtherstudy on the role of anti-VEGF therapy in proliferative sickleretinopathy is warranted.</p></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>IU</given-names></name><name><surname>Cintra</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravitrealbevacizumab (Avastin) injection associated with regression ofretinal neovascularization caused by sickle cell retinopathy</article-title><source>Acta Ophthalmol Scand</source><year>2006</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17083555</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>