<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636120</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_3_223_40362</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417824 </article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ophthalmology Practice</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Practical approach to medical management of glaucoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>Rajul S</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>Shefali R</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Navin</surname><given-names>Shoba</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arun</surname><given-names>Ellen</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Ravi</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>LV Prasad Eye Institute (RSP,RT), Hyderabad, Andhra Pradesh;Sadhuram Eye Hospital (SRP), Hyderabad, Andhra Pradesh;Silome Eye Hospital (SN), LV Prasad Eye Institute, Madanpally,Andhra Pradesh, India; Prime Medical Center (EA), Dubai</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Rajul Parikh, Bombay City Eye Institute &#x00026;Research Center, 5 Babulnath Road, Mumbai, Maharashtra, India. Email: <email>drparikhs@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Primary open angle glaucoma (POAG) is usually a chronic, slowly progressive disease. At present, allresources are directed towards reduction of intraocular pressure (IOP), the only known causal and treatablerisk factor for glaucoma, and medical management is frequently the first choice in most cases. With theintroduction of innovative tools for early diagnosis and newer medications for treatment, decision-making indiagnosis and treatment of glaucoma has become more complex. The philosophy of glaucoma managementis to preserve the visual function and quality of life (QOL) of the individual with minimum effects on QOLin terms of cost, side effects, treatment regime, follow-up schedules as well as socioeconomic burden. Ouraim should be not to treat just the IOP, optic disc or visual field, but to treat the patient as a whole so as toprovide maximum benefit with minimal side effects. In this article, we describe the scientific approach tomedical management, mainly of POAG.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Medical management</kwd><kwd>primary open angle glaucoma</kwd><kwd>target intraocular pressure</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Glaucoma is one of the major causes of visual loss worldwide.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> With the introduction of innovative tools for early diagnosisand newer medications for treatment, decision-making indiagnosis and treatment of glaucoma has become morecomplex; in this article, we describe our approach to medicalmanagement. The approach we describe has evolved overthe two decades of caring for glaucoma patients and withavailable evidence in the literature. We will focus mainly onthe management of primary open angle glaucoma (POGG).As far as primary angle closure disease is concerned, oncethe iridotomy is performed (and the angle opened), medicalmanagement is similar to that of POAG. Differences will bediscussed where relevant.</p><p>At the very outset, we will state our management philosophy.The philosophy of glaucoma management is to preserve thevisual function and quality of life (QOL) of the individual.Essentially, (functional) vision should outlast the patient. Ouraim is not to treat just the intraocular pressure (IOP), opticdisc or visual field, but to treat the patient as a whole so as toprovide maximum benefit with minimal side effects.</p><p>Some of the terms used in this article are defined below:</p><p><bold>POAG:</bold> It is a chronic optic neuropathy with characteristicchanges in the optic disc and corresponding typical defects inthe visual field for which IOP is the only treatable risk factor.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>POAG is a diagnosis of exclusion.</p><p><bold>Normal tension glaucoma (NTG):</bold> The definition is sameas POAG except that the central corneal thickness (CCT)corrected IOP is less than 22 mmHg (mean + 2SD) on diurnalvariation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Like POAG, it is a diagnosis of exclusion; most casesare managed like POAG.</p><p><bold>Pre-perimetric glaucoma:</bold> It is the presence of characteristicoptic disc and nerve fiber layer changes strongly suggestive ofglaucoma but without field defects on conventional automatedperimetry (white on white).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></p><p><bold>Ocular hypertension (OHT):</bold> It is defined as the CCTcorrected IOP above the 97.5 percentile in that population, withopen angles on gonioscopy and no disc or field changes.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></p><p><bold>Target IOP:</bold> Target IOP is the IOP at which the sum of thehealth-related quality of life (HRQOL) from preserved visionand the HRQOL from not having side effects from treatmentis maximized. It can also be defined in other ways includingthe highest IOP in a given eye at which no clinically apparentnerve damage occurs.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></p><p>The basic principles that we follow in the management ofa glaucoma patient are discussed below.</p><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Establish a diagnosis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Establish a baseline IOP</p></list-item><list-item><p>Set a target IOP</p></list-item><list-item><p>Initiate therapy and to lower IOP to target</p></list-item><list-item><p>Follow-up</p></list-item></list></p><sec sec-type=""><title>Establish A Diagnosis</title><p>Glaucoma is suspected (or diagnosed) after a comprehensiveeye examination (CEE). There is no substitute or surrogatefor a CEE. It includes slit lamp biomicroscopy, Goldmannapplanation tonometry, gonioscopy (preferably dynamic,using an indentation lens), indirect ophthalmoscopy andstereoscopic examination of the optic disc and retinal nervefiber layer (RNFL). Those suspected to have POAG need furtherinvestigations, the minimum being automated perimetry (24-2or 30-2 program) for the detection of functional defects. Thediagnosis of POAG is made using a combination of IOP, discand field changes <italic>in the presence of an open angle</italic>.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> shows the flowchart for a work-up of a suspectedglaucoma patient in our clinic.</p><p><bold>Applanation tonometry:</bold> On its own, applanation tonometryhas a poor sensitivity and specificity for the diagnosis ofglaucoma.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> Repeat IOP and diurnal measurements have morevalue. IOP in combination with other signs can help in diagnosis.The Schiotz tonometer is considered outdated and has at best avery limited role to play in modern glaucoma management.</p><p><bold>Gonioscopy:</bold> The diagnosis of POAG is one of exclusionmade after gonioscopy using indentation lenses, understandard testing conditions.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> Gonioscopy helps to rule outangle closure and secondary causes of glaucoma. Gonioscopyis a dynamic procedure and may need to be repeated at regularintervals.</p><p><bold>Automated perimetry:</bold> Automated white-on-whiteperimetry (WWP) is the gold standard for the diagnosis offunctional defects in glaucoma.</p><p><bold>Optic disc and RNFL examination with stereo biomicroscopy:</bold>Clinically, RNFL loss and optic disc changes are best appreciatedusing stereo-biomicroscopy with a 60-90 D indirect lens; red freeillumination is needed for examination of the RNFL. If the discis suspicious, a contact lens examination may reveal additionalinformation. Stereo photographs of the optic disc are the currentgold standard but have some disadvantages. Optic disc drawingsand or descriptions are less acceptable but provide valuableinformation to an experienced examiner.</p><p><bold>Imaging techniques:</bold> The Association of InternationalGlaucoma Societies (AIGS) consensus meeting does notsupport the routine use of newer optic disc imaging techniquesuch as Heidelberg retinal tomography (HRT), scanning laserpolarimetry (GDx VCC), optical coherence tomography (OCT)for all patients but suggests a role for them in decision-makingwhen used by experts for selected cases.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> We use the sensitivity,specificity and likelihood ratios of test parameters on theseimaging techniques to calculate the probability of glaucomain an individual patient.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></p><p>It is important to remember that temporal progression offindings compared to the baseline values (increase in baselineIOP, disc changes, field and imaging parameters), even if theyremain within the normal range, can be suggestive of an earlydisease.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Establish A Good Baseline IOP</title><p>IOP is the only known causal and treatable risk factor.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> A one-time IOP recording is likely to be misleading and is a poorindicator for diagnosis and treatment. Knowledge of diurnalvariation of IOP in an individual provides information about thepeak IOP as well as fluctuation. It helps to set the target IOP anddecide on the group of drugs to be used to initiate treatment.</p><p>Ideally, we would like a formal diurnal curve on all patients.In routine clinical practice, we measure several IOP recordingsat different times of the day. Any &#x02033;high&#x02033; reading is confirmedby repeat IOP measurement. If not possible on 1 day, anestimate is obtained by measuring IOP at different times duringoffice visits. If treatment is initiated or changed, the processis repeated. For patients who present with high IOP (30 ormore), we confirm the IOP and initiate medical managementwithout multiple IOP readings. In such patients, we obtain themultiple IOPs on treatment. While a 24-h diurnal IOP for allpatients (IOP readings taken every three-hourly over a periodof 24 h referred to as diurnal variation test (DVT)) is desired,we usually obtain such a 24-h DVT at least once in all suspectedNTG patients (CCT corrected) who might otherwise undergounnecessary systemic investigations and in those who areprogressing despite &#x02033;well controlled&#x02033; office hours IOP.</p><p>Goldmann applanation tonometer records false high IOPin thick corneas (except in corneal edema) and falsely lowIOPs in thin corneas. If not in all cases, CCT should at least bemeasured in those with suspected OHT and NTG. While noformula for correction of CCT is universally accepted, we useEhlers correction.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Set A Target IOP</title><p>The Early-Manifest Glaucoma Treatment Study showed thatIOP reduction by at least 25% reduced progression from 62 to45% in the treated group compared to an untreated group.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>The Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study (CIGTS)lowered the IOP by 35%, demonstrated equivalence of medicaland surgical treatment, and decreased disease progression toless than 15%.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></p><p>IOP lowering needs to be individualized with the goalof preventing any decrease in the QOL during the patient&#x02032;slifetime. That in essence is the target IOP. There is, however, nohard evidence for the concept or the methods used to determinethe target. The following factors should be considered at thetime of presentation to customize the target IOP:<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></p><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Structural damage: optic disc and RNFL</p></list-item><list-item><p>Functional damage on WWP</p></list-item><list-item><p>Baseline IOP at which the damage occurred (correlate theabove two with baseline IOP).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Age</p></list-item><list-item><p>Presence of additional risk factors</p></list-item></list></p><p>Target IOP has to be individualized based on patient&#x02032;sclinical profile. This can be calculated using tables, graphs orformulae. The formula used by CIGTS is shown below. This issimilar to that published by Jample <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></p><p>Formula for target IOP =</p><p><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-223-i001.jpg" position="float"/></p><p>While we can formally calculate the target IOP in thismanner or using graphs or tables, the rule of thumb is toreduce the IOP by at least 20% in mild, 30% in moderate andmore than 40% in severe glaucoma. Generally, the formulaeand other methods will provide similar values.</p><p>The higher the IOP, the larger the reduction required. If apatient has a starting IOP of 40 mmHg, we would opt for alarger percentage reduction. A 20% reduction from 40 mmHgwould bring the IOP into the 30s; which is not good enougheven for pre-perimetric glaucoma. In an advanced glaucoma(evident by structural and functional damage), in a young ormiddle-aged patient, one may choose to reduce IOP by 50%from the baseline. However, for the same clinical findings ina very old patient, the target may be set to a higher level so asto minimally hamper the QOL for that individual.</p><p>There are limitations to the target IOP approach. There is nosure-fire method of estimating it and no hard evidence that itworks. Also, we do not know what aspect of the IOP actuallycauses the damage (peak IOP, fluctuations, short spikes, etc).Currently, we monitor the patient using visual fields; we needa more sensitive outcome measure to monitor the patient toreset the target if necessary. At the moment, however, it is agood concept to manage the patient.</p><p>A word of caution, there is a real danger of using the targetIOP approach. Despite popular belief that &#x02033;lower is better&#x02033;,not every patient requires the IOP to be lowered to a mean of12 mmHg. Also, the target IOP is just a guideline, not a numberto be strictly adhered to; it is better to use a range rather thana single number. Using a range of IOP provides safety fromunnecessary aggressive therapy.</p><p>The target IOP is not a fixed magic number. Neither is it astatic number, but changes depending on the results on long-term monitoring. If a patient is progressing on the target IOP wehave set, we may need to lower it further. If a patient is stableon our target IOP, it may well be that it could be readjustedhigher; we may try to withdraw some treatment.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Initiate Therapy and Attempt to Lower IOPto Target</title><p>The goal of medical treatment is to obtain &#x02033;24-h&#x02033; IOP controlwith the minimum concentration and number of medications,as well as minimal local and systemic side effects. We routinelyexplain and demonstrate instillation of drops and encourageour patients to perform eyelid closure and punctum occlusionafter instilling every antiglaucoma medication.</p><p>The selection of initial drug depends on the target IOP.The factors to keep in mind while prescribing a drug include:efficacy, compliance, safety, persistence and last, but not theleast, affordability. If the drug is cost-effective and dosage isconvenient, compliance should improve. Introduction of fixedcombination drugs has helped improve compliance and cutdown the costs.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> shows the list of available antiglaucoma medicationswith their mechanism of action and side effects.</p><p>Once initiated, glaucoma therapy is usually lifelong. Thisinvolves considerable expense and inconvenience. Accordinglybefore initiating therapy, we must be sure of the diagnosis andreasonably sure that the medication works. To establish theefficacy of a drug, we perform a unilateral drug trial. Such a drugtrial determines the efficacy of a single or combined therapy inone eye so as to decide if the drug works. The efficacy of thecomponents of a combination must be tested separately.</p><p>We usually start the therapy in worse eye (usually withhigher IOP/more structural and functional damage) first. Afterthe peak IOP reduction ability of that drug is reached, weagain repeat day DVT (IOP reading at every 2&#x000bd; h from 8 AMto 6 PM) to look for reduction in IOP and fluctuation. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>shows the time to peak effect of common antiglaucoma drugs.If the drug achieves our target IOP, it is continued and startedin the second eye. If drug fails to reduce IOP by at least 15%IOP from baseline or produces severe side effects, we do notprescribe that drug; and go on to a unilateral drug trial withour second option. However, if the first drug does reduce IOPmore than 15% from baseline but not to our target IOP level,we have at least established that the medication works. We nowhave a choice of adding a second medication or changing to anew medication. Usually, we will try to keep the tested drug asa reserve medicine to be used in combination if other optionsalso do not provide adequate IOP control.</p><p>In an ideal world (not considering cost), we would like touse a prostaglandin analogue in most glaucoma patients as afirst line. Cost is, however, a consideration and if our target IOPis around 20% IOP reduction from the baseline, beta-blockerscould be the first line of drug. Systemic beta-blocker have theability to achieve 80% of the topical drop&#x02032;s effect on IOP.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref> If thepatient is already on systemic beta-blockers for hypertension,IOP reduction ability of topical beta-blockers will likely bereduced significantly; it should perhaps be avoided as a first-line drug in this instance. They are, however, worth trying asa second line of management if necessary.</p><p>If our target is 30-35% IOP reduction from the baseline,Prostaglandin analogues (PGA) like Latanoprost (0.005%),Bimatoprost (0.03%) or Travatoprost (0.004%) are preferable.Some patients may not respond to one brand of PGA, but mayrespond to another. In a non-responder, it is worthwhile tryinganother brand.</p><p>If 30% or more IOP lowering is required and either aprostaglandin does not achieve this or there is a cost problem,combination of beta-blockers with &#x003b1;-2 agonists like brimonidineP 0.15% or topical carbonic anhydrase inhibitors may suffice.Combination drugs have made life easier, but each component must be individually shown to be effective.</p><p>Generally, the IOP cannot be lowered below the episcleralvenous pressure and once the IOP is lowered by the firstmedication, the amount it can be further lowered (to theepiscleral pressure) is less for the second medication.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>Theoretically, PGA act via the uveoscleral outflow and canreduce IOP below episcleral pressure. Practically, we havenot seen any patient (without other co-morbidity) whoseIOP has actually been reduced below 11 mmHg on anymedication.</p><p>Many ophthalmologists are concerned about waiting forthe results of a unilateral trial, especially if the IOP is &#x02033;high&#x02033;.Glaucoma is a chronic progressive disease and the patienthas probably already had the disease for a long time beforedetection. Nothing acute or significantly detrimental is likelyto happen during the time we do the unilateral trial. However,many patients (and doctors) are uncomfortable with treatingonly one eye especially if the baseline IOP is high. If baseline IOPis at such a level (usually high 20s and above), we could start theunilateral trial as planned along with systemic acetazolamidefor a temporary IOP control for both eyes. As the peak effect andwash period is minimal, we prefer it when situation demandsIOP reduction in contra-lateral eye for temporary time period.Discontinuing the systemic acetazolamide 72 h before the nextfollow-up allows us to assess the effect of the eye drop in oneeye without too much risk to the fellow eye.</p><p>In situations where the patient is unable to return within4-6 weeks to assess the results of the unilateral trial, we starttreatment in both eyes and do a reverse trial. The patientis asked to discontinue the medication under assessment4-6 weeks (depending on the wash-off period for that drug)prior to the follow-up visit.</p><p>The flowchart [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>] shows the overview of unilateral drugtrial and monitoring of medical management of an individualpatient.</p><sec><title>Side effects and contra-indications of anti-glaucoma medications</title><p>While prescribing medications, common side effects and contra-indications of the drug should be kept in mind. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> showsthe reported side effects of the common antiglaucoma drugs.In patients with asthma and heart block, beta-blocker shouldbe avoided. Many older patients have mild chronic obstructivepulmonary disease (COPD) and may feel much better oncea beta-blocker is stopped. We avoid PGAs in inflammatoryglaucoma, in patients with history of herpetic keratitis andcystoid macular edema with a compromised posterior capsule.It is advisable to make the patient aware of the side effects ofPGAs like elongation and hyper-pigmentation of lashes, irishyperchromia before initiating therapy; more so if the therapyis unilateral. Topical carbonic anhydrase inhibitors (CAIs)should be avoided in patients with poor endothelial status as itcan worsen corneal edema in such cases. Alpha-2 agonists cancross blood -brain barrier and are absolutely contra-indicatedin infants and patients using MAO inhibitors. Alpha-2 agonistalso causes drowsiness that can have major impact on a patient&#x02032;sQOL. Educating the patient about punctum occlusion andeyelid closure can decrease this side effect. Oral CAI shouldnot be given for a long duration or be given with consent ofthe patient&#x02032;s physician.</p><p>Whatever therapy we choose, the concept to be kept inmind is that glaucoma therapy is lifelong and directly relatedto HRQOL; be it cost, side effects or regime of the drug.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Follow-up</title><p>Regular follow-up is necessary to detect progression thatmight require escalation of treatment. Progression inglaucoma is assessed by structure (optic disc and RNFL) andfunction (visual field testing with WWP) independently orin association. A higher IOP is a risk factor for progression.Structure, function and IOP should be monitored at regularintervals. The follow-up period depends on the stage of thedisease and stability.</p><sec><title>Individualizing follow-up visits</title><p>If the unilateral drug trial has been started, we review patientsdepending on the peak duration of the drug used. Subsequentfollow-up is customized depending on the decision to continuethe same drug, add or replace the drug in the same eye andthe other eye also.</p><p>Once we are sure that IOP is stable (assessed by day DVT orchecking IOP at frequent intervals at different hours of the dayat different visits), the subsequent follow-up visits of glaucomapatients depend on the severity of glaucoma (amount of discand field damage) at the time of presentation and follow-up,as well as additional risk factors. The initial visits are used toobtain baseline fields.</p><p>Glaucoma (pre-perimetric or early functional damage),with IOP at target might be reviewed in 6 months and then ifstill stable, at yearly intervals. The yearly follow-ups wouldinclude the full CEE as well as several IOPs, visual fields andother imaging tests required.</p><p>Stable patients with moderate damage would be examinedat 6-month intervals. For severe glaucoma in the better eye,the interval could be 3-4 months. If the IOP is slightly higherthan the target level, say 2 mmHg, but the patient has notprogressed on other parameters, we would schedule the nextvisit a few months earlier to measure IOPs and then go backto the routine. If there is confirmed progression in structureor function (repeatable progression of field defect on at leasttwo occasions), even if the office hour IOP is at target level,we repeat DVT to look for undetected IOP peaks or highfluctuations as well as systemic factors like nocturnal dips inblood pressure. While it is controversial, we believe that diurnalfluctuation of 8 mmHg or more is probably an independentrisk factor for progression.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></p><p><bold>Judging progression:</bold> Progression can be judged bydocumenting structural changes in the optic disc and/orfunctional changes on the visual fields. IOP and optic discexaminations are mandatory at every routine visit.</p><p><bold>Progression in structure:</bold> Any new RNFL defect, presenceof new disc hemorrhage or change in neuroretinal rim statusindicates unstable and progressive glaucoma. Such patientsrequires a visual field to document functional progression.</p><p><bold>Progression on visual fields:</bold> In current clinical practice, werely mainly on WWP to detect progression. In our own clinicalroutine: we use the &#x02033;Overview&#x02033; and glaucoma progressionanalysis (GPA) programs. Eyeballing the overview, we get afeel for whether field deterioration is due to generalized sinkingof the hill of vision or whether it is due to glaucoma. GPA isbased on the pattern deviation plot and is a better option todiagnose progression.</p><p>Progression in the research setting requires confirmationover four to six fields.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref> In the clinic, however, the judgmentof progression is more &#x02033;corroborative&#x02033;. There are other factorslike the IOP (hopefully several, over time, at various times ofthe day), appearance of the disc, RNFL, hemorrhage, etc. Ifthese suggest progression, eyeballing the overview gives usan idea as to what is going on and we get a GPA. &#x02033;Possible&#x02033;progression on the GPA corroborates our clinical concern; arepeat field with the message &#x02033;Likely&#x02033; progression is thenprobably good enough to take decisions, especially if thedeteriorating points correlate with our disc findings. It ispossible that GPA might underestimate visual field progressioneven in cases without evidence of increasing media opacity.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>We feel that consideration of the overview program (total andpattern deviation plot) in combination with the GPA analysesaddresses this concern.</p><p><bold>Progression on imaging technologies:</bold> Imaging techniqueoffers exciting possibilities to detect progression. The HRThas the longest track record in documenting structural change(trend analysis and topographic change analysis).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref> GDx andOCT have developed programs more recently. Progression onimaging is more likely to be useful in the earlier stages of thedisease, which is an advantage.</p><p>If the progression is confirmed on both structure andfunction or even if only on visual fields, there is no other optionbut to further reduce our target IOP by adding or substitutingtherapy.</p><p>Everything else being equal, we take more cognizance ofoptic disc deterioration in the presence of a field defect thanwithout. Some findings like disc hemorrhage, RNFL defect or arim notch are so predictive of future field defects that we initiateour routine (DVT, detection of IOP dips etc) on this basis andwould step up therapy without a field defect.</p><p>We treat progression on imaging (trend analysis andtopographic change analysis on HRT) in the same manner.Without a field defect progression (unless associated with thedisc findings referred to above or &#x02033;high&#x02033; IOP), we wouldusually elect to observe the patient more carefully. In thepresence of an existing functional defect (early or moderate),the change is more likely to be real and result in functionaldamage. Accordingly, we consider progression on imagingmore sinister in this situation and treat it akin to discprogression in this situation.</p><p>Either way, if target IOP was not achieved, then in thesecases we may add on or change the therapy.</p><p>Some clinical situations merit mention.</p><p><bold>Maximum medical therapy:</bold> If the IOP is not at target level,we consider adding or substituting the therapy dependingupon target IOP required. The need to decrease the IOP totarget depends on the amount of damage already present.There is no consensus on how many drugs can be used. Thisbrings us to the concept of maximum medical therapy. Maximalmedical therapy can be defined as the minimum number andconcentration of drugs (within the combination of differentclasses of medications) that provides maximum lowering ofIOP. It should be tailored to the individual patient.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></p><p><bold>If the progression is confirmed but IOP is at target (confirmedwith DVT):</bold> Revisit other risk factors like nocturnal hypotension,systemic or topical steroid use, recent major surgery or bloodloss due to trauma, central corneal thickness. We would alsotalk to the patient&#x02032;s physician regarding any hypertension, itscontrol and the avoidance of night-time dips in blood pressureas well as the possibility of sleep apnea. If the patient showsprogression with normal IOPs, we would enquire about otherhabits; yoga, especially &#x02033;aasnas&#x02033; in the inverted position, useof wind instruments, rapid consumption of large quantities ofwater or beer. An &#x02033;alternative medicine&#x02033; prescription of a liter ofwater in the morning mimics the water drinking provocative testand can cause optic nerve damage. This situation also requires arepeat DVT to see if the IOPs are fluctuating beyond the normalrange especially in the early morning hours.</p><p>It is also possible that our assessment of the initial targetIOP was wrong and we need to readjust it. On other hand, wemay have a patient at the opposite end of the spectrum: mild orpre-perimetric glaucoma with stable visual functions at target.In this scenario, it is possible that we may have overestimatedthe target IOP and we may be overtreating the patient. In thisinstance, we would try to withdraw unnecessary drugs.</p><p><bold>Role of surgery in the management of a glaucoma patient:</bold>As this article is primarily about medical management ofPOAG, this section is small. While surgery is usually consideredif the patient is progressing despite maximum medical therapy,socioeconomic and other considerations like age, disease statusin both eyes, presence of visually disabling cataract and generalhealth of the patient may dictate primary intervention. Wemay decide not to operate on an 80-year-old with advancedglaucoma in one eye and very early glaucoma in the other eye.The same holds true for a 45-year-old with terminal malignancy.The decision is tailored to the individual patient. Interventionis only undertaken after a detailed discussion of risks, benefitsand patient preferences.</p></sec><sec><title>Normal tension glaucoma</title><p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Essentially, the approach and treatment is the same asPOAG. We only use the term here because it is in commonuse.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Perform a &#x02033;careful&#x02033; gonioscopy to rule out primary angleclosure.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Perform a CCT to rule out a &#x02033;garden variety&#x02033; POAG. This isespecially true if the IOPs are in the high &#x02033;normal&#x02033; range.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Twenty-four hour DVT prior to any expensive or invasiveinvestigations. IOP fluctuation of more than six to eight issuggestive of IOP-related risk.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Treatment is usually initiated with a PGA.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Certain NTG cases, those with unilateral disease, pallorof the disc, atypical defect and color defects require appropriate cardiovascular or neurological investigation.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Role of neuroprotection: Currently, there is no evidence forneuroprotection as an isolated strategy. Available optionsare calcium channel blockers and alpha-2 agonists. Theiruse could be restricted to those cases in which a strong linkto vasospastic disease is present, thought to be the mostimportant causative factor in those specific cases of NTG.They should be used with caution in combination withbeta-blockers to avoid severe bradycardia. If a glaucomapatient is also on antihypertensives, we may requestthe physician to consider a calcium channel blocker fortreatment. Alpha-2 agonists are currently prescribedprimarily for their IOP lowering effects.</p></list-item></list></p><p><bold>Primary angle closure glaucoma (PACG):</bold> The first line ofmanagement for chronic primary angle closure (PAC), PACG,is laser iridotomy. The details of other laser and surgical optionsfor PACG are out of the scope of this manuscript, but a fewimportant points are highlighted.</p><p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>In general, PACG requires closer monitoring than POAG.Once iridotomy is done and angle is open in at least 180&#x000b0;,medical management should be same as POAG. If theangle does not open, consider other measures like laseriridoplasty.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Effect of PGA is inversely proportional to degree ofclosed angle. The effect of PGA in a totally closed angle isminimal.</p></list-item><list-item><p>If patient is on pilocarpine for whatever reason, the effectof PGA on IOP reduction is minimal and other medication(drugs which work on ciliary body) should be used.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Summary</title><p>POAG, a diagnosis of exclusion is usually a chronic, slowlyprogressive disease. At present, all resources are directedtowards reduction of IOP, the only known causal and treatablerisk factor for glaucoma, and medical management is frequentlythe first choice in most cases. The aim is to prevent anyreduction in QOL from visual disability with minimum effectson QOL in terms of cost, side effects, treatment regime, follow-up schedules as well as socioeconomic burden.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Source of Support: Nil</p></fn><fn><p>Conflict of Interest: None declared</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Number of people with glaucoma worldwide</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>1996</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8695555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glaucoma in China: How big is the problem?</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2001</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11673287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dandona</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dandona</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarty</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Open-angle glaucoma in an urban population in southern India: the Andhra Pradesh Eye Disease Study</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2000</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>1702</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10964833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijaya</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arvind</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Baskaran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of angle-closure disease in a rural southern Indian population</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16534061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijaya</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Baskaran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arvind</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Raju</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of open-angle glaucoma in a rural south Indian population</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>4461</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16303934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Martine</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ritch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shield</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of chronic open-angle glaucoma</article-title><source>The Glaucomas</source><year>1996</year><edition>2nd ed</edition><publisher-loc>St. Louis</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mosby Yearbook Inc</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ritch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shield</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normal tension glaucoma</article-title><source>The glaucomas</source><year>1996</year><edition>2nd ed</edition><publisher-loc>St. Louis</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mosby Yearbook Inc</publisher-name><fpage>770</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mardin</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preperimetric glaucoma diagnosis by confocal scanning laser tomography of the optic disc</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>1999</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10365037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buhrmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The definition and classification of glaucoma in prevalence surveys</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2002</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11815354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Allingham</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Damji</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moroi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafranov</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Shield&#x02032;s Textbook of Glaucoma</source><year>2005</year><edition>5th ed</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams and Wilkins</publisher-name><fpage>438</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tielsch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottsch</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Javitt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between intraocular pressure and primary open angle glaucoma among white and black Americans: The BaltimoreEye Survey</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>1991</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1090</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1867550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrashekar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gonioscopy</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>1998</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10218313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Grave</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wienereb</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Glaucoma diagnosis: Structure and function</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Hague, Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kurger Publication</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandra Sekhar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabakaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesh Babu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic capability of optical coherence tomography (stratus OCT 3) in early glaucoma</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2007</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>2238</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17561260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tugwell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical Epidemiology</article-title><source>A Basic Science for Clinical Medicine</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Little, Brown and co</publisher-name><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cioffi</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebmann</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translating the OHTS results into clinical practice</article-title><source>J Glaucoma</source><year>2002</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12362074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leske</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Heijl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Komaroff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors for glaucoma progression and the effect of treatment:the early manifest glaucoma trial</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>2003</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12523884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applanation tonometry and central corneal thickness</article-title><source>Acta Ophthalmol (Copenh)</source><year>1975</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1172910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heijl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leske</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduction of intraocular pressure and glaucoma progression: Results from the Early Manifest GlaucomaTrial</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>2002</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>1268</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12365904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feiner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Piltz-Seymour</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study: A summary of results to date</article-title><source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source><year>2003</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12698052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodapp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>RK</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical decisions in glaucoma</article-title><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>St Louis</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mosby and Co</publisher-name><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jampel</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Target pressure in glaucoma therapy</article-title><source>J Glaucoma</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9098822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of systemic beta-blocker therapy on the efficacyand safety of topical brimonidine and timolol: Brimonidine StudyGroups 1 and 2</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2000</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10857839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hodapp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>RK</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Clinical decisions in glaucoma</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>St Louis</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mosby and Co</publisher-name><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>124</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asrani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeimer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilensky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gieser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindenmuth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large diurnal fluctuations in intraocular pressure are an independent risk factor in patients withglaucoma</article-title><source>J Glaucoma</source><year>2000</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10782622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Errors in the diagnosis of visual field progression in normal tension glaucoma</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1994</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>1589</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8090461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Artes</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolela</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual field progression in glaucoma:total versus pattern deviation analyses</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>4600</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16303955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Technique for detecting serial topographic changes in the optic disc and peripapillary retina using scanning lasertomography</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10711693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fechtner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maximal glaucoma therapy</article-title><source>J Glaucoma</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>S73</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11890285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>Asia Pacific Glaucoma Guidelines 2003-04</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.seagig.org/guidelines1.php">http://www.seagig.org/guidelines1.php</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart showing the work-up of glaucoma suspect, IOP - Intraocular pressure, RNFL - Retinal nerve fibre layer, D - Diopter,WWP - White on white perimetry, CCT - Central corneal thickness, DVT - Diurnal variation test, POAG - Primary open angle glaucoma, OHT- Ocular hypertension, NTG - Normal tension glaucoma, HVS - Humphrey visual field, SWAP - Short wave automated perimetry</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-223-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Flowchart showing unilateral drug trial and monitoring of medical management for an individual patient (with Permission from AsiaPacific Glaucoma Guidelines, Seagig, 2003-2004)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-223-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Main classes of ocular hypotensive drugs and their mechanisms</p></caption><alt-text>Table 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-223-g002"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>