<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18158403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636062</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_1_45_37595</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Methdology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Understanding and using sensitivity, specificity and predictive values</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>Rajul</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mathai</surname><given-names>Annie</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>Shefali</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chandra Sekhar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Ravi</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>L. V. Prasad Eye Institute, Banjara Hills, Hyderabad, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Rajul Parikh, Victor villa, 5, Babulnath Road,Mumbai - 400007, India Email: <email>drparikhs@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>In this article, we have discussed the basic knowledge to calculate sensitivity, specificity, positive predictivevalue and negative predictive value. We have discussed the advantage and limitations of these measures andhave provided how we should use these measures in our day-to-day clinical practice. We also have illustratedhow to calculate sensitivity and specificity while combining two tests and how to use these results for ourpatients in day-to-day practice.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Predictive values</kwd><kwd>sensitivity</kwd><kwd>specificity</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Modern ophthalmology has experienced a dramatic increasein knowledge and an exponential increase in technology.A lot of this &#x02032;hi-tech&#x02032; explosion involves diagnostic tests.Regrettably, there is sometimes a tendency to use tests justbecause they are available; or because they are hi-tech. Thebasic idea of performing a diagnostic test is to increase (ordecrease) our suspicion that a patient has a particular disease,to the extent that we can make management decisions. In thisarticle, we have tried to explain the rationale behind tests andtheir &#x02032;scientific&#x02032; application in the practical management of apatient.</p><sec sec-type=""><title>Diagnostic Tests</title><p>For this article, the term &#x02032;diagnostic tests&#x02032; will include everythingphysicians do to diagnose disease. This includes assessingsymptoms and signs, as well as what we conventionally refer toas tests: such as laboratory investigations, gonioscopy, OpticalCoherence Tomography (OCT), etc.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Gold Standard</title><p>The gold standard is the best single test (or a combinationof tests) that is considered the current preferred method ofdiagnosing a particular disease (X). All other methods ofdiagnosing X, including any new test, need to be comparedagainst this &#x02032;gold&#x02032; standard. The gold standard is different fordifferent diseases. If we are considering peripheral anteriorchamber depth (van Herick test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>) for the diagnosis of primaryangle closure (PAC), the current gold standard is gonioscopy.The gold standard for demonstrating the functional defectin glaucoma is automated perimetry. The gold standard forX may be considered outdated or inadequate, but any newtest designed to replace the gold standard <italic>has</italic> to be initiallyvalidated against the gold standard. If the new test is indeedbetter, there are ways to prove that; following which the newtest may become the gold standard.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Validity</title><p>It is the extent to which a test measures what it is supposed tomeasure; in other words, it is the accuracy of the test. Validityis measured by sensitivity and specificity. These terms, as wellas other jargon, are best illustrated using a conventional two-by-two (2 x 2) table.</p><p>The information obtained by comparing a new diagnostictest with the gold standard is conventionally summarized in atwo-by-two table [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>].</p><p>In cell &#x02032;a,&#x02032; we enter those in whom the test in questioncorrectly diagnosed the disease (as determined by the goldstandard). In other words, the test is positive, as is the goldstandard. These are the true positives (TP).</p><p>In cell &#x02032;b,&#x02032; we enter those who have positive results for thetest in question but do not have disease according to the &#x02032;goldstandard test.&#x02032; The newer test has wrongly diagnosed thedisease: These are false positives (FP).</p><p>In cell &#x02032;c,&#x02032; we enter those who have disease on the &#x02032;goldstandard test&#x02032; but have negative results with the test in question.The test has wrongly labeled a diseased person as &#x02032;normal.&#x02032;These are false negatives (FN).</p><p>In cell &#x02032;d,&#x02032; we enter those who have no disease as determinedby the &#x02032;gold standard test&#x02032; and are also negative with the newertest. These are true negatives (TN).</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Sensitivity (positive in disease)</title><p>Sensitivity is the ability of a test to correctly classify anindividual as &#x02032;diseased&#x02032; [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>].</p><p>Sensitivity = a / a+c</p><p>	= a (true positive) / a+c (true positive + falsenegative)</p><p>	= Probability of being test positive when diseasepresent.</p><p>Example: One hundred persons with primary angleclosure glaucoma (PACG, diagnosed by &#x02032;gold standard&#x02032;:gonioscopy) are examined by van Herick test. Seventy-five ofthem had narrow peripheral anterior chamber depth [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table3</xref>]. The sensitivity of the peripheral anterior chamber depthexamination to PACG is therefore &#x02013;</p><p>75 / 100 = 75%.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Specificity (negative in health) </title><p>The ability of a test to correctly classify an individual as <italic>disease-free</italic> is called the test&#x02032;s specificity. [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>]</p><p>Specificity = d / b+d</p><p>	= d (true negative) / b+d (true negative + false positive)</p><p>	= Probability of being test negative when disease absent.</p><p>Example: One hundred persons with normal angles(diagnosed by &#x02032;gold standard&#x02032;: gonioscopy) are examinedby peripheral angle chamber depth examination. Eighty-fivepersons had normal peripheral angle chamber depth [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table3</xref>]. The specificity of the peripheral angle chamber depthexamination to PACG is therefore &#x02013;</p><p>85 / 100 = 85%.</p><p>Sensitivity and specificity are inversely proportional,meaning that as the sensitivity increases, the specificitydecreases and vice versa. What do we mean by this? Let ussay that an intraocular pressure (IOP) of &#x02265;25 mmHg is testpositive and &#x0003c;25 mmHg is test negative. Very few normalsubjects would have IOP more than 25 mmHg, and hence thespecificity (NIH &#x02013; negative in health) would be very high. But asa significant number of glaucoma subjects would have an IOP&#x0003c;25 mmHg (remember that close to 50% of glaucomas detectedin population are normal-tension glaucomas), the sensitivity(PID &#x02013; positive in disease) of IOP &#x0003e;25 mmHg in the detectionof glaucoma would be low. Suppose we take the IOP cutoff fortest positive to be 35 mmHg. Almost no normal subject wouldhave this high an IOP, and the specificity would be very high(&#x0003e;99%); and a highly specific test if positive (for example an IOP&#x0003e;35 mmHg), rules in the disease. Remember this as SpPIN: ahighly Specific test if Positive, rules IN disease. Similarly, if wetake a cutoff of 12 mmHg, almost no glaucoma subject wouldhave an IOP &#x0003c;12 mmHg (high sensitivity). An eye with an IOP&#x0003c;12 mmHg is extremely unlikely to have glaucoma. A highlysensitive test if negative, rules out the disease. Remember thisas SnNOUT: a highly Sensitive test if Negative, rules OUTdisease. (Almost all normals would have an IOP &#x0003e;12 mmHg,a very low specificity; but that is a different issue). Anotherexample of SnNOUT would be the absence of venous pulsationin papilledema. The sensitivity of the sign &#x02032;absence of venouspulsation&#x02032; in the diagnosis of papilledema is 99%, and specificityis 90%. So if venous pulsation is present, then we can applySnNOUT and rule out papilledema. At that point in time,papilledema may be evolving and may still develop a fewdays or a week later; or patients may have papilledema, but theintracranial pressure at the time of examination is normal.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Positive Predictive Value (PPV)</title><p>It is the percentage of patients with a positive test who actuallyhave the disease. In a 2 x 2 table [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>], cell &#x02032;a&#x02032; is &#x02032;true positives&#x02032;and cell &#x02032;b&#x02032; is &#x02032;false positives.&#x02032; In real life situation, we do the newtest first and we do not have results of &#x02032;gold standard&#x02032; available.We want to know how this new test is doing. PPV tells us aboutthis &#x02013; how many of test positives are true positives; and if thisnumber is higher (as close to 100 as possible), then it suggeststhat this new test is doing as good as &#x02032;gold standard.&#x02032;</p><p>PPV: = a / a+b</p><p>	= a (true positive) / a+b (true positive + false positive)</p><p>	= Probability (patient having disease when test ispositive)</p><p>Example: We will use sensitivity and specificity provided in<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref> to calculate positive predictive value.</p><p>PPV = a (true positive) / a+b (true positive + false positive)</p><p>	= 75 / 75 + 15 = 75 / 90 = 83.3%</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Negative Predictive Value (NPV)</title><p>It is the percentage of patients with a negative test who donot have the disease. In 2 x 2 table [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>], cell &#x02032;d&#x02032; is &#x02032;truenegatives&#x02032; and cell &#x02032;c&#x02032; is &#x02032;false negatives.&#x02032; NPV tells us howmany of test negatives are true negatives; and if this numberis higher (should be close to 100), then it suggests that this newtest is doing as good as &#x02032;gold standard.&#x02032;</p><p>NPV:	=	d / c+d</p><p>	=	d (true negative) / c+d (false negative + true negative)</p><p>	=	Probability (patient not having disease when test isnegative)</p><p>Example: We will use sensitivity and specificity provided in<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref> to calculate negative predictive value.</p><p>NPV	=	a (true negatives) / c+d (false negative + true negative)</p><p>	=	85 / 85 + 25 = 85 / 110 = 77.3%</p><p>Positive and negative predictive values are directly relatedto the prevalence of the disease in the population [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>].Assuming all other factors remain constant, the PPV willincrease with increasing prevalence; and NPV decreases withincrease in prevalence. This is illustrated by the followingexample.</p><p>A new test has been developed to diagnose primary angleclosure glaucoma (PACG). To clarify the terminology usedin the example, we will repeat definitions of primary angleclosure (PAC) and PACG. PAC is defined as a person with anoccludable angle (&#x0003e;180&#x000b0; of posterior trabecular meshwork notvisible) with peripheral anterior synechiae with or withoutraised intraocular pressure (IOP). Optic disc and visual field donot show glaucomatous damage. PACG is defined as PAC withoptic disc and visual field changes. PAC affects approximately3 to 4% of population, while PACG affects approximately 1%of population.</p><p>This new test has been performed in 1,000 patients that haddocumented PACG (disease positive) on gonioscopy (goldstandard) and 1,000 normal persons as controls. The authorsfound that 900 were correctly classified as PACG by the &#x02032;newtest,&#x02032; and 950 were correctly labeled as open angle [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4A">Table 4a</xref>].The authors would report the sensitivity and specificity of atest as 90 and 95% respectively. With a sensitivity of 90% and aspecificity of 95%, the new test appears to be an excellent test.</p><p>Let&#x02032;s apply this test to a million people where only 1% isaffected with PACG. Of the million people, 10,000 would beaffected with PACG. Since our new test is 90% sensitive, thetest will detect 9,000 (TP) people who are actually affectedwith PACG and miss 1,000 (FN). Looking at those numbers,we would think that our test is very good because we havedetected 9,000 out of 10,000 PACG-affected people. However, ofthe original 1 million, 990,000 are not affected. If we look at thetest results on the normal population (remember, the specificityof the test is 95%), we find that while 940,500 are found to benot affected by the new test (TN), we have 49,500 individualswho are found to be positive by the new test (FP).</p><p>If we start using this new test without confirmatory testingon the gold standard gonioscopy, we would diagnose 49,500people, or approximately 5% of the population, as PACG whenin reality, they are not. The sensitivity and specificity of the testhave not changed. The sensitivity and specificity were howeverdetermined with a 50% prevalence of PACG (1,000 PACG and1,000 normals) with PPV of 95%. We are now applying it to apopulation with a prevalence of PACG of only 1%. With a 1%prevalence of PACG, the new test has a PPV of 15%. Althoughthe sensitivity and specificity of the test have not changed, thePPV has changed drastically. If the prevalence (also known asthe pre-test probability in this situation) of the disease is low,such as with glaucoma or sight-threatening diabetic retinopathyin the general population, the number of false-positive resultswill be far higher than the number of true-positive results.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Thisleads to a number of problems, including labeling of normal asabnormal resulting in unnecessary treatment.</p><p>The NPV of the test also change depending on the prevalenceof the disease and usually in reverse direction to PPV. In theabove example, in high-prevalence situation (50% prevalence)[<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4A">Table 4a</xref>], the NPV was 90%. In low-prevalence situation [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4B">Table4b</xref>], the NPV increased to 99%. So why not use a test for theNPV value? If the prevalence is already so low, the NPV willcertainly reduce it further but still not to zero.</p><p>The PPV can increase if we repeat the test in certain situations.For example, in HIV, if we repeat ELISA with different kit inthe group that is already ELISA positive, the specificity andPPV will increase. However, if the same test is repeated, thenconcordance will be a problem.</p><p>Everything we have discussed so far has assumed that thesensitivity and specificity do not change as one deals withdifferent groups of people. Sensitivity and specificity, however,can change if the population tested is dramatically differentfrom the population you serve, especially if the spectrum of thedisease is different. In more severe disease, we are more likelyto be able to make a diagnosis; and thus sensitivity goes up.</p><p>What if the new test is actually <italic>better</italic> than the gold standard?There is no shortcut to the process of comparing it to the existinggold standard. The new (presumably better) test will detect moredisease than the &#x02032;gold standard.&#x02032; In the 2 x 2 table, the subjectslabeled as &#x02032;diseased&#x02032; by the new test (but still &#x02032;normal&#x02032; on the&#x02032;gold standard&#x02032;) will go in cell &#x02032;b&#x02032; (false positives). If on follow-up,a significant number of these patients actually develop disease(gold standard positive), then the new test is in fact detectingdisease earlier than, and is better than, the gold standard. In someinstances, there may be other strategies available to determinestraight away whether the new test is in fact better.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Clinical application</title><p>So far we have discussed how to calculate sensitivity, specificity,positive and negative predictive values using 2 x 2 table. Nowwe will discuss the clinical application of these parameters.</p><p>The sensitivity, specificity of IOP, torch light test, van Hericktest are shown below [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>].</p><p>Which test should we use to screen the population for angleclosure glaucoma? The prevalence and PPV discussed above(and other reasons provided in the reference) should haveconvinced you that this is a bad idea.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> So let&#x02032;s take an examplein a clinic. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref> shows the sensitivity and specificity ofvarious tests we can use for detecting PACG. Gonioscopy is the&#x02032;gold standard&#x02032; for diagnosis of angle closure, and that&#x02032;s whywe should do gonioscopy in all patients we see in clinics. Allother tests (IOP, torch light test and van Herick test) have poorspecificity.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> Even with specificity as high as 90%, the PPV willbe poor. The prevalence of angle closure (as opposed to angleclosure glaucoma) is approximately 3%. With this prevalence,PPV of IOP would be 15%; torch light test, 7.6%; and for vanHerick test, 15%. These results mean that if we use IOP or vanHerick test to diagnose angle closure, only 15% of suspectedangle closure patients will really have disease, and the other85% would be FP. The sensitivity of these tests is moderate andwill miss most of the disease.</p><p>In day-to-day clinical practice, we can however combineresults of two independent tests to be more confident of thediagnosis &#x02013; for example, combining IOP and optic disc changesfor primary open angle glaucoma (POAG), IOP and peripheralangle chamber depth for diagnosis of PACG, history of diabetesand frequency doubling technology (FDT) defect for diabeticretinopathy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Case 1</title><p>A 54-year-old male patient was diagnosed to have POAG. Hedid not have any ocular or systemic complaints. The vision was20/20, N6 in each eye. The IOPs were 25 mmHg in both eyeson several occasions. Corneal pachymetry was normal and theangle was reported to be open. The optic discs showed changessuggestive of glaucoma, and there were corresponding earlyvisual defects. The patient was started on a unilateral trial oftimolol 0.5% twice daily.</p><p>The van Herick test when the patient was examined 2 weekslater is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2</xref>. The peripheral anterior chamber depthwas less than one-fourth the peripheral corneal thickness inboth eyes.</p><p>With this IOP and van Herick test, a diagnosis of POAGbecomes unlikely. Let us examine the rationale behind thisstatement. The specificity of IOP for glaucoma is 90%. Thatin itself is not enough for a SpPIN, or &#x02032;rule in,&#x02032; and doesn&#x02032;thelp too much. The specificity of the van Herick test for angleclosure is 85%, which again, on its own is not of much helpeither. However, the two tests can be combined to increase thespecificity and perhaps apply SpPIN and &#x02032;rule in&#x02032; diagnosis.The specificity of the two tests can be combined in the followingmanner<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>:</p><p>Specificity of combined test = 1 - (1 - specificity of test 1) &#x000d7;(1 &#x02013; specificity of test 2)</p><p>Plugging in the values for our patient,</p><p>1 - (1 - 0.9) &#x000d7; (1 - 0.85) = 1 - 0.1 &#x000d7; 0.15 = 1 - 0.015</p><p>= 0.985, or 98.5%</p><p>This combined specificity of 98.5% definitely allows us toinvoke SpPIN and rule in a diagnosis: until proved otherwise,this patient has angle closure. (We assume that the IOPspecificity of 90% holds for angle closure glaucoma too.)</p><p>The &#x02032;open angle&#x02032; described earlier is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3.</xref>. Theangles on repeat gonioscopy (indentation) are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>.</p><p>One valid objection to combining tests in this manner is thatthe resultant sensitivity becomes the product of the sensitivitiesof the two tests &#x02013; that is, the product of the sensitivity of anIOP &#x0003e;21 mmHg (50%) and the sensitivity of the van Herick test(69%) = 0.50 &#x000d7; 0.69 = 34.5%. While 35 is a low sensitivity as faras tests in general are concerned, it doesn&#x02032;t really matter here aswe are utilizing the &#x02032;rule in&#x02032; specifically to make the diagnosisin an individual patient.</p><p>Let&#x02032;s take another example: a patient has repeatable IOPmeasurements of 24 mmHg with normal pachymetry, andthe angles this time are <italic>really</italic> open. The specificity of the IOPmeasurement is 90%. And, while not too useful a measure,the cup disc ratio is 0.7 (specificity of CDR &#x0003e;0.55 is 73%). Thecombined specificity of IOP and disc now becomes 1 - (1 -specificity of IOP) &#x000d7; (1 - specificity of Disc) = 1 - (1 - 0.90)&#x000d7;(1 -0.73) = 1- (0.1)&#x000d7;(0.27) = 1 - 0.027 = 97.3%.</p><p>This specificity is high enough to &#x02033;rule in&#x02033; the diagnosis ofPOAG, without further testing. Any further testing is probablyrequired for monitoring. Of course, whether we treat or not isa different matter.</p><p>Some of us want even more evidence than this. The approachwe describe allows incorporation of further testing (includingoptimal and effective use of modern imaging techniques) too.The GDX &#x02032;number (NFI)&#x02032; in the above patient is more than 32(specificity of about 85%). If we combine this with just the IOP,can you calculate the combined specificity?</p><p>1 - (1 - specificity of IOP)) &#x000d7; (1 - specificity of &#x02032;number&#x02032;&#x0003e;30)</p><p>You should get 98.5%.</p><p>This should be confirmatory; but if you are still not satisfiedand want to take it further, you can use the IOP, Disc and theGDX. 1 - (1 - specificity of IOP) &#x000d7; (1 - specificity of Disc)&#x000d7;(1 -specificity of &#x02032;number&#x02032; &#x0003e;30).</p><p>Did you get 99.5%? As a &#x02032;rule in,&#x02032; this is (almost) asgood as it gets. Regrettably, there is no absolute certainty. According toour clinical Bible, absolute certainty is limited to theologiansand like-minded clinicians.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> And as the tests are &#x02032;independent,&#x02032;our estimate of specificity should work. If the tests were notindependent, there would be some &#x02032;convergence,&#x02032; as it istechnically called. When we use three tests, such convergencewould have minimal clinical significance.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Case 2</title><p>A 40-year-old male is suspected to have sarcoidosis. It is anidiopathic multi-system granulomatous disease, where thediagnosis is made by a combination of clinical, radiologicaland laboratory findings. The gold standard is a tissue biopsyshowing noncaseating granuloma. Ocular sarcoidosis couldpresent as anterior, intermediate, posterior or panuveitis; butnone of these are pathognomonic. Therefore, one has to relyon ancillary testing to confirm the diagnosis.</p><p>Angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) has a sensitivity of73% and a specificity of 83% to diagnose sarcoidosis. Abnormalgallium scan has a sensitivity of 91% and a specificity of84%.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Though individually the specificity of either test is notimpressive, when we combine both the tests, the specificitybecomes &#x02013;</p><p>1 - (1 - 0.84) &#x000d7; (1 - 0.83) = 1 - (0.16 &#x000d7; 0.17)</p><p>= 1 - 0.03 = 0.97 = 97%</p><p>The combination sensitivity becomes = 0.73&#x000d7;0.91 = 0.66= 66%.</p><p>Sensitivities can be used in the same manner to rule outdiagnoses. Let us assume that the cup disc ratio (usually uselesswithout a mention of the disc size, but having a sensitivity of50% for a cutoff of &#x0003e;0.55) is 0.6; and the IOP is 21 mmHg (GHT,sensitivity of only 50%). But you feel the disc is suspicious or thepatient has a family history or has been referred or whatever.Based on the above information, could the patient still haveglaucoma? The combined sensitivity is calculated as:</p><p>1 - (1 - sensitivity of IOP)&#x000d7;(1 - sensitivity of CDR &#x0003e;0.55). </p><p>Did you try to calculate that? You should get 75%. That&#x02032;scertainly not good enough to rule out a disease like glaucoma.The visual fields, specifically the glaucoma hemifield test(sensitivity 95%), are normal. The combined specificity nowbecomes 1 - (0.25)&#x000d7;(1 - 0.95) = 98.75. You should be able to ruleout &#x02032;functional&#x02032; glaucoma now. Actually a normal field witha normal GHT with a sensitivity of 95% is on its own a goodenough &#x02032;rule out,&#x02032; but we know that the field may be normalwith a lot of disc damage. So you can use the GDX to combineinformation about the nerve fiber layer. The &#x02032;number&#x02032; on GDXis 31, the sensitivity of which is 74%. What is the combinedsensitivity now? 98.8%. Can we send the patient home now?</p><p>In summary, we have provided the basic knowledgeto calculate sensitivity, specificity, PPV and NPV. Moreimportantly, we have discussed the advantage and limitationsof these measures and provided how we should use thesemeasures in our day-to-day clinical practice. We also haveillustrated how to calculate sensitivity and specificity whilecombining two tests and how to use the results for our patientsin day-to-day practice.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Source of Support: Nil</p></fn><fn><p>Conflict of Interest: None</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tugwell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Clinical Epidemiology: A Basic Science for Clinical Medicine</source><year>1991</year><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Little Brown and co</publisher-name><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Herick</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of width of angle of anterior chamber: Incidence and significance of the narrow angle</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>1969</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5344324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuriakose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Muliyil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of frequency doubling technology perimetry in screening of diabetic retinopathy</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16531665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tugwell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Clinical epidemiology: A basic science for clinical medicine</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Little Brown and Co</publisher-name><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Drance</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of the oblique illumination test to predict angle closure glaucoma</article-title><source>Can J Ophthalmol</source><year>1974</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4820241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Braganza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Muliyil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Flashlight and van Herick&#x02032;s Test are poor predictors of occludable angles</article-title><source>Aust N Z J Ophthalmol</source><year>1996</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8913128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedroza-Seres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The value of combined serum angiotensin-converting enzyme and gallium scan in diagnosing ocular sarcoidosis</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1995</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>2007</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9098308</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>As the disease prevalence increases, the positive predictivevalue also increases</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Van Herick test showing shallow peripheral anterior chamberdepth (&#x0003c; one-fourth the peripheral corneal thickness)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>&#x02018;Open angle&#x02019; in an inappropriate testing condition</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Gonioscopy in an appropriate condition showing closedangle (white arrow) and presence of a peripheral anterior synechia onindentation (black arrow)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Shows 2 &#x000d7; 2 (two-by-two) table</p></caption><alt-text>Table 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g005"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Calculation of sensitivity and specificity</p></caption><alt-text>Table 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g006"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Shows example for the calculation of sensitivity andspecificity</p></caption><alt-text>Table 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g007"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4A" position="float"><label>Table 4a</label><caption><p>Showing example of calculation of predictive valueat 50% prevalence</p></caption><alt-text>Table 4a</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g008"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4B" position="float"><label>Table 4b</label><caption><p>Showing example of calculation of predictivevalues at 1% prevalence</p></caption><alt-text>Table 4b</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g010"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Shows sensitivity, specificity of intraocular pressure,torch light test and van Herick test</p></caption><alt-text>Table 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-45-g009"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>