<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417820</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636110</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_3_203_40358</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417820 </article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Symposium</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Distinguishing infective versus noninfective keratitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mascarenhas</surname><given-names>Jeena</given-names></name><degrees>MS, DNB</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Prashanth</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Cornea and External Eye Diseases, Aravind Eye Hospitals, Madurai - 625 020, Tamil Nadu, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Prashanth CN, Department of Cornea andExternal Eye Diseases, Aravind Eye Hospitals, Madurai - 625 020,Tamil Nadu, India. Email: <email>prashanthcndoctor@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>2</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>For the purpose of this symposium, the term &#x02033;keratitis&#x02033; implies suppurative nonviral and viral keratitis.Corneal ulcers have been described in ancient literature. But even today, despite the availability of a widerange of newer antimicrobials and new diagnostic techniques, infective keratitis continues to pose adiagnostic and therapeutic challenge. This article focuses on the key diagnostic clinical features of the mostcommon organisms causing infective keratitis - bacteria, fungi, viruses, nocardia and acanthamoeba - inIndia. While the clinical features in some cases are fairly straightforward, most cases challenge the clinician.We describe the salient clinical features which can help arrive at a diagnosis to begin appropriate treatmentimmediately, prior to the laboratory report.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Infectious keratitis</kwd><kwd>keratitis</kwd><kwd>marginal keratitis</kwd><kwd>radial perineuritis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>For the purpose of this symposium, the term &#x02033;keratitis&#x02033; impliessuppurative nonviral and viral keratitis. In general, keratitiscould be infective and noninfective. Differentiating betweenthem is crucial in managing both. Careful clinical examination,aided by laboratory investigations, could help in correctdiagnosis and proper management.</p><p>Even though both conditions may involve all age groups,infective keratitis occurs more frequently in children andadults. To describe precisely the ocular features of theseconditions, the clinician must be well trained in slit-lampbiomicroscopy. Other magnifiers like loupes and spectaclesmay not reveal the depth of the lesion and other associatedclinical signs.</p><p>Infective and noninfective keratitis may overlap each other.Noninfective keratitis may become infective by pathogenicor nonpathogenic microbes and may result in sight-threateningcomplications. Infective keratitis could also be suppurativeand nonsuppurative. Suppurative keratitis is frequently causedby bacteria and fungi. Nonsuppurative infective keratitiscould be viral, spirochaetal, parasitic or immune-relatedstromal necrosis.</p><sec sec-type=""><title>Infective nonsuppurative keratitis</title><p>Frequently seen a few decades ago, it is rarely seen now (e.g.,interstitial keratitis due to tuberculosis, leprosy and syphilis).Often they are insidious, chronic and bilateral. There may beobvious associated signs and symptoms of systemic disease.Diagnosis is often clinical, but the laboratory investigationsto rule out or confirm tuberculosis, leprosy and syphilis mayprovide more information to clinch the diagnosis.</p><p>The causative agents of infective keratitis frequentlyisolated in India are:<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></p><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Bacteria: Gram-positive cocci and Gram-negative bacilli</p></list-item><list-item><p>Fungi: Filamentous fungi</p></list-item><list-item><p>Viral: Herpes simplex virus</p></list-item><list-item><p>Parasite: <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> species</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Non-infective keratitis</title><p>The more common entities of noninfective keratitis are:<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></p><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Peripheral ulcerative keratitis (PUK) due to auto-immune diseases</p></list-item><list-item><p>Phlyctenular keratitis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Vernal ulcer or shield ulcer</p></list-item><list-item><p>Staphylococcal marginal keratitis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Contact lens-related sterile infiltrates</p></list-item><list-item><p>Meta herpetic ulcer</p></list-item></list></p><p>PUK [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>] is rare and diagnosis is often by exclusion.Mooren ulcer , senile marginal degeneration, sclerokeratitisand peripheral corneal melt of rheumatoid origin are someof the few to think about, when the clinician encounters anonhealing peripheral corneal ulcer. All these are progressivewith remissions and relapses. Confirmation of diagnosismay warrant a battery of immunological and bio-chemicalinvestigations like IgM rheumatoid factor, c-ANCA, p-ANCA,circulating antibodies, such as ANA, anti-DNA and anti-SM;which could narrow down the spectrum of etiology.</p><p>Vernal keratitis or vernal ulcer is not uncommon. Thediagnosis is confirmed by the presence of papillae on thetarsal conjunctiva of the upper lid and Tranta&#x02032;s dots at limbusor pigmentation involving bulbar conjunctiva. It is mostlyseen in children and adolescents with the classic symptomof itching. Vernal ulcer is usually unilateral and involves thesuperior 1/3rd of the cornea. In a few patients, it may lead toplaque formation and the shield ulcer is graded according tothe density of the plaque<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>].</p><p>Staphylococcal marginal keratitis is mostly bilateral,involves the lower half of cornea, adjacent to the limbus, havinga clear zone of cornea between the lesion and limbus [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>].Being uniform in size, discrete and horizontally oval, theremay be an oval or round scar due to previous attacks. Mostof these patients may have associated blepharitis, meibomitisand rarely acne rosacea.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>Phlyctenular keratitis is often noticed in children witha history of recurrent attacks; lesion may show superficialvascularization like pannus or leash of vessels with scarringdue to previous attacks. Even though tuberculosis etiology wasattributed often, other micro-organisms like <italic>staphylococcus</italic> and<italic>candida</italic> can also cause similar lesions.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> Phlyctenular keratitisrepresents type IV hypersensitivity response.</p><p>Differentiating PUK from other infective peripheral corneallesions is mostly based on clinical diagnosis. Mooren ulcerwill have a typical lesion in the interpalpebral area, peripheralgutter with edematous or necrotic over-hanging edges [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>].Sclera is not involved, which aids in differentiating fromrheumatoid and other autoimmune diseases. In 35-40% ofpatients, Mooren ulcer is bilateral and the reported risk factorsare corneal surgery, corneal trauma and hookworm infestation.Natural evolution of Mooren ulcer could be either perforationor conjunctivilization of Descemet&#x02032;s bed resulting in blindness.Mooren ulcer could occur in any sex and age group.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Clinical Diagnosis of Microbial and Viral Keratitis</title><p>Why is the clinical diagnosis of infective keratitis crucial?Even well-established laboratories can grow up to 60-70% ofocular pathogens from the material sent for culture.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> So, themanagement of rest of 30-40% of patients with corneal ulcersolely depends on clinical diagnosis, a reality we have toaccept even today. Infective keratitis developing after LASIKposes a problem to make clinical diagnosis due to the level ofthe lesion and steroid use. Clinicians should be aware of thecommonly reported microbes from these patients (e.g., <italic>Nocardia</italic>,<italic>mycobacteriae</italic> and filamentous fungi).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> The clinical diagnosisof microbial keratitis often relies on a thorough history,especially history of infectious exposure, epidemiologicaltrends and the morphological features of corneal inflammation.Ophthalmologists use clinical clues to recognize ocular surfaceinfection. Some distinctive, though not pathognomonic, signsunique to the causative organism may help to differentiatebacterial, fungal and amoebic pathogens of the cornea.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></p><sec><title>Bacterial keratitis</title><p>All over the world, bacterial keratitis is more common than fungalkeratitis, but this does not hold true for India and other tropicalcountries.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> In our country, the following risk factors have beenidentified as leading to corneal ulcer: trauma, xerophthalmia,measles, malnutrition, diarrhea, ocular surface problem, eyelidabnormalities and rarely contact lenses. Trauma to the corneaaccounts for 60-68% of cases developing corneal ulcer.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></p><p>The clinical picture may vary especially when the ulcershave been previously treated. However, a few classical clinicaldescriptions are useful. For example, Gram-positive organismstend to produce discrete, small abscess-like lesions and Gram-negative bacteria are more likely to cause diffuse, rapidlyspreading necrotic lesions. Watering, pain and vision loss aremore severe in rapidly spreading bacterial ulcer caused by<italic>Pseudomonas</italic> and <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> species. Indolentulcers due to <italic>Moraxella</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus spp.</italic> may be quietand less symptomatic. Marked lid edema and conjunctivalchemosis and purulent exudate are commonly associated withGram-negative organisms, especially gonococcal infection.Hemorrhagic hypopyon is attributed to either pneumococcalor HSV keratitis. If there is purulent or mucopurulent dischargefrom lacrimal sac, the keratitis could be due to <italic>Pneumococcus</italic> in90% of cases<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>]. Gonococcal ulcer was commonin Indian infants but due to improved antenatal and postnatal care, werarely see this ulcer nowadays.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></p><p>Among the causative organisms for infectious keratitis,<italic>Nocardia</italic> is uncommon. Trauma with organic matter or drysoil is found to be the major predisposing factor. Typically, theulcer runs a slow and protracted course. The lesion appears asa cracked windshield or resembling a group of pinhead-sizeyellowish white infiltrates arranged in a wreath-like fashionwhich is considered as the classic clinical picture<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig.6</xref>]. The ulcer remains superficial and may have associated hypopyon.The ulcer does not respond to conventional treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Viral keratitis</title><sec><title>HSV</title><p>Even though Herpes simplex involves all the layers of cornea,we will limit the discussion to epithelial keratitis only.</p><p>HSV causes a spectrum of ocular diseases, but mostprominent among them are epithelial and stromal keratitis.Recurrence in the same eye is the hallmark of this commonviral infection involving the human cornea.</p></sec><sec><title>Epithelial keratitis</title><p>Symptoms include photophobia/blurred vision, irritation/painand a thin watery discharge occasionally associated with coldsores around the lips and nose or genital sores.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>Corneal vesicles in the epithelium are one of the first manifestations of acute HSVinfection, which manifest as a fine punctate keratitis or stellatewhitish opaque plaques that coalesce into dendritic lesions over24 h.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref> Eruptions of the corneal epithelium due toHSV are characteristically thin, branching dendritic ulcerations, wider,branching dendrogeographic ulcers or map-shaped geographiclesions. The edges of the ulcer become slightly raised due to thepresence of edematous epithelial cells.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> Corneal sensation maybe temporarily reduced or absent in 60% of affected patients.Stromal reaction is usually absent or mild and confined to theanterior layers. Most dendritic ulcers will heal spontaneouslywithin 2 weeks. Trophic or metaherpetic ulceration appears as anovoid lesion which runs a protracted course. The edges are rolledand gray in appearance and do not stain well with rose bengal.The base of the ulcer will stain with fluorescein or rose bengal.The defect may persist for weeks or months carrying with it arisk of melting and perforation. This entity should be thought ofwhen we manage a case of nonhealing corneal ulcer. Sometimes,it is very difficult to differentiate from suppurative keratitis ofnonviral origin [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>]. Presence of old scar or vascularizationmay help in arriving at a correct diagnosis. History of recurrentattacks also helps.</p></sec><sec><title>HZO</title><p>Fifty to 72% of patients with periocular zoster will have ocularinvolvement. The frontal branch of the trigeminal nerve is byfar the most frequently involved nerve.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> Involvement of thenasociliary branch can often herald ophthalmic involvementdue to its innervation to the eye. The classic Hutchinson&#x02032;s sign(eruptions on the side of the tip of the nose) is evidence ofnasociliary involvement and has 85% reliability that the eyewill be involved.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> Herpes zoster begins with a prodrome ofsevere one-sided headache, malaise, fever and chills, followedby erythema and papules in 2 or 3 days. Occasionally, zostermay develop without vesicles and rarely can affect both sidesof the ophthalmic division.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> Previous attack of chickenpoxmay be present. When a young patient gets zoster, one shouldalways rule out HIV infection or other immune-compromiseddiseases.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Fungal keratitis</title><p>This is more prevalent in tropical countries and frequentlyaffects young rural men engaged in agriculture and other ruralpopulation. The incidence ranges from 35 to 50% in India.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>Keratomycoses most often picks up healthy cornea exposed dueto minor abrasions. Chronic ocular surface problem, steroid use,immunocompromised host, diabetics and contact lens wearersmay rarely get fungal ulcer. In 2006, an epidemic of <italic>fusarium</italic>keratitis was reported following the use of contaminatedcontact lens cleaner.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref> In India, <italic>aspergillus</italic> and <italic>fusarium</italic>species are frequently isolated as causative agents.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></p><sec><title>Clinical features</title><p>Classically, fungal ulcer has been described to commenceinsidiously and run an indolent course. General featuresinclude a thickened epithelium, linear infiltrates oftenassociated with satellite lesions, the presence of an endothelialplaque and posterior corneal abscess, an immune ring infiltrate,a cheesy hypopyon (sometimes hemorrhagic) noted to oftenwax and wane, and fibrinoid aqueous reaction. The ulcers oftenappear dry, but most often it is not true. The ulcer base has araised, wet, soft and creamy grayish-white or yellowish-whiteinfiltrate without mucus or exudates. In case of pigmentedfungi, the surface appears dry, tough and leathery [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>]. Inthe early stages, a dendritic pattern may be seen which is oftenmisdiagnosed as HSV keratitis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>]. Absence of lidedema, minimal conjunctival injection and feathery borders in a healthyadult from rural agrarian population with a recent injury to thecornea with organic matter should strongly favor a diagnosisof fungal ulcer, unless otherwise proved.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></p></sec></sec><sec><title>Acanthamoeba keratitis</title><p>Acanthamoeba keratitis is a painful, sight-threatening anddifficult-to-treat corneal infection caused by the parasite<italic>acanthamoeba</italic>.</p><p><italic>Acanthamoebae</italic> are ubiquitous in nature. At least eightpathogenic <italic>acanthamoeba</italic> subtypes cause keratitis. The first caseof keratitis in humans was identified in 1973 in an Americanfarmer with ocular trauma.</p><p>The incidence of acanthamoeba keratitis is about 1% amongculture-positive infective keratitis in India.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> In Europe andthe United States, the incidence among contact lens wearersis 1.65 to 2.01 per million contact lens wearers per year byepidemiologic estimation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref> In India, contact lens wearing israrely associated with acanthamoeba keratitis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></p><sec><title>Clinical features</title><p>Suspicion is paramount. It runs a chronic course and diagnosisis often made several weeks after the onset with a poor responseto conventional treatment regimen for an infective keratitis.It is often misdiagnosed as HSV keratitis, fungal infection ortopical anesthetic abuse. Even though pain out of proportionhas been described as a prominent symptom by many, it is ofthe same severity as reported by patients having other typesof keratitis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref> The disease is usually unilateral, but rarely maybe bilateral in contact lens wearers.</p><p>The corneal epithelium appears sick, edematous, looseand stroma may be hazy; and sometimes mimics an epithelialkeratopathy. Radial perineuritis, one of the early clinicalsigns, is not a, common feature in noncontact lens wearers.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>Hypopyon is common. In well-established cases, the densestromal ring infiltrate at mid-periphery of the cornea, sparingthe pupillary area is considered as the diagnostic clinical sign ofacanthamoeba keratitis [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref>]. Associated scleral involvementnear the limbus could be seen in inappropriately treated cases.Co-infection with bacteria and fungi is not uncommon and isreported as 2-3% in India.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></p><p>Rare form of suppurative keratitis caused by atypical<italic>mycobacteriae</italic> presents with a deep corneal or plaque-like lesionon the endothelium.</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Source of Support: Nil</p></fn><fn><p>Conflict of Interest: None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Current perspectives in infectious keratitis</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>1994</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10576995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arffa</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Grayson&#x02032;s Diseases of the cornea</source><year>1997</year><edition>4th ed</edition><publisher-loc>St.Louis</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangwan</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amniotic membrane transplantation in the management of shield ulcers of vernal keratoconjunctivitis</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1218</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11425678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cetinkaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Akova</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pediatric ocular acne rosacea: Long-term treatment with systemic antibiotics</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17056363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hookworm infestation as a risk factor for Mooren&#x02032;s ulcer in south India</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2007</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17123614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourcier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Borderie</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaumeil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial keratitis: Predisposing factors, clinical and microbiological review of 300 cases</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2003</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12812870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnenfeld</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Azar</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmon</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pflugfelder</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Infectious keratitis after laser-in-situ keratomileusis: Results of ASCRS survey</article-title><source>J Cataract Refract Surg</source><year>2003</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>2001</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14604725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lingappan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelmus</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The clinical diagnosis of microbial keratitis</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2007</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>940</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17408586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharathi</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meenakshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaniappan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aetiological diagnosis of microbial keratitis in South India: A study of 1618 cases</article-title><source>Indian J Med Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17657018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharathi</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meenakshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shivkumar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaniappan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of bacterial keratitis in a referral centre in south India</article-title><source>Indian J Med Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17643035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mruthyunjay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinicomicrobiological review of Nocardia keratitis</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9436875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liesegang</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of herpes simplex virus keratitis and anterior uveitis</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10090358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreyer</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herpes virus infections of the anterior segment</article-title><source>Int Ophthalmol Clin</source><year>1996</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8989597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavan-Langston</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herpes simplex ocular inflammatory disease</article-title><source>Int Ophthalmol Clin</source><year>2006</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16770152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal keratitis</article-title><source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15232472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alfonso</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantu-Dibildox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Munir</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02032;Brien</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insurgence of Fusarium keratitis associated with contact lens wear</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>941</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16769827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharathi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meenakshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Padmavathy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalitha</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study of the spectrum of Acanthamoeba Keratitis: A three-year study at a tertiary eye care referral center in southIndia</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2007</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaunberg</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnow</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epidemic of Acanthamoeba keratitis: Where do we stand?</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9436873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasricha</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acanthamoeba keratitis in non-contact lens wearers in India</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>2004</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>1430</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15477452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Burman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nirmalan</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-contact lens related Acanthamoeba keratitis at a tertiary eye care center in south India: Implications for eye careprograms in the region</article-title><source>Med Sci Monit</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient characteristics, diagnosis and treatment of non-contact lens related Acanthamoeba keratitis</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2000</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1103</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11004092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manikandan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhaskar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Revathy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Narendran</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Panneerselvam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acanthamoeba keratitis: A six-year epidemiological review from tertiary care eye hospital in south India</article-title><source>Indian J Med Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17642743</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Mooren ulcer with perforation</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Shield ulcer with plaque</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Marginal keratitis</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Mooren ulcer</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Bacterial ulcer (Pneumococcal)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Nocardial keratitis</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Neurotrophic sterile ulcer</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Pigmented fungal ulcer</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Early fungal keratitis</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g009"/></fig><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Acanthamoeba keratitis</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 10</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-203-g010"/></fig></floats-group></article>