<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17699952</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636029</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2007_55_5_383_33829</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pterygium-induced corneal refractive changes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Maheshwari</surname><given-names>Sejal</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><aff>Cornea and Refractive Surgery, Shri Ganapati Netralaya, Devalgaonmantha Road, Jalna - 431 203, Maharashtra, India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Sejal Maheshwari, Cornea and Refractive Surgery, Shri Ganapati Netralaya, Devalgaonmantha Road, Jalna - 431 203, Maharashtra, India. Email: <email>sejalm@netralaya.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Sep-Oct</season><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>55</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>To study the effect of pterygium on corneal topography, a retrospective analysis of 151 eyes with primary pterygia was done. All cases underwent videokeratography preoperatively and one month postoperatively. Statistical analysis of average corneal power (ACP), corneal astigmatism, surface regularity index (SRI) and surface asymmetry index (SAI) was done before and one month after surgery. Topographic indices were compared statistically for various grades of pterygia. Increase in the grade of pterygia had a significant effect on topographic indices. Corneal astigmatism reduced from 4.40&#x000b1;3.64 diopter (D) to 1.55&#x000b1;1.63D (<italic> P</italic>  value &#x0003c; 0.001) following surgery. The regularity of corneal surface improved and asymmetry of the cornea reduced one month after surgery. Pterygium leads to significant changes in corneal refractive status, which increase with the increase in the grade of pterygia and improve following pterygium excision.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Astigmatism</kwd><kwd>corneal topography</kwd><kwd>pterygium</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Pterygium is commonly seen in India, a part of the "pterygium belt" described by Cameron.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>  The indications for pterygium surgery are (a) visual impairment; (b) recurrent inflammation; (c) motility restriction; (d) cosmetic disfigurement.</p><p>Pterygium leads to a considerable effect on corneal refractive status which has been previously measured in various studies by refraction,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>  keratometry<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>  and corneal topography.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>  In the present study pre and postoperative corneal topography was evaluated for each case.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>A retrospective analysis of 151 eyes with primary pterygia was done. Patients with history of trauma, previous surgery, patients having corneal scars were not included in the study. On slit-lamp examination with slit beam focused on the nasal limbus, pterygium was graded depending on the extent of corneal involvement:</p><p>Grade I - between limbus and a point midway between limbus and pupillary margin</p><p>Grade II - head of the pterygium present between a point midway between limbus and pupillary margin and pupillary margin (nasal papillary margin in case of nasal pterygium and temporal margin in case of temporal pterygium)</p><p>Grade III - crossing pupillary margin</p><p>Corneal topography analysis was obtained with computerized videokeratography (TMS -2, Computed Anatomy Inc, New York, NY), which was performed by an experienced optometrist one day prior to surgery and one month after it[Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>].</p><p>All eyes underwent pterygium excision with conjunctival autograft transplantation.</p><p>Results were expressed as an arithmetic mean &#x000b1; standard deviation. Values were compared against the grades of pterygium using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). Statistical analysis of average corneal power (ACP), corneal astigmatism was calculated from the Sim K values, surface regulatory index (SRI), surface asymmetry (SAI), min K and refractive cylinder was done before and one month after pterygium surgery using paired <italic> t</italic> -test. Corneal cylinder and refractive cylinder were compared using Mann-Whitney test; corneal astigmatism amongst various grades was compared using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA with Bonferroni&#x02032;s correction of <italic> P</italic>  values for multiple comparison).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Preoperative topographic indices in various grades of pterygium have been shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. Corneal astigmatism, SRI and SAI were seen to increase with the increase in the grade of pterygium. Comparing the corneal astigmatism amongst the various grades of pterygium <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">[Table 2]</xref> a statistically significant increase in astigmatism was noted with the increase in the grade from I to III.</p><p>The comparison and analysis of pre and postoperative values are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>. The mean ACP increased from 42.91&#x000b1;2.20 diopter (D) to 44.25&#x000b1;1.77D (<italic> P</italic>  value &#x0003c; 0.001) after pterygium excision.</p><p>The mean preoperative topographic astigmatism was 4.40&#x000b1;3.64D and reduced postoperatively to 1.55&#x000b1;1.63D (<italic> P</italic>  value &#x0003c; 0.001).</p><p>Refraction was done in 140 eyes; in 11 eyes it was not possible due to cataract. The refractive cylinder before surgery was 1.94&#x000b1;2.24D, which was less than the topographic cylinder of 4.25&#x000b1;3.63D (<italic> P</italic>  value &#x0003c; 0.001). The refractive cylinder reduced from 1.94&#x000b1;2.24D to 0.78&#x000b1;1.07D.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>A pterygium-induced refractive change often leads to visual impairment. These changes are localized and cannot be measured accurately either by refraction or keratometry. In 140 eyes in which refractions were recorded there was poor correlation between the magnitude of refractive cylinder and topographic cylinder. This can be due to the hemi-astigmatic nature of the induced changes. During manifest refraction patient deals with two images, one from the more spherical temporal cornea and one from the flatter nasal cornea. The patient preferentially views the more spherical image and therefore the corneal changes are incompletely reflected in the refraction.</p><p>Keratometry measures only the central cornea and peripheral cornea is ignored and hence the results can be erroneous in eyes with pterygium. Computerized videokeratography remains the best tool for evaluating the corneal surface changes induced by pterygium.</p><p>Pterygium was seen to have a considerable effect on topographic indices in the present series. Flattening was seen in the horizontal meridian, which was associated with astigmatism. The exact mechanism of flattening is not clear. It is thought to be caused by the formation of tear meniscus between the corneal apex and the elevated pterygium, causing an apparent flattening of the normal corneal curvature.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref> </p><p>Lin and Stern found a significant correlation between the pterygium size and corneal astigmatism; they reported pterygium to induce significant degrees of astigmatism once it exceeded&#x0003e; 45% of the radius.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>  Tomidokoro <italic> et al</italic> . evaluated the percentage extension of pterygium on cornea and found larger pterygia to adversely affect astigmatism, asymmetry and irregularity of the cornea.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>  In the current study pterygia were divided into grades depending on the extension of pterygium on the cornea. Grade II or larger pterygium was associated with increase in astigmatism, asymmetry and irregularity. The ACP reduced significantly in Grade II or larger pterygium. Hence, for patients with pterygium requiring cataract surgery, decision of surgery should be taken depending on the grade of pterygium; in cases with Grade I, atrophic and non-progressive pterygium one can consider cataract surgery directly. However, pterygium Grade II or larger significantly affects the refractive component of cornea which can lead to erroneous intraocular lens power calculation and post-cataract refractive surprise. Hence in cases with pterygium Grade II or larger, a stepwise approach should be followed; pterygium excision should be performed prior to cataract surgery. By time-course analysis, cornea has been shown to stabilize one month after pterygium surgery. Hence, cataract surgery or refractive surgery if considered should be performed at least one month after pterygium surgery.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>  Simultaneous cataract and pterygium surgery should not be done in cases with large pterygium as one may have an unexpected refractive surprise postoperatively.</p><p>Stern and Lin reported improvement in topographic indices in 16 eyes; they reported corneal astigmatism to reduce from 5.93&#x000b1;2.46D to 1.92&#x000b1;1.68D.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>  Tomidokoro <italic> et al</italic> . analyzed 119 eyes and reported increase in corneal spherical power from 43&#x000b1;1.18 to 45.2&#x000b1;1.6D.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>  Yagmur <italic> et al</italic> . studied the effect of pterygium excision in 30 eyes and found topographic astigmatism to reduce from 4.65&#x000b1;3.02 to 2.33&#x000b1;2.26D.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>  In the current study all the topographic parameters were seen to improve significantly following pterygium excision.</p><p>The relationship between the preoperative refractive cylinder and postoperative refractive cylinder (Pearson&#x02032;s correlation coefficient, r =. 2986) was expressed by the following equation:</p><p>Postoperative refractive cylinder = 0.283+0.266 x preoperative refractive cylinder.</p><p>Computerized videokeratography remains the best tool in evaluating pterygium-associated corneal changes. The corneal changes are seen to improve significantly following pterygium excision.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demartini</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vastine</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pterygium</article-title><source>Surgical interventions Corneal and External diseases</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>Orlando, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Grune and Straton</publisher-name><fpage>141</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chee</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Refractive change following pterygium surgery</article-title><source>CLAO J</source><year>1998</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9571272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maheshwari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of pterygium excision on pterygium-induced astigmatism</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2003</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12831155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Norn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Astigmatism and surface phenomena in pterygium</article-title><source>Acta Ophthalmol (Copenh)</source><year>1980</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6156565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between pterygium size and induced corneal astigmatism</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9436877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of pterygium excision on induced corneal topographic abnormalities</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9436876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomidokoro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Samejima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokunaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshika</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of pterygium on corneal spherical power and astigmatism</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2000</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>1568</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10919910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cinal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Demirok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Topuz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of pterygium surgery on corneal topography</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Surg Lasers</source><year>2001</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11195741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yagmar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Altan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozcan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ersoz</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual acuity and corneal topographic changes related with pterygium surgery</article-title><source>J Refract Surg</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15796222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Garbus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonnell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonnell</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conjunctival pterygia. Mechanism of corneal topographic changes</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>1990</year><volume>9</volume><lpage>200</lpage><fpage>4</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Corneal topography of a patient with grade II Pterygium showing flattening in the horizontal meridian</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-55-383-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Corneal topography of the same patient 1 month after surgery</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-55-383-g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Grade of pterygium and topographic indices</p></caption><alt-text>Table 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-55-383-g003"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison between corneal astigmatism among various grades</p></caption><alt-text>Table 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-55-383-g004"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Pre and postoperative statistics</p></caption><alt-text>Table 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-55-383-g005"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>