<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18711278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_5_429_42426</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Bovine pericardium in treating large corneal perforation secondary to alkali injury: A case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>Rajesh K</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mokhtar</surname><given-names>Ezanee</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Ophthalmology, School of Medical Sciences, UniversitySains Malaysia, Malaysia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Rajesh Kumar Khanna, 17.6.15, PalladiumCondominium, Jalan Gurney-2, 54000 Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. Email: <email>nidhirajeshkhanna@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Sep-Oct</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date></history><abstract><p>To describe use of a locally processed bovine pericardium (BP) tocover a large central corneal perforation following alkali injuryand discuss postoperative outcome.</p><p>A 27-year-old Malay male patient presented two weeks afteralkali splashed in his left eye while working. A clinical diagnosisof left central corneal ulcer with limbal ischemia following alkaliinjury with secondary infection was made. After failed medicaltherapy, we performed a Gunderson conjunctival flap underlocal anesthesia that retracted after one week and resulted ina large central corneal perforation with surrounding stromalthinning. The perforation was covered with a locally processedBP xenograft (Lyolemb) supplied by the National Tissue Bank,University Sains Malaysia. Nine months follow-up showed awell-taken graft without any exposure/dehiscence and minimalinflammation.</p><p>Amniotic membrane transplantation when used as a patch graftneeds an urgent tectonic graft to promote corneal stability inpatients with severe corneal thinning. The use of processed BPcan be a viable option in treating such cases.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Bovine pericardium</kwd><kwd>chemical injury</kwd><kwd>corneal perforation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Severe corneal ulceration might lead to descematoceleformation and in turn imminent danger of perforation.Various therapeutic measures range from eye patching,bandage soft contact lenses, cyanoacrylate application,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> tosurgical procedures such as tarsorrhaphy,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> conjunctival flap,amniotic membrane transplantation (AMT)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> and penetratingkeratoplasty (PKP). Amniotic membrane transplantation asa patch graft needs an urgent tectonic procedure in severecorneal thinning.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></p><p>Penetrating keratoplasty is an established modalityof treating large corneal perforations. Processed bovinepericardium (BP) has been widely used as a wrap for orbitalimplants due to its excellent suture retention and strength. It iswell tolerated with minimal inflammation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> Easyavailability and low cost make it an alternative modality of treatment,especially if a donor cornea is not available. We report acase of large corneal perforation with surrounding stromalinflammation treated with locally processed BP.</p><sec sec-type=""><title>Case Report</title><p>A 27-year-old Malay male patient presented two weeksafter alkali splashed into his left eye while working. Prior toreporting to us, the patient consulted a general practitionerwho prescribed some topical eye drops (details of thetreatment were not available) and the eye condition worsened.Anterior segment examination revealed a central cornealulcer (1 &#x000d7; 1 mm) with stromal infiltration (4 &#x000d7; 6 mm), limbalischemia, normal anterior chamber depth and visual acuityof counting fingers. A gentle B-scan ruled out any posteriorsegment abnormality.</p><p>A clinical diagnosis of left corneal ulcer with limbal ischemiasecondary to alkali injury with secondary infection was made.Culture from corneal scraping was negative. Despite intensivetherapy with oral (Tab Ciprobay 500 mg twice daily, Bayer)and topical ciprofloxacin (Gutt Ciloxan 0.3% hourly, Alcon)(no topical steroids used) with other supportive therapy (TabVitamin C 1 g daily, Pharmaniaga), further deterioration ledto formation of central corneal perforation with surroundingstromal thinning and flat anterior chamber. The visual acuitywas inaccurate projection of light rays.</p><p>We performed a Gunderson conjunctival flap under localanesthesia (LA), which retracted and failed after one week.Slit-lamp examination revealed a large central corneal perforation(4 &#x000d7; 5 mm) with surrounding stromal thinning involving two-thirds of the cornea without any signs of infection.</p><p>In order to maintain the shape of the eyeball and due to theproblem of non-availability of donor cornea, we decided to useprocessed BP xenograft (Lyolemb) supplied by National TissueBank, Universiti Sains Malaysia after obtaining the consent of thepatient. A 360&#x000b0; peritomy was done and the graft was sutured with7-0 polyglycolic and polylactic acids (Vicryl) to the perilimbalarea with conjunctival advancement. Topical (Gutt Ciloxan 0.3%hourly, Alcon) and oral ciprofloxacin (Tab Ciprobay 500 mgtwice daily, Bayer) was prescribed in the postoperative period[<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>]. The details of anterior segment were difficult toassess due to conjunctival advancement. Nine months follow-upshowed a well-taken graft without any exposure/dehiscence andminimal inflammation [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>]. Slit-lamp examination couldnot reveal the details of the anterior chamber and beyond due toconjunctival advancement and vision was noted as perceptionof light with inadequate projection of rays.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>Conjunctival flap is unlikely to seal large corneal perforationsassociated with corneal melting following chemical injury.Efficacy of AMT alone or with glue in treating small cornealperforation has been well established but found unable topromote corneal stability in patients with severe cornealthinning and therefore, an additional urgent tectonic procedurehas to be undertaken.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Non-availability of donor cornea posesa considerable problem in some countries.</p><p>Processed BP is a tough lyophilised collagen sheet usedas a surgical armamentarium in wrapping orbital implants.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> It renders the material antigenically inert and adds to itsstrength, pliability and longevity.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> It has been shown to bewell tolerated with minimal inflammation in animal studies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>Although theoretic concerns about prion disease can be raised,no evidence of this problem has been reported from over90,000 human implantations.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> Devron reported no significantophthalmic reactions due to this xenograft in his cases of orbitalimplants.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></p><p>At the National Tissue bank, Universiti Sains Malaysia,the procured pericardium sheet was washed using chemicalagent (sterile phosphate buffer at pH 7.4) and frozen to &#x02212;40&#x000b0;C.It was then freeze-dried and packaged in double-layer plasticbag. The processed BP was radio-sterilized at 2.5 mega radsusing gamma radiation and was then ready for use.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> We usedthis locally processed BP in our case. Nine months follow-upshowed good results.</p><p>To our knowledge, there has been no reported case usingBP in corneal perforation. Its use in complicated ocular surfacediseases such as large corneal perforation with corneal meltingcan be promising. Its use needs to be further studied moreextensively as an alternative graft material in large cornealperforations.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Slansky</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Refojo</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohlman</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use ofadhesive for closure of corneal perforations</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>1968</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5699321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azuara-Blanco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dua</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amniotic membranetransplantation for ocular surface reconstruction</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>1999</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10434859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prabhasawat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesavibul</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Komolsuradej</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single andmultilayer amniotic membrane transplantation for persistentcorneal epithelial defect with and without stromal thinning andperforation</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2001</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>1455</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11734521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeBacker</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutton</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Proia</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Holck</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bovinepericardium versus homologous sclera as wrapping materialsfor hydroxyapatite ocular implants: an animal study</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Plastic Reconstr Surg</source><year>1999</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The sclera, the prion and the ophthalmologist</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2002</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11973259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bovine spongiform encephalopathy</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>1988</year><volume>296</volume><fpage>1581</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3135018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devron</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early wound dehiscence with use of hydroxyapatiteorbital implant covered with calf pericardium</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2001</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11351973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rushdan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamzah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arif</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use ofbovine xenograft in reconstruction of traumatic anterior cranialfossa bone defects involving the frontal sinus</article-title><source>Ann Transplant</source><year>1999</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10853777</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Whitish tissue underneath sutures indicating bovinepericardium graft with limbal ischemia one-week postoperatively</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-429-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>A well-taken bovine pericardium graft with early symblepharonand minimal inflammation nine-months postoperatively</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-429-g002"/></fig></floats-group></article>