<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18579988</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636175</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_4_297_39664</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Amniotic membrane transplant with superficial keratectomy in superficialcorneal degenerations: Efficacy in a rural population of north India</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>Aparna</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>Uma</given-names></name><degrees>MS, FRCS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><degrees>MS, FAMS</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Glaucoma Services (AR), RP Centre, All India Institute of MedicalSciences, Ansari Nagar, New Delhi, ICARE Eye Hospital and GlaucomaResearch Centre (US, AKG), Sector-26, Noida, UP, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Aparna Rao, Glaucoma services, Dr. R.P. Centre, AllIndia Institute of Medical Sciences, Ansari Nagar, New Delhi, India.Email:<email>vinodini10375@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Aug</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>3</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>To evaluate the applicability and efficacy of superficial keratectomy with transplantation of preservedamniotic membrane in superficial corneal degenerations in a rural population of Northern India in terms ofvisual improvement and surface regularization.</p></sec><sec><title>Settings:</title><p>Peripheral referral center in rural north India.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>This was a prospective non-comparative interventional case series where 24 eyes of20 farmers from peripheral rural areas (M:F = 19:1) with visually significant superficial degenerative disorders(15 eyes with climatic droplet keratopathy one of which was associated with Salzmann nodular degenerationand nine eyes with band-shaped keratopathy) were subjected to amniotic membrane transplantation (single ormultiple layer) combined with superficial keratectomy. Subjective and objective outcomes after surgery wereevaluated and analyzed and statistical significance of the outcomes in various disorders was evaluated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Eighty-eight per cent (21 eyes) had symptomatic relief from distressing preoperative symptomswhile postoperative visual improvement by two or more lines was achieved in 23 eyes (96%) over a meanfollow-up period of 26.8 &#x000b1; 10.2 months. The surface irregularity present preoperatively was relieved in23 cases while postoperative decline of vision with visually significant scarring was seen in one case (4%),which was labeled as failure.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>Amniotic membrane transplant with superficial keratectomy helped achieve subjective comfort,visual rehabilitation and clinical regularization of the corneal surface in superficial corneal degenerationsduring the mean followup of 26.8 &#x000b1; 10.2 months in rural setups.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Amniotic membrane</kwd><kwd>phototherapeutic keratectomy</kwd><kwd>superficial corneal degeneration</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Superficial corneal degenerations like climatic dropletkeratopathy (CDK), band-shaped keratopathy (BSK), andSalzmann nodular degeneration cause pain, irritation,irregularity of the corneal surface, deterioration of vision byinvolving the central visual axis and vascularization accountingfor a resultant decrease in the quality of life.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> The older methodsof treatment for these disorders (like lubricants, contact lens)provide only temporary symptomatic relief while moreinvasive procedures like penetrating or lamellar keratoplastyare fraught with many other problems like the need for long-term follow-up and medications, high rate of complications likerejection or infections.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> These are therefore not suitable optionsfor patients from remote rural areas with poor follow-up andquestionable compliance. Amniotic membrane transplanthas been proven effective for ocular surface reconstructionand regularization after pterygium surgery, ocular burns andother cicatrizing corneal conditions owing to its advantageousproperties like anti-inflammatory, aid in epithelization and anti-scarring properties in particular.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Newer modes of treatmentfor superficial corneal degeneration include phototherapeutickeratectomy (PTK) which calls for expensive instrumentationthat may not be feasible in rural areas.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> By thisstudy, we therefore endeavored to study the surgical outcomes afterkeratectomy coupled with amniotic membrane transplant inpatients with superficial corneal degenerations like CDK andBSK in a rural setup.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>This was a prospective non-comparative interventionalcase series of 24 eyes of 20 patients with superficial cornealdegenerations, namely CDK, BSK and Salzmann nodulardegeneration, who were subjected to superficial keratectomywith preserved amniotic membrane graft at our peripheralreferral center in rural north India between June 2004 and July2006. This study was conducted in accordance with the ethicalstandards (institutional) and with the Helsinki Declaration.</p><p>Detailed history was obtained from all the patients, includingtheir preoperative symptoms, history of previous medicationsor relevant surgical history. Preoperative assessment of all thepatients included the best corrected visual acuity, applanationtonometry and fundus examination. Ultrasound (B scan)examination was done for assessing the posterior segmentin cases of media opacities precluding fundus examination.The corneal pathology was assessed by slit-lamp examinationin terms of the type of lesion, the area involved and depth ofinvolvement and extent of preoperative thinning. Ultrasoundpachymetry was attempted in all cases to assess the cornealthickness. Qualitative placido disc images were studied atbaseline and at each follow-up in all the cases to assess theamount of surface irregularity in the involved eye.</p><p>Patients with corneal perforation or active ulcers, highintraocular pressure, coexisting fundus abnormalities,significant cataract, associated surface problems like trichiasis,entropion and most importantly, patients with corneal thinning&#x0003e;30%, involvement of the middle or posterior stroma wereexcluded from the study. All patients were counseled in detailabout their condition and a well-informed consent, explainingthe purpose and potential risk of surgery, was taken from thembefore surgery.</p><sec><title>Surgical technique</title><p> Preserved amniotic membrane for this study was procuredfrom LV Prasad Eye Institute, Hyderabad. Frozen pieces of themembrane preserved in Dulbecco&#x02032;s modified Eagle&#x02032;s medium(DMEM) as 4 &#x000d7; 4 cm pieces and spread on nitrocellulose paperwere used for the study (prepared and preserved according tothat prescribed by Kim and Tseng).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></p><p>All eyes were operated by the same surgeons (AR and US).The procedure was performed under peribulbar anesthesia.The level and extent of dissection was determined based onpreoperative findings, i.e. extent of involvement of the cornea,depth of involvement and the amount of corneal thinning.After epithelial debridement with a micro sponge or crescentknife in the involved area [Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1A">1A</xref>], lamellar dissection wasperformed in the involved area. Overzealous dissection wasavoided in eyes with preexisting corneal thinning. Ethylenediamine tetra acetic acid (EDTA) (if available) was used in caseswith BSK after epithelectomy to aid in the lamellar dissectionand removal of calcium deposits.</p><p>The membrane was sutured to the involved ocular surfacewith the epithelial side down and secured with interrupted10-0 nylon sutures to the cornea [Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1B">1B</xref>]. Limbus to limbustotal cover was done in cases with diffuse lesions while themembrane was cut to the desired size in selected cases withless extensive involvement. Multiple layers of the membranewere used in cases with preoperative thinning &#x0003e;20% with onelayer used as filler (placed epithelial side down, left unsutured)and another outer layer sutured to the cornea, epithelial sideup. A large therapeutic contact lens (No 16) was placed overthe membrane for comfort of the patient.</p><p>Postoperatively, the patients were routinely treated withtopical antibiotic drops (Tobramycin, 0.14%) and cycloplegics(tropicamide 0.5%). Cornea was assessed with regard toepithelization (demonstrated by regularity of the surface inall areas and restoration of normal luster of the cornea underthe contact lens), surface regularity of the cornea, residualdisease and scarring. The amniotic membrane was inspectedfor evidence of any retraction or loss of the membrane in thepostoperative period. Bandage contact lens was left <italic>in situ</italic>till the interrupted sutures securing the graft were removed(recycling of the lens done every week). Suture removalwas done by three weeks and any complication noted in thepostoperative period was identified and treated accordingly.The patients were followed up on an outpatient basis (three-monthly). In the postoperative period, complaints pertaining torelief from the preoperative symptoms like watering, irritation,foreign body sensation were assessed through enquiry fromthe patients (no grading of the symptoms was done due toinconsistent responses from the patients with regards to theseverity). Placido images were acquired in the postoperativeperiod after suture removal and during each follow-up.</p><p>The results were analyzed and divided into subjective andobjective success or failure (depending on set criteria) and thecauses of failure, if any, were evaluated. Subjective success wasdefined as relief of all preoperative symptoms and subjectivevisual recovery. Partial success was defined as relief of only onesymptom (watering, irritation with or without visual recovery)or only subjective improvement in vision and no relief of othersymptoms. Failure was defined as deterioration of preoperativevision with or without relief of symptoms. Objective successwas defined as visual recovery postoperatively by at leasttwo or more lines, mild (not visually significant) scarring,regular corneal surface and qualitative improvement in surfaceregularity by placido disc images. Partial success was definedas having moderate scarring with reduced vision, residualdisease, recurrence, or surface irregularity (visually significant).Failure was defined by decrease in postoperative vision, needfor repeat surgery or need for penetrating keratoplasty.</p><p>Statistical analysis was done using SPSS version 10 andstatistical significance was defined as <italic>P</italic> value &#x0003c;0.05 with student&#x02033;t&#x02033; test. Correlation was done using Pearson&#x02032;s correlationcoefficient.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Twenty-four eyes of 20 patients (15 CDK, of which one wasassociated with Salzmann degeneration, nine BSK) from peripheralrural areas in north India were included in the study. No ocularpathology was found in any case of BSK (ruled out on slit-lampand fundus examination); though a screening for systemic causescould not be done in these rural patients, systemic examinationdid not reveal any signs of hypercalcemia or any other systemicdisorder in any of our cases. There were 23 males (96%) and onefemale (4%) with the mean age of the patients being 69.2% &#x000b1; 7.4years (ranging from 56-80 years). The patients were followedup for a mean period of 26.8 &#x000b1; 10.2 months. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> shows thedemographic and clinical characteristics of the cases included inthe study. All patients were found to have preoperative symptomsinterfering with their daily activities. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2A">2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2B">2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2C">2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2D">2D</xref> depictsthe preoperative and postoperative photographs of a case of CDK.</p><p>Fourteen eyes (58%) had lesions involving the whole ofthe cornea while in 10 eyes (42%) the central 4-6 mm of thecornea was involved. Central corneal thickness could not beassessed in any case by pachymetry due to involvement ofthe central visual axis in all the eyes [Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2A">2A</xref>]. Preoperativethinning (therefore demonstrated on slit-lamp examination)up to 10-20 % was present in five eyes (21%). Seventeen eyeshad a preoperative visual acuity less than 20/200 while sevenhad visual acuity between 20/200-20/60 [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>].</p><p>Three cases with corneal thinning by 20% were graftedwith multiple layers of amniotic membrane. Only two caseswith BSK underwent EDTA application with superficialkeratectomy. No intraoperative complications were noted inany case.</p><p>Postoperatively, subjective relief of preoperative wateringdue to the corneal disease was achieved in 88% cases (21 patients)while irritation was relieved in 83% cases (20 patients). Overall,relief of one or more symptoms was seen in 23 eyes. More eyeswith BSK experienced subjective relief than CDK.</p><p>Subjective visual recovery was felt in 88% patients(21 cases; though objectively visual improvement by morethan two lines occurred in 23 eyes, two patients denied anysubjective improvement in their vision postoperatively). Theoverall postoperative vision improved after the procedurewith 23 eyes gaining two-line improvement (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). While67% (16/24 eyes) of eyes had a vision &#x0003c;20/200 preoperatively,only 17% of eyes (4/24 eyes) had similar acuity postoperatively(<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Objective visual improvement was seen in12 of 15 eyes of CDK [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>] as opposed to six of nine eyeswith BSK though this was not statistically significant.</p><p>The surface regularity improved after the procedure in23 cases (96%) as observed in placido disc images evidencedby decreased distortion of the rings in the involved area withdecrease in the area of distorted mires.</p><p>Subjective success was obtained in 17 cases (71%) andobjective success was seen in 18 cases (75%) [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>]. Patientswith BSK had a better subjective success while CDK had abetter postoperative objective success.</p><p>One case of BSK was labeled as a failure with postoperativedecline in vision and severe scarring. Loss of the graft wasseen in this patient on the 12<sup>th</sup> postoperative day associatedwith loose sutures.</p><p>Postoperative complications were few. Central epithelialdefect &#x0003c;3 mm (detected after suture removal at three weeks)was noted in three patients, which healed within five days onconservative treatment (liberal topical lubricants) after sutureremoval and did not require any repeat procedures. A totallimbus to limbus cover was used in these three patients withevidence of retraction in one case on the 10<sup>th</sup> postoperative dayand loss of the membrane in another while the third case hadthe graft <italic>in situ</italic>. Amniotic membrane graft (AMG) retractionwas seen in four cases involving the inferior peripheralcornea only. Recurrence of the lesion around the periphery ofpreviously dissected bed was seen in one eye with CDK at ninemonths (not involving the visual axis) and loss of the graft wasencountered in one case which was labeled as postoperativefailure.</p><p>Comparison of similar age groups with both disorders gavesimilar results. There was no correlation between the age and thefinal visual acuity, subjective or objective outcomes. Preoperativecorneal thinning was associated with postoperative scarring (<italic>r</italic>= 0.4, <italic>P</italic> = 0.002) while no correlation was found between theextent of corneal involvement and the postoperative visualacuity. None of our patients required penetrating keratoplastyor repeat procedure in the follow-up period.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Despite good results in previous studies,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> theneed for a safe and effective alternative to PTK and keratoplasty for visuallyincapacitating degenerative diseases of the cornea, has beenfelt at centers where such facilities are not available, or in ruralplaces where the compliance and long-term follow-up of thepatient is doubtful. Since most of our patients were from arural setting, we did not prefer a controlled study and thereforerecruited no controls (superficial keratectomy alone) in thestudy, keeping in mind the poor ocular hygiene and high riskof postoperative infections over a de-epithelized corneal bed. Inthis study, we obtained only a 71% subjective and 75% objectivesuccess with the procedure. While objective improvement ofvision was obtained in 23 of 24 eyes, two patients denied asubjective improvement. The overall subjective success asregards the relief of preoperative symptoms was observedto be less than the objective success. This difference may inpart reflect the severity of symptoms caused by the surfaceirregularity in such patients.</p><p>Earlier reports have stated good results of the use of themembrane in cases of BSK, where visual acuity improved in fiveof nine (44%) sighted eyes and remained unchanged in four.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>Kwon and associates have reported the safety and efficacy ofsuperficial lamellar keratectomy with amniotic membranein BSK in two cases.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> Phototherapeutic keratectomy in BSKhas also been reported to have successful outcomes.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref> Our study showed more success objectively (six of nine eyes) thansubjectively success (seven of nine eyes), with eight of nine eyesachieving two-line improvement in vision postoperatively, inBSK. One case had loss of the graft on the 12<sup>th</sup> postoperativeday with resultant scarring and decrease in vision which wastherefore labeled as failure.</p><p>Al-Towerki<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> has studied the surgical outcome of superficialkeratectomy using microkeratome (free flap) for treatment ofirregular CDK. Successful outcomes of laser procedures havealso been reported in CDK.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> We obtained a betterobjective than subjective success in CDK, with improvement of &#x0003e;twolines in 15 eyes.</p><p>Studies of PTK in CDK have quoted success in reducingcorneal opacification in 98% of cases of CDK.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref> In a study byPeter Hersh and associates, of PTK in spheroidal degeneration,the uncorrected visual acuity improved in 20 eyes of 28 caseswith loss of vision noted in two cases.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref> Two patientssubsequently underwent penetrating keratoplasty. In our studywith amniotic membrane, objective success was obtained in 12out of 15 cases with CDK while only 10 of 15 eyes were relievedof their symptoms. None of the cases required penetratingkeratoplasty or a repeat procedure.</p><p>Recurrence of CDK has been reported in two eyes afterkeratoplasty, 3.5 years after lamellar and six years afterpenetrating keratoplasty.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref> A similar study reported favorableoutcomes of lamellar keratoplasty for indications includingCDK and BSK, though graft infection was seen in seven eyes.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>We did not encounter any case of postoperative infection inour study, though recurrence of CDK around the dissectedbed was seen at nine months postoperatively, which, however,did not affect the final visual outcome or necessitate a repeatprocedure. Amniotic membrane grafting not only was easilyavailable but also obviated devastating complications and didnot require any long-term treatment.</p><p>Eyes with CDK in this study experienced more objectiveimprovement while those with BSK had better subjective reliefin our study. The more diffuse involvement of the cornea inBSK could account for less objective improvement in this subsetas compared to CDK, which is more localized, facilitatingeasy removal of the lesion. This also could in part explain thebetter subjective relief after surgery in eyes with BSK. We didnot find any difference in the time for disintegration of theamniotic membrane in either of them (45-60 days after sutureremoval).</p><p>Quantitative analysis of corneal topography, thoughpreferable for this study, was not possible owing to lack ofnecessary equipment for the same in a remote rural setup.Nevertheless, comparisons between the preoperative andpostoperative placido images in our study showed decreaseddistortion of the rings in the involved area with decrease inthe area of distorted mires in all the cases though no definiteconclusion of the effect of this procedure on the cornealtopography could be drawn from the study due to lack ofquantitative data.</p><p>The learning curve for the surgical procedure was steepwith no major intraoperative or postoperative complicationsencountered. The procurement of the membrane was easy andone membrane could be used collectively for two to three eyeswhen cut to the desired size of the lesion.</p><p>Amniotic membrane grafting with superficial keratectomyproved to be an effective alternative in rural patients withsuperficial corneal degenerations, both in terms of subjectiverelief to the patient with improved vision and objectiveregularization of the corneal surface in a rural set up.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank LVPEI for providing us with preserved amnioticmembrane and whose cooperation was valuable in the completion ofthis study.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p>Presented at: Best Free paper award at Annual UP stateOphthalmological Society, Ghaziabad 2005 and Annual DelhiOphthalmological Society, Delhi 2006</p></fn><fn><p>Source of Support: Nil</p></fn><fn><p>Conflict of Interest: None declared</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climatic droplet keratopathy</article-title><source>Surv Ophthalmol</source><year>1992</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1549808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ing</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ing</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ten-yearpostoperative results of Penetrating keratoplasty</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1998</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>1855</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9787355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maharajan</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanmuganathan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell-Richards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dua</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amniotic membrane transplantationfor ocular surface reconstruction: Indications and outcomes</article-title><source>Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapuano</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excimer laser phototherapeutic keratectomy: Long-term results and practical considerations</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9071527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Atzler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratkay</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic use of the193-nm excimer laser in corneal pathologies</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><year>1997</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9176678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sekundo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tietjen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Laser-assisted subepithelial keratectomy(LASEK): Review of the current state of knowledge</article-title><source>Ophthalmologe</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12955440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghiselli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Durrie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Waring</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02032;&#x000c7;onell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A prospective multicenter trial of excimerlaser phototherapeutic keratectomy for corneal vision loss</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>1996</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8694083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaidman</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual and refractive results of combinedPTK/PRK in patients with corneal surface disease and refractiveerrors</article-title><source>J Cataract Refract Surg</source><year>2006</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>958</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16814053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hafner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Langenbucher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term results ofphototherapeutic keratectomy with 193-nm excimer laser formacular corneal dystrophy</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2005</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16138998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alio</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Javaloy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Merayo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Galal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated superficiallamellar keratectomy augmented by excimer laser masked PTKin the management of severe superficial corneal opacities</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2004</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>1289</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15377553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hafner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Langenbucher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Naumann</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phototherapeutickeratectomy (o-PTK) with 193 nm excimer laser for superficialcorneal scars: Prospective long-term results of 31 consecutiveoperations</article-title><source>Ophthalmologe</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14991309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhasawat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfonso</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amnioticmembrane transplantation after the primary surgical managementof band keratopathy</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11333320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New treatment for band keratopathy:Superficial lamellar keratectomy, EDTA chelation and amnioticmembrane transplantation</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15308858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moniz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of phototherapeutic keratectomyin various superficial corneal pathologies</article-title><source>J Refract Surg</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>S243</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12699182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sah</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phototherapeutic keratectomy innine eyes with superficial corneal diseases</article-title><source>Refract Corneal Surg</source><year>1993</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrell</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of band keratopathy withexcimer phototherapeutic keratectomy: Visual, refractive andsymptomatic outcome</article-title><source>Eye</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12640412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Towerki</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superficial keratectomy using microkeratome fortreatment of irregular climatic droplet keratopathy (free flap)</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><year>2007</year><volume>245</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16705450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badr</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>al-Rajhi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagoner</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Teichmann</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phototherapeutic keratectomy for climaticdroplet keratopathy</article-title><source>J Refract Surg</source><year>1996</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8963799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hersh</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnstein</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Etwaru</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excimer laserphototherapeutic keratectomy surgical strategies and clinicaloutcomes</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1996</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>1210</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8764789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>al-Rajhi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrence of climatic dropletkeratopathy: Two case reports</article-title><source>Acta Ophthalmol Scand</source><year>1996</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>642</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9017061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukhija</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saroha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indications and outcomeof optical partial thickness lamellar keratoplasty</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12605042</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1A" position="float"><label>Figure 1A</label><caption><p>Surgical procedure of superficial keratectomy with amniotic membrane grafting (see text-surgical technique). (A) Intraoperativephotograph showing the amniotic membrane placement over dissected bed after lamellar dissection with crescent knife</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1A</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-297-g001"/></fig><fig id="F1B" position="float"><label>Figure 1B</label><caption><p>Surgical procedure of superficial keratectomy with amniotic membrane grafting (see text-surgical technique). (B)Intraoperative photograph showing amniotic membrane (figure showing total limbus to limbus cover) being secured to the cornea</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1B</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-297-g002"/></fig><fig id="F2A" position="float"><label>Figure 2A</label><caption><p>Pre- and postoperative clinical photographs of operated eyes with climatic droplet keratopathy. (A) Preoperative photoshowing elevated lesions of spheroidal degeneration (red arrow) involving central cornea.</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2A</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-297-g003"/></fig><fig id="F2B" position="float"><label>Figure 2B</label><caption><p>Pre- and postoperative clinical photographs of operated eyes with climatic droplet keratopathy. (B) Preoperative placidoimages of same patient showing severe distortion of central rings (red arrow).</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2B</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-297-g004"/></fig><fig id="F2C" position="float"><label>Figure 2C</label><caption><p>Pre- and postoperative clinical photographs of operated eyes with climatic droplet keratopathy. (C) Postoperativeslit-lamp photograph showing clearing of central cornea with minimal scarring (yellow arrow) and residual lesions (white arrow).</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2C</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-297-g005"/></fig><fig id="F2D" position="float"><label>Figure 2D</label><caption><p>Pre- and postoperative clinical photographs of operated eyes with climatic droplet keratopathy. (D) Postoperative placidoimages showing regularization of the central rings in the visual axis (yellow arrow) with residual irregularity in the periphery (Whitearrow)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2D</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-297-g006"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of preoperative and postoperative visual acuity of all patients subjected to the study</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-297-g007"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of patients subjected to superficial keratectomy and amniotic membrane grafting for superficial cornealdegenerations</p></caption><alt-text>Table 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-297-g008"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of objective and subjective outcomes after superficial keratectomy coupled with amniotic membrane grafting in superficial corneal degenerations</p></caption><alt-text>Table 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-297-g009"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>