<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636036</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_1_1_37580</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The journey continues ... and so we evolve</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>Barun Kumar</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><aff>P. D. Hinduja National Hospital and Medical Research Centre, Veer Savarkar Marg, Mahim, Mumbai - 400 016, India. E-mail: <email>editor@ijo.in</email></aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>Three years ago, when the new team took over the editorialresponsibilities of the Indian Journal of Ophthalmology (IJO),the vision of our team was expressed in the first editorial. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>When I look back, I feel satisfied with the evolution of IJO inthe last three years.</p><p>The number of issues published in a year has increased fromfour to six in the year 2007. While this gave more opportunitiesfor authors to publish their research, the editorial office had towork harder to cope with the increased workload. The numberof articles published in 2007 has increased to 181 from 79 articlespublished in 2005. The percentage of accepted articles (43% inthe year 2005 to 37% in the years 2006 and 2007) has remainednearly unchanged, indicating no compromise in the quality ofarticles accepted.</p><p>The increase in the frequency of publication of IJO, coupledwith the increase in our membership in these three years hasresulted in the almost doubling of the number of copies ofIJO printed per year (30,800 copies in 2005 to 60,500 copies in2007). In spite of the extra burden on the finances (printingand postage cost of the 100% increase in number of copies)and the decrease in color processing charges (borne by theauthors) by more than 80%, the editorial office is maintaining aself-sufficient and comfortable financial position. Furthermore,the financial model developed is ready to take up any furtherburden involved in implementing new ideas in the interest ofthe journal and the association.</p><p>We had undertaken the gigantic task of uploading ourwebsite with full text of all back issues of IJO from its inceptionin 1953. I am happy to report that more than 80% of articlespublished have been digitized and made available online onour website. This has increased the visibility of all the articlespublished so far. Retrieval is now easy and free unlike manyother international journals due to our &#x02033;open access&#x02033; policy<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> andwebsite linkage with PubMed /MEDLINE. All this has resultedin increased citation of the articles published in IJO [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>], areal value addition to the authors. This puts the authors at parwith authors of any other peer-reviewed journal.</p><p>Our website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ijo.in/">http://www.ijo.in/</ext-link> has many special features. It hasan &#x02033;open access&#x02033; policy providing access to the full text of anarticle absolutely free of cost. The articles can be instantaneouslytranslated into eight different languages (Japanese, Chinese,Korean, French, German, Spanish, Dutch, and Portuguese)for non-English speaking readers. It also provides the citationas well as access history of all articles. The popularity of thiswebsite can be judged by the fact that it has over 2000 visitorsdaily. In addition to this, IJO attracts readers from all the partsof the world [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>].</p><p>IJO stands at the fifth position in the Google directoryamong all Ophthalmology journals in the world (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/Top/Health/Medicine/Medical_Specialties/Ophthalmology/Journals/">http://www.google.com/Top/Health/Medicine/Medical_Specialties/Ophthalmology/Journals/</ext-link>. It also stands at the second positionin the Google directory of all Indian biomedical publications(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/Top/Regional/Asia/India/Health/Publications/">http://www.google.com/Top/Regional/Asia/India/Health/Publications/</ext-link>).</p><p>IJO has been included in the &#x02033;Science Citation IndexExpanded&#x02033; since January 2008. This is a very prestigiousachievement as only six biomedical journals from India arelisted in this index. This indexing will provide the official&#x02033;Impact Factor&#x02033; of IJO<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> from the year 2010. Apart from this,IJO is also indexed with PubMed/MEDLINE, Excerpta Medica/EMBASE, Biological Abstracts, SCOPUS, CAB Abstracts andIndex Copernicus. This in turn has increased the visibility andaccessibility of articles published in IJO.</p><p>The number of submissions has increased by more than100% in the last three years [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>]. There are many authorsfrom abroad who have submitted their articles to IJO. We haveincreased our list of reviewers in the last three years [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>]for better quality control of accepted articles. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> clearlyshows the significant increase in the number of internationalreviewers.</p><p>Given the availability and popularity of the Internet evenin remote areas of India, we are happy to announce that fromthe year 2007, manuscript submission and management hasgone completely online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.journalonweb.com/ijo">http://www.journalonweb.com/ijo</ext-link>. Thishas made the processing of submitted manuscripts smooth,fast and transparent [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>]. The mean number of days takenfor the acceptance of an article has reduced from 253.82 daysin 2005 to 83.15 days in 2007. Authors can themselves trace theprogress of their manuscript online.</p><p>To give our journal an international look, a new cover designwas implemented and has been appreciated by all members.</p><p>In order to improve the quality of research and writingskill of authors, two research methodology workshops havebeen conducted by the IJO editorial office in association withP. D. Hinduja National Hospital and the Medical ResearchCentre, Mumbai. Inspired by the positive feedback of the firsttwo workshops, we have planned a third workshop in the lastweek of January 2008. This has helped in the improvement ofthe quality of authorship and review.</p><p>Last but not the least, keeping in view the difficulty weexperienced during the initial period of setting up an editorialoffice, I propose to further develop and pass on the efficient, full-fledged, permanent working system that we have established.This would enable a smooth transition for any future editorialteam, whenever it may be required.</p></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changing times, evolving responses</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2005</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Humanity&#x02032;s Quest for Knowledge - Open Access- The IJO Initiative</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2005</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15976461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The enigma of impact factor</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17090872</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>World map depicting places from where people are accessing the website</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-1-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Number of manuscripts submitted in IJO</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-1-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Yearwise break up of IJO reviewers</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-1-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Year wise citation details</p></caption><alt-text>Table 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-1-g004"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Year wise time taken (Mean in days) by the articles in different phases.</p></caption><alt-text>Table 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-1-g005"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>