<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417825</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636108</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_3_231_40363</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417825 </article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Periocular necrotizing fasciitis associated with kerato-conjunctivitis and treated with medical management: A		case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Shome</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><degrees>DNB, FRCS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>Vandana</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jayadev</surname><given-names>Chaitra</given-names></name><degrees>DO</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Kiran</given-names></name><degrees>Dip Diabetology</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>Sundaram</given-names></name><degrees>DO</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Retina (SN,CJ), Department of Cornea and AnteriorSegment (VJ), Department of Internal Medicine (KS), Departmentof Ophthalmic and Facial Plastic Surgery orbital Diseases and OcularOncology (DS), Aditya Jyot Eye Hospital Pvt Ltd, Mumbai, India andfrom the Department of Ocular Oncology (DS), Tata Memorial Centre,Mumbai, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Debraj Shome, Department of Ophthalmic andFacial Plastic Surgery, Orbital Diseases and Ocular Oncology, AdityaJyot Eye Hospital Pvt Ltd, Plot No 153, Road No 9, Major ParmeshwaranRoad, Wadala, Mumbai - 400 031, India. Email: <email>debraj_shome@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We report a 25-year-old systemically healthy male who presentedwith periocular necrotizing fasciitis (NF) in the left eyelid. Thiswas associated with the presence of immunologically mediatedmarginal kerato-conjunctivitis, in the same eye. This potentiallydangerous lid infection and the associated ocular surface infectionresolved successfully, with medical management. We report thiscase to highlight the successful conservative management ofperiocular NF and the hitherto unreported anterior segmentinvolvement.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Kerato-conjunctivitis</kwd><kwd>medical management</kwd><kwd>necrotizing fasciitis</kwd><kwd>periocular infection.</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Necrotizing fasciitis (NF) is the anatomical descriptionused to describe the extensive necrosis of the subcutaneoustissues that is most commonly caused by a rapidly spreadinginfection of <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic> in the subcutaneous plane.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>Necrotizing fasciitis is a serious life-threatening condition,with reported mortality of more than 20%. The limbs,perineum and abdomen are frequently involved with facialinvolvement being rare. The organisms most closely linkedto NF are <italic>Group A beta-hemolytic streptococci</italic> (NF Type II),though these bacteria are isolated in only a minority of thecases.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> The rarer NF Type I is caused due to polymicrobialinfections and the usual pathogens are obligate and facultativeanerobes.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></p><p>Periocular NF is reported to have a better prognosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>Though reports of resolution of periocular NF post surgicaldebridement are common, a detailed Medline and Embasesearch revealed only one case series reporting resolutionwith conservative management.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> In addition, to the best ofour knowledge, there are no published reports of anteriorsegment ocular involvement in periocular NF. We report thiscase to highlight the successful conservative managementof periocular NF and the hitherto unreported ocularinvolvement.</p><sec sec-type=""><title>Case Report</title><p>A 25-year-old systemically healthy male patient presentedwith complaints of severe photophobia, redness, discharge,pain and severe swelling of the lids in the left eye, since twodays.</p><p>Past history was significant for a boil on the lowereyelid, two days ago. On examination, the best-correctedvisual acuity was 20/20 and 20/30, in the right and left eyesrespectively. Right eye examination was unremarkable. Theleft eye showed severe lid edema with scales on the skin andassociated kerato-conjunctivitis [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1A">Fig. 1A</xref>]. The cornea showedmultiple marginal infiltrates. Photographic documentationof the anterior segment condition was impossible because ofthe severe photophobia. Extraocular movements were full.A conjunctival swab and a periorbital skin swab were sentfor culture and sensitivity. The corneal infiltrates were alsocultured on blood agar and Sabouraud&#x02032;s dextrose agar. Thepatient was seen by our infectious diseases expert and startedon intravenous co-amoxiclav (Augmentin, GlaxoSmithKline)1 g twice daily, intravenous ceftriaxone (ceftriaxone sodium,Sandoz, Novartis) 1 g twice daily and oral metronidazole(Flagyl, Searle) 500 mg three times daily, pending sensitivityreports. Topical loteprednol etabonate (0.5%) (Alrex eye drops,Bausch and Lomb Incorporated) every three hourly andciprofloxacin (0.3%) (Ciplox eye drops, Cipla) six times a daywere started, in the left eye.</p><p>On follow-up two days later, the patient was symptomaticallymuch better. The skin scabs had fallen off, revealing violaceous,sub-epidermal necrosis. The conjunctival inflammation hadreduced and the corneal marginal infiltrates had almostdisappeared [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1B">Fig. 1B</xref>]. Culture and sensitivity results showed<italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, sensitive to the administered medications.The culture plates for corneal infiltrates showed negativegrowth and were discarded after three weeks. The patient wassero-negative for HIV.</p><p>Five days later, the skin lesions had healed and theconjunctivitis had resolved. Intravenous antibiotics werestopped and the patient was started on oral co-amoxiclav(Augmentin, GlaxoSmithKline), 625 mg thrice a day, for aweek.</p><p>On final follow-up a month later, periocular skin discolorationwas the only sequalae noted [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>Infections in the periocular region occur post surgicalprocedures, post trauma, furunculosis or even without anyantecedent cause.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></p><p>Ideally, a combination of intensive parenteral antimicrobialtherapy and prompt surgical debridement of necrotic tissueshould be done. Intravenous pooled immunoglobulin andheparinization may also have beneficial roles by neutralizingsuper-antigen activity and aiding antibiotic perfusion.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>Necrotizing fasciitis is a clinical diagnosis. Necrotizingfasciitis limited to the eyelids looks and behaves differentlyfrom NF affecting other parts of the body, due to the excellentblood supply in the eyelid area.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Mild cases, especially thoserestricted to the eyelids alone may respond to medical therapy.The increased blood supply allows for delayed debridement,because the local vasculature allows for better access ofthe systemic antibiotics to the infected area. The marginalzone of tissue surrounding the infected area has betterlocal blood supply and hence a higher chance of avoidingnecrosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></p><p>We report the case of a 25-year-old male patient who presentedwith periocular NF associated with kerato-conjunctivitis.Associated kerato-conjunctivitis is commonly reported followinglid infection of staphylococcal etiology. The paucity of literatureregarding this entity, in association with <italic>staphylococcus</italic>-inducedperiocular NF probably stems from an under-reporting bias.These infiltrates are usually the result of an immunologicalreaction with staphylococcal antigens but in cases with severeinfection as in our patient, the infiltrates need to be cultured foran infectious etiology. The patient responded to conservativemedical management with systemic antibiotics, topical antibioticsand topical steroids. We report this case to highlight the successfulconservative management of periocular NF and the hithertounreported anterior segment involvement.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urschel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Necrotizing soft tissue infections</article-title><source>Postgrad Med J</source><year>1999</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10621873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kronish</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>McLeish</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eyelid necrosis and periorbital necrotizing fasciitis: Report of a case and review of the literature</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1991</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2023741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luksich</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holds</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartstein</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservative management of necrotizing fasciitis of the eyelids</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2002</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>2118</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12414425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seal</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Necrotizing fasciitis</article-title><source>Curr Opin Infect Dis</source><year>2001</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11979121</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1A" position="float"><label>Figure 1A</label><caption><p>(A) External photograph of patient at presentation, showing left-sided severe lid edema, erythema and necrotic tissue with overlyingskin scabs</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1A</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-231-g001"/></fig><fig id="F1B" position="float"><label>Figure 1B</label><caption><p>(B) Slit-lamp photograph of the left eye, in diffuse illumination (with upper eyelid retracted), showing periocular skinerythema and kerato-conjunctivitis</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1B</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-231-g003"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>External photograph of patient, a month post presentation,showing healed skin lesions, with symmetrical palpebral apertures</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-231-g002"/></fig></floats-group></article>