<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18292627</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636094</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_2_147_39121</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Management of an irradiated anophthalmic socket following dermis-fat graft rejection: A case		report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Raizada</surname><given-names>Kuldeep</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shome</surname><given-names>Debraj</given-names></name><degrees>DNB, FRCS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Honavar</surname><given-names>Santosh G</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Departments of Ocularistry (KR) and Ophthalmic Plastic Surgery Orbitand Ocular Oncology (SGH), LV Prasad Eye Institute, Hyderabad, India;Department of Ophthalmic and Facial Plastic Surgery Orbit and OcularOncology (DS), Aditya Jyot Eye Hospital Pvt. Ltd. and Department ofOcular Oncology, Tata Memorial Centre, Mumbai, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Kuldeep Raizada, LV Prasad Eye Institute,LV Prasad Marg, Banjara Hills, Hyderabad - 500 034, India. Email: <email>ocularist@lvpei.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Mar-Apr</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access		article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits		unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Dermis-fat graft (DFG) is often the only promising option in casesof severely contracted sockets. However, there is an increased riskof graft failure in irradiated sockets with decreased vascularity.In such difficult cases, repeat DFG implantation also has higherrisks of graft failure.</p><p>We describe an ingenious method of successful managementof an irradiated anophthalmic socket following DFG infection andnecrosis, with acceptable cosmetic results. At surgery, an orbitalimpression was taken with ophthalmic grade alginate. Based onthis measurement, a custom-made stem pressure socket-expandermade up of high density polymethyl methacrylate (PMMA) wasfitted, a week post surgery and kept <italic>in situ</italic> for six weeks.</p><p>On review, the fornices had considerably deepened. Theexpander device was removed and the patient was now fittedwith a custom-made thicker prosthesis made up of high-densityPMMA. The patient has followed up for a year subsequently andthe prosthesis has remained stable.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Contracted socket</kwd><kwd>socket expansion</kwd><kwd>stem pressure socket-expander</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Dermis-fat graft (DFG) is often the most promising optionin maintaining orbital volume, preserving the fornices andconserving the conjunctiva in cases of complicated orbits andcontracted sockets. Although significant atrophy of primarygrafts does not occur very frequently,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> irradiated socketsmay have decreased vascularity and increased risks of graftinfection and failure. In such difficult cases, repeat DFG orbitalimplantation may also suffer a slightly increased frequency andamount of graft absorption.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></p><p>We describe a method of successful management of anirradiated anophthalmic socket following DFG infection, withacceptable cosmetic results.</p><p>We performed a Medline search with the key words&#x02033;anophthalmic socket&#x02033;, &#x02033;contracted socket&#x02033; &#x02033;socket expansion&#x02033;&#x02033;dermis-fat graft failure&#x02033; and various combinations thereof.All cross-references in citing literature were included in oursearch and referenced. To the best of our knowledge, a similartechnique has not been reported previously on irradiatedsocket.</p><sec sec-type=""><title>Case Report</title><p>A three-year-old boy presented to us with a contracted rightsocket and history of prosthesis instability, since one year. Hehad been enucleated elsewhere for retinoblastoma of the righteye, one year prior to presentation, without orbital implant.Subsequently, the right socket had received irradiation, detailsof which were unavailable. The fitted prosthesis was extremelyunstable with repeated extrusion.</p><p>On examination, the left eye was unremarkable. The rightsocket was quiet, healthy with evidence of severe surface andvolume contracture. The patient underwent DFG implantation,under general anesthesia. A conformer for socket maintenancewas inserted, on table, post surgery. The patient was startedon topical betamethasone eye drops and oral antibiotics (anAmpicillin-Cloxacillin combination was used), post surgery.On review, a week later, the graft was taking up satisfactorily.The oral antibiotics were stopped, the topical steroids weretapered off and the patient was asked to review with us sixweeks later. However, the patient presented to us three weekslater with a painful inflamed socket. On examination, the socketwas severely infected with copious discharge. The DFG hadsloughed off completely [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1A">Fig. 1A</xref>]. The socket inflammation wastreated with topical antibiotics, anti-inflammatory and systemicantibiotic medication. The patient was reviewed at one weekand at three weeks. At three weeks, the orbital inflammationhad subsided completely. The fornices were seen to be severelyshallow (Grade IV contracture)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> and there was severe volumecontracture (Grade IV),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> as before. At this stage, the optionsof a second DFG or a larger prosthesis, to compensate for thevolume loss, were considered. However, it was impossiblefor the patient to retain a conformer or any prosthesis at thisstage, due to the extreme surface as well as volume contracture.Considering the possible high risk of DFG failure, the patient&#x02032;sparents were not in favor of another surgical procedure. It wasunder these circumstances that a new technique was attempted,with informed consent.</p><p>An orbital impression was taken with ophthalmic gradealginate [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1B">Fig. 1B</xref>]. Based on this measurement, a custom-madestem pressure socket-expander was made from high-densitypolymethyl methacrylate (PMMA) and fitted a week later[<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1C">Fig. 1C</xref>]. This conformer was kept <italic>in situ</italic> for six weeks, withpressure exerted by a tight sticking tape on the stem of theconformer [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1D">Fig. 1D</xref>]. Instructions to change this tape everysix-hourly, to ensure adequate sticking and sufficient pressureto the socket expander, were given to the patient.</p><p>On review, six weeks later, the expander device was removedand the socket examined. The socket surface had completelylined with the conjunctiva and the fornices had deepenedsufficiently to accommodate a conformer. We documentedthe expansion of the socket objectively with our ingeniouslydevised slit-lamp measurement device.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>The patient was now fitted with a custom-made thickerprosthesis made up of high-density PMMA [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2A">Fig. 2A</xref>]. Cosmesiswas satisfactory [Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2B">2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2C">C</xref>]. The patient has beenfollowed up for a year and the prosthesis has remained stable.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>In a case of failed DFG in an irradiated socket; expansileexpanders can be used. Other useful described techniquesinclude prefabricated temporalis muscle and/or fascia pedicledflap along with fornix formation sutures, which are to beretained for a minimum of three weeks.</p><p>We treated a patient with DFG necrosis and a severelycontracted anophthalmic socket with a custom-made stempressure socket expander device. This device helped deepenthe fornices, with stable prosthesis placement subsequently.The prosthesis was thicker to ensure adequate volumereplacement and was made up of high-grade PMMA toensure lesser weight. This prosthesis also had a superior shelfextending backwards into the socket, to provide additionalstability. This provided acceptable cosmesis, under thecircumstances.</p><p>We documented the expansion of the socket objectively withthe slit-lamp measurement device. Though it might be difficultto envisage socket expansion solely due to the mechanicalpressure exerted by a tape running from the forehead to thecheek, the expansion was possibly due to a combination of theshape of the socket expander, its reach deep into the socketand the mechanical force applied by the sticking tape, changedrepeatedly, to ensure proper sticking.</p><p>The use of a pressure conformer has been previouslydescribed in the literature,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> but to the best of our knowledge,the entire procedure of fitting a special prosthesis post socketexpansion, in these patients with severely contracted sockets,has not yet been described in the literature. However, it isworthwhile to remember that this case of single-time placementof a non-expansile custom-made stem pressure socket expanderin an avascular irradiated socket needs to be conducted on alarger sample size with a longer duration of follow-up, to judgethe true efficacy of this procedure.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosniak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lisman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dermis-fat orbital implantation: 118 cases</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Surg</source><year>1983</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>941</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6361650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosniak</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications of dermis-fat orbital implantation</article-title><source>Adv Ophthalmic Plast Reconstr Surg</source><year>1990</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2248708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putterman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Karesh</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A surgical technique for the successful and stable reconstruction of the totally contracted ocular socket</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Surg</source><year>1988</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3353085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raizada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shome</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Honavar</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New measurement device and technique for assessing implant and prosthetic motility</article-title><source>Ophthal Plast Reconstr Surg</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Workman</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of Inferior Cul-De-Sac</article-title><source>Int Ophthalmol Clin</source><year>1970</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1A" position="float"><label>Fig. 1A</label><caption><p>(A) Custom-molded socket expander device: external photograph of patient presenting with a painful inflamed right socket</p></caption><alt-text>Fig. 1A</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-147-g001"/></fig><fig id="F1B" position="float"><label>Fig. 1B</label><caption><p>(B) Custom-molded socket expander device: photograph of orbital impression taken with ophthalmic grade alginate</p></caption><alt-text>Fig. 1B</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-147-g003"/></fig><fig id="F1C" position="float"><label>Fig. 1C</label><caption><p>(C) Custom-molded socket expander device: external photograph of patient fitted with custom-made stem pressure socket-expander</p></caption><alt-text>Fig. 1C</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-147-g004"/></fig><fig id="F1D" position="float"><label>Fig. 1D</label><caption><p>(D) Custom-molded socket expander device: external photograph of patient fitted with custom-made stem pressure socket-expander, withtape</p></caption><alt-text>Fig. 1D</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-147-g005"/></fig><fig id="F2A" position="float"><label>Fig. 2A</label><caption><p>(A) Custom-molded socket expander device: photograph of thicker prosthesis made up of high-density PMMA</p></caption><alt-text>Fig. 2A</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-147-g002"/></fig><fig id="F2B" position="float"><label>Fig. 2B</label><caption><p>(B)Custom-molded socket-expander device: external photograph of patient fitted with custom prosthesis</p></caption><alt-text>Fig. 2B</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-147-g006"/></fig><fig id="F2C" position="float"><label>Fig. 2C</label><caption><p>(C)Custom-molded socket-expander device: external photograph of patient fitted with custom prosthesis</p></caption><alt-text>Fig. 2C</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-147-g007"/></fig></floats-group></article>