<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microb Cell Fact</journal-id><journal-title>Microbial Cell Factories</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2859</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19138404</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636759</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1475-2859-8-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2859-8-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Isolation and characterisation of polychlorinated biphenyl (PCB) degrading fungi from a historically contaminated soil</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tigini</surname><given-names>Valeria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>valeria.tigini@unito.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prigione</surname><given-names>Valeria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>valeria.prigione@unito.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Di Toro</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>sara.ditoro@marcopolo-e.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>Fabio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>fabio.fava@unibo.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Varese</surname><given-names>Giovanna C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>cristina.varese@unito.it</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Plant Biology, University of Turin, viale Mattioli 25, 10125 Turin, Italy</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>DICASM, Faculty of Engineering, Alma Mater Studiorum-University of Bologna, viale Risorgimento 2, 40136 Bologna, Italy</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Marcopolo Engineering SpA, via XI Settembre 37, 12011 Borgo San Dalmazzo, Cuneo, Italy</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/8/1/5"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Tigini et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tigini et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Tigini               Valeria                              valeria.tigini@unito.it            </dc:author><dc:title>            Isolation and characterisation of polychlorinated biphenyl (PCB) degrading fungi from a historically contaminated soil         </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Microbial Cell Factories 8(1): 5-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1475-2859(2009)8:1&#x0003c;5&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1475-2859</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) are widespread toxic pollutants. Bioremediation might be an effective, cost competitive and environment-friendly solution for remediating environmental matrices contaminated by PCBs but it is still unsatisfactory, mostly for the limited biodegradation potential of bacteria involved in the processes. Very little is known about mitosporic fungi potential in PCB bioremediation and their occurrence in actual site historically contaminated soils. In the present study, we characterised the native mycoflora of an aged dump site soil contaminated by about 0.9 g kg<sup>-1 </sup>of Aroclor 1260 PCBs and its changing after aerobic biotreatment with a commercial complex source of bacteria and fungi. Fungi isolated from the soil resulting from 120 days of treatment were screened for their ability to adsorb or metabolise 3 target PCBs.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The original contaminated soil contained low loads of few fungal species mostly belonging to the Scedosporium, Penicillium and Aspergillus genera. The fungal load and biodiversity generally decreased throughout the aerobic treatment. None of the 21 strains isolated from the treated soil were able to grow on biphenyl (200 mg L<sup>-1</sup>) or a mixture of 2-chlorobiphenyl, 4,4'-dichlorobiphenyl and 2,2',5,5'-tetrachlorobiphenyl (20 mg L<sup>-1 </sup>each) as sole carbon sources. However, 16 of them grew in a mineral medium containing the same PCBs mixture and glucose (10 g L<sup>-1</sup>). Five of the 6 isolates, which displayed the faster and more extensive growth under the latter conditions, were found to degrade the 3 PCBs apparently without the involvement of ligninolytic enzymes; they were identified as Penicillium chrysogenum, Scedosporium apiospermum, Penicillium digitatum and Fusarium solani. They are the first PCB degrading strains of such species reported so far in the literature.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The native mycoflora of the actual site aged heavily contaminated soil was mainly constituted by genera often reported as able to biodegrade organopollutants. It was generally remarkably reduced after the biotreatment, which however resulted in the selection of few mitosporic fungal species able to biodegrade PCBs. This is the first study in which an extensive characterisation of the cultivable indigenous mycoflora of an actual site aged PCB contaminated soil, as well as its changes upon soil bioremediation treatment, was conducted. Moreover, this is the first paper in which 5 strains ascribable to 4 mitosporic species able to biodegrade PCB are reported in the literature.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) are highly toxic priority pollutants widespread in several former industrial sites and related terrestrial and aquatic habitats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Such pollutants accumulate in the food chain where can exert toxic effects; thus, their removal from soils and sediments is a priority of great relevance in several industrialized Countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Bioremediation might be an effective, cost competitive and environment-friendly strategy for remediating soils contaminated by low concentrations of mixtures of low chlorinated PCBs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Till now, most of the work has been focused on the characterisation of PCB degrading bacteria in soils and sediments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] and addressed to stimulate soil bacterial activity through soil supplementation with oxygen, biphenyl, exogenous specialized bacteria and by treatment conditions able to provide a high degree of soil mixing and homogeneity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>On the contrary, little is known about the PCB biodegradation potential of fungi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], despite of their well documented ability to biodegrade a large variety of aromatic priority pollutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] and their advantages over the bacterial systems in organopollutant removal from complex environmental matrices (i.e. production of robust nonspecific extracellular enzymes and free radical attack system, that can degrade poorly bioavailable or water insoluble complex mixtures of organic pollutants), that make them unique and of great potential in the bioremediation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge no screenings and characterisation studies of fungi occurring in actual PCB contaminated soils have been conducted so far. In fact, the very few species known to degrade PCBs are principally ligninolytic fungi that have already been selected for the degradation of other aromatic pollutants: <italic>Phanerochaete chrysosporium</italic>, <italic>Trametes versicolor</italic>, <italic>Lentinus edodes</italic>, <italic>Pleurotus ostreatus</italic>, <italic>Grifola frondosa </italic>and <italic>Coriolopsis polyzona </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Whereas mitosporic fungi have been rarely considered for PCBs degradation despite of their biotransformation capabilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p><p>PCBs degradation by fungi is generally affected by several cultural conditions (i.e. medium composition, initial PCBs concentration, etc.) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] and substantial amounts of PCBs can be abiotically removed through fungal mycelia sorbtion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. In addition, the fungal PCB degradation pathway has still not been completely elucidated. Only recently the mitosporic fungus <italic>Paecilomyces lilacinus </italic>and the yeast-like fungus <italic>Trichosporon mucoides </italic>were found to metabolize low chlorinated biphenyls through monohydroxylation of both the unsubstituted and the chlorinated aromatic ring of the molecules followed by the cleavage of hydroxylated ring system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Literature also indicates the non-specific ligninolytic systems (e.g laccases and peroxidases) as the main putative enzymes involved in PCB degradation by fungi, and in particular by basidiomycetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]; however the involvement of other enzymes, such as mono- and dioxygenases, has been also hypothesized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>].</p><p>In a recent study, the effects of a not acclimated commercial consortium of exogenous microorganisms (Enzyveba) in the aerobic microbial decontamination of an highly and historically PCB contaminated soil was studied in laboratory-scale slurry- and solid-phase bioreactors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. A partial biodegradation of PCBs, along with a moderate decrease of the initial soil ecotoxicity, were observed in the not-inoculated reactors. Enzyveba markedly enhanced PCB-biodegradation rate and extent as well as the final soil detoxification, in particular under slurry-phase conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Nothing is known about the nature and metabolic properties of indigenous mycoflora of the original soil and how it changed throughout the treatment, in the absence and the presence of Enzyveba and under the different conditions. The present study was undertaken to investigate all the potential role of the indigenous mycoflora in the observed decontamination of the soil. Moreover, fungi isolated at the end of the bioremediation trial were selected for biodegradation experiments towards 3 PCB congeners. PCBs decrease due to biosorption and/or biodegradation was evaluated and the production of laccase (LAC), Mn-dependent peroxidase (MnP), and Mn-independent peroxidase (MiP) was investigated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>Mycological characterisation of the actual site PCB historically contaminated soil</title><p>The site soil displayed a fungal load lower than 10000 colony forming units per g of soil dry weight (CFU g<sup>-1</sup><sub>dw</sub>) and a total of only 16 fungal taxa (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Such a fungal load and biodiversity are about 10 times lower than those typically observed in unpolluted soils, where fungal concentrations of about 10<sup>5 </sup>CFU g<sup>-1 </sup>dry weight of soil due to 90&#x02013;140 different species are detected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. This finding can be ascribed to the high soil content of PCBs and heavy metals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], which might have caused a remarkable selection of indigenous soil mycoflora, as already observed by other authors in historically strongly contaminated soils [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. However, the same finding is noteworthy since, according to the literature, micromycetes are very sensitive to high concentrations of PCBs and are often absent in matrices with over than 500 mg kg<sup>-1 </sup>of such pollutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Fungal entities isolated from the contaminated soil</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Fungal entities</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>MEA</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>PR478A</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Mean of media</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Acremonium strictum </italic>W. Gams</td><td align="center">42 (0.4%)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">21 (0.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aspergillus flavus </italic>Link var. <italic>flavus</italic></td><td align="center">42 (0.4%)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">21 (0.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus </italic>Fresenius var. <italic>fumigatus</italic></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">83 (0.9%)</td><td align="center">42 (0.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aspergillus versicolor </italic>(Vuillemin) Tiraboschi</td><td align="center">42 (0.4%)</td><td align="center">54 (0.6%)</td><td align="center">48 (0.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB+ sterile ialine basidiomycetes</td><td align="center">4 (0.0%)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2 (0.0%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cladosporium herbarum </italic>(Persoon) Link</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">42 (0.4%)</td><td align="center">21 (0.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yeasts</td><td align="center">4546 (45.8%)</td><td align="center">1088 (11.4%)</td><td align="center">2817 (28.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Paecilomyces marquandii </italic>(Massee) S. Hughes</td><td align="center">75 (0.8%)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">38 (0.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium brevicompactum </italic>Dierckx</td><td align="center">13 (0.1%)</td><td align="center">4 (0.0%)</td><td align="center">9 (0.1%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium paneum </italic>Frisvad (ined.)</td><td align="center">88 (0.9%)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">44 (0.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium phoeniceum </italic>J.F.H. Beyma</td><td align="center">42 (0.4%)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">21 (0.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium waksmanii </italic>K.M. Zalessky</td><td align="center">42 (0.4%)</td><td align="center">229 (2.4%)</td><td align="center">135 (1.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Phomopsis </italic>sp.</td><td align="center">54 (0.5%)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">27 (0.3%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>(Saccardo) Saccardo</td><td align="center">4892 (49.3%)</td><td align="center">8046 (84.3%)</td><td align="center">6469 (66.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Trichurus spiralis </italic>Hasselbring</td><td align="center">4 (0.0%)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2 (0.0%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Umbelopsis isabellina </italic>(Oudemans) W. Gams</td><td align="center">42 (0.4%)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">21 (0.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total CFU g<sup>-1</sup><sub>dw</sub></td><td align="center">9928</td><td align="center">9547</td><td align="center">9736</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Fungal entities are expressed as number of colony forming units per g of soil dry weight (CFU g<sup>-1</sup><sub>dw</sub>). In brackets is indicated the percentage of occurrence of the species with respect to the total CFU g<sup>-1</sup><sub>dw</sub>. "DBB +" means positive to the reaction with Diazonium Blue B salts.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The soil mycoflora was dominated by mitosporic fungi (71%) and yeasts (29%) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). None of the isolates was able to produce decolourisation halos on PR478A. <italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>(anamorphic state of <italic>Pseudoallescheria boydii</italic>) was dominant. This species is normally associated with heavily polluted environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] and often involved in the degradation of aromatic hydrocarbons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Also the genera <italic>Penicillium </italic>and <italic>Aspergillus </italic>were relevant in terms of quality (i.e. number of species) and quantity (i.e. fungal load). Strains belonging to these two genera have been often isolated from polluted soils, and their remarkable degradative capability towards different organopollutants has been recently reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. To the best of authors's knowledge, this is the first time that a mycological characterisation of an actual site soil heavily contaminated by PCBs and heavy metals is reported in the literature.</p></sec><sec><title>Mycological characterisation of soil during the aerobic bioremediation treatment</title><p>The mycoflora occurring in the soil at the beginning and at the end of bioremediation (corresponding to the 3<sup>rd </sup>and the 120<sup>th </sup>day of treatment, respectively) under slurry and solid phase conditions, in the presence and the absence of Enzyveba (see Di Toro et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] for more details on the process) was analysed using selective media. As Spearman test did not point out any significant difference among MEA and PR478A media, the results of the identification are presented as the mean of the data obtained from them (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Fungal entities isolated from bioreactors at the beginning and at the end of the biotreatment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="4">3 days</td><td align="center" colspan="4">120 days</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Entities</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">B</td><td align="center">C</td><td align="center"><italic>D</italic></td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">B</td><td align="center">C</td><td align="center"><italic>D</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Acremonium curvulum </italic>W. Gams</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">50 (0.4%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aspergillus foetidus </italic>Thom &#x00026; sRaper</td><td></td><td align="center">50 (0.5%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus </italic>Fresenius var. <italic>fumigatus</italic></td><td align="center">100 (0.6%)</td><td align="center">100 (1.0%)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">50 (0.4%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aspergillus ochraceus </italic>K. Wilhelm</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">100 (0.9%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aspergillus ustus </italic>(Bainier) Thom &#x00026; Church</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">211,5 (0.7%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Basidiomycete with clamp connections</td><td align="center">450 (2.5%)</td><td align="center">300 (3.0%)</td><td align="center">5499 (17.2%)</td><td align="center">4849 (18.8%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Basidiomycete with clamp connections and arthroconidia</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">211,5 (0.7%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Basidiomycete with clamp connections and chlamidospores</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">776 (3.0%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB+ avellaneous basidiomycete with arthroconidia</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">211,5 (0.7%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB+ dematiaceous basidiomycete</td><td align="center">50 (0.3%)</td><td></td><td align="center">423 (1.3%)</td><td align="center">194 (0.8%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB+ ialinus basidiomycete with arthroconidia</td><td align="center">250 (1.4%)</td><td align="center">100 (1.0%)</td><td align="center">634.5 (2.0%)</td><td align="center">388 (1.5%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB+ ialinus basidiomycete with chlamidospores</td><td align="center">100 (0.6%)</td><td align="center">100 (1.0%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB+ ialinus basidiomycete morphotype 1</td><td></td><td align="center">100 (1.0%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB+ ialinus basidiomycete morphotype 2</td><td align="center">800 (4.5%)</td><td align="center">750 (7.5%)</td><td align="center">5710.5 (17.9%)</td><td align="center">3685 (14.3%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB+ ialinus basidiomycete morphotype 3</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">423 (1.3%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>(Balsamo) Vuillemin</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">306 (3.6%)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cladosporium chlorocephalum </italic>(Fresenius) E.W. Mason &#x00026; M.B. Ellis</td><td align="center">500 (2.8%)</td><td align="center">200 (2.0%)</td><td align="center">846 (2.6%)</td><td align="center">1357.5 (5.3%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cladosporium herbarum </italic>(Persoon) Link</td><td align="center">650 (3.7%)</td><td align="center">50 (0.5%)</td><td align="center">1480.5 (4.6%)</td><td align="center">388 (1.5%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Clitocybe </italic>sp.</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">211.5 (0.7%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Engyodontium album </italic>(Limber) de Hoog</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">211.5 (0.7%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Eurotium herbariorum </italic>(F.H. Wiggers: Fries) Link</td><td align="center">50 (0.3%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Fusarium solani f. pisi </italic>(Jones) Snyder &#x00026; Hansen</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">50 (0.4%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Geomyces pannorum </italic>(Link) Sigler &#x00026; J.W. Carmichael <italic>var. pannorum</italic></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">306 (3.6%)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Microsporum gypseum </italic>(E. Bodin) Guiart &#x00026; Grigoraki</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">50 (0.4%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Myrothecium roridum </italic>Tode</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">211.5 (0.7%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium aculeatum </italic>Raper &#x00026; Fennel</td><td align="center">50 (0.3%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium aurantiogriseum </italic>Dierckx</td><td align="center">50 (0.3%)</td><td></td><td align="center">634.5 (2.0%)</td><td align="center">1745.5 (6.8%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium camemberti </italic>Thom</td><td align="center">100 (0.6%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium chrysogenum </italic>Thom</td><td align="center">1350 (7.6%)</td><td align="center">400 (4.0%)</td><td align="center">4864.5 (15.2%)</td><td align="center">582 (2.3%)</td><td align="center">50 (0.4%)</td><td></td><td align="center">6430 (75.0%)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium commune </italic>Thom</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">211.5 (0.7%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium crustosum </italic>Thom</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">388 (1.5%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium digitatum </italic>(Persoon) Saccardo</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">1160 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium glabrum </italic>(Wehmer) Westling</td><td align="center">1650 (9.3%)</td><td align="center">250 (2.5%)</td><td align="center">211.5 (0.7%)</td><td align="center">1357.5 (5.3%)</td><td align="center">50 (0.4%)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">1160 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium palitans </italic>Westling</td><td align="center">100 (0.6%)</td><td></td><td align="center">2538 (7.9%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium paneum </italic>Frisvad (ined.)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">50 (0.4%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium paxilli </italic>Bainier</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">211.5 (0.7%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium polonicum </italic>K.M. Zalessky</td><td align="center">250 (1.4%)</td><td></td><td align="center">211.5 (0.7%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium purpurescens </italic>Raper &#x00026; Thom</td><td align="center">550 (3.1%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">306 (3.6%)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium restrictum </italic>J.C. Gilman &#x00026; E.V. Abbott</td><td align="center">150 (0.8%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium solitum </italic>Westling</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">2133.5 (8.3%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">2320 (25.0%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium spinulosum </italic>Thom</td><td align="center">900 (5.1%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium waksmanii </italic>K.M. Zalessky</td><td align="center">50 (0.3%)</td><td align="center">50 (0.5%)</td><td></td><td align="center">1164 (4.5%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>(Saccardo) Saccardo</td><td align="center">9400 (53.1%)</td><td align="center">7500 (75.4%)</td><td align="center">6557 (20.5%)</td><td align="center">6400 (24.8%)</td><td align="center">11250 (96.2%)</td><td align="center">16150 (100%)</td><td align="center">1225 (14.3%)</td><td align="center">4641 (50.0%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Schizophyllum commune </italic>Fries</td><td align="center">50 (0.3%)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">194 (0.8%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB-dematiaceous sterile mycelium</td><td align="center">50 (0.3%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DBB-moniliaceous sterile mycelium</td><td align="center">50 (0.3%)</td><td></td><td align="center">211.5 (0.7%)</td><td align="center">194 (0.8%)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="right">Total CFU g<sub>(dw)</sub><sup>-1 </sup>(mean &#x000b1; st.dev)</td><td align="center">17700 &#x000b1; 6199 a*</td><td align="center">9950 &#x000b1; 3913 b*</td><td align="center">31937 &#x000b1; 17655 c*</td><td align="center">25796 &#x000b1; 14905 ac*</td><td align="center">11700 &#x000b1; 5371 a*</td><td align="center">16150 &#x000b1; 6277 b*</td><td align="center">8573 &#x000b1; 15568 c*</td><td align="center">9281 &#x000b1; 21817 c*</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="8"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="right">PCBs removal in mg kg<sup>-1 </sup>(mean &#x000b1; st.dev)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">65 &#x000b1; 4</td><td align="center">28 &#x000b1; 3</td><td align="center">129 &#x000b1; 8</td><td align="center">74 &#x000b1; 50</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Fungal entities are expressed in number of colony forming units per g of soil dry weight (CFU g<sup>-1</sup><sub>dw</sub>). In brackets is indicated the percentage of presence of the given species with respect to the total CFU g<sup>-1</sup><sub>dw</sub>. A = Bioaugmented solid-phase bioreactors, B = Enzyveba-free solid-phase bioreactors, C = bioaugmented slurry-phase bioreactors, D = Enzyveba-free slurry-phase bioreactors. "DBB + or -" means positive or negative to the reaction with Diazonium Blue B salts. Different small letters indicate significant differences among fungal loads; * indicates significant differences among fungal loads after 3 days and after 120 days (Mann Whitney, P = 0.05). PCB depletion occurs in bioreactors is also reported.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>After 3 days of aerobic treatment under slurry or solid phase conditions, the total fungal load of soil supplemented with nutrients and, when indicated, Enzyveba ranged from 9950 CFU g<sup>-1</sup><sub>dw </sub>to 31937 CFU g<sup>-1</sup><sub>dw</sub>. The highest fungal loads were observed in the slurry phase reactors (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), probably for the higher degree of mixing achieved in these reactors than in the solid-phase ones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The addition of Enzyveba generally resulted in a fungal load increase that was significant under solid state condition (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Nevertheless, the mycoflora observed in the bioaugmented reactors was not so abundant and diversified as expected on the basis of the fungal content of the inoculum applied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. This could be due to the toxic effects of soil pollutants towards very sensitive germinating propagules probably generated in the soil bioreactors during the first few days of treatment. A total of 48 entities were identified (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). <italic>S. apiospermum </italic>was the dominant species in all the bioreactors, followed by basiodiomycetes which often caused decolourisation halos on Poly R 478. High loads of <italic>Penicillium </italic>spp. were also detected (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><p>At the end of the treatment, lower fungal loads and species numbers were generally observed (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). No significant differences between inoculated and Enzyveba-free bioreactors were recorded, while higher fungal loads were generally observed under solid-phase conditions than the slurry phase ones, probably for long term unfavourable submerged mycelium growing conditions and the high toxic pollutant bioavailability guaranteed by the latter conditions with respect to the former ones.</p><p>All strains isolated from soil at the end of the treatment were ascribable to 14 species of mitosporic fungi, 7 of which came from the inoculum. <italic>S. apiospermum </italic>and <italic>Penicillium </italic>spp. were the dominant species (up to 100% in the soil resulting from solid-phase reactors and 75% in that resulting from slurry-phase ones). Noteworthy is the complete disappearance of basidiomycetes, since several fungi of this group are considered eligible candidates for PCBs degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Tolerance vs PCBs and growing capability of isolated fungi</title><p>None of the 21 strains isolated from the bioreactors at the end of the bioremediation experiment were able to grow on biphenyl (200 mg L<sup>-1</sup>), or on a mixture of 2-chlorobiphenyl, 4,4'-dichlorobiphenyl and 2,2',5,5'-tetrabiphenyl (each at 20 mg L<sup>-1</sup>) in the absence of any other carbon source (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Actually, fungi are rarely reported as PCB degraders in absence of alternative carbon source [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], although the growth capability on biphenyl has been considered an indicator of the ability to degrade PCBs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Sixteen strains were able to growth in minimal medium with the 3 PCBs and glucose (10 g L<sup>-1</sup>), but less rapidly and extensively than the control with glucose only; this evidence analogously to others already reported in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] confirms PCBs ability to adversely affect fungal growth, thus permitting to hypothesize that tolerance towards PCBs is a reliable indication of fungal ability to cometabolize PCBs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. On the basis of these considerations, the 6 strains that displayed the most rapid and extensive growth on PCBs and glucose (<italic>Aspergillus fumgatus</italic>, <italic>Penicillium chrysogenum</italic>, <italic>Penicillium digitatum</italic>, <italic>Fusarium solani </italic>and two strains of <italic>Scedosporium apiospermum</italic>) were selected for further degradation experiments.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Ability of the fungal isolates to grow on different carbon sources</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><bold>Fungal strains</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Origin (bioreactors)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Growth on Glucose</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Growth on Glucose + hexane</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Growth on biphenyl</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Growth on PCBs mix</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Growth on PCBs mix + Glucose</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Acremonium curvulum </italic>MUT 598</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus </italic>MUT 4026</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aspergillus ochraceus </italic>MUT 675</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>MUT 676</td><td align="center">C</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Fusarium solani </italic>MUT 4020</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Geomyces pannorum </italic>MUT 588</td><td align="center">C</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Microsporum gypseum </italic>MUT 631</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium digitatum </italic>MUT 4079</td><td align="center">D</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium glabrum </italic>MUT 594</td><td align="center">D</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium chrysogenum </italic>MUT 4021</td><td align="center">C</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">++++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium chrysogenum </italic>MUT 4023</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium chrysogenum </italic>MUT 4025</td><td align="center">C</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium chrysogenum </italic>MUT 610</td><td align="center">C</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium paneum </italic>MUT 649</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium purpurescens </italic>MUT 583</td><td align="center">C</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Penicillium solitum </italic>MUT 610</td><td align="center">D</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>MUT 614</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>MUT 631</td><td align="center">B</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>MUT 637</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>MUT 641</td><td align="center">C</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+++</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>MUT 697</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">++++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>- no growth; + explorative growth consisting of few pellets; ++ evident mycelium in several pellets; +++ consistent mycelium in numerous pellets; ++++ consistent mycelium in homogeneous sporulating colony.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>PCB biotransformation potential of selected isolates</title><p>The ability of the 6 selected fungi to remove 2-chlorobiphenyl, 4,4'-dichlorobiphenyl and 2,2',5,5'-tetrachlorobiphenyl in liquid mineral medium is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. All the applied PCBs were remarkably removed (from 17% to 86%) by the fungi within 30 days of incubation. Considering that PCB recovery yields of the applied solvent extraction procedure was between 88 and 95% and that abiotic losses due to PCB volatilization associated to fungi cultivation were about 7%, it can be concluded that almost the whole observed PCB depletion yields were due to fungal biosorption and biodegradation processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. To determine the role of the two processes to the final PCB removal observed, heat killed controls were developed and used to determine PCB sorption by each fungal strain. Nevertheless, inactivated fungal mycelia usually adsorb pollutants more effectively than living mycelia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Indeed, biosorption of organopollutants and metal ions generally encompasses a number of metabolism-independent processes, still largely unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>], taking place essentially at the cell wall level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] and differently in living and inactivated mycelia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. In the present study inactivated mycelia adsorbed the applied PCBs up to 3 times more efficiently than living mycelia (data not shown). Despite of this, the absorption data obtained were used to calculate the PCB biodegradation yields reported in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, even though this might have resulted in a remarkable underestimation of the biodegradation potential of the assayed cultures.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Adsorption and biodegradation of target PCBs after 30 days of incubation</bold>. PCB removal due to biodegradation (light grey); PCB removal due to biosorption (dark grey). A.f. = <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus </italic>MUT 4026; P.c. = <italic>Penicillium chrysogenum </italic>MUT 4021; F.s. = <italic>Fusarium solani </italic>MUT 4020; P.d. = <italic>Penicillium digitatum </italic>MUT 4079; S.a.1 = <italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>MUT 641; S.a.2 = <italic>Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>MUT 631. Different small letters correspond to significant differences among PCBs biodegradation percentages achieved by different fungal strains towards the same congener. Different numbers correspond to significant differences among PCBs biodegradation percentages achieved by the same fungal strain towards different congeners.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-8-5-1"/></fig><p>The PCB biosorption ability of 6 fungi was different and generally remarkable (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). <italic>A. fumigatus </italic>was the less efficient PCB removing strain and it seemed to exert its activity almost exclusively through biosorption. PCBs biosorption very often increased with the chlorination degree of biphenyl molecule; this finding, which is consistent with other evidences reported in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], indicates that the process is controlled by specific physical-chemical features of the molecule, such as steric conformation, charge distribution, polarity and water solubility, probably able to affect the overall pollutants-biomass binding sites interactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>].</p><p>The PCBs biodegradation efficiency was very different among the 6 strains, indicating that different fungal species, but also different strains of the same species, metabolize congeners differently, as already pointed out by other authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. <italic>P. chrysogenum </italic>almost always displayed the highest degradation potential against all the 3 PCB congeners (up to 72%). High PCB biodegradation yields (up to 48%) were also displayed by the two strains of <italic>S. apiospermum</italic>, whereas <italic>P. digitatum </italic>and <italic>F. solani </italic>showed moderate degradation capabilities (up to 24%) towards the 3 PCBs. Thus, 3 out of the 6 tested strains displayed a remarkable ability to biodegrade the 3 target PCBs, including 2,2',5,5'-tetrachlorobiphenyl, which is the highest chlorinated and most recalcitrant biphenyls among those applied. Notably, the same species have already been reported to degrade several organic xenobiotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>], but they have never been quoted so far for their ability to degrade PCBs.</p><p>Unfortunately, all attempts to determine the main metabolites of PCB biodegradation in the cultures of the most active strains failed. In a preliminary experiment not described in the present paper, a prominent HPLC-detectable compound was found to temporarily accumulate in the culture of <italic>P. chrysogenum</italic>. Such a peak had retention times and diode array UV-absorption spectra very similar to those of pure chlorobenzoic acids; however, it did not co-eluted with any of chlorobenzoic acids we tested, i.e. 2-,3- and 4-monochlorobenzoic acids and 2,3-, 2,4-, 2,5-, 2,6-, 3,5-, and 3,4-dichlorobenzoic acids. The peak could not also be characterised as chlorocatechols or chloroacetophenons, which are other common aromatic intermediates of PCB aerobic bacterial degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. None significant net release of Cl<sup>- </sup>was observed in the biologically active cultures of all PCB degrading strains. Thus, no information on the possible PCB biodegradation routes in the PCB biodegrading fungi described in this study are available.</p></sec><sec><title>Enzymatic analysis</title><p>During PCB biodegradation experiments, only laccase activity was detected in the culture media of 6 assayed fungi. No MiP or MnP activities were detected in the same cultures, either in the presence or in the absence of PCBs, and this provides evidence that extracellular peroxidases were not involved in PCBs degradation. However, also the involvement of laccase in PCB biodegradation in the tested strains is not fully clear as it was produced extensively by <italic>S. apiospermum </italic>MUT 641 (up to 237 U L<sup>-1</sup>) and only in presence of PCBs but not by the parallel highly PCB biodegrading <italic>S. apiospermum </italic>strain MUT 631. On the other hand, biodegradation of aromatic compounds in these species have been so far ascribed to the production of dioxygenases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. <italic>A. fumigatus, P. chrysogenum </italic>and <italic>P. digitatum </italic>displayed low (up to 14 U L<sup>-1</sup>) and similar laccase activities irrespective of the presence of PCBs. <italic>F. solani </italic>also showed a moderate (up to 34 U L<sup>-1</sup>) and constant laccases activity throughout the whole experiment both in presence and the absence of PCBs.</p><p>Laccase activity has been already reported in other <italic>A. fumigatus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] and <italic>Penicillium </italic>spp. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] organopollutant biodegrading strains, but their direct involvement in pollutant degradation has been rarely reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Laccase production by <italic>Fusarium </italic>spp. seems to be constitutive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>], however organopollutants degradation by these species seems to be independent from laccase production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><p>Hence, for almost all fungi employed in this study, no clear correlation between PCBs degradation yields and tested ligninolytic enzymes production was observed and this suggests that also other enzymes, such as mono- or dioxygenase, can be involved in PCBs degradation by fungal isolates described in this work. Further studies will be addressed to investigate the involvement of laccases in PCB degradation by using purified enzymes.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>For the first time in the literature, the mycoflora of an actual site soil historically contaminated by high concentration of PCBs and heavy metals was characterised before, at the beginning and at the end of an aerobic biotreatment performed under laboratory conditions resembling those more commonly applied on the large scale on site remediation of PCB-contaminated soils. The original site soil showed a low concentration of few fungi. <italic>Scedosporium apiospermum, Penicillium </italic>spp. and <italic>Aspergillus </italic>spp. were the dominant species. The indigenous mycoflora was quantitatively and qualitatively further reduced during the biological treatment.</p><p>Nineteen of 21 mitosporic fungi isolated from the soil at the end of its biotreatment grew in the presence of a mixture of 2-chlrobiphenyls, 4,4'-dichlorobiphenyls and 2,2',5,5'-tetrachlorobiphenyl when also glucose was provided. Three of them, <italic>P. chrysogenum </italic>and the two <italic>S. apiospermum </italic>strains, never described as PCB degrader in the literature so far, extensively biodegrade the 3 target PCBs. This degradation, however, can not be clearly correlated with the tested ligninolytic enzymes. In addition, the data presented in this study provide evidence of the relevant role that indigenous fungal biomass might have on the final restoration of actual site historically PCB contaminated soils and of that fungal monitoring as well as fungal needs should be planned in designing an effective contaminated soil bioremediation strategy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Soil characteristics</title><p>The actual site historically contaminated soil employed was strongly polluted by both medium-highly chlorinated biphenyls, largely attributable to Aroclor 1260, and heavy metals. Its main physical, chemical and microbiological characteristics as well the conditions under which it was subjected to biological treatment are reported by Di Toro and collaborators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p><p>In brief, the soil was treated for 120 days under aerobic slurry and solid phase conditions in the absence and in the presence of Enzyveba [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], which is a complex consortium of bacteria and fungi patented and commercialized by Marcopolo Engineering Spa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. Soil samples collected at the beginning (after 3 days of treatment) and at the end of the experiment (120 days) were in this study subjected to mycological analysis and employed for fungi isolation and identification.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of fungi from the soil before and after the bioremediation treatment</title><p>Samples of 10 g dry weight (dw) of site soil along with 10 g of dried soil resulting from bioreactors after 3 and 120 days of treatment were suspended in 90 ml Na<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>&#x000b7;10 H<sub>2</sub>O to disperse organic colloids; further dilutions were made in saline solution (9 g L<sup>-1</sup>NaCl). The final dilution (1:10000) was plated (1 ml per plate) on 20 replicates: 10 on generic MEA (20 g L<sup>-1 </sup>malt extract, 20 g L<sup>-1 </sup>glucose, 2 g L<sup>-1 </sup>peptone, 18 g L<sup>-1 </sup>agar) and 10 on the PR478A (20 g L<sup>-1 </sup>malt extract, 20 g L<sup>-1 </sup>glucose, 2 g L<sup>-1 </sup>peptone, 18 g L<sup>-1 </sup>agar, 0.2 g L<sup>-1 </sup>Poly R478) containing the dye Poly R478, whose degradation by ligninolytic enzymes is considered predictive of the polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons biodegradation capabilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. Both media were supplemented with 15 mg L<sup>-1 </sup>streptomycin sulphate and 50 mg L<sup>-1 </sup>chloramphenicol to inhibit bacteria growth. Plates were incubated at 28&#x000b0;C and after about 3&#x02013;4 days they were read to identify the colonies; serial readings were made to report decolourisation halos, to isolate and to track the progress of slowly growing fungi, for 4 weeks. The number of colony forming units per g of dry weight (CFU g<sup>-1</sup><sub>dw</sub>) was calculated both for the total mycoflora and for each species or morphotype. Fungi were identified conventionally according to their macroscopic and microscopic features. After determination of their genera [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>], they were transferred to the media recommended by the authors of selected genus monographs for species identification. Sterile mycelia were classified according to their hyphal pigments and their production of chlamydospores, sclerotia or vesicles. Sterile mycelia with clamp connections or positive to the reaction with Diazonium Blue B salts (DBB), according to Summerbell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>], were classified as basidiomycetes. When necessary, fungi identification was confirmed by the amplification and the direct sequencing of the internal transcribed spacers (ITS1 and ITS4) of the ribosomial DNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] and of the &#x003b2;-tubulins Bt2a and Bt2b [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>].</p><p>The nonparametric Mann-Whitney test for independent groups was run to assess the significance (<italic>p </italic>&#x02264; 0.05) of the differences among all thesis (media, incubation conditions, soil augmentation). The nonparametric Wilcoxon signed ranks test for dependent groups was run to assess the significance (<italic>p </italic>&#x02264; 0.05) of the differences among sampling times (at the beginning and the end of the experiment). The nonparametric Spearman test was run to assess the significance (<italic>p </italic>&#x02264; 0.05) of the quantitative and qualitative differences between the two media (MEA and PR478A).</p></sec><sec><title>Tolerance and growing capability test</title><p>Fungal strains isolated from the bioreactors at the end of the bioremediation treatment were studied for their potential PCBs degradation capabilities. They were inoculated as a conidial suspension (10<sup>5 </sup>conidia in 100 &#x003bc;l of sterile saline solution) in parallel 100 ml-flasks with Teflon liner-screw caps, containing 3 ml of a modified minimal medium MMM (1.7 g L<sup>-1 </sup>ammonium nitrate, 2 g L<sup>-1 </sup>KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 g L<sup>-1 </sup>MgSO<sub>4</sub>&#x000b7;7H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.157 g L<sup>-1 </sup>CaCl<sub>2</sub>&#x000b7;4 H<sub>2</sub>O, 10 ml L<sup>-1 </sup>micronutrient stock solution) with one of the following carbon sources: a) 10 g L<sup>-1 </sup>glucose (Sigma, Milan, Italy), to check the vitality of the inocula; b) 0.2 g L<sup>-1 </sup>biphenyl (Sigma, Milan, Italy), supplied by adding 18 &#x003bc;l of a 33.33 g L<sup>-1 </sup>stock solution in hexane (Carlo Erba, Milan, Italy), to determine the ability of tested strains to metabolize biphenyl, which is the non-chlorinated analogue of PCBs generally used by PCB degrading microorganisms; c) a mixture of 2-Chlorobiphenyl, 4,4'-Dichlorobiphenyl and 2,2',5,5'-Tertachlorobiphenyl (Sigma, Milan, Italy), each at the final concentration of 20 mg L<sup>-1</sup>, supplied by adding 18 &#x003bc;l of a 10 g L<sup>-1 </sup>stock solution in hexane (Carlo Erba, Milan, Italy), to determine the ability of tested strains to metabolize target PCBs; d) the PCBs mix mentioned above plus 10 g L<sup>-1</sup>glucose, to determine the ability of tested strains to co-metabolize PCBs; e) 10 g L<sup>-1 </sup>glucose plus 18 &#x003bc;l hexane (the same solvent quantity utilised in the parallel cultures), to check the influence of the applied solvent on fungal growth; and f) MMN without carbon source, to check explorative fungal growth due to conidial energy reserves. Flasks were incubated at 25&#x000b0;C and 110 rpm for two weeks. Each trial was performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec><title>PCBs biodegradation in microcosms</title><p>From the previous growth test, 6 fungi were selected for further studies to determine their PCB biodegradation/biosorption potential. They were inoculated (10<sup>5 </sup>conidia in 100 &#x003bc;l of distilled water) in 500 ml-flasks, containing 300 ml of EQ (20 g L<sup>-1 </sup>glucose, 2 g L<sup>-1 </sup>ammonium tartrate, 2 g L<sup>-1 </sup>KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 g L<sup>-1 </sup>MgSO<sub>4</sub>&#x000b7;7H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.157 g L<sup>-1</sup>, Ca(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>&#x000b7;4H<sub>2</sub>O, 10 ml L<sup>-1 </sup>micronutrient stock solution), and incubated in the dark at 110 rpm and 25&#x000b0;C. After 7 days, biomasses were collected with a sieve (150 &#x003bc;m pore), homogenized and then rinsed and centrifuged in sterile distilled water five times, in order to remove residual C traces of the culture medium. Half of each biomass was inactivated in distilled water by autoclaving at 121&#x000b0;C for 30 min.</p><p>The static bioreactors were prepared by placing 0.5 g fresh weight (fw) of the wringed biomass of each fungus in 500 ml-flasks with Teflon liner-screw caps, containing 25 ml of MMM, supplemented with glucose (10 g L<sup>-1</sup>) and the mixture of 3 PCBs (final concentration: 20 mg L<sup>-1 </sup>each). Heat-killed controls (composed by inactivated fungal biomass in the presence of PCBs) were obtained by preparing microcosms as described above, but inoculating them with 0.5 g fw of wringed inactivated biomass. Abiotic controls (PCBs without fungal biomass) and vitality controls (fungus with glucose and without PCBs) were also set up. Microcosms were incubated statically at 25&#x000b0;C in the dark for 30 days. The PCBs disappearance due to biodegradation was estimated at the end of the experiment subtracting the amount of PCBs not extracted from heat-killed control from the total PCBs removed by active mycelia. Each trial was performed in 6 replicates (3 for PCBs degradation and 3 for fungal growth evaluation and enzymatic analyses), with the exception of biotic and abiotic controls, performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec><title>Extractions and analytical procedures</title><p>At the end of the experiment PCBs were extracted from the entire microcosms (i.e., the mycelium and the liquid phase were solvent-extracted together) by using 21.5 ml of hexane and acetone mixture (9:1), vigorously agitated for 5 min and then sonicated for 10 min. The qualitative and quantitative analysis of PCBs occurring in the organic extracts was performed using a gas chromatograph (6890N), equipped with a HP-5 capillary column (30 mby 0.25 mm) and an electron capture detector (&#x003bc;ECD) (Agilent Technologies, Inc. Life Sciences and Chemical Analysis Group, Santa Clara, CA, USA), according to the procedure described by Fava and collaborators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. The depletion of each added PCB was calculated from the average of 3 GC analyses of samples collected from the biological replicates at each given sampling time. Chlorobenzoic acids and related potential aromatic mononuclear intermediates of PCB biodegradation were batch extracted from acidified water phases by using diethyl-ether [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. HPLC analysis of the obtained was performed with a Beckman HPLC system equipped with a Beckman ultrasphere 4.6 &#x000d7; 250 mm ODS column (5 &#x003bc;m particle diameter) and a 168 System Gold Diode Array detector operating at 235 and 254 nm (Beckman Instruments, Fullerton, CA, USA) as mentioned the same paper.</p><p>The concentration of Cl<sup>- </sup>was monitored sampling 1.5 ml of culture medium from 3 parallel cultures after 1 day (T0), 15 days (T1) and 30 days (T2) of treatment and measuring on 0.2 &#x003bc;m pore-filtered samples by using a Dionex DX-120 IC system equipped with an IonPac AS14 4 &#x000d7; 250 mm column, a conductivity detector combined to a ASRS-Ultra conductivity suppressor system (Dionex Corporation, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). The eluent was a solution of 3.5 mM Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3 </sub>and 1.0 mM NaHCO<sub>3 </sub>prepared in ultra-resi-analyzed water; the flow rate was 1.2 ml min<sup>-1 </sup>and the injection volume was 20 &#x003bc;l. Chloride ion concentrations were determined by performing the average of the results obtained from the analyses of samples collected from the 3 parallel identical microcosms at each given sampling time.</p></sec><sec><title>Enzymatic analysis</title><p>The activities of laccase (LAC), Mn-dependent peroxidase (MnP), and Mn-independent peroxidase (MiP) were monitored, sampling 1.5 ml of culture supernatants both from each flask with and without PCBs at T0, T1 and T2. Enzyme activities were measured spectrophotometrically (Amersham Biosciences Ultrospec 3300 Pro) using MBTH/DMAB as the chromogen (in the presence of Mn<sup>2+ </sup>+ H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, in the presence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>without Mn<sup>2+</sup>, in the absence of both H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>and Mn<sup>2+</sup>, and in the presence of Na-citrate respectively). The MiP activity was calculated by subtracting reference values, and MnP activity by subtracting MiP values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>VT carried out the experimental work described in the paper and drafted the manuscript. VP took part in the fungal identification and PCBs extraction, SDT performed the chemical analysis, FF and GCV coordinated the research as well as the manuscript preparation. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was founded by MARCOPOLO ENGINEERING S.p.A. (Borgo S. Dalmazzo, Italy) and by grants from the University of Turin.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borja</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taleon</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Auresenia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallardo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polychlorinated biphenyls and their biodegradation</article-title><source>Process Biochem</source><year>2005</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1999</fpage><lpage>2013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procbio.2004.08.006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasilyeva</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Strijakova</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioremediation of soil and sediment contaminated by polychlorobiphenyls</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2007</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18069324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1134/S002626170706001X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Focht</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies for the improvement of aerobic metabolism of polychlorinated biphenyls</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>346</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Moder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Czihal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peroxidative degradation of selected PCB: a mechanistic study</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1827</fpage><lpage>1834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11061304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0045-6535(00)00132-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Toro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanaroli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intensification of the aerobic bioremediation of an actual site soil historically contaminated by polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) through bioagumentation with non acclimated, complex source of microorganisms</article-title><source>Microb Cell Fact</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16549016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2859-5-11</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of exogenous specialized bacteria in the biological detoxification of a dump site-polychlorinated biphenyl-contaminated soil in slurry phase conditions</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>1999</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10397860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0290(19990720)64:2&#x0003c;240::AID-BIT13&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-F</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Gioia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of the reactor configuration in the biological detoxification of a dump site polychlorobiphenyl-contaminated soil in lab slurry phase conditions</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2000</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002530050015</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pieper</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aerobic degradation of polychlorinated biphenyls</article-title><source>Applied Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2005</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-004-1810-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyauchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Masai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of two biphenyl dioxygenases for biphenyl/PCB degradation in a PCB degrader, Rhodococcus sp strain RHA1</article-title><source>Biosci Biotech Bioch</source><year>2007</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>1002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1271/bbb.60663</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambo</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodegradation of polychlorinated biphenyls in Aroclor 1232 and production of metabolites from 2,4,4'-trichlorobiphenyl at low temperature by psychrotolerant Hydrogenophaga sp strain IA3-A</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>1318</fpage><lpage>1329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17448167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2006.03268.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krcm&#x000e1;r</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubatova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Votruba</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbanova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Novotny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation of polychlorinated biphenyls by extracellular enzymes of Phanerochaete chrysosporium produced in a perforated plate bioreactor</article-title><source>World J Microb Biot</source><year>1999</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008994912875</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz-Aguilar</surname><given-names>GML</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-V&#x000e1;zquez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Poggi Varaldo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation by white rot fungi of high concentrations of PCB extratcted from a contaminated soil</article-title><source>Adv Environ Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1093-0191(01)00102-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamei</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kogura</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism of 4,4'-dichlorobiphenyl by white-rot fungi Phanerochaete chrysosporium and Phanerochaete sp. MZ42</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16528513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-005-0303-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirota</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzukia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suea</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagasakac</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hisamatsua</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonokia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exoenzymes of Trametes versicolor can metabolize coplanar PCB congeners and hydroxy PCB</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2007</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>S54</fpage><lpage>S57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17250871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2006.05.090</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabinovich</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolobova</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasil'chenko</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal decomposition of natural aromatic structures and xenobiotics: a review</article-title><source>Appl Biochem Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:ABIM.0000010343.73266.08</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mycoremediation, Fungal Bioremediation</source><year>2006</year><publisher-name>Wiley-Interscience</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novotny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>BRM</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbanova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubatova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Removal of PCBs by various white rot fungi in liquid cultures</article-title><source>Folia Microbiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9340310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02898723</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishibori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Masai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohdaira</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation of polychlorinated biphenyls by a 'Maitake' mushroom, Grifola frondosa</article-title><source>Biotechnol Lett</source><year>1999</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1005457201291</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubatova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbanova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichlerova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Homolka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nerud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PCB congener selective biodegradation by the white rot fungus Pleurotus ostreatus in contaminated soil</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2001</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11297400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0045-6535(00)00154-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verdin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahraoui</surname><given-names>ALH</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation of benzo[a]pyrene by mitosporic fungi and extracellular oxidative enzymes</article-title><source>Int Biodeter Biodegr</source><year>2004</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibiod.2003.12.001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sietmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gesell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative ring cleavage of low chlorinated biphenyl derivatives by fungi leads to the formation of chlorinated lactone derivatives</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2006</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16352329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2005.10.050</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mancera-Lopez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Esparza-Garcia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavez-Gomez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Vazquez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Saucedo-Castaneda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrera-Cortes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioremediation of an aged hydrocarbon-contaminated soil by a combined system of biostimulation-bioaugmentation with filamentous fungi</article-title><source>Int Biodeter Biodegr</source><year>2008</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibiod.2007.05.012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mineralization of polychlorinated biphenyls by <italic>Phanerochaete chrysosporium</italic>: a ligninolytic fungus</article-title><source>Enzyme Microb Technol</source><year>1985</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>196</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carswell</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgiou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mineralization of biphenyls and PCB by the white rot fungus <italic>Phanerochaete chrysosporium</italic></article-title><source>Biotecnol Bioeng</source><year>1992</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1395</fpage><lpage>1402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.260401114</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hockey</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation of 4,4'-dichlorobiphenyl, 3,3',4,4'-tetrachlorobiphenyl, and 2,2',4,4',5,5'-hexachlorobiphenyl by the white rot fungus Phanerochaete chrysosporium</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>3904</fpage><lpage>3909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8526503</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gesell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Specht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Francke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biotransformation of biphenyl by Paecilomyces lilacinus and characterisation of ring cleavage products</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1551</fpage><lpage>1557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11282604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.67.4.1551-1557.2001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sietmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biotransformation of biarylic compounds by yeasts of the genus Trichosporon</article-title><source>System Appl Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12421071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1078/0723-2020-00131</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Elsas JD, Trevors JT</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The fungi in soil</article-title><source>Modern Soil Microbiology Marsel Dekker</source><year>1997</year><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>127</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luppi Mosca</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipello Marchisio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micoflora di un terreno orticolo</article-title><source>Allionia</source><year>1976</year><fpage>XXI</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baudino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversit&#x000e0; e biomassa fungina in un suolo inquinato da metalli pesanti</article-title><source>Degree thesis</source><year>2001</year><publisher-name>University of Turin, Plant Biology Department</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Filipello Marchisio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Luppi Mosca</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micoflora di fumarole dell'isola di Pantelleria (Sicilia, Italia)</article-title><source>Alliona</source><year>1982</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'Annibale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosetto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Federici</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Petruccioli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of Autochthonous Filamentous Fungi in Bioremediation of a Soil Historically Contaminated with Aromatic Hydrocarbons</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16391021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.72.1.28-36.2006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Quensen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Young Y and Cerniglia CE</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial reductive dechlorination of polychlorinated biphenyls</article-title><source>Microbial Transformation and Degradation of Toxic Organic Chemicals</source><year>1995</year><publisher-name>New York: Wiley-Liss</publisher-name><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>216</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>ECMM-ISHAM Working Group on <italic>Pseudoallesceria/Scedosporium apiospermum </italic>infection</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scedosporium-ecmm.com/"/></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clau&#x000df;en</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodegradation of phenol and p-cresol by the hiphomycete Scedosporium apiospermum</article-title><source>Res Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9766239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0923-2508(98)80322-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janda-Ulfig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulfig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guarro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study of the growth of Pseudallescheria boydii isolates from sewage sludge and clinical sources on tributyrin, rapeseed oil, biodiesel oil and diesel</article-title><source>Ann of Agr Env Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18581978</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin-Gil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Navas-Gracia</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Sobrino</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Correa-Guimaraes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Navarro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Bascones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos-Sanchez</surname><given-names>MDC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composting and vermicomposting experiences in the treatment and bioconversion of asphaltens from the Prestige oil spill</article-title><source>Bioresource Technol</source><year>2008</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>1821</fpage><lpage>1829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2007.03.031</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Adholeya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification, ligninolytic enzyme activity and decolorization potential of two fungi isolated from a distillery effluent contaminated site</article-title><source>Water Air Soil Poll</source><year>2007</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11270-007-9366-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anastasi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Varese</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipello Marchisio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and identification of fungal communities in compost and vermicompost</article-title><source>Mycologia</source><year>2005</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16389954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3852/mycologia.97.1.33</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gadd MG</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Bioremediationotential of white rot fungi</article-title><source>Fungi in Bioremediation</source><year>2001</year><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murado</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tejedor</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Baluja</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction between polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) and soil microfungi. Effect of Aroclor 1254 and other PCBs on Aspergillus flavus cultures</article-title><source>Bull Environ Contam Toxicol</source><year>1976</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>768</fpage><lpage>774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">820390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01685631</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaudette</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorak</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of gas chromatography and mineralization experiments for measuring loss of selected polychlorinated biphenyl congeners in cultures of white rot fungi</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>2020</fpage><lpage>2025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9603809</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casieri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Prigione</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Anastasi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tigini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Varese</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism-independent biosorption of industrial dyes by fungal biomasses revealed by batch sorption experiments and confocal microscopy</article-title><source>Special Issue on Conventional and non-conventional adsorbents for dye removal from aqueous solutions International Journal of Chemical Engineering</source><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moeder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cajthaml</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koeller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbanova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure selectivity in degradation and translocation of polychlorinated biphenyls (Delor 103) with a Pleurotus ostreatus (oyster mushroom) culture</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2005</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1370</fpage><lpage>1378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16291407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2005.02.098</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aksu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of biosorption for the removal of organic pollutants: A review</article-title><source>Process Biochem</source><year>2005</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procbio.2004.04.008</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brahimihorn</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Binding of textile azo dyes by Myrothecium verrucaria</article-title><source>J Ind Microbiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01583631</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clau&#x000df;en</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodegradation of phenylbenzoate and some of its derivatives by Scedosporium apiospermum</article-title><source>Res Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10466410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0923-2508(99)80077-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leit&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos Oliveira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation of phenol by a halotolerant strain of Penicillium chrysogenum</article-title><source>Int Biodeter Biodegr</source><year>2007</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibiod.2006.09.009</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation of metabolites of benzo[a]pyrene by coupling Penicillium chrysogenum with KMnO4</article-title><source>J Environ Sci-China</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17915736</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugareva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinekamp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brakhage</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of the laccase-encoding gene abr2 of the dihydroxynaphthalene-like melanin gene cluster of Aspergillus fumigatus</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16988817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00203-006-0144-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Laccase activities of a soil fungus Penicillium simplicissimum in relation to lignin degradation</article-title><source>World J Microb Biot</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-005-9025-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canero</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>MIG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analyses of laccase genes from Fusarium oxysporum</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2008</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-98-5-0509</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pointing</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of different carbon and nitrogen regimes on Poly R decolorization by white-rot fungi</article-title><source>Mycol Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0953756201005202</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domsch</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gams</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Compendium of soil fungi</source><year>1980</year><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Arx</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cramer J</surname></name></person-group><source>The genera of fungi sporulating in pure culture</source><year>1981</year></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiffer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Les deut&#x000e9;romyc&#x000e8;tes Classification et cl&#x000e9;s d'identification g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rique</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Paris: INRA</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summerbell</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The staining of filamentous fungi with diazonium blue B</article-title><source>Mycologia</source><year>1985</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3793357</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Innis MA, Gelfand JJ, Sninsky, White TJ</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Amplification and direct sequencing of fungal ribosomal RNA genes for phylogenesis</article-title><source>PCR Protocols: A Guide to Methods and Applications</source><year>1990</year><publisher-name>New York: Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>322</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ITS primers with enhanced specificity for baidiomycetes &#x02013; Application to the identification of mycorrhizae and rusts</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>1993</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8180733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.1993.tb00005.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of prime sets designed for use with the PCR to amplify conserved genes from filamentous Ascomycetes</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7747954</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanaroli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial reductive dechlorination of pre-existing PCBs and spiked 2,3,4,5,6-pentachlorobiphenyl in anaerobic slurries of a contaminated sediment of Venice Lagoon (Italy)</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-6496(03)00069-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Gioia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soya lecithin effects on the aerobic biodegradation of polychlorinated biphenyls in an artificially-contaminated soil</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>2001</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0290(20000120)72:2&#x0003c;177::AID-BIT6&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-K</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>BRM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasek</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of temperature on the production of manganese peroxidase and lignin peroxidase by <italic>Phanerochaete-Chrysosporium</italic></article-title><source>Folia Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02814523</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>