<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18292635</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636082</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_2_163_39129</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Combination of photodynamic therapy with intravitreal bevacizumab for post-peribulbar anesthesia (penetrating		trauma)-persistent choroidal neovascular membrane</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Nikunj</given-names></name><degrees>DNB</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Urmi</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>The Eye Super-Specialities, An LV Prasad Eye Institute Collaborating Center, Ghatkopar (East), Mumbai - 400 077, Maharashtra,India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Nikunj Shah, The Eye Super-Specialities, AnLV Prasad Eye Institute Collaborating Center, 201 Punit Plaza, Next toRajawadi Post offi ce, Ghatkopar (East), Mumbai - 400 077, Maharashtra,India. Email: <email>urminikunj@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Mar-Apr</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access		article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits		unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We report a case of a choroidal neovascular membrane (CNVM)following ocular penetration during peribulbar anesthesia in a 55-year-old male patient. A combination of photodynamic therapywith intravitreal bevacizumab led to resolution of the persistentCNVM.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Bevacizumab</kwd><kwd>choroidal neovascular membrane</kwd><kwd>penetrating ocular injury</kwd><kwd>peribulbar anesthesia</kwd><kwd>photodynamic therapy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Peribulbar anesthesia is an established technique of anesthesiafor ocular surgeries.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> Ocular penetration and its complicationsfollowing peribulbar anesthesia have often been reported inthe literature.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></p><p>We are unaware of previous reports of a choroidalneovascular membrane (CNVM) following penetrating ocularinjury due to peribulbar anesthesia and its response to standardphotodynamic therapy (PDT) along with intravitreal anti-vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) agents.</p><sec sec-type=""><title>Case Report</title><p>A 55-year-old male patient presented to us with history ofsudden onset metamorphopsia in the left eye. He was operatedin the same eye four months back for vitreous hemorrhagesecondary to ocular penetration following peribulbaranesthesia for cataract surgery (both the surgeries were doneelsewhere). He was a known case of open angle glaucomaunder treatment with timolol maleate 0.5% eye drops twicea day and dorzolamide eye drops thrice a day over the pastthree years.</p><p>On examination, the best-corrected visual acuity in theright eye was finger counting (FC) three feet, &#x0003c;N36 and in theleft eye was 20/120, N18. The intraocular pressure (IOP) was14 mmHg in either eye with applanation tonometer. Fundusexamination showed retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) atrophyat the macula in the right eye and a large scar running acrossthe macula bordered by fluid and hemorrhage at its distal endin the left [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>]. There was an advanced glaucomatous opticneuropathy (cup disc ratio - 0.9:1 with pale neuro-retinal rim)in either eye.</p><p>On fundus fluorescein angiography (FFA) of the left eye,there was a linear hypofluorescence running across the maculacorresponding to the needle tract through the RPE. At its distaledge was found a hyperfluorescent area with leakage suggestiveof a CNVM [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, inset]. Patient was subjected to standardfluence PDT for the same. There was persistence of CNVM onemonth following PDT [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2L">Fig. 2, left</xref>]. At this point of time patientwas subjected to combination therapy of a standard fluencePDT with intravitreal bevacizumab (2.5 mg/0.1 ml, Off-label)injection immediately after the PDT, which was uneventful. Sixmonths following the treatment visual acuity had stabilized to20/60, N12 with no leakage on FFA [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2R">Fig. 2, right</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>Globe penetration is a less common complication of peribulbaranesthesia (0.006%).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> This incidence is likely to be higher inpatients with high myopia owing to the increased axial lengthas in our patient.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> However, as the cataract surgery was doneelsewhere the exact technique and sequence of events was notknown.</p><p>The presumed etiology of CNVM, due to ocularperforation during peribulbar anesthesia, can be postulatedby the development of vitreous hemorrhage immediately afterthe cataract surgery and the relation of the CNVM with the needletract on FFA. PDT is an established treatment for predominantlyclassic CNVM following age related macular degeneration(ARMD). Photodynamic therapy seems to be effective againstCNVM due to choroidal rupture following blunt trauma.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></p><p>Intravitreal bevacizumab (Genentech) has been foundsuccessful in the treatment of a wide variety of ocularpathologies including CNVM of varied etiologies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> It was chosenin our patient (who had advanced glaucoma) because of lesserpropensity to elevate IOP compared to triamcinolone acetate.As the effect of bevacizumab would have been short-lived ina vitrectomized eye a combined treatment was preferred overmonotherapy.</p><p>Thus, CNVM following ocular penetration is a rare butsight-threatening complication of peribulbar anesthesia. Acombination therapy of PDT with intravitreal bevacizumabseems to be an effective therapy.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>DB</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name><name><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and complication rate of 16,224 consecutive peribulbar blocks: A prospective multicenter study</article-title><source>J Cataract Refract Surg</source><year>1994</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8064611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McKibbin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of ocular perforations resulting from peribulbar anaesthesia</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>1999</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10858774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lingam</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Badrinath</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chawla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinal detachment secondary to ocular perforation during retrobulbar anaesthesia</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>1995</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8522363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orbital regional anaesthesia: Complications and their prevention</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16770022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gadkari Salil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of 19 cases of inadvertent globe perforation due to periocular injections</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2007</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17322598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanmugam</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photodynamic therapy of a post traumatic choroidal neovascular membrane</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2005</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15976472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bashshur</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazarbachi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schakal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>El Haibi</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Noureddin</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravitreal bevacizumab for the management of choroidal neovascularization in age-related maculardegeneration</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16815245</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Fundus examination of the left eye shows a large scar running across the macula bordered by fluid and hemorrhage at its distal end.Inset: Fundus fluorescein angiography of the left eye shows a linear hypofluorescence running across the macula corresponding to theneedle tract through the retinal pigment epithelium. At its distal end was found a hyperfluorescent area with leakage suggestive of achoroidal neovascular membrane</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-163-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2L" position="float"><label>Fig. 2, left</label><caption><p>Left: Fundus fluorescein angiography of the left eye shows persistent leakage from the choroidal neovascular membrane (after firstphotodynamic therapy)</p></caption><alt-text>Fig. 2, left</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-163-g002"/></fig><fig id="F2R" position="float"><label>Fig. 2, right</label><caption><p>Right: Fundus fluorescein angiography of the left eye at the last visit shows absence of leakage from the choroidal neovascularmembrane</p></caption><alt-text>Fig. 2, right</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-163-g003"/></fig></floats-group></article>