<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18579985</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636169</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_4_279_39663</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cyclooxygenase-2 expression in primary and recurrent pterygium</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Karahan</surname><given-names>Nermin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baspinar</surname><given-names>Sirin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ciris</surname><given-names>Metin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baydar</surname><given-names>Cetin Lutfi</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kapucuoglu</surname><given-names>Nilgun</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Departments of Pathology (NK, MC, NK), Forensic Medicine (CLB),Suleyman Demirel University School of Medicine, Isparta, Turkey,Department of Pathology (SB), Egirdir Bone Joint Diseases Treatmentand Rehabilitation Hospital, Isparta, Turkey</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Nermin Karahan, Suleyman Demirel University,School of Medicine, Department of Pathology, Isparta-Turkey. Email: <email>nerminkarahan@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Aug</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Pterygia are common, benign, fibrovascular, and infiltrative processes of the corneo-conjunctival junction of unknown pathogenesis. Cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) mediates the rate-limiting stepin arachidonic acid metabolism. Extensive evidence indicates that the COX-2 prostanoid pathway is involvedin inflammation. The aim of the study was to document the immunohistochemical expression of COX-2 inprimary and recurrent pterygia.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>In this study, 21 primary pterygia and 12 recurrent pterygia from subjects undergoingpterygium surgery and six normal corneal-scleral tissue specimens were studied immunohistochemically forCOX-2 expression.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>COX-2 was expressed in primary pterygia and recurrent pterygia specimens. There was a statisticallysignificant difference in COX-2 expressions in fibroblasts between primary and recurrent pterygium cases(<italic>P</italic> = 0.001). There were statistically significant differences in COX-2 expressions in surface epithelium(<italic>P</italic> = 0.028) and stromal inflammatory cells (<italic>P</italic>=0.000) between control tissues and primary pterygiatissues. We also detected statistically significant differences in COX-2 expressions in surface epithelium (<italic>P</italic>=0.000),stromal fibroblasts <italic>P</italic>=0.000 (stromal fibroblasts and inflammatory cells), vessels (<italic>P</italic> = 0.027) andinflammatory cells (<italic>P</italic>=0.001) between control tissues and recurrent pterygia tissues.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>This is the first study to document the expression of COX-2 in primary and recurrent pterygia. Inour opinion after excision of pterygia, fibroblastic proliferation continues and this contributes to recurrence.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cyclooxygenase-2</kwd><kwd>immunohistochemistry</kwd><kwd>primary pterygium</kwd><kwd>recurrent pterygium</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Pterygia are common, frequently recurring ocular surface lesionscharacterized by tissue remodeling, cellular proliferation,angiogenesis, and inflammation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> Irritation of theye by ultraviolet (UV) light in sunny, dry, dusty areas and repeatedmicrotrauma can lead to development of pterygium insusceptible individuals.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> Pterygia are histopathologicallyfibrovascular proliferations. This expansiveness of fibrovascularproliferation is considered as a convenient morphological indexfor evaluation of recurrence risk after surgical treatment.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Pterygia usually recur after surgical excision.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> The causeof recurrence may be related to several factors includingenvironmental factors. If etiological and pathogenic differencesbetween recurrent and non-recurrent cases are discovered, thetype of treatment can be more easily selected and convenienttreatment can be found.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></p><p>Histopathological findings reveal epithelial hyperplasiaand exuberant fibrovascular tissue in the stroma of pterygia.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>Importantly, the extent of fibrovascular proliferation in thestroma has been used as a reliable morphological index forpredicting pterygium recurrence following primary excision.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref> Cyclooxygenase-1 (COX-1) and cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2)mediate the rate-limiting step in arachidonic acid metabolism.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>Expression of COX-2 mRNA and protein is often enhanced invarious human cell types by inflammatory cytokines such asinterleukin-1&#x003b2; (IL-1&#x003b2;) and tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1; (TNF-&#x003b1;).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>Both isoforms of cyclooxygenase, constitutive COX-1 andinducible COX-2, catalyze the production of prostanoids fromarachidonic acid.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> COX-2-induced production of prostanoidsis often implicated in inflammatory diseases, characterizedby edema and tissue injury due to the release of manyinflammatory cytokines and chemotactic factors, prostanoids,leukotrienes, and phospholipase.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></p><p>COX-2 expression is induced by various stimuli, and theover-expression is closely related to the pathogenesis of somedegenerative diseases including cancer.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> Several lines ofevidence indicate that COX-2 over-expression can be a causalfactor for tumor growth and metastasis. Over-expression ofCOX-2 <italic>in vitro</italic> promotes cell proliferation in human prostatecancer cells and enhances invasiveness of human bladder,breast and colon cancer cells.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> Moreover, thefindings regarding the effects of COX-2 in cutaneous tumor formationhave also been reported in pterygium, including disruptionof apoptosis, limbal epithelial proliferation, abnormal p53gene expression, and upregulation of basic fibroblast growthfactor, vascular endothelial growth factor, and nitric oxidesynthase.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></p><p>The aim of the study was to find out the relationshipbetween COX-2 expression and primary as well as recurrentpterygium.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>Resected pterygium tissue samples from 33 patients of 21with primary pterygium, 12 with recurrent pterygium andsix normal corneo-scleral tissues were included in this study.Primary and recurrent pterygium samples were selectedretrospectively from archival material of the department ofpathology, Suleyman Demirel University School of Medicine.All pterygia were sectioned along the longitudinal axis toinclude from the cap (leading edge) to the basal (body) region.Normal corneo-scleral tissues were obtained during forensicautopsy cases with attorney&#x02032;s permission.</p><p>Immunohistochemical analysis for COX-2 was performedon formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded archival tissue usingthe streptavidin-biotin-peroxidase technique. For all cases,4 &#x000b5;m histological section was deparaffinized in xylene anddehydrated in descending dilution of ethanol. For the antigenretrieval, slides were treated by microwave heating in citratebuffer (pH 6.0) for 10 min. Endogenous peroxidase activitywas blocked by 20 min of incubation with 0.3% hydrogenperoxidase. Slides were tested with COX-2 antibody (1:100Epitope specific rabbit antibody, Lab Vision). Sections weretested with streptavidin-biotin-peroxidase kit (Ultra VisionLarge Volume Detection System Anti-polyvalent, HRP, LabVision, USA), and after incubation the reaction productwas detected using diaminobenzidine (DAB). Finally, thesections were counterstained with Mayer&#x02032;s hematoxylin, andmounted with mounting medium. Tissue of colon cancerfrom a human served as the positive control in the COX-2immunostaining.</p><p>Two observers analyzed the staining for COX-2.Immunohistochemical analysis of the primary and recurrentpterygium was performed with anti-COX-2 antibody. Themean overall intensity of the immunostaining in the surfaceepithelium and stromal cells was scored in the analyzedsections of primary and recurrent pterygium samples asfollows: 0 = absent immunostaining; 1 = weak immunostaining(few cells being positive focal or scattered); 2 = strongimmunostaining (diffuse staining throughout the tissue). Thehistology was checked using slides stained with HematoxylinEosin.</p><p>For statistical evaluation, the SPSS software version 13.0 wasused. The Fisher exact and chi-square tests were used to analyzethe distribution of COX -2 positive cases according to severalhistopathological features. <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered assignificant.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Our group consisted of 23 (59%) men and 16 (41%) women.Ages of the patients ranged from 36 to 80 (median 54 years).Eleven of 21 primary pterygium cases were males and 10 ofthem were females. Eight of the recurrent pterygium cases weremales and four were females. Four of the six healthy conjunctivacases were males and two of them were females.</p><p>COX-2 immunostaining was observed mainly in thecytoplasm of surface epithelium, stromal inflammatory cells,capillary vessels and fibroblasts. There were statisticallysignificant differences in COX-2 expressions in the surfaceepithelium (<italic>P</italic> = 0.028) and stromal inflammatory cells (<italic>P</italic>=0.000)between control tissues and primary pterygia tissues.</p><p>We also detected statistically significant differences in COX-2expressions in surface epithelium (<italic>P</italic>=0.000), stromal fibroblasts<italic>P</italic>=0.000 (stromal fibroblasts and inflammatory cells), vessels(<italic>P</italic> = 0.027) and inflammatory cells (<italic>P</italic>=0.001) between controltissues and recurrent pterygia tissues.</p><p>Statistical significance was not observed in epithelialstaining of primary and recurrent pterygium cases (<italic>P</italic> = 0.06).In 14 primary pterygium cases and in all recurrent pterygiumcases, COX-2 expressions were detected in fibroblasts. Inall the recurrent pterygium cases COX-2 showed strongexpression. There was a statistically significant difference inCOX-2 expression in fibroblasts between primary and recurrentpterygium cases (<italic>P</italic> = 0.001).</p><p>COX-2 expressions in both epithelium and stroma of normalcorneo-scleral tissue, primary and recurrent pterygia areshown in Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>. The relation between COX-2 expressions inepithelium and stroma of normal corneo-scleral tissue, primaryand recurrent pterygia are shown in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Pterygium has long been considered to be a chronic degenerativecondition. However, after over-expression of the p53 proteinwas found in the epithelium of pterygium, some researchersbegan to feel that pterygium was an ultraviolet (UV)-relatedtumor rather than a degenerative disease.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></p><p>Although the pathogenesis of pterygia is still poorlyunderstood, epidemiologic evidence suggests that environmentalstress may have a role.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Recently, several cytokinessuch as TNF-&#x003b1;, fibroblast growth factor (FGF), and transforming growthfactor-&#x003b2; (TGF-&#x003b2;), have been localized to both resident andinflammatory cells in pterygia.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> Kria <italic>etal</italic>.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> recently reportedthat pterygium fibroblasts express potent fibroangiogenic factorssuch as basic fibroblast growth factor (&#x003b2;-FGF), platelet derivedgrowth factor (PDGF), TGF-&#x003b2; and TNF-&#x003b1;, suggesting that theymay have a possible role in pterygium pathogenesis.</p><p>COX-2 is an inducible immediate-early gene which is up-regulated by various stimuli, including mitogens, cytokines,growth factors, and tumor promoters.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> Extensive evidenceindicates that COX-2 prostanoid pathway is involved ininflammation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> COX-2 modulates angiogenesis by increasingthe production of angiogenic factors, such as vascularendothelial growth factor.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> Chiang <italic>etal</italic>.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref> investigatedthe expression of COX-2 in pterygium and found 75 (83.3%)specimens stained positive for COX-2 in the pterygiumgroup. The staining was limited to the cytoplasm of theepithelial layer and predominantly over the basal epitheliallayer. No substantial staining was visible in the subepithelialfibrovascular layers. All specimens were negative in the normalconjunctiva and limbus group. In our study we detected COX-2expression both in normal corneo-scleral tissues, primarypterygia and recurrent pterygia in superficial epithelium andalso in stromal cells with immunohistochemical methods. Wealso found that COX-2 expressions were significantly moreintense in stromal fibroblasts of recurrent pterygia comparedto primary pterygia. This finding manifests that fibroblasticproliferation is more developed in recurrent pterygia comparedto primary pterygia.</p><p>Also, in all the recurrent pterygia there were COX-2expressions detected in stromal inflammatory cells. Althoughwe observed that COX-2 expression is more excessive inrecurrent pterygia compared to primary pterygia, this wasnot statistically significant. It may be due to our small seriesof recurrent pterygia.</p><p>Pterygium is now considered to be a result of uncontrolledcellular proliferation, similar to that in tumors, in which thereis damage to cellular regulation and control of the cell cycle.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>Mitogenity, construction of a new vascular net and remodelingof the extracellular matrix were observed in pterygia. Altogetherthey create a new vascular and fibrotic tissue, which has anaggressive way of growing to and over the cornea.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></p><p>Changes in the proteoglycans are known to induceedematous changes, which in turn cause fibroblast proliferation.It is not yet clear how the tissue alterations are initiated andkept in progress.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref> Controversial factors includethe mutation of limbus stem cells, modification of stromal fibroblasts,and immunological and other processes in the matrix. Innew models of pterygial pathogenesis, interactions betweenepithelial cells, fibroblasts, and matrix are considered as wellas the denaturing action of the matrix metalloproteinases.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></p><p>The management of pterygia is still a challenge for theophthalmologist. Many surgical procedures have beenproposed for pterygium removal.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref> However, surgery aloneis not sufficient and cannot prevent a high incidence ofrecurrence.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref> There are theories that the causes consideredas etiological agents in recurrence development in pterygiaare inflammations besides UV-rays and other environmentalfactors.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> In our opinion after excision of pterygia, fibroblasticproliferation continues and this contributes to recurrence.</p><p>However if a fibroblastic cell invasion of the cornea isconsidered to be the essential pathology, then a recurrence couldbe ascribed to the same cause, namely, an accelerated reinvasionof the cornea. As Cameron<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref> indicated, the recurrence wouldappear to be due to an accelerated fibroblastic proliferationproduced by the trauma of operation. In our opinionfibroblastic proliferation explains the clinical appearance andbehavior of a recurrent pterygium. As a result, in the light ofthese findings, we think that after pterygium excision, selectiveCOX-2 inhibitors may be helpful to prevent recurrence.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Source of Support: Nil</p></fn><fn><p>Conflict of Interest: None declared</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coroneo</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Girolamo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pathogenesis of pterygia</article-title><source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10621537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maske</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis of pterygium</article-title><source>Eye</source><year>1989</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2695353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degrassi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Piantanida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nucci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unexpected histologicalfindings in pterygium</article-title><source>Optom Vis Sci</source><year>1993</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1058</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8115131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avisar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avisar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary pterygium recurrence time</article-title><source>Isr Med Assoc J</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11729580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marvovich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morad</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandbank</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiogenesis in pterygium:Morphometric and immunohistochemical study</article-title><source>Curr Eye Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12518239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chee</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dear</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of pterygium morphology onpterygium recurrence in a controlled trial comparing conjunctivalautografting with bare sclera excision</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>1997</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>1235</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9338666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Touhami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Pascuale</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawatika</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Valle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>RH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Dubovy S</surname><given-names>al</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of myofibroblasts in fibrovasculartissues of primary and recurrent pterygia</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2005</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15722301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kria</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amemiya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunohistochemical localizationof basic fibroblast growth factor, platelet derived growth factor,transforming growth factor and tumor necrosis factor in a primarypterygium</article-title><source>Acta Histochem</source><year>1996</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8739304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Girolamo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Coreneo</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UVB-Elicited inductionof MMP-1 expression in human ocular surface epithelial cells ismediated through the ERK1/2 MAPK- dependent pathway</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>4705</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14578390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcovich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morad</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandbank</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiogenesis in pterygium:Morphometric and immunohistochemical study</article-title><source>Curr Eye Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12518239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>DuBois</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of cyclooxyigenasesin inflammation, cancer and development</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>7908</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10630643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuwano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuneyoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclooxygenase2 is a key enzyme for inflammatory cytokine-induced angiogenesis</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14769824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Garavito</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWitt</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostaglandin endoperoxideH synthases (cyclooxygenases)-1 and -2</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>33157</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8969167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsujii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>DuBois</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclooxygenase-2 expression inhuman colon cancer cells increases metastatic potential</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>3336</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9096394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Koshida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Namiki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cyclooxygenase-2 promotes prostate cancer progression</article-title><source>Prostate</source><year>2002</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12386924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclooxygenase-2 increased the angiogenic andmetastatic potential of tumor cells</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2002</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>886</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12470662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COX-2overexpression increases motility and invasion of breast cancercells</article-title><source>Int J Oncol</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1393</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abnormal expression of thep53 tumor suppressor gene in the conjunctiva of patients withpterygium</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>1997</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9063255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apoptosis andapoptosis related gene expression in normal conjunctiva andpterygium</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2000</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10655200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dushku</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pterygia pathogenesis:Corneal invasion by matrix metalloproteinase expressingaltered limbal epithelial basal cells</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>2001</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11346397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of vascularendothelial growth factor and inducible nitric oxide synthase inpterygia</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11588427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclooxygenase 2 expression in pterygium</article-title><source>Mol Vis</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17515883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perra</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minerba</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Demurtas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress in pterygium: Relationship between p53 and8-hydroxydeoxyguanosine</article-title><source>Mol Vis</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1136</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17093398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pterygium</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16714259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakoonwatanyoo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of p63 inpterygium and normal conjunctiva</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14701960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pterygium: Prevalence, demography and riskfactors</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Epidemiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10487976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Spitznas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Topological-histologicalinvestigation of the pterygium</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><year>2001</year><volume>239</volume><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11450493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirst</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of pterygium</article-title><source>Aust N Z J Ophthalmol</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histology of pterygium: An electron microscopicstudy</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>1983</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>604</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6882718</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Weak COX-2 expression in epithelium and stroma of normal corneo-scleral tissue (A) (COX- X100), (B) (COX-2X200)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-279-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Moderate COX-2 expression in epithelium and stroma of primary pterygium tissue (A) (COX-2X100), (B) (COX-2X200)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-279-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Strong COX-2 expression in epithelium and stroma of recurrent pterygium tissue (A) (COX-2X100), (B) (COX-2X200) Epithelium (E),fibroblasts (F), capillaries (C) and infl ammatory cells (I) were shown in figures with arrows</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-279-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Cyclooxygenase-2 expressions in epithelium and stroma of normal corneo-scleral tissue and primary pterygia</p></caption><alt-text>Table 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-279-g004"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Cyclooxygenase-2 expressions in epithelium and stroma of normal corneo-scleral tissue and recurrent pterygia</p></caption><alt-text>Table 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-279-g005"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Cyclooxygenase-2 expressions in epithelium and stroma of primary and recurrent pterygia</p></caption><alt-text>Table 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-279-g006"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>