<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Physiol (1985)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Appl. Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jap</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Applied Physiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">8750-7587</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1522-1601</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Physiological Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19008490</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636937</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JAPPL-90578-2008</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.90578.2008</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Variations within oxygen-regulated gene expression in humans</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>Jerome T. S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elvidge</surname><given-names>Gareth P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Glenny</surname><given-names>Louisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gleadle</surname><given-names>Jonathan M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Chun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ragoussis</surname><given-names>Jiannis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Thomas G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>Nick P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Winchester</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>Patrick H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>Peter A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d33e124">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="d33e124"><label>1</label>Department of Physiology, Anatomy and Genetics and <label>2</label>Wellcome Trust Centre for Human Genetics, University of Oxford, Oxford; and <label>3</label>Division of Medicine, University College, London, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><corresp>Address for reprint requests and other correspondence: P. A. Robbins, Dept. of Physiology, Anatomy and Genetics, Sherrington Bldg., Parks Rd., Oxford OX1 3PT, UK (e-mail: <email>peter.robbins&#x00040;dpag.ox.ac.uk</email>)</corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>G. P. Elvidge and L. Glenny contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 12 months and 0 days and was based on the copyright element. --><volume>106</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009, American Physiological Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.the-aps.org/publications/journals/funding_addendum_policy.htm">www.the-aps.org/publications/journals/funding_addendum_policy.htm</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zdg00109000212.pdf"/><abstract><p>The effects of hypoxia on gene transcription are mainly mediated by a transcription factor complex termed hypoxia-inducible factor (HIF). Genetic manipulation of animals and studies of humans with rare hereditary disease have shown that modifying the HIF pathway affects systems-level physiological responses to hypoxia. It is, however, an open question whether variations in systems-level responses to hypoxia between individuals could arise from variations within the HIF system. This study sought to determine whether variations in the responsiveness of the HIF system at the cellular level could be detected between normal individuals. Peripheral blood lymphocytes (PBL) were isolated on three separate occasions from each of 10 healthy volunteers. After exposure of PBL to eight different oxygen tensions ranging from 20&#x00025; to 0.1&#x00025;, the expression levels of four HIF-regulated transcripts involved in different biological pathways were measured. The profile of expression of all four transcripts in PBL was related to oxygen tension in a curvilinear manner. Double logarithmic transformation of these data resulted in a linear relationship that allowed the response to be parameterized through a gradient and intercept. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) on these parameters showed that the level of between-subject variation in the gradients of the responses that was common across all four HIF-regulated transcripts was significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.008). We conclude that statistically significant variation within the cellular response to hypoxia can be detected between normal humans. The common nature of the variability across all four HIF-regulated genes suggests that the source of this variation resides within the HIF system itself.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>hypoxia-inducible factor</kwd><kwd>reverse transcription quantitative polymerase chain reaction</kwd><kwd>oxygen tension</kwd><kwd>peripheral blood lymphocytes</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. The article must therefore be hereby marked &#x0201c;<italic>advertisement</italic>&#x0201d; in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><p><sc>maintenance of oxygen homeostasis</sc> is crucial for the survival of aerobic organisms. Hypoxia induces a range of responses at both molecular and systemic physiological levels in order to maintain a sufficient supply of oxygen to cells. In addition, the response to localized hypoxia within tissues is important to the outcome of various disease states. For example, the local hypoxia resulting from coronary artery disease causes a beneficial angiogenic response in which collateral vessels are formed in order to bypass the area of stenosis in the diseased artery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">43</xref>). In cancer, cellular hypoxia is important in promoting angiogenesis and metastasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r45">45</xref>).</p><p>Among humans, there is a considerable degree of variability in physiological responses to hypoxia. Interindividual and population-specific variability has been reported in the ventilatory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r55">55</xref>), pulmonary-vascular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">21</xref>), and erythropoietin (Epo) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r52">52</xref>) responses to hypoxia. Similarly, variation has also been reported in the response to hypoxia in different disease states. For example, variations in angiogenic responses to hypoxia may alter adaptive changes in coronary artery disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">43</xref>) and susceptibility to diabetic retinopathy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r1">1</xref>).</p><p>While these variations in systems-level responses to hypoxia are well characterized in humans, little is known about the variations in the cellular and molecular mechanisms that give rise to these differences. The oxygen-regulated transcription of genes is largely governed by a transcription control complex termed hypoxia-inducible factor (HIF). HIF is part of a well-understood pathway linking changes in the concentration of molecular oxygen to alterations in transcription of a broad range of genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r42">42</xref>). Genetic manipulation of this system in mice and a rare genetic disease (Chuvash polycythemia) that results in partial HIF activation in humans have both shown that this system plays an important role in determining a number of physiological characteristics including the erythropoietic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r54">54</xref>), ventilatory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">48</xref>), and cardiopulmonary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r54">54</xref>) responses to hypoxia. Our hypothesis is that variations within the HIF transcription system underlie at least part of the variation in systems-level responses to hypoxia among normal human individuals. The aim of this study was to determine whether variations within the HIF transcription system can be detected between normal individuals. If such variations can be detected, then this would provide a platform for future studies in humans to explore links between functional variation within the HIF system and variation within integrated physiological responses to hypoxia.</p><p>The experimental approach adopted was to compare the between-subject variation in the response of the HIF system to changes in oxygen tension with the within-subject variation in these responses. One significant problem is that the &#x003b1;-subunit of HIF (HIF-&#x003b1;) is a highly labile protein present in low quantities within the cell. As a consequence, assay-to-assay variability in the quantification of HIF-&#x003b1; protein would almost certainly exceed any naturally occurring differences in expression between individuals. For this reason, rather than attempting to quantify directly the variation in the level of HIF-&#x003b1; protein with varying oxygen tension, we chose to quantify variations in the level of mRNA of selected HIF-regulated transcripts. Since these downstream products of HIF regulation are almost certainly affected by genetic variation between individuals besides that within the HIF system, we chose to examine four different mRNAs that encode proteins with functions in four different biological pathways. Variation in the amplitude of responses to hypoxia that is common across genes is highly likely to arise from variation in the HIF system.</p><p>Peripheral blood lymphocytes (PBL) represent a cell type relatively easily obtainable from human subjects for experimental study in which induction of HIF by hypoxia can be observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r32">32</xref>). In this study we measured the expression of four selected HIF-regulated mRNA transcripts in human PBL under oxygen tensions ranging from 20&#x00025; to 0.1&#x00025;. The results were analyzed by using analysis of variance (ANOVA) to identify the between-subject variation that was common across the four different transcripts and compare this with the level of within-subject variation.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Overall experimental design.</title><p>An initial study identified HIF-regulated genes that were expressed in PBL and showed a high level of induction by hypoxia. After this, blood was taken on three separate occasions from each of 10 subjects. PBL were isolated, aliquoted, and incubated under a range of oxygen tensions. The abundance of four different HIF-regulated transcripts, together with an internal control transcript, was quantified with reverse transcription quantitative PCR (RTqPCR). The results of transcript expression were parameterized and then subjected to ANOVA using SPSS (SPSS, Chicago, IL) to determine whether significant interindividual variation in transcript expression was present among the subjects that was common across the four genes.</p></sec><sec><title>Selection of HIF-regulated genes for assessment of HIF system variability.</title><p>We previously showed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">48</xref>) that the HIF-regulated gene transcripts aldolase C (<italic>ALDC</italic>) and vascular endothelial growth factor (<italic>VEGF</italic>) show robust hypoxic induction over a range of hypoxic stimuli in PBL. To identify additional HIF-regulated gene transcripts showing hypoxic induction in PBL, we performed three independent paired 20-h incubations at 20&#x00025; and 1&#x00025; oxygen tensions of six PBL samples from one subject as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">48</xref>). The six RNA samples from these experiments were analyzed for transcript expression with a Sentrix-6 BeadChip platform (Illumina). After analyses of transcript expression, the gene-specific signal intensities in the euoxic samples were compared with those of the hypoxic samples. The average ratios of the hypoxia to euoxia signal intensities from the three repeat experiments together with all the results of the microarray analyses have been deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information Gene Expression Omnibus database under accession number <ext-link xlink:href="GSE7833" ext-link-type="gen">GSE7833</ext-link>. From the results of this microarray screening process we selected two further HIF-regulated gene transcripts, prolyl-4-hydroxylase &#x003b1;1 (<italic>P4HA1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r50">50</xref>) and adrenomedullin (<italic>AM</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r34">34</xref>), to be used in the assessment of variability of the HIF system among human subjects. <italic>AM</italic> and <italic>P4HA1</italic> were both among the 100 transcripts showing the highest levels of hypoxic induction out of 47,000 transcripts interrogated by the BeadChip arrays.</p></sec><sec><title>Subjects recruited for main study.</title><p>Ten healthy human subjects were recruited for the study. Their physical characteristics are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>. Subjects gave informed consent before donating samples of venous blood. The study conformed to the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and had approval from the Oxfordshire Clinical Research Ethics Committee. All subjects were healthy, although one female subject (<italic>1508</italic>) was noted to be mildly iron deficient with low serum iron and ferritin levels. This subject did not appear unusual with respect to any of the experimental results.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of hypoxically regulated gene expression in PBL over a range of oxygen tensions.</title><p>PBL from each subject were isolated, aliquoted, and incubated as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">48</xref>). In brief, 40 ml of venous blood was centrifuged over density gradient medium (Ficoll-Paque Plus, Amersham Biosciences, Chalfont, UK) to isolate the mononuclear cells. These were then incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 30 min over a hydrophilic membrane to induce cellular adhesion by the monocytes, leaving a supernatant containing the PBL. The PBL were aliquoted into gas-permeable tissue culture dishes and incubated at eight different oxygen tensions (20&#x00025;, 10&#x00025;, 5&#x00025;, 2&#x00025;, 1&#x00025;, 0.5&#x00025;, 0.2&#x00025;, 0.1&#x00025;) for 20 h. The incubations were achieved by suspending each tissue culture dish inside a large glass container that was flushed with the relevant gas mixture for 10 min before the incubation period. The composition of the gas before and after incubation was checked to ensure it had remained constant by using a paramagnetic oxygen analyzer that had been calibrated with a standard gas mixture. After completion of the incubations, total RNA was harvested from the PBL by a column-based extraction method (RNAqueous-4PCR, catalog no. 1914, Ambion). RTqPCR using TaqMan primers and probes was used to determine the expression of <italic>ALDC, VEGF, AM</italic>, and <italic>P4HA1</italic> together with &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>-microglobulin (<italic>&#x003b2;2MG</italic>), which had shown no induction in hypoxia in the preliminary experiments and was therefore used as an internal control, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">48</xref>). A calibrator sample of complementary DNA (cDNA) was run with each set of qPCR reactions. In one subject (<italic>1286</italic>), the RNA samples of one repeat experiment at 5&#x00025; O<sub>2</sub> and another repeat experiment at 1&#x00025; O<sub>2</sub> gave uninterpretable results with RTqPCR and were thus excluded from further analyses. Relative HIF-regulated gene expression was quantified by a method described by Pfaffl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r38">38</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis.</title><p>Variations in gene expression with oxygen tension from all of the experiments were first examined on linear and double logarithmic plots. Because the responses appeared linear in the double logarithmic plots, the results for each experiment on each subject could be parameterized by linear regression on these values. This provided one value for the gradient of the response and another value for the intercept (expression at 10&#x00025; oxygen). Next, in order to weight equally the results of the different genes studied within the statistical analysis, the slopes and intercepts for each gene were scaled so that each had a variance of unity. The main statistical analysis was undertaken with ANOVA. The principal factors used in the analysis were &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;gene.&#x0201d; In addition to the principal factors, the interactive factors of &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; with &#x0201c;gene&#x0201d; (reflecting the variation between subjects that varies between different genes) and &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; with &#x0201c;experimental repeat&#x0201d; (reflecting the variation between individual experiments) were also included in the ANOVA. For the purposes of generating the appropriate error terms, &#x0201c;gene&#x0201d; was considered as a fixed factor and &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;experimental repeat&#x0201d; were considered as random factors. The significance of the &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; factor represents the main outcome measure of this study, because it reflects the variation between subjects that is common across the four HIF-regulated genes under study.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>To show the overall variation in transcript level with oxygen tension in human subjects, the data from all of the repeat experiments at each oxygen tension are plotted for each gene in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref> (where &#x003b2;<italic>2MG</italic> has been used as an internal control). All four genes show a similar response profile to oxygen; there is a relatively small increase in gene expression from 20&#x00025; to 2&#x00025; oxygen and a very large increase from 2&#x00025; to 0.1&#x00025; oxygen, with no indication of a plateau in the response being reached. In contrast, the threshold cycle values from the RTqPCR for the internal control gene, <italic>&#x003b2;2MG</italic>, showed no relationship with hypoxia. It is also clear from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref> that there is inherently more variation in the gene expression measurements at lower oxygen tensions. When the same values are plotted on a double logarithmic scale as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>, the relationship between transcript expression and oxygen tension appears to be linear, with a similar degree of variation in gene expression measurements occurring at each oxygen tension. These appearances are further confirmed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>, where the mean values for gene expression at each value for oxygen tension are plotted in a double logarithmic format together with the intersubject standard deviations. The linear nature of the response when plotted in double logarithmic format is apparent from the simple linear regressions shown for each of the genes.</p><p>The observations above indicate that it is possible to parameterize the responses of individual experiments by simple linear regression on the logarithmic values for gene expression and oxygen tension. Examples of this are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref> for two subjects; <italic>subject 2000</italic> shows a relatively high degree of variation in expression with oxygen tension, while <italic>subject 1973</italic> shows a relatively low degree of variation. <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref> reports the mean values obtained for the slope and intercept (at 10&#x00025; O<sub>2</sub>) for each subject for each gene.</p><p>The results of ANOVA on the gradients of the responses are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>. First, the interaction of &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; with &#x0201c;experimental repeat&#x0201d; reflects the variability between experiments (i.e., between data derived from different blood samples) that is common across the four genes studied. This did not quite reach statistical significance (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.057), which suggests that the data are not overly affected by variation between experiments. Second, the interaction of &#x0201c;gene&#x0201d; with &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; (gene&#x0002a;subject) reflects variation between subjects that is different between different genes. This is significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), but because this variation is not common across the four HIF-regulated genes studied, it cannot be ascribed to differences within the HIF system. Finally, the &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; term reflects the variation in induction by hypoxia between subjects that is common across all four genes studied. This is significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.008) and forms the principal finding of the study. Effectively, the result demonstrates that subjects can be phenotyped according to their overall sensitivity to the induction of oxygen-regulated gene expression by hypoxia. The factor of &#x0201c;gene&#x0201d; in the ANOVA is of no interest because genes are expected to vary naturally in their degree of induction by hypoxia and, in this analysis, it is also confounded by the scaling process.</p><p>The results of the ANOVA of the intercepts at 10&#x00025; O<sub>2</sub> are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>. First, the interaction of &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; with &#x0201c;experimental repeat&#x0201d; is not significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.123), suggesting that the data for the intercepts are also not overly affected by variation between experiments. Second, the interaction of &#x0201c;gene&#x0201d; with &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; (gene&#x0002a;subject) is significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.001), suggesting that there is variation between subjects that is different between different genes. Finally, in contrast to the data for the gradients, the &#x0201c;subject&#x0201d; term is not significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.115), suggesting that any variation in the intercept values among the subjects is unlikely to be due to overall differences in the HIF system.</p><p>As a final analysis, the ANOVA was repeated on the values for gradient and intercept before they were scaled so as to have equal variance for each gene. In no case did the conclusions from this analysis differ from those obtained from the scaled values.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The results from this study demonstrated that there were significant differences between individuals for the basal expression of the various HIF-regulated genes when no hypoxic stimulus was present. For these basal expression levels, there was no common pattern across the genes studied, suggesting that different regulatory mechanisms are important in determining basal expression for the different genes. However, there were also significant differences between individuals in the degree to which expression of these genes was induced by hypoxia. In contrast with levels of basal expression, there was a common pattern across the genes for the induction in expression by hypoxia, such that if one gene was strongly induced by hypoxia in an individual then this would tend to be the case for all the other genes within that individual. It is this result that suggests that individuals differ significantly in a factor that is common to all the genes studied in relation to the induction of their expression by hypoxia.</p><p>As outlined in the introduction, it is already recognized that individuals differ in many of their phenotypic responses to hypoxia. Generally, these phenotypes are very complex and integrative in nature, and their origins remain obscure. In contrast, the phenotype of this study is much narrower and is tightly linked to one particular biochemical pathway&#x02014;the HIF transcription activation pathway. It was therefore less likely that significant variation would exist between individuals, but because it does exist, it is suggestive of the presence of functional genetic variants in humans within the HIF transcription activation pathway. Although not investigated in this study, the phenotype provides a tool to explore the genetic origins of functional variation within the HIF pathway and to explore associations with more complex phenotypes.</p><p>There have been relatively few other human studies of variation in the transcription of HIF-regulated genes. However, variation in the hypoxic induction of <italic>VEGF</italic> has been investigated in peripheral blood monocytes (PBM) taken from patients with coronary artery disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r49">49</xref>) and also from patients with diabetic retinopathy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r31">31</xref>). Positive associations were observed between the level of induction of <italic>VEGF</italic> by hypoxia and both the degree of coronary artery collateral formation and the degree of diabetic retinopathy. The authors of these studies suggest that the variability in induction of <italic>VEGF</italic> by hypoxia may reflect interindividual differences in the responsiveness of the HIF system to hypoxia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">43</xref>). However, other explanations remain possible. First, because only the expression of <italic>VEGF</italic> was investigated, it is possible that the regulatory differences were entirely specific to VEGF and did not involve the HIF signaling pathway. Second, in these experiments the PBM were resuspended in the patients&#x02019; own plasma before incubation under euoxic or hypoxic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">43</xref>), and it is therefore possible that differences in the plasma constituents could underlie some of the variability in induction of VEGF by hypoxia. The present study controls for both these issues, and thus provides further support for the notion that the sensitivity of VEGF to induction by hypoxia is related to the sensitivity of other HIF-regulated genes to hypoxia.</p><p>One potential problem with our experimental system is that the method used to isolate PBL was not selective for lymphocyte subtypes. Although such cell types are closely related, there is still a theoretical possibility that the differences seen in the responses reflect, to some extent, differences in the proportions of lymphocyte subtypes among the subjects. Against this possibility we have found that, for <italic>ALDC</italic>, the average gradient of the log-log relationships between gene expression and oxygen tension for Epstein-Barr virus-transformed B lymphocytes from a number of normal subjects was very similar to that of the mixed population of PBL in this study (J. T. S. Brooks, unpublished observations).</p><p>As noted in the introduction, HIF plays an important role in promoting angiogenesis, both in cardiovascular disease and cancer&#x02014;the latter supporting the development of metastases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r45">45</xref>). There is also evidence that the degree of induction of HIF-regulated genes in human cancers is a powerful predictor of outcome, with higher degrees of induction associated with poorer prognosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r53">53</xref>). Our study raises the possibility that individuals may differ innately in this process. Although this study was not primarily concerned with the roles of the HIF system in PBL, it is nevertheless worth noting its involvement in a number of different functions. These include its involvement in autoimmunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r29">29</xref>), in myeloid cell function in inflammation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r18">18</xref>), in T-lymphocyte physiology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r33">33</xref>), and in fighting bacterial, viral, and parasitic infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r56">56</xref>).</p><p>One interesting area of speculation concerns the particular genetic variation that gives rise to the variation in the sensitivity of the HIF system to decreasing oxygen tension. The major regulatory step in this system is the oxygen-dependent hydroxylation of HIF at specific proline residues that tags the protein for subsequent von Hippel-Lindau (VHL) protein binding and subsequent ubiquitin-mediated proteasomal degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">26</xref>). The recent identification of a mutation in the HIF-2&#x003b1; gene that is associated with congenital erythrocytosis suggests that variation within the HIF genes themselves could be one source of variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r37">37</xref>). The prolyl hydroxylation of HIF is mediated by three isoenzymes termed prolyl hydroxylase domain (PHD) proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r19">19</xref>), the activities of which are dependent on oxygen as a cosubstrate together with Fe<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> and ascorbate as cofactors. The three PHD isoenzymes remain active at oxygen tensions at least as low as 0.2&#x00025; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r4">4</xref>), and the rate of hydroxylation is exquisitely sensitive to oxygen tension over the range of values typically encountered in mammalian cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref>). Thus genetic variability within any of the genes coding for the PHD isoenzymes and/or any factors that influence the activity of the PHD enzymes may well be a source of interindividual differences in the sensitivity of the HIF system. Recently, mutations within the PHD2 gene have been identified that are associated with a congenital polycythemia syndrome characterized by inappropriately raised Epo levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r36">36</xref>). In vitro transfection studies suggest that these PHD2 variants have reduced hydroxylase activity that results in raised levels of transcription of HIF-regulated genes compared with wild-type PHD2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r36">36</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, we have demonstrated that it is possible to resolve differences between normal individuals in the induction by hypoxia of a range of HIF-regulated genes. The use of PBL to derive this phenotype provides an approach that is both reproducible and relatively noninvasive, in the sense that it does not require tissue biopsy of specific cell types. As such, our experimental system provides an intermediate biochemical phenotype by which the cellular responsiveness to hypoxia may be quantified for individuals. Such a system provides an opportunity to try to relate variations in the HIF system both upward toward the variations in integrated responses to hypoxia observed between individuals and downward toward genetic variations within the HIF system that may underlie the biochemical phenotype.</p></sec><sec><title>GRANTS</title><p>This work was supported by a PhD studentship from the Medical Research Council.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Prof. Frances Ashcroft and Prof. Alan Cooper for access to real-time PCR facilities used in mRNA transcript quantification.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aiello</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, Gardner TW, King GL, Blankenship G, Cavallerano JD, Ferris FL, Klein R. Diabetic retinopathy. <source>Diabetes Care</source><volume>21</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;156, <year>1998</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9538986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>, Chen H, Gordeuk VR, Sergueeva AI, Polyakova LA, Miasnikova GY, Kralovics R, Stockton DW, Prchal JT. Endemic polycythaemia in Russia: mutation in the VHL gene. <source>Blood Cells Mol Dis</source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;62, <year>2002</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11987242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>, Chen H, Hirota K, Gordeuk VR, Jelinek J, Guan Y, Liu E, Sergueeva AI, Miasnikova GY, Mole D, Maxwell PH, Stockton DW, Semenza GL, Prchal JT. Disruption of oxygen homeostasis underlies congenital Chuvash polycythaemia. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>614</fpage>&#x02013;621, <year>2002</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12415268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Appelhoff</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, Tian YM, Raval RR, Turley H, Harris AL, Pugh CW, Ratcliffe PJ, Gleadle JM. Differential function of the prolyl hydroxylases PHD1, PHD2, and PHD3 in the regulation of hypoxia-inducible factor. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume>: <fpage>38458</fpage>&#x02013;38465, <year>2004</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15247232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Balanos</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, Dorrington KL, Robbins PA. Desferrioxamine elevates pulmonary vascular resistance in humans: potential for involvement of HIF-1. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><volume>92</volume>: <fpage>2501</fpage>&#x02013;2507, <year>2002</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baroldi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> Coronary heart disease: significance of the morphologic lesions. <source>Am Heart J</source><volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;5, <year>1973</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4682003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beall</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, Strohl KP, Blangero J, Williams-Blangero S, Almasy LA, Decker MJ, Worthman CM, Goldstein MC, Vargas E, Villena M, Soria R, Alarcon AM, Gonzales C. Ventilation and hypoxic ventilatory response of Tibetan and Aymara high altitude natives. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source><volume>104</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;447, <year>1997</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9453694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beall</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, Goldstein MC. Hemoglobin concentration of pastoral nomads permanently resident at 4,850&#x02013;5,450 meters in Tibet. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source><volume>73</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;438, <year>1987</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3661681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brusselmans</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, Compernolle V, Tjwa M, Wiesener MS, Maxwell PH, Collen D, Carmeliet P. Heterozygous deficiency of hypoxia-inducible factor-2&#x003b1; protects mice against pulmonary hypertension and right ventricular dysfunction during prolonged hypoxia. <source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>111</volume>: <fpage>1519</fpage>&#x02013;1527, <year>2003</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12750401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bushuev</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name>, Miasnikova GY, Sergueeva AI, Polyakova LA, Okhotin D, Gaskin PR, Debebe Z, Nekhai S, Castro OL, Prchal JT, Gordeuk VR. Endothelin-1, vascular endothelial growth factor and systolic pulmonary artery pressure in patients with Chuvash polycythemia. <source>Haematologica</source><volume>91</volume>: <fpage>744</fpage>&#x02013;749, <year>2006</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16769575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, Kojima H, Lukashev D, Armstrong J, Farber M, Apasov SG, Sitkovsky MV. Differential effects of physiologically relevant hypoxic conditions on T lymphocyte development and effector functions. <source>J Immunol</source><volume>167</volume>: <fpage>6140</fpage>&#x02013;6149, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11714773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cario</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, Schwarz K, Jorch N, Kyank U, Petrides PE, Schneider DT, Uhle R, Debatin KM, Kohne E. Mutations in the von Hippel-Lindau (VHL) tumor suppressor gene and VHL-haplotype analysis in patients with presumable congenital erythrocytosis. <source>Haematologica</source><volume>90</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;24, <year>2005</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carmeliet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, Dor Y, Herbert JM, Fukumura D, Brusselmans K, Dewerchin M, Neeman M, Bono F, Abramovitch R, Maxwell P, Koch CJ, Ratcliffe P, Moons L, Jain RK, Collen D, Keshert E. Role of HIF-1&#x003b1; in hypoxia-mediated apoptosis, cell proliferation and tumour angiogenesis. <source>Nature</source><volume>394</volume>: <fpage>485</fpage>&#x02013;490, <year>1998</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9697772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, Stray-Gundersen J, Levine BD. Individual variation in response to altitude training. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1448</fpage>&#x02013;1456, <year>1998</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9760340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, Wang Z, Nuyten DS, Rodriguez EH, Schaner ME, Salim A, Wang Y, Kristensen GB, Helland A, Borresen-Dale AL, Giaccia A, Longaker MT, Hastie T, Yang GP, van de Vijver MJ, Brown PO. Gene expression programs in response to hypoxia: cell type specificity and prognostic significance in human cancers. <source>PLoS Med</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e47</fpage>, <year>2006</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16417408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Conforti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, Petrovic M, Mohammad D, Lee S, Ma Q, Barone S, Filipovich AH. Hypoxia regulates expression and activity of Kv1.3 channels in T lymphocytes: a possible role in T cell proliferation. <source>J Immunol</source><volume>170</volume>: <fpage>695</fpage>&#x02013;702, <year>2003</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12517930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cormier-Regard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, Nguyen SV, Claycomb WC. Adrenomedullin gene expression is developmentally regulated and induced by hypoxia in rat ventricular cardiac myocytes. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>273</volume>: <fpage>17787</fpage>&#x02013;17792, <year>1998</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9651380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, Yamanishi Y, Clausen BE, Forster I, Pawlinski R, Mackman N, Haase VH, Jaenisch R, Corr M, Nizet V, Firestein GS, Gerber HP, Ferrara N, Johnson RS. HIF-1alpha is essential for myeloid cell-mediated inflammation. <source>Cell</source><volume>112</volume>: <fpage>645</fpage>&#x02013;657, <year>2003</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12628185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, Gleadle JM, McNeill LA, Hewitson KS, O'Rourke J, Mole DR, Mukherji M, Metzen E, Wilson MI, Dhanda A, Tian YM, Masson N, Hamilton DL, Jaakkola P, Barstead R, Hodgkin J, Maxwell PH, Pugh CW, Schofield CJ, Ratcliffe PJ. <italic>C. elegans</italic> EGL-9 and mammalian homologs define a family of dioxygenases that regulate HIF by prolyl hydroxylation. <source>Cell</source><volume>107</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;54, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11595184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garruto</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, Chin CT, Weitz CA, Liu JC, Liu RL, He X. Hematological differences during growth among Tibetans and Han Chinese born and raised at high altitude in Qinghai, China. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source><volume>122</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;183, <year>2003</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12949837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Groves</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, Droma T, Sutton JR, McCullough RG, McCullough RE, Zhuang J, Rapmund G, Sun S, Janes C, Moore LG. Minimal hypoxic pulmonary hypertension in normal Tibetans at 3,658 m. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><volume>74</volume>: <fpage>312</fpage>&#x02013;318, <year>1993</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8444708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, Lam JC, Bezman NA, Rathmell WK, Simon MC. von Hippel-Lindau mutation in mice recapitulates Cuvash polycythemia via hypoxia-inducible factor-2&#x003b1; signaling and splenic erythropoeisis. <source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>117</volume>: <fpage>3879</fpage>&#x02013;3889, <year>2007</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17992257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hirshman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, McCullough RE, Weil JV. Normal values for hypoxic and hypercapnic ventilatory drives in man. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1095</fpage>&#x02013;1098, <year>1975</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1141125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hirsila</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, Koivunen P, Gunzler V, Kivirikko KI, Myllyharju J. Characterization of the human prolyl 4-hydroxylases that modify the hypoxia-inducible factor. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>278</volume>: <fpage>30772</fpage>&#x02013;30780, <year>2003</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12788921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ivan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, Kondo K, Yang H, Kim W, Valiando J, Ohh M, Salic A, Asara JM, Lane WS, Kaelin WG. HIF&#x003b1; targeted for VHL-mediated destruction by proline hydroxylation: implications for O<sub>2</sub> sensing. <source>Science</source><volume>292</volume>: <fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;468, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11292862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jaakkola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, Mole DR, Tian YM, Wilson MI, Gielbert J, Gaskell SJ, Kriegsheim A, Hebestreit HF, Mukherji M, Schofield CJ, Maxwell PH, Pugh CW, Ratcliffe PJ. Targeting of HIF-&#x003b1; to the von Hippel-Lindau ubiquitylation complex by O<sub>2</sub>-regulated prolyl hydroxylation. <source>Science</source><volume>292</volume>: <fpage>468</fpage>&#x02013;472, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11292861</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, Yoshikawa T, Shida A, Asanuma Y, Murao M. Control of breathing in young twins. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>&#x02013;542, <year>1982</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7200088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, Peng YJ, Manalo DJ, Semenza GL, Prabhakar NR. Defective carotid body function and impaired ventilatory responses to chronic hypoxia in mice partially deficient for hypoxia-inducible factor 1&#x003b1;. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>99</volume>: <fpage>821</fpage>&#x02013;826, <year>2002</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11792862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, Gu H, Nomura S, Caldwell CC, Kobata T, Carmeliet P, Semenza GL, Sitkovsky MV. Abnormal B lymphocyte development and autoimmunity in hypoxia-inducible factor 1alpha-deficient chimeric mice. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>99</volume>: <fpage>2170</fpage>&#x02013;2174, <year>2002</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11854513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lukashev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, Klebanov B, Kojima H, Grinberg A, Ohta A, Berenfeld L, Wenger RH, Ohta A, Sitkovsky M. Cutting edge: hypoxia-inducible factor 1&#x003b1; and its activation-inducible short isoform I.1 negatively regulate functions of CD4&#x0002b; and CD8&#x0002b; T lymphocytes. <source>J Immunol</source><volume>177</volume>: <fpage>4962</fpage>&#x02013;4965, <year>2006</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17015677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, Nakhoul FM, Skorecki K, Rubin A, Miller BP, Leibu R, Levy NS, Levy AP. Hypoxic induction of vascular endothelial growth factor is markedly decreased in individuals who do not develop retinopathy. <source>Diabetes Care</source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1375</fpage>&#x02013;1380, <year>2000</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10977036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, Makino Y, Okamoto K, Poellinger L, Ohnuma K, Morimoto C, Tanaka H. TCR engagement increases hypoxia-inducible factor-1&#x003b1; protein synthesis via rapamycin-sensitive pathway under hypoxic conditions in human peripheral T cells. <source>J Immunol</source><volume>174</volume>: <fpage>7592</fpage>&#x02013;7599, <year>2005</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15944259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, Yang J, Biju MP, Joseph SK, Johnson RS, Haase VH, Freedman BD, Turka LA. Hypoxia inducible factor 1&#x003b1; regulates T cell receptor signal transduction. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>102</volume>: <fpage>17071</fpage>&#x02013;17076, <year>2005</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16286658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, Claycomb WC. Hypoxia regulates the expression of the adrenomedullin and HIF-1 genes in cultured HL-1 cardiomyocytes. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>265</volume>: <fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;386, <year>1999</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10558876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Percy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, Zhao Q, Flores A, Harrison C, Lappin TR, Maxwell PH, McMullin MF, Lee FS. A family with erythrocytosis establishes a role for prolyl hydroxylase domain protein 2 in oxygen homeostasis. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>103</volume>: <fpage>654</fpage>&#x02013;659, <year>2006</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Percy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, Furlow PW, Beer PA, Lappin TR, McMullin MF, Lee FS. A novel erythrocytosis-associated PHD2 mutation suggests the location of a HIF binding groove. <source>Blood</source><volume>110</volume>: <fpage>2193</fpage>&#x02013;2196, <year>2007</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17579185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Percy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, Furlow PW, Lucas GS, Li X, Lappin TR, McMullin MF, Lee FS. A gain-of function mutation in the HIF2A gene in familial erythrocytosis. <source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>358</volume>: <fpage>162</fpage>&#x02013;8, <year>2008</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18184961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pfaffl</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> A new mathematical model for relative quantification in real-time RT-PCR. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>29</volume>: <fpage>e45</fpage>, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11328886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Polyakova</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> Familial erythrocytosis among the residents of the Chuvash ASSR. <source>Probl Gematol Pereliv Krovi</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;33, <year>1974</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richalet</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, Souberbielle JC, Antezana AM, Dechaux M, Le Trong JL, Bienvenu A, Daniel F, Blanchot C, Zittoun J. Control of erythropoiesis in humans during prolonged exposure to the altitude of 6,542 m. <source>Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</source><volume>266</volume>: <fpage>R756</fpage>&#x02013;R764, <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, Javierre C, Garrido E, Segura R, Ventura JL. Normoxic ventilatory response in lowlander and Sherpa elite climbers. <source>Respir Physiol</source><volume>113</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;64, <year>1998</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9776551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schofield</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, Ratcliffe PJ. Signalling hypoxia by HIF hydroxylases. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>338</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;626, <year>2005</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16139242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, Lavie L, Hochberg I, Beyar R, Stone T, Skorecki K, Lavie P, Roguin A, Levy AP. Interindividual heterogeneity in the hypoxic regulation of VEGF: significance for the development of coronary artery collateral circulation. <source>Circulation</source><volume>100</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;522, <year>1999</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10430770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scoggin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, Doekel RD, Kryger MH, Zwillich CW, Weil JV. Familial aspects of decreased hypoxic drive in endurance athletes. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;468, <year>1978</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">632187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Semenza</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name> Involvement of hypoxia-inducible factor 1 in human cancer. <source>Intern Med</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;83, <year>2002</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11868612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sergeyeva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, Gordeuk VR, Tokarev YN, Sokol L, Prchal JF, Prchal JT. Congenital polycythemia in Chuvashia. <source>Blood</source><volume>89</volume>: <fpage>2148</fpage>&#x02013;2154, <year>1997</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9058738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shimoda</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, Manalo DJ, Sham JS, Semenza GL, Sylvester JT. Partial HIF-1&#x003b1; deficiency impairs pulmonary arterial myocyte electrophysiological responses to hypoxia. <source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source><volume>281</volume>: <fpage>L202</fpage>&#x02013;L208, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11404263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, Brooks JT, Balanos GM, Lappin TR, Layton DM, Leedham DL, Liu C, Maxwell PH, McMullin MF, McNamara CJ, Percy MJ, Pugh CW, Ratcliffe PJ, Talbot NP, Treacy M, Robbins PA. Mutation of von Hippel-Lindau tumour suppressor and human cardiopulmonary physiology. <source>PLoS Med</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e290</fpage>, <year>2006</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16768548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, Kim KS, Lee S. Hypoxic regulation of VEGF, HIF-1(alpha) in coronary collaterals development. <source>Korean J Intern Med</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;302, <year>2005</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16491827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, Takahashi S, Shiga Y, Yoshimi T, Miura T. Hypoxic induction of prolyl 4-hydroxylase alpha (I) in cultured cells. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>275</volume>: <fpage>14139</fpage>&#x02013;14146, <year>2000</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10799490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Winslow</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> High-altitude polycythemia. In: <source>High Altitude and Man</source>, edited by West JB and Lahiri L. Baltimore, MD: Williams and Wilkins, <year>1984</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Winslow</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, Chapman KW, Gibson CC, Samaja M, Monge CC, Goldwasser E, Sherpa M, Blume FD, Santolaya R. Different hematologic responses to hypoxia in Sherpas and Quechua Indians. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1561</fpage>&#x02013;1569, <year>1989</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2732148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, Buffa FM, Silva P, Miller C, Valentine HR, Turley H, Shah KA, Cox GJ, Corbridge RJ, Homer JJ, Musgrove B, Slevin N, Sloan P, Price P, West CML, Harris AL. Relation of a hypoxia metagene derived from head and neck cancer to prognosis of multiple cancers. <source>Cancer Res</source><volume>67</volume>: <fpage>3441</fpage>&#x02013;3449, <year>2007</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17409455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>, Shimoda LA, Iyer NV, Huso DL, Sun X, McWilliams R, Beaty T, Sham JS, Wiener CM, Sylvester JT, Semenza GL. Impaired physiological responses to chronic hypoxia in mice partially deficient for hypoxia-inducible factor 1&#x003b1;. <source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>103</volume>: <fpage>691</fpage>&#x02013;696, <year>1999</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10074486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, Droma T, Sun S, Janes C, McCullough RE, McCullough RG, Cymerman A, Huang SY, Reeves JT, Moore LG. Hypoxic ventilatory responsiveness in Tibetan compared with Han residents of 3,658 m. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><volume>74</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;311, <year>1993</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8444707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zinkernagel</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, Johnson RS, Nizet V. Hypoxia inducible factor (HIF) function in innate immunity and infection. <source>J Mol Med</source><volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1339</fpage>&#x02013;1346, <year>2007</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18030436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="f1"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Relative expression of vascular endothelial growth factor (<italic>VEGF</italic>), aldolase C (<italic>ALDC</italic>), adrenomedullin (<italic>AM</italic>), and prolyl-4-hydroxylase &#x003b1;1 (<italic>P4HA1</italic>) over a range of oxygen tensions in peripheral blood lymphocytes. Data are for 3 repeat experiments on each of 10 human subjects.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdg0010983150001"/></fig><fig position="float" id="f2"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Relative expression in peripheral blood lymphocytes of <italic>VEGF, ALDC, AM</italic>, and <italic>P4HA1</italic> over a range of oxygen tensions plotted on a double logarithmic scale. Data are as for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdg0010983150002"/></fig><fig position="float" id="f3"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Mean values for relative expression of <italic>VEGF, ALDC, AM</italic>, and <italic>P4HA1</italic> at 20&#x02013;0.1&#x00025; O<sub>2</sub> from all repeat experiments on all subjects plotted on a double logarithmic scale. Error bars are &#x000b1;SD for the intersubject variability. Lines are the best fit by simple linear regression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdg0010983150003"/></fig><fig position="float" id="f4"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Relative values of <italic>VEGF, ALDC, AM</italic>, and <italic>P4HA1</italic> expression over a range of oxygen tensions in 3 repeat experiments performed on peripheral blood lymphocytes of <italic>subject 2000</italic>, showing a high sensitivity to changing oxygen tensions, and of <italic>subject 1973</italic>, showing, in contrast, a low sensitivity to changing oxygen tensions. Mean values for the gradients of the responses for each transcript (m) are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdg0010983150004"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Physical characteristics of participants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom">Subject No.</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Age, yr</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Sex</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Body Mass Index, kg/m<sup>2</sup></th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Ethnicity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1096</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">27</td><td align="center" valign="top">M</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">21.6</td><td align="left" valign="top">Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1229</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">24</td><td align="center" valign="top">M</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">19.4</td><td align="left" valign="top">Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1286</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">23</td><td align="center" valign="top">M</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">19.4</td><td align="left" valign="top">Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1490</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">21</td><td align="center" valign="top">M</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">23.1</td><td align="left" valign="top">Asian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1506</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">27</td><td align="center" valign="top">F</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">20.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1508</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">38</td><td align="center" valign="top">F</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">20.9</td><td align="left" valign="top">Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1513</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">30</td><td align="center" valign="top">F</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">22.5</td><td align="left" valign="top">Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1522</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">26</td><td align="center" valign="top">M</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">26.5</td><td align="left" valign="top">Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1973</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">30</td><td align="center" valign="top">M</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">21</td><td align="left" valign="top">Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>2000</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">41</td><td align="center" valign="top">M</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">22.9</td><td align="left" valign="top">Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">29</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="char" char="." valign="top">21.8</td><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">SD</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">7</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="char" char="." valign="top">2.1</td><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Gradients and intercepts (log values at 10&#x00025; O<sub>2</sub>) for log-log relationships between gene expression and percent oxygen concentration</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom">Subject No.</th><th valign="bottom" colspan="4" align="center">Gradients<hr/></th><th valign="bottom" colspan="4" align="center">Intercepts</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>VEGF</italic></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>ALDC</italic></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>AM</italic></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>P4HA1</italic></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>VEGF</italic></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>ALDC</italic></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>AM</italic></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>P4HA1</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1096</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.43</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.31</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.43</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.47</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.72</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.25</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.19</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1229</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.5</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.35</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.39</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.52</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.86</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.48</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.07</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1286</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.57</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.36</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.37</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.55</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.68</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.18</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.28</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1490</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.41</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.37</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.37</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.52</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.57</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.08</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1506</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.59</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.52</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.36</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.49</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.6</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.48</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1508</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.57</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.45</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.33</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.42</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.36</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.21</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.37</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1513</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.44</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.36</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.31</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.48</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.53</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.38</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.29</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1522</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.4</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.37</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.26</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.46</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.47</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.39</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.31</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>1973</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.28</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.27</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.28</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.41</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.48</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.21</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.09</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>2000</italic></td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.67</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.52</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.36</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.52</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.98</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.53</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.11</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.49</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.39</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.35</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.48</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.63</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.34</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.05</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">&#x02212;0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">SD</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.12</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.08</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.05</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.05</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.19</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.13</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.23</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.23</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>VEGF</italic>, vascular endothelial growth factor; <italic>ALDC</italic>, aldolase C; <italic>AM</italic>, adrenomedullin; <italic>P4HA1</italic>, prolyl-4-hydroxylase &#x003b1;1.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t3"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>ANOVA on scaled gradients for double logarithmic relationship between gene expression and oxygen tension</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom">Source</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Sum of Squares</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Degrees of Freedom</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Mean Square</th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>F</italic> Value</th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Intercept</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">3,593.701</td><td align="center" valign="top">1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">3,593.701</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">723.373</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">44.712</td><td align="center" valign="top">9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">4.968<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t3fn1">&#x0002a;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Gene</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">465.756</td><td align="center" valign="top">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">155.252</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">127.026</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">32.999</td><td align="center" valign="top">27</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">1.222<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t3fn2">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Subject</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">44.712</td><td align="center" valign="top">9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">4.968</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">3.289</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">41.919</td><td align="center" valign="top">27.751</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">1.511<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t3fn3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Gene &#x0002a; subject</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">32.999</td><td align="center" valign="top">27</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">1.222</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">3.006</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">24.391</td><td align="center" valign="top">60</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.407<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t3fn4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Experimental repeat &#x0002a; subject</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">13.897</td><td align="center" valign="top">20</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.695</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">1.709</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.057</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">24.391</td><td align="center" valign="top">60</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.407<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t3fn4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Each data point in the analysis consists of 1 gradient for 1 gene from 1 experiment; this gives a total of 120 data points. The scaling ensured that the variance for the measurements for each gene was unity. The factors employed are as described in <sc>materials and methods</sc>. ANOVA, analysis of variance; MS, mean square.</p></fn><fn id="t3fn1"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>MS(subject);</p></fn><fn id="t3fn2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>MS(gene &#x0002a; subject);</p></fn><fn id="t3fn3"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>MS(gene &#x0002a; subject) &#x0002b; MS(experimental repeat &#x0002a; subject) &#x02212; MS(error);</p></fn><fn id="t3fn4"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p>MS(error).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t4"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>ANOVA on scaled intercepts at 10&#x00025; O<sub>2</sub> for double logarithmic relationship between gene expression and oxygen tension</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom">Source</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Sum of Squares</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Degrees of Freedom</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Mean Square</th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>F</italic> Value</th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Intercept</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">158.576</td><td align="center" valign="top">1</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">158.576</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">50.948</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">28.012</td><td align="center" valign="top">9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">3.112<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t4fn1">&#x0002a;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Subject</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">28.012</td><td align="center" valign="top">9</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">3.112</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">1.812</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.115</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">43.765</td><td align="center" valign="top">25.475</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">1.718<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t4fn2">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Gene</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">171.103</td><td align="center" valign="top">3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">57.034</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">39.127</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">39.357</td><td align="center" valign="top">27</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">1.458<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t4fn3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Gene &#x0002a; subject</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">39.357</td><td align="center" valign="top">27</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">1.458</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">2.685</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">32.568</td><td align="center" valign="top">60</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.543<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t4fn4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Experimental repeat &#x0002a; subject</td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Hypothesis</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">16.062</td><td align="center" valign="top">20</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.803</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">1.480</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.123</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;Error</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">32.568</td><td align="center" valign="top">60</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top">0.543<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t4fn4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top"/><td align="center" valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Each data point in the analysis consists of 1 intercept for 1 gene from 1 experiment; this gives a total of 120 data points. The scaling ensured that the variance for the measurements for each gene was unity. The factors employed are as described in <sc>materials and methods</sc>.</p></fn><fn id="t4fn1"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>MS(subject);</p></fn><fn id="t4fn2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>MS(gene &#x0002a; subject) &#x0002b; MS(experimental repeat &#x0002a; subject) &#x02212; MS(error);</p></fn><fn id="t4fn3"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>MS(gene &#x0002a; subject);</p></fn><fn id="t4fn4"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p>MS(error).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>