<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417836</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636106</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_3_253_40373</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417836 </article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter to the Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sterilization of phacoemulsification handpieces</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Ravi</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><aff>L.V. Prasad Eye Institute, L.V. Prasad Marg, Banjara Hills,Hyderabad - 500 034, Andhra Pradesh, India.  Email: <email>rt@ravithomas.com</email></aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage seq="a">253</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>Dear Editor,</p><p>A recent editorial briefly discussed some issues concerningsmall incision cataract surgery including phacoemulsification.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>I would like to bring some related matters to the attention ofmy colleagues.</p><p>It seems to be an open secret that sterilization ofphacoemulsification handpieces between cases is not the normin many operating rooms in our country. And while sterilizationof the tips alone is probably better than no sterilization, itis neither safe, nor is a preferred practice. I have also heardcomments that the handpiece &#x02033;tuning&#x02033; process itself is sufficientto sterilize the tips; this creates a false sense of security not basedon any evidence whatsoever. I had suggested poor training asone remediable cause of such malaise.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> There are other measuresinvolving the industry that also need to be addressed.</p><p>While the primary responsibility is the surgeon&#x02032;s, theindustry supplying the phacoemulsification machines maybe guilty of omission, they could do more. The need forstrict sterilization protocols for the handpieces and machinescan easily be disseminated and demonstrated at the time ofinstallation and corrected during service calls. Printing therecommendation in the brochure is good preventive practice,but probably not good enough to counter accusations whensomething goes wrong: correcting misplaced beliefs such asthe (lack of) need to sterilize the handpieces or the effect ofultrasound energy on tip sterilization is partly the industry&#x02032;sresponsibility. Regrettably I have been unable to persuade thosein the business that I have spoken to, to specifically educatetheir customers about these aspects. They seemed strangelyreluctant to instruct or officially condemn the non-sterilizationof phacoemulsification handpieces between cases.</p><p>The risk of infection with and appropriate sterilizationprocedures for machines with internal tubings is a controversialmatter. While there are publications linking internal tubingsto infections,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> I am told there is also onenon-peer-reviewed company document to refute this. Having experienced infectionstracked to such internal tubings by modern epidemiologicaland microbiological techniques, I have tried to convince onereputed manufacturer of such machines to at least disseminatenewly revised cleaning instructions for their product to theirnumerous installations. Implementation was promised 2 yearsago. However, despite the fact that the revised protocol wasdeveloped by their own engineers they have, to date, neithercommitted to its dissemination nor demonstrated to all theircustomers. They have not even done this for all customers withservice contracts. Perhaps they have too many installations tocater to or are overly worried about the possible fall out, but Ido think industry responsibility should go beyond the sale oftheir machines. Indeed I get this distinct feeling of d&#x000e9;j&#x000e0; vu: weexperienced a similar lack of responsibility and follow-up withcontaminated irrigating solutions used in cataract surgery.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>Internal tubings may be more controversial and may not meritproduct recall, they certainly merit post-sales education ofsafety measures developed by their own engineers.</p><p>Whereas the issue of internal tubings and infections may becontentious, the actual training of novice surgeons on patientsby company technicians is certainly not,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> it is crime. Again,while they concur with my point of view on this unsafe practicein casual conversation, I have been unable to persuade eventhe same company to take an official stand on this.</p><p>We can only speculate on the reasons for this casual attitudeand how commercial concerns may tie in. I am bringing theseissues to the attention of the readership since it is eventuallyour responsibility to ensure safe practices, not only by ourcolleagues, but our industry partners as well.</p></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of SICS in the Indian Scenario</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2008</year><volume>56</volume><comment>[In press]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation of medical college departmentsof ophthalmology in India and change following provision ofmodern instrumentation and training</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2008</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18158398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kenchappa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangwan</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathengay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-resolution genotyping of Pseudomonasaeruginosa strains linked to acute post cataract surgeryendophthalmitis outbreaks in India</article-title><source>Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob</source><year>2005</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>19</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16343353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cruciani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Malena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amalfitano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonomi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular epidemiology in a cluster of cases of postoperativePseudomonas aeruginosa endophthalmitis</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9502450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaluski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Clayman</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Karsenti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourzeix</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tournemire</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Faliu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa endophthalmitis caused bycontamination of the internal fluid pathways of a phacoemulsifier</article-title><source>J Cataract Refract Surg</source><year>1999</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10198860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contaminated irrigasol solution</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>1998</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>173</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10085632</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>