<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Adv Urol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AU</journal-id><journal-title>Advances in Urology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1687-6369</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1687-6377</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19223964</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636561</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2009/492462</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Management of Upper Tract Urothelial Carcinoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Norm D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">The Robert H. Lurie Comprehensive Cancer Center and Department of Urology, Feinberg School of Medicine, Northwestern University, Chicago, IL 60611-3008, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Norm D. Smith: <email>n-smith3@northwestern.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>2009</volume><elocation-id>492462</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Norm D. Smith.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>Upper tract urothelial carcinoma (UTUC) of the kidney and ureter is arare neoplasm with roughly 3000 cases diagnosed in the United States in 2007,compared to approximately 67000 cases of bladder cancer. UTUC accounts for approximately 10% of cancersarising from the kidney and less than 5% of all urothelial malignancies. Predominantly due to the rarity of the disease, there isonly limited data to guide cliniciansin decision making which consists mostly of small retrospective studies andexpert opinion. As such, this special issue of Advances in Urology &#x0201c;ComprehensiveManagement of Upper Tract Urothelial Carcinoma&#x0201d; focuses both on controversiesin management as well as practical issues in the care of patients with UTUC. Asthe Guest Editor, my goal has been to ask a series of questions and seek answersfrom international experts in the field.</p><p>The first practical matter is to address when endoscopic management ofUTUC is appropriate? Our first article &#x0201c;Endoscopic Management of UpperTract Urothelial Carcinoma&#x0201d; by Katie Moore et al. addresses this issue generally. Then, the paper entitled &#x0201c;EndourologicManagement of Upper Tract Transitional Cell Carcinoma Following Cystectomy andUrinary Diversion&#x0201d; by Jeffrey John Tomaszewski et al. tackles the difficult situation of UTUC after radical cystectomy andurinary diversion. Finally, after initial endoscopic management of UTUC, whatis the role of upper tract topical chemotherapy or BCG? This topic is thesubject of the paper entitled &#x0201c;Review of Topical Treatment of UpperTract Urothelial Carcinoma&#x0201d; by Kenneth G. Nepple et al.</p><p>The next issue of focusis the clinical scenario when UTUC cannot be managed endoscopically. Arelaparoscopic and open nephroureterectomy equivalent operations?  What is thebest way to handle the distal ureter and bladder cuff? These challenging topicsare addressed by a series of articles: &#x0201c;Laparoscopic Nephroureterectomy:Oncologic Outcomes and Management of Distal Ureter: Review of the Literature&#x0201d;by Andre Berger and Amr Fergany, &#x0201c;Laparoscopic Nephroureterectomy: The Distal Ureteral Dilemma&#x0201d;by Shalom Srirangam et al., as well as &#x0201c;Laparoscopic Nephroureterectomy andManagement of the Distal Ureter: A Review of Current Techniques and Outcomes&#x0201d;by Davis Viprakasit et al. Regardless of open versus laparoscopic approaches tonephroureterectomy, what is the role and extent of lymphadenectomy in themanagement of UTUC? This critical issue is dealt with in the paper entitled &#x0201c;RetroperitonealLymph Nodes in Transitional Cell Carcinoma of the Kidney and Ureter&#x0201d; byShilajit D. Kundu and Scott E. Eggener.</p><p>The last matter is the managementof patients with locally advanced or metastatic UTUC. Is there a role foradjuvant chemotherapy? What are the best agents for metastatic UTUC? Can datafrom bladder cancer be applied to the upper tracts? These timely topics areconcentrated upon in the article &#x0201c;The Role of Chemotherapy in Upper TractUrothelial Carcinoma&#x0201d; by Peter H ODonnell and Walter M. Stadler. Finally, thesevarious issues are brought together and placed into perspective in the review entitled&#x0201c;Comprehensive Management of Upper Tract Urothelial Carcinoma&#x0201d; by GeorgiosKoukourakis et al.</p><p>It has been my privilege to serve as the GuestEditor for this special issue of Advances in Urology &#x0201c;Comprehensive Managementof Upper Tract Urothelial Carcinoma.&#x0201d;</p><p content-type="signature-group">			<named-content content-type="signature">Norm D. Smith</named-content>		</p></body></article>