<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18579998</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636179</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_4_331_41420</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Illuminated curved 25-gauge vitrectomyprobe for removal of subsclerotomyvitreous in vitreoretinal surgery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chalam</surname><given-names>Kakarla V</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Gaurav Y</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>Swati</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Shailesh K</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida College ofMedicine, Jacksonville, FL 32209, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. K.V. Chalam, 580 West, 8<sup>th</sup> Street, Tower 2,3<sup>rd</sup> floor, USA. Email: <email>kchalam@jax.ufl.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Aug</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Incarceration of vitreous in sclerotomy sites during pars planavitrectomy can lead to wound-related complications similarto vitreous incarceration in cataract surgery. We describe anilluminated curved 25-gauge vitrectomy probe for removingvitreous from sclerotomy sites. Polyester tubing is used tosecure a fiber optic endoilluminator (0.5 mm) with the curved25-gauge vitrector (0.5 mm). The resultant illuminated curvedvitrector (20 G) has a diameter of 1.0 mm. It facilitates completeremoval of vitreous around the internal sclerotomies under directvisualization in both phakic and pseudophakic eyes. The samewas confirmed with ultrasound biomicroscopy of the sclerotomysites. Curved vitrector reduces postoperative complicationsrelated to incarcerated vitreous in phakic and pseudophakic eyesand other sclerotomy-related wound complications.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Illuminated 25-gauge vitrectomy probe</kwd><kwd>pars plana vitrectomy</kwd><kwd>phakic</kwd><kwd>sclerotomy site</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Pars plana vitrectomy (PPV) can be complicated by developmentof peripheral retinal tears and subsequent retinal detachment.Following scleral penetration in PPV, vitreous incarcerationis seen in all cases histopathologically. Often this is relatedto high flow rate of infusion fluid and associated increase inintraocular pressure.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></p><p>Various degrees of fibrous or fibrovascular ingrowth occurs atthe sclerotomy site during wound healing. Degree and strengthof fibrous ingrowth is a function of size of the sclerotomy,intraocular pressure at the time of sclerotomy closure, depthof incarceration of vitreous within the sclerotomy, age of thepatient, hemorrhage in vitreous cavity, vascularization of thesclerotomy, race (blacks predisposed more than whites), andpresence of posterior vitreous detachment.</p><p>Approximately 7% of vitrectomy cases develop peripheralretinal breaks postoperatively.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> Vitreous incarceration in thesclerotomy can lead to fibrovascular proliferation and anteriorhyaloid proliferation in diabetic patients leading to recurrentvitreous hemorrhage.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Complete shaving of the vitreous fromthe internal sclerotomy site significantly reduces vitreousincarceration.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> Existing instrumentation does not allow shaving ofthe vitreous around the internal sclerotomy in phakic patients.</p><p>We report a new technique that allows complete removalof incarcerated vitreous from sclerotomy sites in both phakicand pseudophakic eyes with an illuminated curved 25-gauge (25-G) vitrectomy probe through conventional sclerotomy for20-gauge (20-G) instruments.</p><sec><title>Design</title><p>The 25-gauge curved vitrectomy probe was a prototypemanufactured by Bausch and Lomb (Rochester, NY). Theradius of curvature at the shaft is 19.4 mm. The length ofthe probe is 25 mm with a uniform 25-G diameter (0.5 mm).Construction of the illuminated vitrectomy probe is similarto that described previously with a 20-G vitrectomy probe.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>A seamless strong polyester (polyethylene terephthalate) heatshrunk tubing (Advanced Polymers, Inc. Salem, NH) is usedto secure a fiberoptic endoilluminator with a curved 25-Gvitrector ([Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1A">1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1B">B</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2A">2A</xref>]: Vitrector and EM).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> The tubinghas an internal diameter of 0.05 inches and thickness of 0.0005inches. The resultant illuminated vitrector has a diameter of1.0 mm (0.5 mm fiberoptic light source + 0.5 mm 25-G vitrector)[Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2B">2B</xref>]. The assembly is sterilized with gamma radiation,ethylene oxide or cold gas sterilization.</p></sec><sec><title>Technique</title><p>Standard surgical technique with microvitreoretinal blade isused to create the sclerotomies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> The posterior PPV is completedusing a 20-G vitrector. At the end of the procedure the 20-Gcutter is replaced with the 25-G illuminated curved vitrector[<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>]. The illumination of the probe facilitates visualizationof the vitreous on the opposite vitreous base (180&#x000b0; away), whilethe curved design of the probe avoids crystalline lens touch[Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>]. This allows the surgeon to use the other hand todepress the opposite sclera, which enables viewing of theinternal sclerotomy with its surrounding vitreous through thewide-angle lens system [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>]. Position of the endoilluminatortip from the vitrector port can be varied by a gentle slidingmaneuver during the surgery to optimize the illuminationof the incarcerated vitreous. The vitreous incarcerated in theinternal sclerotomy opening is shaved completely under directvisualization. No leakage around the sclerotomy sites wasnoted with the assembly. Vitreous was removed completelyfrom the sclerotomy sites uneventfully.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>Excision of the peripheral vitreous in a phakic eye with aclear lens is one of the most challenging tasks in vitreoretinalsurgery. With the advent of the wide-angle viewing systems,visualization of the peripheral vitreous base has improvedsignificantly. The potential of iatrogenic trauma to the posteriorlens surface by the straight vitrectomy probe restricts accessto the peripheral vitreous near the sclerotomy site.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> A curvedinstrument allows access to the internal sclerotomy site withoutdamaging the posterior lens surface [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>].<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></p><p>While using the curved or conventional vitrector, the surgeonholds the endoilluminator while the assistant depresses thesclera for view of the anterior vitreous. This makes the surgeryassistant-dependent, time-consuming, and limits the dynamicviewing of the vitreous base with the endoilluminator.</p><p>The 20-G curved illuminated vitrector addresses theproblems of illumination of the peripheral vitreous and safetyof the crystalline lens.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> However, it requires a larger sclerotomy(18-G) than conventionally used, thereby increasing the riskof sclerotomy-related leakage and vitreous incarceration.Due to the smaller diameter of the shaft, the 25-G curvedilluminated vitrector allows removal of the vitreous from theinternal sclerotomy site through a conventional sclerotomy(20-G) while preserving the safety of the posterior lens surface.Clinical examination as well as ultrasonographic examinationconfirmed this in both pseudophakic and phakic patients[Fig- <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6A">6A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6B">B</xref>].</p><p>An illuminated sleeve (Synergetics, Inc. St. Charles, MO)that wraps around a straight 25-G vitrector provides the benefitof illuminated 25-G vitrector in a pseudophakic eye. However,the illuminated sleeve does not conform to the curved 25-Gvitrector and cannot be used in phakic eyes without risk oflens touch.</p><p>Effective and complete removal of vitreous from theinternal sclerotomy prevents postoperative complicationsassociated with wound healing. Sabti <italic>et al</italic>., studied 22 eyeswith ultrasound biomicroscopy (UBM) of which 11 underwentPPV with complete shaving of the vitreous from the internalsclerotomy site by indentation with a straight conventionalvitrector, while 11 eyes in the control group underwentconventional PPV only. Complete vitreous shaving around thesclerotomy site significantly reduced vitreous incarceration.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>Removal of vitreous from the internal sclerotomy assumesadded importance during implantation of intra-vitreal drugdelivery systems where large sclerotomies are necessary toaccommodate the size of the implant (2 to 4 mm).</p><p>In a prospective study utilizing UBM to study the internalsclerotomy site in diabetic patients undergoing vitrectomy,Bhende <italic>et al</italic>., noted that eyes with postoperative vitreousincarceration developed fibrovascular proliferation six monthsafter surgery.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></p><p>This is a known high-risk factor for recurrent vitreoushemorrhage after PPV in diabetics.</p><p>We have successfully employed this instrument in 100complicated vitreoretinal procedures, of which 41 were phakiceyes. No lens-related complications occurred, though novicesurgeons may experience a learning curve with the new device.In summary, the 25-G curved illuminated cutter combines theadvantage of a self-illuminated vitrectomy probe and customcurved design that avoids crystalline lens touch. In addition,its usage through a standard 20-G sclerotomy in facilitatingcomplete removal of vitreous from the internal sclerotomyprevents sclerotomy-related complications.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peyman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alturki</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>NC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Surgical managementof incarcerated retina in the sclerotomy</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Surg</source><year>1992</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1480374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Territo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gieser</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of thecannulated vitrectomy system on the occurrence of iatrogenicsclerotomy retinal tears</article-title><source>Retina</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9355191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhende</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Agraharam</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gopal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumasri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukumar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ultrasound biomicroscopy of sclerotomy sitesafter pars plana vitrectomy for diabetic vitreous hemorrhage</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2000</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>1729</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10964837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapusta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Overbury</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasoundbiomicroscopy of sclerotomy sites: The effect of vitreous shavingaround sclerotomy sites during pars plana vitrectomy</article-title><source>Retina</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11642375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inexpensive illuminated vitrectomycutter</article-title><source>Retina</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>891</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14707857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>Advanced Polymers, Inc. website.</source><date-in-citation>[cited on 2005 May]</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.advpoly.com/NewsData/PressRelease101102.asp/">http://www.advpoly.com/NewsData/PressRelease101102.asp/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Principles and techniques of vitreoretinal surgery</article-title><source>Retina</source><year>2006</year><volume>Vol. 3</volume><publisher-loc>St Louis</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CV Mosby</publisher-name><fpage>2150</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chalam</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation andcomparison of lens and peripheral retinal relationships with theuse of endolaser probe and newly designed curved vitrectomyprobe</article-title><source>Retina</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14707833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 30-degree curved endolaser probe</article-title><source>Ann Ophthalmol</source><year>1990</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2244720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chalam</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A curved vitrectomy probe</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Surg Lasers Imaging</source><year>2004</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15185799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chalam</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Illuminated curved vitrectomyprobe for vitreoretinal surgery</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Surg Lasers Imaging</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18050823</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1A" position="float"><label>Figure 1A</label><caption><p>Illuminated curved 25-gauge vitrector assembly</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1A</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-331-g001"/></fig><fig id="F1B" position="float"><label>Figure 1B</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the illuminated curved 25-gauge vitrector assembly</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1B</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-331-g002"/></fig><fig id="F2A" position="float"><label>Figure 2A</label><caption><p>Scanning electron microscope picture of the illuminated curved 25-gauge vitrector tip.</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2A</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-331-g003"/></fig><fig id="F2B" position="float"><label>Figure 2B</label><caption><p>Width of 20-gauge vitrector on theleft (approximately 1 mm) and illuminated curved 25-gauge vitrectoron the right side of the scale (approximately 1 mm)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2B</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-331-g004"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Intra-operative picture showing illuminated curved 25-gaugevitrector through a conventional 20-gauge sclerotomy</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-331-g005"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Intra-operative photograph demonstrating shaving of thevitreous (arrow) incarcerated in the internal sclerotomy (arrowhead).Inset: showing the picture diagram</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-331-g006"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Cadaveric eye demonstrating that curved probe providessafe access to incarcerated vitreous around the internal sclerotomy inphakic eyes without lens touch</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-331-g007"/></fig><fig id="F6A" position="float"><label>Figure 6A</label><caption><p>Intra-operative photograph showing complete removalof the vitreous from the sclerotomy site.</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 6A</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-331-g008"/></fig><fig id="F6B" position="float"><label>Figure 6B</label><caption><p>Ultrasound picture of the sclerotomy showing complete removal of the vitreous from the sclerotomy site</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 6B</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-331-g009"/></fig></floats-group></article>