<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417826</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636109</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_3_233_40364</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Calculating graft size and position in rotational corneal autografting: A simplified approach</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>Srinivas K</given-names></name><degrees>DNB, FRCS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>Dennis SC</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FRCOphth</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Ophthalmology and Visual Sciences, The ChineseUniversity of Hong Kong, Hong Kong Special Administrative Region,P. R. China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Srinivas K. Rao, Department of Ophthalmologyand Visual Sciences, The Chinese University of Hong Kong UniversityEye Center, Hong Kong Eye Hospital, 147K, Argyle Street, Hong Kong. Email: <email>srinikrao@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>In eyes with eccentric corneal opacities partially involvingthe pupillary area, using a rotational corneal autograft, canhelp restore vision without the immunological complicationsassociated with allografts. In this report, we describe a simpleintraoperative method for determining trephine size andplacement for rotational corneal autografting. This surgicalapproach helps in the planning and execution of rotationalcorneal autografting, to obtain good outcomes.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Corneal autograft</kwd><kwd>graft rejection</kwd><kwd>rotational autograft</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Rotational corneal autografts are infrequently performed, butoffer important advantages in patients with central cornealscars. Recent studies indicate that endothelial cell loss afterthis procedure is lower than after homologous penetratingkeratoplasty.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> Although astigmatism continues to be aproblem due to the eccentric nature of corneal trephinationin rotational keratoplasty, the important immunologicaladvantages of this procedure make it an attractive option inindicated patients.</p><p>However, for the procedure to result in visual benefits, it isessential that the central corneal opacity is shifted out of theentrance pupil of the eye. Formulae have been described thathelp assess the suitability of the procedure and choose the sizeof the trephine to be used.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> The use of digitalphotographs and imaging software to assess the suitability of the procedurehas also been described.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> A possible drawback of techniquesthat use photographs is that the two-dimensional images donot take into account the curvature of the cornea and this mayresult in errors in calculation.</p><p>Despite the preoperative assessment, it is important toensure intraoperatively that these calculations produce thedesired effect. In this context, it is important not just to choosean appropriate trephine size, but also to ensure that the trephineis appropriately positioned on the cornea. We described a simplemethod that helped in ensuring that the rotational cornealautograft would produce the desired result - this was performedin the operation theater prior to corneal trephination.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>A paracentral corneal opacity involving the pupil is shown in<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1A">Fig. 1A</xref>. The anatomical center of the cornea is measured usingcalipers and is inked with a marking pen (mark 1). Assuminga postsurgical functional pupil size of 3 mm and adding0.5 mm for suture placement (to preserve the clear zone for theentrance pupil), a second mark is made in the opacity 2.0 mmfrom the first mark (mark 2), which denotes the minimum areaof clear cornea that is desired postoperatively in the opaquearea [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1B">Fig. 1B</xref>]. The third mark (mark 3) is made 1.5 mm frommark 1, 180&#x000b0; away from mark 2 that indicates the other marginof the entrance pupil and the rotated corneal opacity shouldnot cross this point. The distance from mark 2 to the centraledge of the corneal opacity is measured and in this example,is 3.5 mm. A fourth mark (mark 4) is made in line with and4 mm away from mark 3 [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1C">Fig. 1C</xref>]. This indicates the locationof the edge of the rotated opacity and in this case in order tofurther move the opacity from the pupillary margin, 0.5 mmhas been added to the measured distance of 3.5 mm. Thisdetermination is also aided by the preference to stay 0.5-1 mmaway from the limbus.</p><p>The distance from mark 4 to mark 2 provides the trephinesize required - in this case, 7.5 mm. Hence, the trephine canbe correctly positioned, if its edges touch marks 4 and 2 andis centered on a mark midway between these points. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1D">Fig. 1D</xref>shows the effect of rotation of the calculated corneal graft.The points 2 and 4 depict the margins of the rotated graft.Within the graft, the points 1 and 3 are now interposed, thusenabling rotation of the clear peripheral cornea to overlie thepupillary area.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, a similar paracentral opacity is shown, whichhowever involves less of the pupillary area. In this eye, sincemore peripheral cornea is available for rotation, mark 2 is made2.5 mm away from the center. This allows the use of an 8-mmtrephine with at least 4 mm of central clear cornea.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, a central corneal opacity is shown; by followingthe principles in Example 1 and placing mark 4 at the limbus,a central 3 mm clear area is obtained.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, a larger central opacity is shown and in this case,even if the trephine is positioned at the limbus, the resultantclear central area does not cover the pupil and hence in thiscase, a rotational autograft is best avoided.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Using this approach has helped us plan corneal rotational graftsprecisely, with good outcomes. We have used this techniquein 20 eyes over the past 10 years. Endothelial counts werenot performed in all eyes, but none of the eyes have had acorneal endothelial failure after the surgical procedure. Thevisual outcomes have been varied and this depends on thepreoperative amblyopic status of the eye, associated intraocularchanges in the lens and retina and the astigmatic error afterthe procedure.</p><p>It allows intraoperative confirmation of the feasibility ofthis surgical procedure and takes into account the cornealcurvature and allows accurate placement of an appropriatelysized trephine. In comparison with other procedures describedin the literature, this is a simpler approach that does not needaccess to digitized photographs or computer software, althoughthose methods also work well. Importantly, it helps identifycases in which this procedure is unlikely to result in good outcomes, in which a penetrating graft may be performed as a primaryprocedure.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertelmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcome of rotational keratoplasty: Comparison of endothelial cell loss in autografts vs allografts</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>2004</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>1437</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15477453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohringer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundmacher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endothelial cell loss after autologous rotational keratoplasty</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><year>2005</year><volume>243</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15069566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brubaker</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A method for ipsilateral rotational autokeratoplasty</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1978</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>1312</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">370710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Panda-Jonas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calculation of size and location of autologous ipsilateral rotating keratoplasty</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><year>1994</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7959093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karpouzas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pouliquen</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computerized method for rotational autokeratoplasty</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>1991</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1935131</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1A" position="float"><label>Figure 1A</label><caption><p>(A) Schematic of cornea with opacity involving pupillaryarea - the red line shows graduations on a 1-mm scale</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1A</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-233-g001"/></fig><fig id="F1B" position="float"><label>Figure 1B</label><caption><p>(B) The center of the cornea is marked (1) and a point 2.0 mm away from the center,is marked (2) in the opacity</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1B</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-233-g005"/></fig><fig id="F1C" position="float"><label>Figure 1C</label><caption><p>(C) A third mark (3) is made 1.5 mm awayfrom the central mark, in line with the second mark; a fourth mark (4)is made 4.0 mm away from the third</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1C</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-233-g006"/></fig><fig id="F1D" position="float"><label>Figure 1D</label><caption><p>(D) Depiction of rotation of calculated corneal graft</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1D</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-233-g007"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(A) Schematic of cornea with opacity involving pupillary area- the red line shows graduations on a 1-mm scale, (B) The center of thecornea is marked and a point 2.5 mm away from the center, is markedin the opacity, (C) A third mark is made 2.0 mm away from the centralmark, in line with the second mark; a fourth mark is made 3.5 mm awayfrom the third, (D) Depiction of rotation of calculated corneal graft</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-233-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(A) Schematic of cornea with opacity involving pupillary area -the red line shows graduations on a 1-mm scale, (B) The center ofthe cornea is marked and a point 2.0 mm away from the center, is markedin the opacity, (C) A third mark is made 1.5 mm away from the centralmark, in line with the second mark; a fourth mark is made 4.5 mm awayfrom the third, (D) Depiction of rotation of calculated corneal graft</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-233-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>(A) Schematic of cornea with opacity involving pupillary area -the red line shows graduations on a 1-mm scale, (B) The center of thecornea is marked and a point 2.0 mm away from the center, is markedin the opacity, (C) A third mark is made 1.5 mm away from the centralmark, in line with the second mark; a fourth mark is made 4.5 mm awayfrom the third, (D) Depiction of rotation of calculated corneal graft</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-233-g004"/></fig></floats-group></article>