<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18158409</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636039</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_1_68_37602</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A typical presentation and diagnostic pitfalls: A case of rapidly progressive bilateral proptosis in a child aged 18 months</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>Subrahmanya K</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>Sachet P</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barthakur</surname><given-names>Rimli</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>Maya</given-names></name><degrees>DNB</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Ophthalmology, K S Hegde Medical Academy,Mangalore, India (SKB); Department of Ophthalmology, ManipalTeaching Hospital, Manipal College of Medical Sciences, Pokhara,Nepal (SPS,RB,MN).</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Subrahmanya K Bhat, Department ofOphthalmology, K S Hegde Medical Academy, Deralakatte, PostNithyananda Nagar, Mangalore - 575 018, Karnataka State, India. Email: <email>drsbhatk@yahoo.co.in</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We report an atypical presentation of non-Hodgkin lymphoma(NHL) in a child aged 18 months who presented with rapidlyprogressive bilateral proptosis. Computerized search usingMedline did not reveal a similar presentation of NHL in such ayoung child. It stresses the need for an early histopathologicalstudy including immunohistochemistry and demonstratesthe dramatic local response to combined radiotherapy andchemotherapy even in advanced stages without any ocular side-effects.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Bilateral</kwd><kwd>non-Hodgkin lymphoma</kwd><kwd>pediatric</kwd><kwd>proptosis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>There has been a progressive increase<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> in the incidence oflymphoma over the years with frequent reports of varyingand atypical presentations and a bewildering number ofconfusing classifications which still do not fit all the cases.This is especially true with respect to non-Hodgkin lymphoma(NHL). This case report discusses the difficulties encountered indiagnosis, the need for an early incisional biopsy and a completeimmunohistopathological study with all the markers. It also highlights the fact that lymphomas respond dramatically to combined radiotherapy and chemotherapy.</p><sec sec-type=""><title>Case History</title><p>An 18-month-old female child presented with a history ofrapidly increasing prominence of both eyes of two monthsduration. It was first noticed in the left eye, the right eye wasinvolved two to three days later. The child had occasional feverand did not have any major eye or systemic disease before theonset of prominence of the eyes. Her brother, five years old,was healthy.</p><p>The child weighed 9 kg and was afebrile. Examination of theeyes revealed an axial proptosis which measured 22 mm rightand 23 mm left eye at an outer intercanthal distance of 82 mm.Lid edema, prominent vessels over the lids and lagophthalmoswere more pronounced in the left than the right eye [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>].There was gross congestion and chemosis of the conjunctivaand exposure keratitis in the left eye. The conjunctiva wasmildly congested in right eye and the cornea was clear. Ocularmotility was restricted in all directions of gaze in both eyes.Pupils were normal and reactive in both the eyes and visionappeared normal. Fundus examination of right eye revealeda normal optic disc but the left eye showed an edematousdisc. Based on clinical findings, neuroblastoma, granulocyticsarcoma, multifocal eosinophilic granuloma and inflammatorypseudotumor were considered in the differential diagnosis.</p><p>Blood examination revealed hemoglobin of 10.9 gm%,erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) of 35 mm, bleeding timeof 1 min 25 sec and clotting time of 7 min 02 sec and bloodcounts were normal. Peripheral blood smear showed microcytichypochromic picture without any abnormal or atypical cells andadequate platelets. Routine ENT and pediatric referral did notreveal any abnormality. Chest X-ray was normal. Computerizedtomography [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>] showed diffuse infiltration of the orbit anderosion of medial wall of the orbit bordering the nose and lateralwall of the nose bordering the infratemporal fossa on both sides.Adjacent paranasal sinuses were normal. A malignant lesionwas suspected and orbital biopsy was advised.</p><p>An incisional biopsy was done from both orbits to confirma single bilateral etiology. Histopathological sections [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>]study showed solid sheets of predominantly undifferentiatedcells along with a few interspersed elongated and fusiformcells with central nucleus and eosinophilic cytoplasm. Theundifferentiated cells were round to elongated with largepleomorphic nucleus and prominent single to multiple nucleoliwith numerous atypical mitosis. Amidst these there were alsoa few vacuolated cells. These features favored the diagnosis ofundifferentiated rhabdomyosarcoma. Immunohistochemistrywas advised to confirm the diagnosis. Bone marrow waspositive for malignant cells and cerebrospinal fluid showedmetastasis to the brain. Ultrasound scan of the abdomen andpelvis showed hepatomegaly with multiple small hypoechoiclesions. Renal function tests were normal. Serum calcium (12mg/dl) and phosphorus (7 mg/dl) were slightly higher thannormal. Liver function tests were normal except serum alaninetransaminasae (50 U/L).</p><p>In consultation with an oncologist a multimodal treatmentwas planned with radiotherapy and chemotherapy. As thepatient&#x02032;s left eye was at risk due to exposure keratitis andpapilledema, it was decided to start local external beamirradiation followed by chemotherapy. A total of 46 cGy with180 cGy per fraction were given over a period of five weeks.Lens was shielded from exposure to radiation. Chemotherapywas planned as per IRS-IV protocol with injection vincristine1.5 mg/ m<sup>2</sup> IV weekly for 12 weeks and on Week 16, injectiondactinomycin 0.015 mg/Kg/day from Day 1 to Day 5, everythree weeks up to 16 weeks, injection cyclophosphamide 2.2g/m<sup>2</sup> with mesna 440mg/m<sup>2</sup> for one day per cycle every threeweeks up to 16 weeks. Chemotherapy was interrupted due toanemia and low neutrophil counts requiring blood transfusion.Proptosis completely disappeared, the exposure keratitis ofthe left eye healed and disc edema totally subsided 2.5 monthsafter starting therapy [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>]. Patient did not have any visualdeficit in either eye. Unfortunately, patient expired 6.5 monthsafter she was first seen in our hospital due to central nervoussystem infiltration. She did not develop any complications dueto radiation during her follow-up.</p><p>As this was an unusual presentation, tissue block was sentfor immunohistochemistry with an academic interest. Themarkers<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> used were Cytokeratin (epithelial tumors), Vimentin(mesenchyme-derived neoplasms including lymphomas,melanomas, some sarcomas and certain neural tumors),Leukocyte Common Antigen (lymphoma), CD20 and CD79A(B-cell neoplasms), CD3, CD43 and CD 99 (T-cell neoplasms),CD 30 (anaplastic large cell lymphoma and Hodgkin disease),Desmin (rhabdomyosarcoma), Synaptophysin (neuroblastoma),Myeloperoxidase (granulocytic sarcoma), HMB45 (melanoma),TDT (lymphoblastic lymphomas and leukemia) and Ki-67(proliferation-related marker). It was negative for all markersexcept Vimentin and Leukocyte Common Antigen [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>]. KI67 was 60 to 70% positive. The immunohistochemistry reportwas unclassifiable high-grade NHL.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>Lymphomas are solid malignant neoplasms that originatefrom leukocytes, mostly lymphocytes, dendritic histiocytesand plasma cells. Lymphoma occurs most commonly in lymphnodes and primary lymphoid tissue but also in extranodalsites, including the orbit, skin oropharynx, gastrointestinaltract and bone marrow. Systemic NHL in adults is usuallyseen in the fifth or sixth decade and presentation in childhoodis extremely rare.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>Most orbital lymphomas are NHL and tend to present in thesixth and seventh decade and present anteriorly in the orbit.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>Presentation before the age of 20 is rare.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> In one reported caseseries,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> although NHL was the most frequent malignant tumorof the eye and ocular adnexae (55%), the youngest patient was15-years-old (15 to 96) and the median age was 71 years.</p><p>In another review<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> of 145 patients of lymphoma orbit and/adnexa and/ocular, the youngest patient was three-years-old(three to 96 years) and the median age was 66 years and 10%were bilateral. Exophthalmia was seen in 27%. Kodsi <italic>et al</italic>. intheir review of 340 orbital tumors in children found only 18.2%of them to be malignant<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> (11.5% primary and 6.8% metastatic).Among 62 malignant tumors rhabdomyosarcoma (24) was themost common malignant neoplasm, with lymphoma (five)much less frequent.</p><p>Most of the lymphomas of the eye and its adnexa are NHL ofB-cell type.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Computed tomography demonstrates the moldingof the mass to orbital structures, such as the globe and orbitalbones, without bony erosion except in large cell lymphoma.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>Radiotherapy is effective in indolent forms and chemotherapyis applied in aggressive lymphomas and a combination of radio-and chemotherapy may even be more effective.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> The presenceof bilateral involvement, extension to the subcutaneoustissue or temporalis fossa is associated with increased risk ofdissemination.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> Higher grade and destruction of orbital wallsuggest a poor prognosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></p><p>In conclusion, it was a rare presentation of a primaryorbital NHL in a child aged 18 months presenting as rapidlyprogressive bilateral axial proptosis with an early metastasis. Inthis case the tumor was so poorly differentiated that it couldn&#x02032;tbe classified.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Bony erosion of orbital and nasal wall insteadof molding to the adjoining structures was seen. There wasno radiation-induced complication in the eye with the dosagegiven, over a follow-up period of 6.5 months.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margo</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulla</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Malignant tumors of the orbit, Analysis of the Florida Cancer Registry</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1998</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richard J</surname><given-names>Cote</given-names></name><name><surname>Clive R</surname><given-names>Taylor</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ivan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunohistochemistry and related Marking techniques</article-title><source>Andersons pathology part I</source><year>1996</year><publisher-name>Mosby-Year book Inc</publisher-name><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Diebold</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Flandrin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller-Hermelink</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vardiman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>WHO classification of neoplastic diseases of the hematopoietic and lymphoid tissues: Report of the Clinical Advisory Committee Meeting- Airlie House, Virginia, November 1997</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>3835</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10577857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hindola</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brian</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Geoffrey</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>William</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Edward</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lymphocytic, plasmacytic, histiocytic and hematopoietic tumors of the orbit.</article-title><source>Duane&#x02032;s Clinical Ophthalmology 2003 Edition on CD-ROM</source><volume>Vol 2</volume><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams and Wilkins Publishers, Inc</publisher-name><comment>Chapter 39</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumbroso-Le Rouic</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent-Salomon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dendale</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Asselain</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ophthalmologic and intraocular non-Hodgkin&#x02032;s lymphoma: A large single centre study of initial characteristics, natural history and prognostic factors</article-title><source>Hematol Oncol</source><year>2004</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16134191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kodsi</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shetlar</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garitty</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartley</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of 340 orbital tumors in children during a 60-year period</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>1994</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>82,</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8116746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Delecluse</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Anagnostopoulos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Foss</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hummel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lymphoproliferative lesions of the ocular adnexa, analysis of 112 cases</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1998</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>1430</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9709754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schick</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lermen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Uns&#x000f6;ld</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of primary orbital lymphomas</article-title><source>Eur J Haematol</source><year>2004</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14962237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunce</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cree</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Plowman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Histological features of ocular adnexal lymphoma (REAL classification) and their association with patient morbidity and survival</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2000</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>907</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10906102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of radiotherapy for primary orbital lymphoma</article-title><source>Am J Clin Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12040284</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Clinical appearance, A and B - at presentation, C - immediatelyafter incision biopsy and D - 2.5 months after starting therapy</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-68-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Computerized tomography showing erosion of medial orbitalwalls into nose and lateral wall of the nose bordering infratemporalfossa on both sides</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-68-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>H and E staining A (10X), B (40X) showing solid sheets ofpredominantly undifferentiated cells along with a few interspersedelongated and fusiform cells with central nucleus and eosinophiliccytoplasm. The undifferentiated cells are round to elongated with largepleomorphic nucleus and prominent single to multiple nucleoli withnumerous atypical mitosis. Few vacuolated cells are also seen. PositiveLeukocyte Common Antigen (C) and Vimentin stains (D)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-68-g003"/></fig></floats-group></article>