<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18292624</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636089</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_2_135_39118</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ophthalmology Practice</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Learning micro incision surgery without the learning curve</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Ravi</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Navin</surname><given-names>Shoba</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>Rajul</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>LV Prasad Eye Institute, Hyderabad, India (RT, RP); Silome EyeHospital, LV Prasad Eye Institute, Madanpalli, India (SN).</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Ravi Thomas, LV Prasad Eye Institute, BanjaraMarg, Banjara Hills, Hyderabad-500 034, Andhra Pradesh, India. Email: <email>rt@ravithomas.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Mar-Apr</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access		article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits		unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We describe a method of learning micro incision cataract surgery painlessly with the minimum of learningcurves. A large-bore or standard anterior chamber maintainer (ACM) facilitates learning without change ofmachine or preferred surgical technique. Experience with the use of an ACM during phacoemulsification isdesirable.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Anterior chamber maintainer</kwd><kwd>micro incision cataract surgery</kwd><kwd>phacoemulsification</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type=""><title>Introduction</title><p>Surgery for cataract has witnessed a technological revolutionand the advances continue.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> The situation in India, a countrythat performs nearly four million cataracts extractions annually,is particularly exciting.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> While extra-capsular and manualsmall incision surgery are the predominant techniques incurrent use, most ophthalmologists naturally aspire towardsthe technologically advanced phacoemulsification as a nextstep or preferred method. The technology and techniqueof phacoemulsification too have seen rapid advances. Safermachines with advanced software allow surgeons to performcataract surgery safely with less and less ultrasound power.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Thesearch for smaller and smaller incisions too continues. Towardsthis end, &#x02033;micro incision&#x02033; cataract surgery (MICS) is nowbecoming popular.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> In order to decrease the size of the incision,MICS requires the use of a &#x02033;naked&#x02033; phacoemulsification needle,that is, a needle without the irrigating sleeve. The increasedrisk of incision burn is addressed by &#x02033;cold&#x02033; phaco technology.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>The rollable lenses for insertion through this type of incisiondo not have the track record of usual foldable lenses; manyusing this technique would also insert an endocapsular ringto prevent shrinkage of the bag. The literature on the subject issparse, with studies showing no real advantage of MICS overstandard phacoemulsification.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> There is, however, amarket value for the latest in surgical techniques. There is also another,perhaps more legitimate need to master MICS: such a techniqueor modification thereof would be required to use the much-awaited injectable intraocular lenses.</p><p>We describe an approach to achieve skill in MICS withoutany change in machine or phacoemulsification technique thatcan be achieved with the minimum of learning curves.</p><sec><title>Learning micro incision cataract surgery</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Anesthesia: While there is no need to change your preferredtechnique of anesthesia, we make an argument for a formal&#x02033;block&#x02033; while in the learning stage.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The details described hereafter is applicable to right eye.A standard 20-gauge myringotomy blade is used to makea paracentesis incision in the upper temporal quadrantaround the 10 o&#x02032;clock position [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>]. This incision isprimarily used for the phacoemulsification.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The chamber is deepened with the preferred viscous orvisco-elastic agent.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A continuous curvilinear capsulotomy is performed in theusual manner with a bent needle introduced through theparacentesis incision. The diameter of the capsulotomy isabout 5.5 mm.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The myringotomy blade is used to make anotherparacentesis incision at 6 o&#x02032;clock [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>]. This incision isused to insert and fixate the anterior chamber maintainer(ACM). Accordingly, we try to create an incision withan intra-stromal length of 1.5 mm. Alternatively, aparacentesis similar to the first, but with a longer intra-stromal track is created at the 7 o&#x02032;clock position. An ACM[<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>] attached to a bottle of irrigating fluid is insertedinto the anterior chamber and the stop-cock is opened.The ACM can be the same as that used for standardBlumenthal Cataract surgery (Visitech Instruments Fl,USA; catalogue number: 58514). If you use this ACM, wewould suggest that you also use an irrigating chopper.We prefer to use a slightly larger bore ACM designedby Professor Ehud Assia (Ccrnea infusion terminal;Ophthaltech; Switzerland). Even with this ACM, weprefer the extra irrigation from an irrigating chopper,which almost eliminates fluctuations in chamber depth.We have used the regular chopper and technique too butthen have to accept and be prepared for the slight anteriorchamber fluctuations that may occur. Whatever the ACMused, the higher the bottle height, the better.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A paracentesis incision is made approximately 90degrees away from the incision that has been created forphacoemulsification.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The sleeve for the phacoemulsification needle is cutat its base. The &#x02033;naked&#x02033; phacoemulsification needle isintroduced into the anterior chamber through the supero-temporal incision. The irrigating chopper or preferredinstrument is introduced through the incision created forthis purpose. Phacoemulsification is performed using thesurgeons preferred technique. We use the stop and chopmethod [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>The cortex is extracted using a single port aspirationcanula attached to a syringe and introduced through oneof the incisions as is usual with the Blumenthal technique.Alternatively, a canula attached to the machine can be usedfor this step. The availability of two incisions allows easyaccess to the cortex that might otherwise be difficult toaccess.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An endo-capsular ring is inserted into the capsular bag. Thiscan be done with the ACM open or with a visco surgicaldevice filling the anterior chamber. We prefer to extend thewound slightly and use an injector for this step, but thiscan easily be done with using forceps too.</p></list-item><list-item><p>If the wound has not been extended to inject the endo-capsular ring, it is now extended slightly. Just enough toaccept the cartridge for the rollable IOL (IOCARE; Baroda;India). The lens is injected into the capsular bag. This step toocan be done with the ACM or with visco surgical device.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Any visco surgical device is aspirated using the single portcanula attached to a syringe or using the machine. TheACM is removed and the incisions hydrated to achieve awatertight wound.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The first postoperative day picture is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>. Thehydrated incisions are clearly visible. This usually clearsby the first week visit.</p></list-item></list></p><p>This technique of learning MICS was used by the seniorauthor to teach himself in nine cases. The assessment of ease ofperformance was subjective. The cases selected had a minimumpupillary dilatation of 5.5 mm, nuclear sclerosis up to Grade 3;one patient had a mature cataract. There were no complicationsrelated to the technique: corneal burns were not encountered.The subjective assessment of fluctuations was no different thanwith regular phacoemulsfication performed by the same author;the irrigating chopper was used to further stabilize the chamberif any fluctuation was encountered. Two patients had hydrationof the incision used for phacoemulsification. In one patient thisinterfered with the removal of the epinucleus and made theinsertion of the endocapsular ring more difficult than usual.Mild hydration of the phaco wound and mild Descemet&#x02032;s foldswere seen on Day 1 in all cases. The uncorrected visual acuityat one week ranged from 20/80 to 20/ 30. The uncorrected andbest-corrected visual acuity at five weeks ranged from 20/60 to20/ 25 and 20/25 to 20/20 respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>For those who are familiar with the use of the ACM for theBlumenthal technique and have used it for phacoemulsificationtoo, this switch from regular phacoemulsification to MICSis literally without a learning curve. For reasons discussedelsewhere, we have recommended and used the ACM even forroutine phacoemulsification.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> Not least of these is that it makesteaching of routine phacoemulsification so easy. And followingdiscussions with and a demonstration by Prof Assia, we realizedthat we could perform MICS without too much difficulty andwithout any change in technique. While we usually use &#x02033;cold&#x02033;phaco (Sovereign; AMO; India), we have used other machinessuch as the Legacy (Alcon; India) as well. The ACM preventscorneal burns. In fact, since starting phacoemulsifcation in 1992,the author (RT) has not had a single corneal burn. We attributethis to the use of the ACM.</p><p>The larger bore maintainer and a higher bottle height preventfluctuations of the anterior chamber. The added irrigation froman irrigating chopper provides additional safety. We wouldcertainly recommend this while using the usual BlumenthalACM.</p><p>What if we run into trouble and need to convert?What if there is a posterior capsular rent? As with regularphacoemulsification, knowledge of manual small incisioncataract Surgery (MSICS) is of help here. The corneal wound isignored. A conjunctival incision is made and we proceed withthe Blumenthal technique of MSICS described elsewhere.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> Ifthe posterior capsule has been breached and vitreous is in theanterior chamber (best checked with an endo-illuminator), thebottle height is lowered and a partial anterior vitrectomy isperformed using the paracentesis incision. With the ACM on,the second hand is free to sweep vitreous from the wound andperform other maneuvers.</p><p>We acknowledge some major limitations of this article. Thetechnique and learning curve described is for a reasonablyexperienced surgeon. Accordingly, the method is ideallyextrapolated to those with similar experience in routinephacoemulsification. The amount of prior skill required tolearn this technique safely in the manner described is unknown;it is our impression however that it would not require a17-year track record. Experience with the use of the ACM isdesirable and easily obtained. Assessment of anterior chamberfluctuations and corneal hydration were subjective. Finally,while no complications were encountered in this series, thetrue rate of complications could be as high as 28%.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> Keeping inmind that we have encountered no corneal burns in 17 years,as the technique is essentially the same, the incidence of thiscomplication at least is likely to be rare. There is no reason whythe incidence of other complications of phacoemulsificationshould be any different.</p><p>In summary, we have described how the use of an appropriateACM and chopper can help acquire skill in MICS. For a surgeonfamiliar with the use of the ACM or willing to try its use inphacoemulsification, performing MICS should not requireadditional expert assistance.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Source of Support: Nil</p></fn><fn><p>Conflict of Interest: None declared</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linebarger</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardten</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phacoemulsification and modern cataract surgery</article-title><source>Surv Ophthalmol</source><year>1999</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10541151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dandona</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dandona</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajashekar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcome and number of cataract surgeries in India: Policy issues for blindness control</article-title><source>Clin Experiment Ophthalmol</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12580890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovations in phacoemulsification technology</article-title><source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source><year>2007</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17159443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weikert</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update on bimanual microincisional cataract surgery</article-title><source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16436926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New phacoemulsification technology</article-title><source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15650578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Prats</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Galal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramzy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcomes of microincision cataract surgery versus coaxial phacoemulsification</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2005</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>1997</fpage><lpage>2003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16183129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krummenauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biaxial microincision versus coaxial small-incision clear cornea cataract surgery</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2006</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>1818</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17011959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuriakose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards achieving smallincision cataract surgery 99.8% of the time</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2000</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11116514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tugwell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Clinical epidemiology, Basic science for clinical medicine</source><year>1991</year><edition>2nd ed</edition><publisher-name>Little Brown</publisher-name><fpage>176</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>A myringotomy knife is used to create a beveled incision in the upper temporal quadrant, right eye</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-135-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Another paracentesis incision with a longer intra-stromal course is created at the 6 o'clock position, right eye</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-135-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>A large-bore anterior chamber maintainer (Ophthaltech, Switzerland) is inserted into the anterior chamber, right eye</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-135-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Phacoemulsification is performed using the &#x0201c;naked&#x0201d;phacoemulsification needle and an irrigating chopper. The anteriorchamber maintainer (large-bore or regular) and the chopper maintainthe anterior chamber and prevent a burn, right eye</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-135-g004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>First postoperative day, showing the rollable lens <italic>in situ</italic>. Thepupil was dilated for the photograph. Notice the hydrated paracentesisincisions, right eye</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-135-g005"/></fig></floats-group></article>