<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18292634</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636080</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_2_161_39128</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A case of neurofibromatosis 1 presenting with optic pathway glioma with an early onset and an aggressive		course</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>Suma</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Archana</given-names></name><degrees>DNB</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Manish</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhuttan</surname><given-names>Samdeep</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Pediatric Ophthalomology Department, Dr. Shroff&#x02032;s Charity Eye Hospital, Daryaganj, New Delhi, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Ganesh Suma, Dr. Shroff&#x02032;s Charity EyeHospital, Kedarnath Road, Daryaganj, New Delhi - 110 002, India. Email: <email>drsumaganesh@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Mar-Apr</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>8</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access		article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits		unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Optic pathway glioma associated with neurofibromatosis 1has a classically indolent course. However, involvement ofthe optic radiations is relatively rare and is associated with amore aggressive course. A three-year-old girl presented withstrabismus and loss of vision in the left eye with relative afferentpupillary defect and optic disc pallor. She had multiple caf&#x000e9; aulait spots. Visually evoked potential was suggestive of an opticnerve conduction defect and magnetic resonance imaging of thebrain was suggestive of an optic pathway glioma involving theoptic nerves, the optic chiasma and the optic tracts. The opticradiations and the dentate nuclei had hamartomas. Optic nervebiopsy confirmed pilocytic astrocytoma. Radical radiotherapyunder general anesthesia was subsequently given. This casereport aims to highlight the involvement of the optic radiationsand the unusually aggressive clinical course in this case.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Glioma</kwd><kwd>neurofibromatosis 1</kwd><kwd>optic radiations</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Neurofibromatosis Type 1 (NF-1) is a relatively common(incidence 1 in 3000) autosomal dominant disorder.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> In additionto multiple peripheral neurofibromas, NF-1 predisposesto central nervous system (CNS) tumors. Most of these arepilocytic astrocytomas, arise in children and are located in theoptic pathways or in the brainstem.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> A majority of the gliomasarising in association with NF-1 are indolent<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> and in the youngerage group do not require active intervention until progressionis documented or the disease is severe enough to affect visualoutcome. However, optic pathway gliomas in NF-1 may rarelyinvolve the optic radiations. Optic radiation involvement maysignal a more aggressive optic pathway glioma in patients withNF-1.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> We report the case of a three-year-old girl presentingwith an unusually aggressive optic pathway glioma involvingthe optic radiations associated with NF-1 and treated withradiotherapy.</p><sec sec-type=""><title>Case Report</title><p>A three-year-old female child presented in the last week of April2005 with a history of the left eye squinting intermittently andnot focusing well since 10 days. There were pigmented skinlesions present since infancy.</p><p>On ophthalmic evaluation, the best-corrected vision in theright eye was 20/40 (N9) and in the left eye was counting fingersat one foot with accurate projection of rays. There was lefteye exotropia with poor fixation without any abnormal headposture. There was no nystagmus. Corneal reflex test showed adeviation of 10 degrees. Prism bar cover test showed a deviationof 20 prism diopters for distance and near.</p><p>The extraocular movements were full. She had a relativeafferent pupillary defect (RAPD) in the left eye. The skinshowed multiple caf&#x000e9; au lait spots, [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>] some larger than5 mm in the greatest diameter. Axillary and inguinal freckleswere also present.</p><p>Visually evoked potential showed an optic nerve conductiondefect and delayed latency in the left eye as compared to theright with normal amplitudes in both. Electroretinographywas normal.</p><p>A brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>]performed in May 2005 showed a fusiform enlargement of theleft optic nerve with a thickened right optic nerve.</p><p>The optic chiasma showed enhancement extending toinvolve the optic tracts bilaterally. Posteriorly non-enhancingaltered signals appearing hyperintense were seen along theoptic radiations. A non-enhancing hyperintense signal wasseen in the dentate nuclei bilaterally - consistent with the classichamartomatous CNS fibromas of NF-1.</p><p>The patient was referred to a neurosurgeon and the biopsyof the optic nerve was done through left frontal temporalcraniotomy, which revealed Rosenthal fibers with eosinophilicglobular bodies [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>] strongly positive for Glial FibrillaryAcidic Protein (GFAP) stain confirming a diagnosis of pilocyticastrocytoma of the optic nerve.</p><p>A diagnosis of NF-1 with bilateral optic pathway glioma -pilocytic astrocytoma was made.</p><p>Radical radiotherapy under general anesthesia was givenin September 2005; post radiotherapy, the gliomas significantlyregressed in size with reduced enhancement on a repeat MRIdone in April 2006. The altered signal in the dentate nucleihowever was unchanged. On post radiotherapy follow-up,visual acuity in the right eye was 20/40 and in the left eye wasno perception of light. The fundus examination showed discpallor both eyes, left eye more than right.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>The most common differential diagnosis of a child withpainless loss of vision, RAPD, strabismus and an abnormaldisc includes optic glioma, optic nerve meningioma, opticneuritis and Autosomal Dominant Optic Atrophy (ADOA).The diagnosis of optic nerve glioma associated with NF-1 inthis case was suggested by caf&#x000e9; au lait spots, asymmetric discpresentation and later supported by MRI findings and finallythe biopsy report.</p><p>NF-1 is a rare condition characterized by hamartomas ofneural crest origin. It has an autosomal dominant inheritancealthough half the cases are new mutations.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></p><p>Among the various clinical manifestations, astrocytomas arethe major type of CNS tumors in NF-1 and pilocytic astrocytoma(WHO Grade I) the main histological subtype.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> A stable or avery slow progressive course that may account for the overallgood prognosis of CNS tumors in NF-1 usually characterizespilocytic astrocytomas. Optic radiation involvement thoughrare may signal a more aggressive optic pathway glioma inpatients with neurofibromatosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></p><p>In pediatric patients with NF-1 and optic pathway gliomas,the likelihood of visual loss is dependent on the extent andlocation of the tumor by MRI and is particularly associatedwith the involvement of post chiasmal structures.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></p><p>Considering the risk of visual loss, the NF-1 optic pathwayglioma task force<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> has recommended annual screeningincluding neuroimaging, for children with asymptomaticNF-1 till the age of six. Thereafter, the interval is yearly forthose with optic pathway glioma and two-yearly for the rest.Recommended guidelines for therapy include observation inthe case of a stable painless intraorbital tumor and good vision;a tumor causing disfiguring proptosis and poor vision shouldbe excised. Progressive chiasmal tumors should be treatedwith radiotherapy. Juvenile pilocytic astrocytoma has a betterprognosis among all the histological subtypes and a five-yearsurvival rate of 80 to 100% has been documented.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></p><p>Our case was unusual in presenting with an unusuallyaggressive course at a younger age with involvement of theoptic radiations requiring radiotherapy for the same. Wewould like to reiterate the importance of a thorough systemicevaluation of any child presenting with unexplained visual lossand strabismus along with the importance of neuroimaging inthe diagnosis and prognostication of neurofibromatosis andoptic nerve glioma. Finally, optic nerve glioma involving thepost chiasmal structures including the optic radiations canpresent as a more aggressive variant and warrants interventionfor the same.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mario</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Ramsby</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging lesion analysis in neurofibromatosis type 1</article-title><source>Arch Neurol</source><year>1998</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9561977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guillamo</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prognostic factors of CNS tumours in Neurofibromatosis 1 (NF1): A retrospective study of 104 patients</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2002</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Astrup</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural history and clinical management of optic pathway glioma</article-title><source>Br J Neurosurg</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14579898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optic radiation involvement in optic pathway gliomas in neurofibromatosis</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2004</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15013861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathophysiology of neurofibromatosis type 1</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>842</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16754926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di</surname><given-names>Mario</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsby</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging lesion analysis in neurofibromatosis type I</article-title><source>Arch Neurol</source><year>1998</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9561977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balcer</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual loss in children with neurofibromatosis type 1 and optic pathway gliomas: Relation to tumor location by magneticresonance imaging</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2001</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11292406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurofibromatosis 1: Recommendations for management</article-title><source>Arch Pediatr</source><year>2002</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11865551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mamelak</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Prados</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Obana</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment options and prognosis for multicentric juvenile pilocytic astrocytoma</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>1994</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8207524</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Cafe au lait spots</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-161-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>MRI showing involvement of the optic tracts and optic radiations (left top and bottom), the fusiform dilatation showing the opticnerve glioma (on the top right) and a post radiotherapy image showing some regression of the involvement of the optic radiations (bottomright)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-161-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Histopathological slide showing Rosenthal fibers and eosinophilic granular bodies suggestive of pilocytic astrocytoma. Glialfibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) stain with magnification, &#x000d7;100</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-161-g003"/></fig></floats-group></article>