<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18292631</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636076</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_2_155_39125</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Direct aspiration of capsular bag material in a case of sequestered endophthalmitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gopal</surname><given-names>Lingam</given-names></name><degrees>MS, FRCS Ed</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nagpal</surname><given-names>Amit</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>Aditya</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Sri Bhagwan Mahaveer Vitreoretinal Services, Medical and Vision Research Foundations, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Lingam Gopal, Vision Research Foundation,18, College Road, Chennai - 600 006, India. Email: <email>drlg@snmail.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Mar-Apr</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access		article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits		unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Chronic recurrent endophthalmitis can occur followinguncomplicated cataract surgery with intraocular lens implantationsecondary to organisms sequestered in the capsular bag. Thereis a need to identify these sequestered organisms to facilitateappropriate management. Frequently, specimens from the anteriorchamber and vitreous cavity could be unyielding, especially inthe early cases in which the vitreous is still uninvolved. Thisarticle highlights the technique of directly sampling the capsularbag material in the effective diagnosis of the organism, whichfacilitated the total cure by irrigation with appropriate antibioticsinto the capsular bag.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Culture technique</kwd><kwd>delayed onset endophthalmitis</kwd><kwd>phacoantigenic uveitis</kwd><kwd><italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic></kwd><kwd>sequestered endophthalmitis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Chronic localized endophthalmitis (delayed onsetendophthalmitis) is an important cause of chronic, recurrentinflammation in pseudophakic eyes caused by organismssequestered between the intraocular lens (IOL) optic andposterior capsular bag or at the equator. The clinical pictureof the disease is highly variable and may be predictiveof the disease. But the diagnosis is clinched through themicrobiological isolation of the organism from the intraocularspecimens. We describe a simple and effective technique whichresulted in positive yield of causative organism in such a case.This offered a chance to salvage the IOL, by delivering theappropriate antibiotics into the capsular bag.</p><sec sec-type=""><title>Case Report</title><p>A 64-year-old male presented to us six months after anuneventful phacoemulsification with IOL implantation, withhistory of four episodes of redness and pain starting twomonths after surgery. The signs and symptoms apparentlyresponded to topical prednisolone acetate eye drops (eighttimes a day and tapered gradually), but recurred followingcessation of the treatment. According to the records, hisvitreous was never involved. Two anterior chamber tapsdone previously were negative on microbiological workup.The last aqueous tap was negative even on polymerasechain reaction (PCR) examination for <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic>genome and <italic>eubacterial</italic> genome. At presentation, his visionwas 20/60 in the affected eye. There were keratic precipitates,aqueous flare and cells. The IOL was <italic>in situ</italic> and there wasno definitive plaque made out at the posterior capsule. At12 O&#x02032;clock meridian, some creamy material was suspectedbehind the anterior capsule. Under direct vision using theoperating microscope, with maximum pupillary dilatation, a27-gauge needle connected to a 2-ml syringe was introducedfrom the infero-temporal quadrant of the limbus under topicalanesthesia. With the bevel of the needle facing forwards, theanterior capsule was lifted gently and the creamy material wasscraped. The loosened material was gently aspirated and wassubjected to smear (KOH, Calcoflour white and Gram&#x02032;s stain)and culture (blood agar, chocolate agar, Brucella blood agar,brain heart infusion broth and Robertson&#x02032;s cooked meat broth).The smear showed plenty of gram-positive pleomorphic bacilli[<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>], which grew <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic> on Brucella bloodagar, confirmed with PCR technique. Once the organism wasidentified, vancomycin (1 mg) was injected into the capsularbag, repeated again after an interval of five days. The infectionwas totally controlled and he could be weaned off all themedications (moxifloxacin and prednisolone drops initiallyinstilled eight times a day and tapered within one month).At the last examination one year after the intracapsular baginjection, his vision was 20/20 and the eye was quiet.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>Postoperative delayed onset or chronic endophthalmitis due tosequestered organisms in the capsular bag is not an uncommoncomplication of an otherwise uncomplicated phacoemulsificationsurgery with IOL implantation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref><italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic> isthe most commonly isolated organism, with others such as<italic>Acinetobacter calcoaceticus</italic>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> <italic>Torulopsis candida</italic>(<italic>Candida famata</italic>),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref><italic>Corynebacterium minutissimum</italic>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> <italic>Alcaligenes xylosoxidans</italic>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref><italic>Propionibacterium granulosum</italic>, being reported occasionally. In allthese patients, the spectrum of organisms and potential difficultyencountered in achieving a positive culture result emphasizesthe need for effective sample collection and culture techniques.Hence, it is imperative to identify the organism to facilitateappropriate and timely management. Since very often thevitreous is uninvolved in the initial stages to a significant degree,vitreous specimens are likely to be negative. Even the aqueous tapcan be negative for organisms - both by routine culture methodsas well as PCR. The technique described here aims at identifyingthe possible location of the organisms in the form of cheesyplaque-like colonies by careful slit-lamp examination, followedby scraping of the sequestered organisms from the capsule orthe equator with a needle tip before aspirating the material. Webelieve that the microbiological positivity can be substantiallyimproved with this technique. With predominantly posteriorlylocated plaques, one may have to modify the technique slightlyto reach beyond the equator of the IOL where the dead spaceexists and may harbor the organisms.</p><p><italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic> has been isolated from the intraocularspecimens with culture and PCR techniques on aqueous andvitreous humor yielding variable results, but the capsularbag biopsy and histopathological examination has invariablyyielded positive results and confirmation of the organism.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> Both light and transmission electron microscopy have documented aclose association between <italic>propionibacterium acnes</italic> and posteriorcapsular plaque or plaques in the capsular fornices.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></p><p>Tessler <italic>et al</italic>., in a similar study concluded that <italic>Propionibacteriumacnes</italic> endophthalmitis might be one instance in which theculture of the aspirate from the capsular bag may provide ahigher yield of positive results than cultures of vitreous andaqueous humor.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref> In the same report, they described a techniqueof collection of the specimen for microbiological and cytologicalworkup under topical anesthesia through anterior chamberparacentesis, followed by irrigation of the capsular bag withclindamycin.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></p><p>The technique described in this report is similar but withan additional feature. By deliberately scraping the area ofsuspected colonization, the colonies are loosened and suckedinto the syringe.</p><p>One of the conditions, which is often confused with thisentity is phacoantigenic uveitis with retained lens matter, whichusually resolves after simple removal of lens fragments fromthe anterior chamber without the use of intraocular antibiotics.The differentiation can be made accurately (especially from thefungal colony) if the lens matter or the plaque is removed fromthe capsular bag and subjected to careful microbiological andhistopathological studies.</p><p>The present case report stresses on the fact that postoperativelow-grade chronic localized inflammation can be accuratelydiagnosed and the causative organism can be found out bysampling the capsular bag material rather than the vitreous.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winward</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pflugfelder</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>HW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Roussel</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative Propionibacterium endophthalmitis Treatment strategies and long-term results</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1993</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8479698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meisler</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zakov</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruner</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcmohan</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zachary</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endophthalmitis associated with sequestered intraocular <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic></article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>1987</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3499078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roussel</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Culbertson</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic postoperative endophthalmitis associated with <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic></article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>1987</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>201</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawusch</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Michels</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruner</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Annable</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endophthalmitis due to <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic> sequestered between IOL optic and posteriorcapsule</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Surg</source><year>1989</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2927902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gopal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Saswade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Battu</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative endophthalmitis caused by sequestered <italic>Acinetobacter calcoaceticus</italic></article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2000</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10704562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nerenberg</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Torulopsis candida (<italic>Candida famata</italic>) endophthalmitis simulating <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic>syndrome</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>1991</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1718</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1841584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arsan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sizmaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozkanm</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Duman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Corynebacterium minutissimum</italic> endophthalmitis- Management with antibiotic irrigation of the capsularbag</article-title><source>Int Ophthalmol</source><year>1995-1996</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8864817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Holz</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Alcaligenes xylosoxidans</italic> and <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic> postoperative endophthalmitis in apseudophakic eye</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2000</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10927000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buggage</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Callanan</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic> endophthalmitis diagnosed by microdissection and PCR</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2003</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12928300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tessler</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preliminary study of a new intraocular method in the diagnosis and treatment of <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic>endophthalmitis following cataract extraction</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Surg</source><year>1993</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8321509</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Photomicrograph of the grams stained smear revealing plenty of gram-positive pleomorphic bacilli (&#x000d7;60)</p></caption><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="IndianJOphthalmol-56-155-g001"/></fig></floats-group></article>