<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18579983</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2636177</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IndianJOphthalmol_2008_56_4_267_41409</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Finer nuances of clinical study agreements for research trials</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>Barun Kumar</given-names></name></contrib><aff>P. D. Hinduja National Hospital and Medical Research Centre,Veer Savarkar Marg, Mahim, Mumbai - 400 016, India.Email: <email>editor@ijo.in</email></aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Aug</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>56</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>Most of the doctors in India appear to be excited by the fact that clinical trials conducted in India are on the rise and our countrymay become a major hub for the same. The clinical trials may be institution-based or multi-centric and are increasingly beingfunded by pharmaceutical or biotechnical companies, research organizations or by the government, either partly or fully.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> The conduct of these trials is handled by contract research organizations (CROs) and site managementorganizations (SMOs). All the parties involved have something at stake: the researchers/ institutions may have financial andnon-financial gain,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> the CROs and SMOs have priority to facilitate and complete the trialssuccessfully in the shortest possible time, and the sponsors&#x02032; stake is the highest as a positive outcome would lead to approvalof their product by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) or can lead to an increased sale of their FDA-approved products. The clinicalstudy agreement (CSA) is a legal document which is sent by the company or CROs and SMOs to the participating researchers or institutionsfor execution. Researchers or institutions are by and large na&#x003bf;ve in realizing the importance of CSAs. Every effort should be madeto keep the conflict of interest out of the CSA,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>which usually runs in many pages and is drafted by the sponsors or CROs. This is considered as a legal documentbetween the sponsors and institutions/researchers. In a famous case between Olivieri and Apotex, Apotex threatened Olivieriwith legal action if she disclosed her genuine concerns about the safety of treatment to any third party without its consent.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> Later, Aberman, the dean of the institution said: &#x02033;If there&#x02032;s a contract between twoparties, a third party doesn&#x02032;t have the right to step in and urge one of the parties not to abide by it&#x02033;.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> Olivieri admitted that it was her mistake to sign the contract to keep the resultsconfidential, without even showing the contract to a lawyer. Unfortunately, she was the sole signatory from the institution or theuniversity. The main purpose of this editorial is to highlight some of the issues which should be looked into and addressed bythe researchers before signing the CSAs.</p><p>Research in an institute is not only guided by the Institutional Review Board (IRB) but also by the legal agreement betweensponsors and the institution. The institutions should ensure the proper conduct of trials at their end. Hence, the CSA shoulddescribe the party&#x02032;s roles in the design and conduct of trials, access to data, and publication commitment including publicationrights and responsibility. The International Committee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE) revised its &#x02033;Uniform requirementsfor manuscripts submitted to biomedical journals&#x02033; to maintain the sanctity of research and publication.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> The revisions made it mandatory for full disclosure of the sponsors&#x02032; role as well as the assurance thatresearchers are not under the control of sponsors and have full independent control of study design, access to data, editorial and publication decisions.</p><p>Schulman <italic>et al</italic>.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> conducted a national survey in the US and concluded,&#x02033;academic institutions routinely engage in research that fails to adhere to ICMJE guidelines for trial design, access to data,and publication rights&#x02033;. These were the findings of theinstitutions in the US where the median number of site agreements executed in the previous year was 103 (inter-quartile range,50 to 210).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> The institutions in India should be careful as their exposure in this field islimited.</p><p>It is worthwhile noting certain findings of a survey conducted in the US of medical-school research administrators responsiblefor negotiating CSA with industry sponsors.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> More than 85% respondents would not approveof the provision wherein industry sponsors get authority either to revise the manuscript or to take decision regarding publication ofthe research. Only 24% would agree to allow the sponsors to insert their own statistical analysis and 47% would disallowit. Fifty per cent would allow the sponsors to draft the manuscript while 40% would disallow it. Forty-one per cent would allowthe provision of prohibiting the investigators from sharing data with third parties after the trial is over, 34% would disallowit and 24% were not sure about their stand. The data of this survey reflects the viewpoint of administrators who were experts innegotiating a large number of CSAs, as 51% of the respondents had handled more than 100 agreements in the previous year. Hence,while negotiating any contract one cannot ignore the outcome of this survey.</p><p>There is no guarantee that there will be no dispute after signing the contract. In the same survey mentioned earlier by Mello<italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> 82% of institutions had at least one dispute with the industrysponsor in the previous five years, in spite of having a CSA. Seventy-five per cent institutions had payment-related disputes,30% were related to intellectual property, 17% were related toaccess or control of data, 16% each were related to content of manuscripts and confidentiality of data. It is interesting to notethat while 7% disputes went in litigation and arbitration, 37% were resolved quickly and 55% required extendednegotiations. In case of dispute with sponsors resulting in litigation, the area of jurisdiction should be restricted to the area andcountry of the investigators to avoid unnecessary harassment.</p><p>The members of ICMJE pledged in 2001 not to review or publish articles where CSA prohibits researchers from the freedomof publication.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> This implies that the CSA of sponsored trials will be reviewed prior to theinitiation of processing of submitted manuscripts. Du Val<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> points out four major drawbacks inreviewing post-trial completion of the CSA and subsequent restriction of publication. First, after the completion of research, it willbe unethical and a betrayal of the faith of subjects, not to publish, if scientifically significant findings are made. Second, thisapproach will not ensure review of CSAs if the findings are not submitted for publication such as in studies not intended forpublication or studies with negative results. Third, it may not be possible for editors to undertake a comprehensive review of CSAs tojudge the ethical standard of the same. Fourth, denying publication subverts the core issue of under-reporting. With these limitationsin mind Du Val<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> has suggested thorough review of CSA by theIRB before signing the contract.</p><p>Let us look at the key issues that can arise and that should be addressed ethically in all CSAs. Publication issue must be lookedinto minutely. Blumenthal <italic>et al</italic>.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref> reported that 19.8% of a randomsample of academic life scientists from major research institutions had their publication delayed by more than six months due tointerference by sponsors. In a classic example, a group of researchers completed a study sponsored by Boots pharmaceuticals Inc.comparing the efficacy of sponsor&#x02032;s synthetic thyroid (synthyroid) with three other rival preparations. The researchers found itto be equally effective but the researchers and sponsors had anticipated synthyroid to be superior. Because of the restrictions posed inthe agreement, Boots could block the publication of this significant finding for around seven years.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> Another glaring example of sponsors&#x02032; interference is the dispute betweenOlivieri and Apotex mentioned earlier.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>Disclosure to ensure patient safety is also an important aspect in professional standards of care. The CSA must give freedom toresearchers to use discretion to determine what disclosures or warnings are to be made to subjects. Data analysis and reporting isanother core issue; researchers should have complete freedom to analyze it independently. Any restrictions imposed by sponsorsthrough CSA are not liked by the editors.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> One should realize that statistics is the onlyscience where different conclusions can be drawn using the same data. Confidentiality of information is also an important issue and CSAoften seeks to protect the confidentiality of the sponsor&#x02032;s intellectual property. However, investigators should be permitted todisclose certain relevant information if required, in the best interest of science. Even certain information to the subjects should bepermitted though the CSA. Financial costs and injury compensation to subjects should be clarified in the CSA. The cost ofinvestigations, treatment and harm caused directly due to the research participation should be the responsibility of the sponsors.However, the sponsors can be absolved of this liability if the subject had grossly deviated from the protocol of the study. Provisionfor proper identification of harms and losses should be incorporated in the CSA to protect the independence and integrity of theinstitution and researchers. Certain reasonable exceptions to this may be if the harm has occurred due to acts of negligence or omissionby the researcher or institution or if the investigator admits wrongdoing without the consent of the sponsors. The clause of prematuretermination of agreement and research should be clearly mentioned in the CSA. The valid ground for termination could be eitherineffective treatment (to protect subjects from receiving the experimental drug) or clearly effective treatment (to give benefit ofeffective treatment to control group). The other reasons for termination could be safety concerns if the side-effects of the treatmentare found to be unacceptable. Sometimes, the study might have to be terminated if the continuation of study is not found to befeasible. Sponsors should not be allowed to terminate the study due to lack of commercial viability or because the study provesto be negative for the sponsor.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></p><p>In the excitement of getting an opportunity to participate in sponsored trials and the associated benefits thereof, one should notignore the importance of CSA and every effort should be made to modify it to safeguard the interest of investigators, institutionsand subjects. Scientific harassment by pharmaceutical companies does occur.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref> The review of CSAby IRB as suggested by DuVal<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> is very helpful for the same besides maintaining the ethicalstandard of a clinical study.</p></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Working with the private sector: The need for institutional guidelines</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2002</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12193362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conflict of interest in biomedical publications</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><year>2007</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du Val</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Institutional ethics review of clinical study agreements</article-title><source>J Med Ethics</source><year>2004</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14872068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constraints of interest: Lessons at the hospital for sick children</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>1998</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9834722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuchman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Legal issues surrounding privately funded research cause furore in Toronto</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>1998</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9834722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Uniform Requirements for manuscrips submitted to biomedical journals</article-title><source>www.icmje.org/</source><date-in-citation>[last updated on 2001 Oct] [last accessed on 2008 Jun 7]</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icmje.org/">http://www.icmje.org/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulman</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Seils</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Timbie</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugarman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dame</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinfurt</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A national survey of provisions in clinical-trial agreements between medical schools and industrysponsors</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>347</volume><fpage>1335</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12397192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarridge</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Studdert</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Academic medical centers&#x02032; standards for clinical-trial agreements with industry</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>2202</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15917385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidoff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Between the lines: Navigating the uncharted territory of industry-sponsored research</article-title><source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11900164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Causino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Withholding research results in academic life science: Evidence from a national survey of faculty</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2001</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>2192</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rennie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thyroid storm</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1997</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>1238</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9103350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidoff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>DeAngelis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Drazen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000d8;jgaard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sponsorship, authorship and accountability</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>345</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Societal responsibilities of clinical trial sponsors. Lack of commercial pay off is not a legitimate reason for stoppinga trial</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2001</year><volume>322</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hailey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scientific harassment by pharmaceutical companies: Time to stop</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2000</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10674057</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>