<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Autom Methods Manag Chem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAMMC</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Automated Methods and Management in Chemistry</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1463-9246</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-5068</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19223968</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2637369</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2008/504092</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Effect of Isotopic Composition on the Uncertainty  of Routine Metal Mass Concentration Measurements in  Ambient Air</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Richard J. C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>Sharon L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Andrew S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yardley</surname><given-names>Rachel E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Analytical Science Team, National Physical Laboratory, Teddington, Middlesex TW11 0LW, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Richard J. C. Brown: <email>richard.brown@npl.co.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Recommended by Peter Stockwell</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>2008</volume><elocation-id>504092</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Richard J. C. Brown et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The main sources of uncertainty encountered during the analysis of the mass concentration of metals in ambient air as part of the operation of the UK Heavy Metals Monitoring Network are presented.  It is observed that the uncertainty contribution from possible variation in the isotopic composition of the sample depends on the element in question, but can be significant (e.g., for Pb, Cd, and Hg). The working curve method for the ICP-MS analysis of metals in solution, with a low resolution, high throughput instrument measuring at one <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> ratio per element, relies on the relative abundance of the isotopes under consideration being the same in both the sample and the calibration solution.  Calculation of the uncertainty in this analysis assumes that the isotopic composition variation within the sample and calibration solution is limited to a defined range. Therefore, in order to confirm the validity of this quantification methodology and its uncertainty budget, the isotopic composition of the calibration standards used for quantification has been determined. The results of this analysis are presented here.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="section" id="sec1"><title>1. INTRODUCTION</title><p>The general publicand the environment can be exposed to several classes of hazardous compoundscontaining metallic elements which occur naturally or are released by domesticor industrial processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The total concentration levels of Pb, Ni, As, and Cd allowable in the PM<sub>10</sub> fraction of ambient air (particles with an aerodynamic diameter of 10 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m orless) are now limited by European legislation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. In order to enforce this legislation, to measure human and environmentalexposure, and to show compliance with limit and target values, the totalconcentration levels of ambient metals, at multiple sites on nationwide airquality monitoring networks, need to be measured. To this end, nationwidenetworks for the measurement of a wide range of particulate-borne and gaseouspollutants are now well established in many developed countries around theworld.  NPL currently manages andoperates the UK Heavy Metals Monitoring Network (the &#x0201c;network&#x0201d;) on behalf ofthe UK Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra).  The &#x0201c;network&#x0201d; consists of 24 monitoring sitesaround the UK collecting PM<sub>10</sub> particulate matter which is then sentback to NPL for the analysis of the mass concentration of Ni, As, Cd, Pb, (asrequired by European legislation) and also Hg, Cr, Cu, Fe, Mn, V, Zn, and Pt tocontribute to long-term UK data sets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].  Whilst the data quality objectives laid downby the air quality legislation are not especially exacting&#x02014;the maximumallowable expanded uncertainty for Pb determination is 25%, and for Ni, As, andCd is 40%&#x02014;it is still necessaryto ensure that these objectives are routinely and consistently met. Additionally NPL also sets a self-imposed maximum measurement uncertainty of40% on the nonmandated metals.</p><p>To determine the mass concentration of particulate-phase metals in ambientair, particles are collected onto air filters which are then digested in acidbefore being analysed by inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry (ICP-MS). The ICP-MS is calibrated by a working curve method using matrix matchedsolutions prepared from commercially available elemental solutions certifiedfor metal mass fraction, and compared with NIST standard reference material(SRMs) by NPL to ensure consistency and accuracy. Whilst NPL includes acomponent of uncertainty to take account of the possibility of the isotopiccomposition of metals in ambient air varying within natural limits, for aworking curve method this assumes that the isotopic composition of thecalibration standards being used also falls within this assumed range. If itdoes not, then an additional uncertainty contribution, or a correction factor,may need to be applied. In order to validate this hypothesis, the isotopiccomposition of the standards used for these routine analyses requires measurement. This workpresents the results of this analysis and the effect of these findings on theuncertainty budget of the measurement. We also present the contributions tooverall uncertainty budget from the possible variations in the isotopiccompositions of the ambient air samples.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec2"><title>2. EXPERIMENTAL</title><p>Particulatesamples were taken at all sites in the &#x0201c;network&#x0201d; using Partisol 2000instruments (fitted with PM<sub>10</sub> heads) operating at a calibrated flowrate, nominally of 1 m<sup>3</sup>&#x000b7;h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, in accordance with Europeanstandard method EN 12341 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].  Samples were taken for a period of one week [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]onto 47 mm diameter GN Metricel membrane filters. The analysis forparticulate-phase metals took place using a PerkinElmer Elan DRC II ICP-MS,following NPL's UKAS accredited procedure, which is fully compliant with therequirements of European standard method EN 14902 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>](the EU &#x0201c;reference method&#x0201d; for the analysis of metals in ambient air).  Upon arrival at NPL, the filters sampled withparticulate matter were cut accurately in half, and each portion digested attemperatures up to 220&#x000b0;C using a CEM Mars X microwave. The digestion mixturesused were as follows.<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>Hg and Pt: 5 mlof nitric acid and 5 ml hydrochloric acid.</p></list-item><list-item><p>All other metals:8 ml of nitric acid and 2 ml hydrogen peroxide.</p></list-item></list></p><p> These digested solutions were then diluted with deionised water (Millipore, Milli Q, Mass, USA) prior to analysis. ICP-MSanalysis took place as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] using at least four-matrix-matched gravimetricallyprepared calibration solutions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]prepared from monoelemental standard solutions (VWR, checked for totalelemental composition against the NIST SRM 3100 series). A detector dead timecorrection was applied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]and a full span dual detector linearity check was performed in order tominimise any detector nonlinearity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] since the concentration of different isotopes withinthe samples may span several orders of magnitude. A quality control standardwas repeatedly analysed (after every two solutions), and the change in responseof the quality control standard was mathematically modelled to correct for thelong-term drift of the instrument. The short-term drift of the ICP-MS was corrected by the use of an internalstandards mixture (containing Y, In, Bi, Sc, Ga, and Rh) continuously added tothe all samples via a mixing block. Each sample was analysed in triplicate,each analysis consisting of five replicates. For each element, one isotope at one <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> value was chosen andmonitored. The mass of each metal in solution (and its uncertainty) was thendetermined by a method of generalised least squares using XLGENLINE (anNPL-developed programme [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>])to construct a calibration curve. The analysis of the isotopic ratios of thecalibration standards was performed by determining the blank-correctedintensity at each appropriate <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> ratio. The isotopic composition of the calibration standards was measured byanalysing the separate monoelemental standard solutions used to make up thecalibration solutions. All the usual corrections for isobaric and polyatomiccorrections were applied. The mass fraction of the sum of all isotopes of metalanalyte in each standard solution was approximately 1 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/g. All isotopes ofthe elements of interest were measured, not simply the ones used forquantification. Whilst no additional effort was made to determine additionalcorrections for isotopes not usually used for quantification by the NPLprocedure, additional type-B uncertainty components were included in theuncertainty budget to account for unresolved inaccuracies owing to mass biasand mass discrimination effects, based on conservative estimates from existingliterature data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Given the low precision of the measurements, these factors are expected to havea minimal contribution to the overall uncertainty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Uncertainty contributions werealso added to account for residual dead time effects and detector nonlinearity. Matrix effects were minimised by the matrix matching of all solutions prior toanalysis.  Total expanded measurement uncertainties for each analysis arecalculated using a full GUM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]approach and are expressed with a coverage factor of <italic>k</italic> = 2 representingthe 95% confidence interval.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec3"><title>3. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><p>The working curvemethod for the ICP-MS analysis of metals in solution, with a low resolution,high throughput instrument measuring at one <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> ratio per element relieson the relative abundance of the isotopes under consideration being the same inboth the sample and the calibration solution. If this is not the case, amultiplicative bias in the observed results for element <italic>X</italic>, <italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub>,will be observed, and is given by<disp-formula id="eq1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>cal</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x02009;</mml:mi><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>sam</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>sam</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x02009;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>cal</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>a</italic>,cal</sub> is the amount of isotope <italic>a</italic> of element <italic>X</italic>in the calibration standard, &#x02211;<sub><italic>i</italic></sub><italic> n</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,cal</sub> is the amount of all isotopes of element <italic>X</italic> inthe calibration standard, <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>a</italic>,sam</sub> is the amount of isotope <italic>a</italic> of element <italic>X</italic>in the sample, and &#x02211;<sub><italic>i</italic></sub><italic> n</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,sam</sub> is the amount of all isotopes of element <italic>X</italic> inthe sample [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. When the relative abundance of the isotope used for quantification in both thesample and the calibration solution is the same, then <italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub> = 1 and no bias is observed. It is interesting tonote that the isotopic composition with respect to the other isotopes not usedfor quantification has no effect on the measurement. (As and Mn are alsomeasured by the &#x0201c;network,&#x0201d; but are monoisotopicand therefore not considered as part of this treatment).</p><p>Rather than assess theisotopic composition of each individual sample, the uncertainty budgetdeveloped for this measurement includes a component of uncertainty to recognisethat the isotopic composition of the sample may fall anywhere within the rangeof natural variations, or the representative isotopic composition, whichever isthe larger range [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. (The actual range of isotopiccomposition in environmental samples may be considerably narrower [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>].)In practice, this assumption assigns <italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub> = 1 but imposes a relative uncertainty on thisvalue equal to the possible range of isotope abundances expected for theisotopes used for quantification. Relatively little detail exists in theliterature on the isotopic composition of metals in ambient air particulates. The vast majority of the work that has been published has been on Pb isotopiccomposition, where the greatest variation is expected. Determination of isotoperatios has been mostly used as a route to determining the origin of the Pbsampled, particularly with regard to specific industrial processes orlong-range pollutant transport [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].  One study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]has examined the Pb isotopic composition in deposition in order to compare howthis changed before and after the closure of a local Pb mine. Others studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]have used the changing Pb isotope ratios in ambient particulate matter todemonstrate the seasonal variation long-range transport of pollutants acrossthe Asian continent. Measured Pb isotope ratios have also been used as a routeto determine the changing origins of Pb emissions in an urban environmentduring and after the phasing out of leaded petrol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Cu and Zn isotopes ratios have been analysed near a large Zn refinery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]as a means of determining the origin of metallic ores, and Sr and Nd isotoperatios have been used in the discrimination of emissions from variousindustrial sources and traffic emissions, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. In all cases, the observed ranges of the isotopic compositions fell well withinthe natural ranges predicted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] and these natural ranges have been used to constructthe uncertainty budget presented in this paper. Moreover, when the isotopiccomposition of samples under consideration in this study has been measuredperiodically, the abundance of the isotope used for quantitation has alwaysbeen well within these ranges as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The major contributions to the overall measurement uncertainty for thedetermination of the mass concentration of metal in ambient air are shown in<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>.</p><p>As can be seen, thecontribution from the possible variation in the isotopic composition of thesample is strongly dependent on the element being determined. This contributionis very significant for Pb, significant for Hg, and Cd, less significant forCu, Zn and Pt, and negligible for Cr, Ni, Fe, and V.  This is highlighted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> which showsthe fraction of the overall measurement uncertainty contributed by uncertaintyin the isotopic composition of the sample being measured [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. As expected from the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, thiscontribution is very significant for Pb, notable for Hg, Cd and possibly Cu,and insignificant for all other elements.</p><p>The summary uncertainty budgetpresented in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref> (and the measurement equation from which this hasbeen developed) is only valid if the abundance of the isotope used forquantification in the calibration standards also falls within this rangeallowed for the samples.  If it does not,then an additional uncertainty contribution, or a correction factor, may needto be applied. This is not something that may be taken for granted since thecalibration standards may often have been prepared from isotopically enrichedpure materials, and must be measured in order to determine whether an increasein the uncertainty estimate for the overall determination was required. Theresults of the determination of the isotopic composition of the calibrationstandards used are shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3(b)</xref> which show that the majorityof isotopes demonstrated good agreement between the measured value and theexpected range of isotopic abundances.<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1"> Table 1</xref> highlights the level of thisagreement for the isotopes used for quantification.</p><p>Where there is agreement withthe predicted range, we may assume that the uncertainty budget for themeasurement already covers the expected range of isotopic compositions for bothsample and calibration standard. Where <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref> shows a lack of agreement, anadditional component of uncertainty equal to the discrepancy in agreement needsto be added to justify the uncertainty statement. Given the large overallmeasurement uncertainties reported for the measurement of metal massconcentration in ambient air, these small additional uncertainty components areunlikely to increase the overall uncertainty of the measurement significantly. (An additional component of uncertainty has been added, rather than adding aterm into the uncertainty budget to correct for bias, since in all cases thestandard error of the mean of the isotopic composition measurements is greaterthan the observed disagreement in all cases, and thus a bias correction term isnot justified.) Perhaps not surprisingly, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref> highlights that a disagreementwas found for the elements with the smallest predicted range of isotopiccompositions, where the accuracy of the isotopic measurement is morecritical.</p><p>A brief inspection of Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3(b)</xref> suggests that the bias between the measured isotopic abundanceand the centre of the expected range of isotopic abundances shows some tendencyto increase as the isotopic abundance decreases. This relationship is plottedin <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>. Since the isotopes used for quantification are generally ones withhigh abundances, little attention is usually paid to the less abundantisotopes, and therefore, there may well be more bias in these measurementsowing to unresolved interferences, unresolved detector nonlinearity, andinstrument instabilities which have a larger proportional effect on themeasurement results than for high abundance species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec4"><title>4. CONCLUSIONS</title><p>A summary of the main sources ofuncertainty encountered during the analysis of the mass concentration of metalsin ambient air as part of the operation of the UK Heavy Metals MonitoringNetwork has been presented. It has been observed that the uncertaintycontribution from possible variations in the isotopic composition of the sampledepends on the element in question, but can be significant (as in the cases ofPb, Cd, and Hg). The working curve method for the ICP-MS analysis of metals insolution, with a low resolution, high throughput instrument measuring at one <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> ratio per element relies on the relative abundance of the isotopes underconsideration being the same in both the sample and the calibration solution. Calculation of the uncertainty in this analysis assumes that the isotopiccomposition variation within the sample and calibration solution is limited toa defined range.</p><p>The results of the isotopicanalysis of these calibration standards have shown that the isotopiccomposition of the calibration standards agrees with the expected range ofisotopic comparisons in the samples for all but four elements. In these cases,additional uncertainty components were required to be added to the uncertaintybudget to account for this bias, although the increase in the overall uncertaintyof the measurement was not significant. It is interesting to note that theisotopic composition with respect to the other isotopes not under considerationnot used for quantification has no effect, in theory, on the measurement.</p><p>The bias between the measuredisotopic abundance and the centre of the expected range of isotopic abundancesshows some tendency to increase as the isotopic abundance decreases. It hasbeen suggested that since the isotopes used for quantification are generallyones with high abundance and little attention is paid to the lower abundanceisotopes, the bias in these measurements may well be due to unresolvedinterferences, unresolved detector nonlinearity, and instrument instabilitywhich have a larger proportional effect on the measurement results than forhigh abundance species.</p><p>In future, it may beexpeditious to determine more rigorously the isotopic composition of samplescollected across the &#x0201c;network&#x0201d; so that the uncertainty contribution from <italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub> for the elements where this is mostsignificant (in particular Pb) may be reduced, thereby reducing the overallmeasurement uncertainty.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>Useful discussions with Dr. Henrik Skov from the National Environmental Research Institute (DMU, Denmark) are gratefully acknowledged. The UK Department for Innovation, University and Skills' funding of the National Measurement System Chemical and Biological Metrology Programme, and the UK Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs' funding of NPL's operation and management of the UK Heavy Metals Monitoring Network, are both gratefully acknowledged.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Ambient air pollution by As, Cd and Ni compounds, position paper. Brussels: working group on As, Cd and Ni compounds</article-title><comment>European Commission DG Environment, Brussels, Belgium, 2000</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><article-title>Council Directive 1999/30/EC of 22 April 1999 relating to limit values for sulphur dioxide, nitrogen dioxide and oxides of nitrogen, particulate matter and lead in ambient air</article-title><source><italic>Official Journal of the European Union</italic></source><year>1999</year><volume>L163</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><article-title>Council Directive 2004/107/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 15 December 2004 relating to arsenic, cadmium, mercury, nickel and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in ambient air</article-title><source><italic>Official Journal of the European Union</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>L023</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RJC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use and abuse of limits of detection in environmental analytical chemistry</article-title><source><italic>The ScientificWorldJOURNAL</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>801</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yardley</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhunthan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Twenty-five years of nationwide ambient metals measurement in the United Kingdom: concentration levels and trends</article-title><source><italic>Environmental Monitoring and Assessment</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>142</volume><issue>1&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17879136</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="other"><collab>EN 12341:1999 Air quality</collab><article-title>Determination of the PM10 fraction of suspended particulate matter. Reference method and field test procedure to demonstrate reference equivalence of measurement methods</article-title><comment>CEN, Brussels, Belgium, 1999</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the optimum sampling time for the measurement of pollutants in ambient air</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Automated Methods and Management in Chemistry</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>2008</volume><fpage>6 pages</fpage><comment>Article ID 814715.</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="other"><collab>EN 14902:2005</collab><article-title>Ambient air quality-standard method for the measurement of Pb,Cd, As and Ni in the PM10 fraction of suspended particulate  matter</article-title><comment>CEN, Brussels, Belgium, 2005</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yardley</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Milton</surname><given-names>MJT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sample matrix and critical interference effects on the recovery and accuracy of concentration measurements of arsenic in ambient particulate samples using ICP-MS</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Analytical Atomic Spectrometry</italic></source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>705</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RJC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study of the critical uncertainty contributions in the analysis of PCBs in ambient air</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Automated Methods and Management in Chemistry</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>2008</volume><fpage>14 pages</fpage><comment>Article ID 179498.</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelms</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu&#x000e9;tel</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Prohaska</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>PDP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of detector dead time calculation models for ICP-MS</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Analytical Atomic Spectrometry</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>338</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Onakunle</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>XLGENLINE version 1.0, document CMSC/M/06/657</article-title><comment>NPL, Teddington, UK, 2007</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of reference materials by isotope dilution mass spectrometry</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Analytical Atomic Spectrometry</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>22</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>492</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>JC-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>W-F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applications of lead isotope ratio measurements</article-title><source><italic>Trends in Analytical Chemistry</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>460</fpage><lpage>480</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="other"><collab>ISO Guide 98:1995</collab><article-title>Guide to the expression of uncertainty in measurement (GUM)</article-title><comment>ISO, Geneva, Switzerland, 1995</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milton</surname><given-names>MJT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wielgosz</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of the international system of units (SI) in isotope ratio mass spectrometry</article-title><source><italic>Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>2201</fpage><lpage>2204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12442296</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;hlke</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>de Laeter</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bi&#x000e8;vre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isotopic compositions of the elements, 2001</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Physical and Chemical Reference Data</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coplen</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;hlke</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bi&#x000e8;vre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isotope-abundance variations of selected elements (IUPAC technical report)</article-title><source><italic>Pure and Applied Chemistry</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>74</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1987</fpage><lpage>2017</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munksgaard</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lead isotope ratios determined by ICP-MS: monitoring of mining-derived metal particulates in atmospheric fallout, Northern Territory, Australia</article-title><source><italic>Science of the Total Environment</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>217</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>125</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>S-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeng</surname><given-names>W-L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lead isotope ratios in ambient aerosols from Taipei, Taiwan: identifying long-range transport of airborne Pb from the Yangtze Delta</article-title><source><italic>Atmospheric Environment</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>40</volume><issue>28</issue><fpage>5393</fpage><lpage>5404</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CSL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X-D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>A-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy metals and Pb isotopic composition of aerosols in urban and suburban areas of Hong Kong and Guangzhou, South China&#x02014;evidence of the long-range transport of air contaminants</article-title><source><italic>Atmospheric Environment</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>41</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>447</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of lead isotope ratios and elemental concentrations in PM10 fraction of airborne particulate matter in Shanghai after the phase-out of leaded gasoline</article-title><source><italic>Atmospheric Environment</italic></source><year>2004</year><volume>38</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1191</fpage><lpage>1200</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattielli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimetz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Zn-Cu isotopic study and speciation of airborne metal particles within a 5-km zone of a lead/zinc smelter</article-title><source><italic>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>70</volume><issue>18</issue><supplement>supplement 1</supplement><fpage>p. A401</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geagea</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Stille</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier-Lafaye</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tracing of industrial aerosol sources in an urban environment using Pb, Sr, and Nd isotopes</article-title><source><italic>Environmental Science and Technology</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>42</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18323089</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Butterfield</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhunthan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yardley</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NPL Report AS20: Report to the Department of Environment, Food and Rural Affairs by the National Physical Laboratory: Annual Report for 2007 on the UK Heavy Metals Monitoring Network</article-title><comment>NPL, Teddington, UK, 2008</comment></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Relative contributions to thestandard uncertainty of the determination of metal mass concentration inambient air, as part of the UK Heavy Metals Monitoring Network. This exampleshows a measurement with an overall expanded uncertainty at the 95% confidenceinterval of approximately 20%. The changing uncertainty contribution from thevariation in the sample isotopic composition for the different metals measuredby the &#x0201c;network&#x0201d; is indicated by the additional lines and labelling on thebottom bar.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAMMC2008-504092.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The fraction of the overallmeasurement uncertainty for each metal contributed by the uncertainty in <italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAMMC2008-504092.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(a) V, Cr, Fe, Ni, Cu, and Zn: comparison ofthe measured relative isotopic abundance of the calibration standards (blackcircles, with the grey bars representing the standard error of the mean)against the expected range in natural, or representative, isotopic compositions(whichever is the larger range) (black bars). The relative atomic mass number isdisplayed for each isotope, with the boxed number being the isotope used forthe quantification of the samples. Values are normalised to the centre of thenatural (or representative) composition range for each isotope. The relativeabundance is displayed for each element in the separate plot beneath the mainchart. (b) Cd, Pt, Hg, and Pb: comparisonof the measured relative isotopic abundance of the calibration standards (blackcircles, with the grey bars representing the standard error of the mean)against the expected range in natural, or representative, isotopic compositions(whichever is the larger range) (black bars). The relative atomic mass numberis displayed for each isotope, with the boxed number being the isotope used forthe quantification of the samples. Values are normalised to the centre of thenatural (or representative) composition range for each isotope. The relativeabundance is displayed for each element in the separate plot beneath the mainchart.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAMMC2008-504092.003"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The relationship between the relative isotopic abundance of all theisotopes considered and the relative difference between the measured isotopicabundance and the centre of the expected range of isotopic abundance.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAMMC2008-504092.004"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Agreement between the measured abundances for the isotopes used for quantifications and the expected abundance ranges.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isotope used for quantification</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agreement with predicted range</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>50</sup>V</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No +0.01 %</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>52</sup>Cr</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No, &#x02212;0.1%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>56</sup>Fe</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No, +0.4 %</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>60</sup>Ni</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No, +0.3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>63</sup>Cu</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>66</sup>Zn</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>111</sup>Cd</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>194</sup>Pt</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>200</sup>Hg</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>208</sup>Pb</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-wrap></article>