<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Obstet Gynecol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IDOG</journal-id><journal-title>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1064-7449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-0997</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19223967</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2637368</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2008/727505</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antibiotic Resistance Patterns in Invasive Group B Streptococcal Isolates</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castor</surname><given-names>Mei L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1, 2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>Cynthia G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Como-Sabetti</surname><given-names>Kathryn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Facklam</surname><given-names>Richard R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrieri</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bartkus</surname><given-names>Joanne M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Juni</surname><given-names>Billie A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cieslak</surname><given-names>Paul R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>Monica M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I8"><sup>8</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dumas</surname><given-names>Nellie B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I9"><sup>9</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schrag</surname><given-names>Stephanie J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lynfield</surname><given-names>Ruth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Prevention and Control Division, Minnesota Department of Health, 625 Robert Street North, P.O. Box 64975, Saint Paul, MN 55164, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Epidemic Intelligence Service, Epidemiology Program Office, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 1600 Clifton Road NE, Atlanta, GA 30333, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Respiratory Diseases Branch, Division of Bacterial and Mycotic Diseases, National Center for Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 1600 Clifton Road NE, Atlanta, GA 30333, USA</aff><aff id="I4"><sup>4</sup>Streptococcus Laboratory, Respiratory Diseases Branch, Division of Bacterial and Mycotic Diseases, National Center for Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 1600 Clifton Road NE, Atlanta, GA 30333, USA</aff><aff id="I5"><sup>5</sup>Pediatrics and Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, Clinical Microbiology Laboratory, University of Minnesota Medical School, 420 Delaware Street SE Minneapolis, MN  55455, USA</aff><aff id="I6"><sup>6</sup>Public Health Laboratory Division, Minnesota Department of Health, 601 Robert Street North, P.O. Box 64899, Saint Paul, MN  55164, USA</aff><aff id="I7"><sup>7</sup>Public Health Division, Oregon Department of Human Services, 800 NE Oregon Street, Portland, OR 97232, USA</aff><aff id="I8"><sup>8</sup>Atlanta Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Emory University School of Medicine, 1670 Clairmont Rd, Station 151 Decatur, GA  30033, USA</aff><aff id="I9"><sup>9</sup>Wadsworth Center, New York State Department of Health, 120 New Scotland Avenue, Albany, NY 12208, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Ruth Lynfield: <email>ruth.lynfield@state.mn.us</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Recommended by Reginald Sauve</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>2008</volume><elocation-id>727505</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Mei L. Castor et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Antibiotics are used for both group B streptococcal (GBS) prevention and treatment. Active population-based surveillance for invasive GBS disease was conducted in four states during 1996&#x02013;2003. Of 3813 case-isolates, 91.0% (3471) were serotyped, 77.1% (2937) had susceptibility testing, and 46.6% (3471) had both. All were sensitive to penicillin, ampicillin, cefazolin, cefotaxime, and vancomycin.  Clindamycin and erythromycin resistance was 12.7% and 25.6%, respectively, and associated with serotype V (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001). Clindamycin resistance increased from 10.5% to 15.0% (<italic>X</italic><sup>2</sup> for trend 12.70; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001); inducible clindamycin resistance was associated with the <italic>erm</italic> genotype. Erythromycin resistance increased from 15.8% to 32.8% (<italic>X</italic><sup>2</sup> for trend 55.46; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001).  While GBS remains susceptible to beta-lactams, resistance to alternative agents such as erythromycin and clindamycin is an increasing concern.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="section" id="sec1"><title>1. INTRODUCTION</title><p>Early-onset group B  <italic>Streptococcal</italic> (GBS)infection, occurring in the first 7 days of life, is a leading cause ofinvasive bacterial infection among newborns and generally results from verticaltransmission of GBS from colonized mothers to their infants. Neonatal infectionis commonly characterized by bacteremia, pneumonia, and meningitis; mortalityfrom early-onset disease is estimated at 5%. GBS disease among pregnant womenmanifests as urinary tract infections, bacteremia, chorioamnionitis, endometritis,or septic abortions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Among non-pregnant adults, GBS disease typically occursamong older or immunocompromised persons.</p><p>In the 1990s, the incidence ofearly-onset neonatal GBS disease declined dramatically after widespreadimplementation of intrapartum antibiotic prophylaxis (IAP). Revisions to IAPguidelines in 2002 included universal GBS screening of pregnant women withvaginal and rectal cultures at 35&#x02013;37 weeks'gestation, with IAP given to those with positive cultures. Susceptibility testingfor erythromycin and clindamycin of GBS isolates is recommended for colonizedwomen who are thought to be at high risk for anaphylaxis to penicillin orampicillin. Cefazolin is recommended for those who cannot take penicillin butare at low risk for anaphylaxis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>Publications fromthe United States and Canada report clindamycin resistance (3%&#x02013;21%) anderythromycin resistance (5%&#x02013;29%) in GBSisolates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Alteration ofthe erythromycin-binding site on the 50S ribosomal RNA subunit, conferred by the <italic>erm</italic> gene, and active efflux of theerythromycin, conferred by the <italic>mef</italic> gene, are the most common macrolide resistance mechanisms in beta-hemolyticstreptococci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The <italic>erm</italic> geneconfers resistance to macrolides, lincosamides, and streptogramin B-type antibiotics(MLS<sub>B</sub>) and may be expressed constitutively or it may be inducible. The <italic>mef</italic> gene confers resistance only tomacrolide antibiotics, the M phenotype. The inducible MLS<sub>B</sub> phenotypemay be detected in the laboratory by a disk approximation method (D-test),which involves placement of an erythromycin and a clindamycin disk in closeproximity on the surface of an agar plate. Clinical and Laboratory StandardsInstitute (CLSI) guidelines for antimicrobial susceptibility testing now include a method forperforming the D-test on beta-hemolytic streptococci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>Serotypedistribution in invasive GBS disease is of interest in determining potentialvaccine composition. Serotype III has a high association with late-onsetneonatal disease, specifically meningitis. Serotype V has emerged as a morefrequent serotype in recent years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Other common serotypes include Ia andII.</p><p>We analyzed GBS surveillance data from fourdistinct US sites to understand serotype and antimicrobial susceptibility patterns ininvasive isolates from perinatal (pregnant and neonatal cases) and non-pregnantadult populations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec2"><title>2. METHODS</title><p>Invasive GBSisolate data regarding antimicrobial susceptibility, serotype, andepidemiologic data were collected from selected counties in four states(Georgia, Minnesota, New York, and Oregon); all participated in the Centers forDisease Control and Prevention's (CDC) Active Bacterial Core surveillance (ABCs)system of the Emerging Infections Program network for 1996&#x02013;2003. Georgia's initial surveillance area of eightcounties in the Atlanta area expanded in 1997 to 20 counties. New York'sinitial surveillance area of seven counties in 1997 expanded to 15 counties in2000 (seven-county Rochester area and eight-county Albany area). Oregon's three-county and Minnesota's statewidesurveillance areas remained unchanged throughout the study period. Totalsurveillance populations ranged from 8.7 million in 1996 to 13.2 million in2003. By state, 2003 surveillance populations were 4.5 million in Georgia, 5million in Minnesota, 2.1 million in New York, and 1.5 million in Oregon.</p><p>A case of invasiveGBS was defined by bacterial isolation from a normally sterile site in asurveillance area resident. GBS isolation from amniotic fluid or placentas wasincluded when fetal demise occurred. Early-onset neonatal cases were classifiedby a first positive culture on days 0&#x02013;6 of life and late-onsetat 7&#x02013;89 days of life. Maternal cases were those identified during the antepartum or postpartumperiods (30 days after a delivery or miscarriage). The case-finding methodologyused for the ABCs system has been previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Laboratory auditsare performed every 6 months to capture any missed cases. Antimicrobialsusceptibility testing was performed at the Minnesota Department of Health(MDH) laboratory or CDC laboratories. Serotyping of Minnesota isolates wasperformed at the University of Minnesota and CDC, and isolates from other geographic siteswere tested at CDC. Lancefield immunoprecipitation techniques were used forserotyping. Antimicrobial susceptibility testing was performed using brothmicrodilution in microtiter plates containing cation-adjusted Mueller Hintonbroth with 3% lysed horse blood (PML Microbiologicals, Wilsonville, Ore)with CLSI susceptibility definitions used when available.</p><p>The constitutive (c) MLS<sub>B</sub> phenotype was inferred from broth microdilution MIC data. Isolates found to be erythromycin-resistant and clindamycin-susceptible wereevaluated for inducible (i) clindamycin resistance using the double disk diffusion(D-test) method with clindamycin (2 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g) and erythromycin (15 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g) disks (BectonDickinson Diagnostic Systems, Sparks, Md) placed 15 mm apart. Strains thatremained clindamycin-susceptible (those that did not have flattening of thesusceptibility zone adjacent to the erythromycin disk) were determined to be ofthe M phenotype.</p><p>PCR was used todetect the presence of the most common macrolide resistance determinants in allisolates with an M or iMLS<sub>B</sub> phenotype. Testing was also done on asmall subset of isolates with a cMLS<sub>B</sub> resistance phenotype. PCR fordetection of <italic>erm</italic>A, <italic>erm</italic>B, and <italic>erm</italic>C was performed as described by Sutcliffe et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Detectionof <italic>erm</italic>TR and <italic>mef</italic> (the primers amplify both <italic>mef </italic>Aand <italic>mef </italic>E) was performed using primersdesigned at MDH. The PCR reactions for <italic>erm</italic>TRand <italic>mef </italic>A/E contained 10 mM Tris HCl,50 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>M forward and reverse primers, and 2 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>lof template DNA in a total volume of 50 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>L. Primers used for the amplificationof <italic>erm</italic>TR, a subclass of <italic>erm</italic>A [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], were TR-322U,5&#x02032;-GGGTCAGGAAAAGGACAT-3&#x02032;, and TR619L, 5&#x02032;-CCTAAAGCTCGTTGGGTATT-3&#x02032;. Primers usedfor the amplification of <italic>mef </italic>A/E weremef-3301U, 5&#x02032;-AGGGCAAGCAGTATCATTAATCA-3&#x02032;, and mef-3673L, 5&#x02032;-CTGCAAAGACTGACTATAGCCT-3&#x02032;. Optimumannealing temperatures for <italic>erm</italic>TR and <italic>mef </italic>PCR were 56&#x000b0;C and 55&#x000b0;C, respectively. PCR products were resolved on a 2% agarose gel. The expected fragment size for <italic>erm</italic>TR was 317 bp and for <italic>mef</italic> was 394 bp.</p><p>SAS (version 9.1)was used for frequency and univariate analysis. Trend analyses were performedwith Epi Info (CDC, Atlanta, Ga) statistical software (version6.04c). Chi-square calculations were used to compare continuous variables, withYates continuity-corrected chi-square used to compare categorical variables. The Mantel-Haenszel chi-square test for trend was used to examine trends acrossthe study period; the Mantel-Haenszel extended test adjusted for possibleconfounders. An alpha &#x02264;0.05-significance level was used.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec3"><title>3. RESULTS</title><p>Of the 5 373patients, 71% had isolates submitted to a public health laboratory and the antimicrobialsusceptibility testing was performed on 77.1% (2 937). The plurality of isolates were from Minnesota (46.8% or 1 375),followed by Georgia (26.1% or 768), New York (16.9% or 496), and Oregon (10.2% or 300). The perinatal category comprised 24.4% (1 311)of the total sample with 12.5% (671) early-onset, 7.9% (424) late-onset, and4.0% (216) maternal patients. The non-pregnant adult category accounted for73.5% (3 951) of the total.</p><p>All 2 937isolates were susceptible to penicillin, ampicillin, cefotaxime, andvancomycin. Although no CLSIbreakpoints existed for the first-generation cephalosporins (cephalothin andcefazolin), all the isolates tested had minimum inhibitory concentrations(MICs) &#x02264; 0.5 mcg/mL and were, therefore, considered susceptible. Similarly, no breakpoints existed for cefuroxime and cefoxitin. All 1 201Minnesota isolates tested for cefuroxime susceptibility had MICs &#x02264; 0.12 mcg/mLand were, therefore, considered susceptible. Of 2 937isolates tested for cefoxitin susceptibility, 36.7% (1 078) had MICs &#x02264; 2 mcg/mL; 62.5%(1 835) had MICs = 4 mcg/mL; 0.7% (22) hadMICs = 8 mcg/mL; and 0.1% (4) had MICs &#x02265; 16 mcg/mL.</p><p>Clindamycinresistance was identified in 12.7% (374), and erythromycin resistance wasidentified in 25.6% (752) of isolates tested. During the study period, asignificant increase was observed in the proportion of isolates resistant toeach of these antibiotic(for clindamycin 10.5% in 1996 versus 15.0% in 2003, <italic>X</italic><sup>2</sup> for trend = 12.70, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001, for erythromycin15.8% in 1996 versus 32.8% in 2003, <italic>X</italic><sup>2</sup> for trend = 55.46, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). Concurrent resistance to both clindamycin anderythromycin was identified in 12.6% (370) of isolates tested.</p><p>Significantdifferences were identified between Minnesota and New York  isolates in clindamycin resistance (13.2% versus 9.3%, <italic>P</italic> = .03) anderythromycin resistance (24.5% and 31.4%, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .01). Georgia isolates were more likely to beresistant to clindamycin than New York isolates (15.1% and 9.3%, <italic>P</italic> = .02), but Georgia isolates were less likely to be resistant to erythromycin than to New York isolates (26.3% and 31.4%, <italic>P</italic> = .04) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><p>The proportion ofisolates resistant to clindamycin and erythromycin did not differ significantlybetween the perinatal and non-pregnant adult patient groups (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). Within the perinatal group, the overall clindamycin resistance was 13.1%, withno significant changes between the early-onset (14.9%), late-onset (10.3%), andmaternal populations (13.7%). Likewise, no significant differences inerythromycin resistance levels were identified between the different perinatalgroups (21.9% overall; 21.2% for early-onset, 22.1% for late-onset, and 23.9%maternal).</p><p>Serotyping was performed on 64.6% (3 471) of isolates. The largest proportion wasfrom Georgia (34.7%), followed by Minnesota (28.5%), New York (23.9%), and Oregon (12.9%).<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1"> Table 1</xref> illustrates the serotypes identified during the study period,with predominant serotype groups being V, Ia, and III. The proportion ofisolates with serotype III was observed to have a significant downward trend (<italic>X</italic><sup>2</sup> trend = 38.8; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001) during the study period from 25% in 1996 to 17%in 2003; no such trend was observed with the other predominant serotypes.</p><p>The most common serotype in the perinatalpopulation was serotype III (37.0%; 351/948). This was significantly differentthan for non-pregnant adults in which serotype V was most common (31.5%; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001).</p><p>Both susceptibility and serotyping testing wereperformed on 2 551 isolates. The largest proportion of these isolates were from Minnesota (38.9%), followed by Georgia (30.1%), New York (19.4%), and Oregon (11.8%). Clindamycin resistance was 3.9 times (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001) more likely to occur inserotype V isolates (25.8%) than in other serotypes (8.2%). In addition,erythromycin resistance was 2.9 times (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001) more likely to occurin serotype V isolates (42.2%) than in other serotypes (20.2%). Subanalysiswithin the different disease categories indicated a significant associationamong clindamycin or erythromycin resistance and early-onset (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001),late-onset (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001), and non-pregnant adult populations (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .001). No such association was observed among the maternal population.</p><p>Threehundred fifty-five erythromycin-resistant (47%) isolates were furthercharacterized. Seventy-eight isolates (22%) had an M phenotype and all of theseisolates contained <italic>mef</italic> only. Fifty-two percent (184/355) wereconstitutively resistant to clindamycin (cMLS). Seventeen were further tested. Ten were positive for <italic>erm</italic>B andseven contained <italic>erm</italic>TR; one isolatehad both <italic>mef</italic> and <italic>erm</italic>TR and one isolate had both <italic>mef</italic> and <italic>erm</italic>B. Twenty-five percent of isolates had inducibleclindamycin resistance (iMLS). All of the iMLS isolates were tested forresistance genes; 83 (92%) contained <italic>erm</italic>TR,1 isolate contained <italic>erm</italic>B, and 6 isolateswere negative for <italic>erm</italic>TR and <italic>erm</italic>B.</p><p>Univariate analysis was conducted comparingresistance genes to serotypes. Serotype V was associated with a lowerproportion of <italic>mef</italic> positive isolatescompared to all other serotypes (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .01). In contrast, serotypes Ia,Ia/c, and III were associated with a higher proportion of <italic>mef</italic>-positive isolates compared to all other serotypes (all <italic>P</italic> values &#x0003c;.01). Serotype V had a higher proportion of isolates with <italic>erm</italic>TR, 73% of 37 testedcompared with 29% among all other serotypes (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .01).</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec4"><title>4. CONCLUSIONS</title><p>This study demonstrated the prevalence ofresistance to antibiotics commonly used for prophylaxis or treatment of GBSinfections among a large, multisite, collection of isolates. We found that all invasive GBS isolates tested were susceptible topenicillin and ampicillin, the first-line agents recommended for IAP and tocefazolin and vancomycin, second-line agents recommended for use among IAPcandidates who report penicillin allergies. In contrast, GBS resistanceto clindamycin (12.7%) and erythromycin (25.6%) was common. Subanalysis of early-onsetpatient isolates indicated clindamycin resistance at 14.9% and erythromycinresistance at 21.2%. These findings are consistent with previous reports in theliterature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] and support the2002 guidelines requiring susceptibility testing of isolates from IAPcandidates with penicillin allergy. Of note, because of reports ofsubtherapeutic concentrations in amniotic fluid and fetal serum, certain healthcare specialists donot recommend using erythromycin for IAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Clinicians should be aware ofthe potential for MLS resistance when determining empiric regimens that targetGBS disease.</p><p>We found an overallconcordance between the MLS phenotype and resistance genotype. D-testingrevealed inducible clindamycin resistance in <italic>erm</italic>-containing GBS isolates and also detected resistance inisolates with determinants not identifiable by existing PCR methods. Our findings support the 2002 CDC guidelineto test both erythromycin and clindamycin susceptibilities if one of theseagents is being considered. Further D-testing should be done if erythromycinresistance and clindamycin susceptibility are found. Rarely, clindamycinresistance without concurrent erythromycin resistance can be observed; this hasbeen associated with the <italic>lin</italic>B gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Minimal differences were identified inclindamycin and erythromycin resistance levels across the four geographic areasas well as between the perinatal and non-pregnant adult groups. This indicatesthat GBS-resistance patterns might reflect more of a national than a regionalphenomenon.</p><p>We noted high cefoxitin MICs to GBS among ourGBS isolates. This is not surprising because cefoxitin is a cefomycin, a classof antibiotics which typically provides optimal coverage for anaerobes but lacks adequate activityagainst gram-positive bacteria. Cefoxitin is likely to provide suboptimal GBScoverage for chorioamnionitis and postpartum endometritis.</p><p>The predominant GBS serotypes were Ia, III,and V, which together comprised approximately 70% of all isolates serotyped. The predominance of these serotypes among the perinatal population isconsistent with reports in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] as is the association betweenserotype V and erythromycin or clindamycin resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. We found an association of serotype V with the <italic>erm</italic> genotype which confers resistance toboth erythromycin and clindamycin.</p><p>This study has severallimitations, including variability in surveillance periods for isolatescollected, a varying proportion of cases with isolate collection andsusceptibility and serotyping results, and differences in surveillancepopulations. However, the ABCs surveillance system is an active, multiregional, andpopulation-based system,and the methods to determine susceptibilities and serotyping werestandardized. Continued surveillance of invasive GBS disease includingsusceptibility and serotype determinations will impact plans for preventionincluding IAP agents and vaccine design.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>The authors acknowledge Jean Rainbow, Craig A. Morin, Richard N. Danila, Kirk E. Smith, and John Besser from theMinnesota Department of Health. They also thank Henrietta Shellae Lewis, Anne Schuchat,Carolyn Wright, Tami Hilgar Skoff, Delois Jackson, and John Elliott from the Centersfor Disease Control and Prevention. Moreover, the authors acknowledge the efforts of AureaE. Flores from the University of Minnesota Medical School, Karen R. Stefonek from the OregonDepartment of Human Services. Furthermore, they also admit the efforts of PatriciaMartell-Cleary and Wendy Baughman from the Georgia Emerging Infections Program. Finally, the authors thank Kathryn E. Arnold from the Georgia Division of PublicHealth. <italic>Financial support for this studywas from CDC's Emerging Infections Program.</italic> The findings and conclusions inthis report are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the viewsof the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schrag</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zywicki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Group B streptococcal disease in the era of intrapartum antibiotic prophylaxis</article-title><source><italic>The New England Journal of Medicine</italic></source><year>2000</year><volume>342</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10620644</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schrag</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorwitz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fultz-Butts</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuchat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention of perinatal group B streptococcal disease. Revised guidelines from CDC</article-title><source><italic>MMWR Recommendations and Reports</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><issue>RR-11</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial susceptibilities of group B streptococci isolated between 1992 and 1996 from patients with bacteremia or meningitis</article-title><source><italic>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>42</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1517</fpage><lpage>1519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9624508</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F-YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Azimi</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisman</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic susceptibility profiles for group B streptococci isolated from neonates, 1995&#x02013;1998</article-title><source><italic>Clinical Infectious Diseases</italic></source><year>2000</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10913400</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearlman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Faix</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frequent resistance of clinical group B streptococci isolates to clindamycin and erythromycin</article-title><source><italic>Obstetrics &#x00026; Gynecology</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>92</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9699763</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arisoy</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Altini&#x0015f;ik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>T&#x000fc;nger</surname><given-names>&#x000d6;</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurutepe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ispahi</surname><given-names>&#x000c7;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maternal carriage and antimicrobial resistance profile of group B <italic>Streptococcus</italic></article-title><source><italic>Infection</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14562949</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Foxman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tallman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearlman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlates of antibiotic-resistant group B <italic>Streptococcus</italic> isolated from pregnant women</article-title><source><italic>Obstetrics &#x00026; Gynecology</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>101</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12517649</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biedenbach</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial susceptibility profile among <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-haemolytic <italic>Streptococcus</italic> spp. collected in the SENTRY Antimicrobial Surveillance Program&#x02014;North America, 2001</article-title><source><italic>Diagnostic Microbiology and Infectious Disease</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12944022</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leclercq</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of resistance to macrolides and lincosamides: nature of the resistance elements and their clinical implications</article-title><source><italic>Clinical Infectious Diseases</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11797175</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="gov"><collab>NCCLS</collab><article-title>Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing; fifteenth informational supplement</article-title><source><italic>CLSI/NCCLS Document</italic></source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Wayne, Pa, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name><comment>M100-S15.</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Modansky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Invasive group B streptococcal disease: the emergence of serotype V</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Infectious Diseases</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>173</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8568297</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuchat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Active bacterial core surveillance of the emerging infections program network</article-title><source><italic>Emerging Infectious Diseases</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11266299</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grebe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tait-Kamradt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wondrack</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of erythromycin-resistant determinants by PCR</article-title><source><italic>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>40</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2562</fpage><lpage>2566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8913465</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Courvalin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seppala</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nomenclature for macrolide and macrolide-lincosamide-streptogramin B resistance determinants</article-title><source><italic>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</italic></source><year>1999</year><volume>43</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2823</fpage><lpage>2830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10582867</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearlman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention of early-onset group B streptococcal disease in newborns</article-title><source><italic>Obstetrics &#x00026; Gynecology</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>102</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12907122</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Clindamycin and erythromycin resistance among invasive Group B streptococci isolates by year (<italic>n</italic> =  2 937 isolates).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IDOG2008-727505.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Clindamycin and erythromycin resistance among invasive Group B streptococci isolates by state (<italic>n</italic> =  2 937 isolates).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IDOG2008-727505.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Resistance invasive Group B streptococci isolates among pregnant women and newborns (perinatal) and non-pregnant adults (<italic>n</italic> =  2 887 isolates).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IDOG2008-727505.003"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of serotypes and resistance to erythromycin and clindamycin among invasive group B streptococcus isolates.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Serotyped isolates with susceptibility results</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Serotype</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serotyped isolates </th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythromycin-resistant </th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clindamycin-resistant  </th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no. (%)*</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no. (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no. (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>n</italic> = 3471)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>n</italic> = 2551)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>n</italic> = 669)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>n</italic> = 301)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ia, Ia/c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">835 (24.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">573</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ib, Ib/c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">296 (8.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">231</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II, II/c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">357 (10.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III, III/c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">680 (19.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">496</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (12)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V, V/c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">951 (27.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">695</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">293 (44)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166 (55)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT, NTc</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247 (7.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other**</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (3.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*of isolates serotyped.</p><p>						**IV, IV/c, VI, VI/c, and VIII.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-wrap></article>