<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Emerg Surg</journal-id><journal-title>World Journal of Emergency Surgery : WJES</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1749-7922</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19178687</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639546</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1749-7922-4-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1749-7922-4-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Emergency surgery, acute care surgery and the boulevard of broken dreams</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Catena</surname><given-names>Fausto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>fcatena@aosp.bo.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Ernest E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ernest.moore@dhha.org</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>General, Emergency and Transplant Surgery DPT, St Orsola-Malpighi University Hospital Bologna, Bolgna, Italy</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Surgery, Denver Health Medical Center, University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, Denver, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wjes.org/content/4/1/4"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Catena and Moore; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Catena and Moore; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Catena               Fausto                              fcatena@aosp.bo.it            </dc:author><dc:title>            Emergency surgery, acute care surgery and the boulevard of broken dreams         </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>World Journal of Emergency Surgery 4(1): 4-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1749-7922(2009)4:1&#x0003c;4&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1749-7922</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>The scenario sounds familiar. Last night I returned home very late after a full day of emergency surgeries. While I was having my usual cold dinner in front of the television with my entire family asleep, I received disturbing news; a famous Italian actor had undergone emergency surgery in Honduras. the actor had been participating in a "reality show" and experienced severe back pain. For this reason, he was treated for one week with a NSAID. Suddenly, he developed acute abdominal pain and was taken to the nearest hospital. The diagnosis was acute appendicitis and he underwent immediate laparotomy via a Mc Burney incision. Unfortunately, the surgeons were mistaken. The problem was a large perforated duodenal ulcer and the actor then underwent a midline incisioThe patient was subsequently transferred to a Miami acute care hospital.</p><p>The story is always the same; we can call it emergency surgery, acute care surgery, or "Samantha," but the key point is that we do not have a widespread set of minimum standards for emergency surgery.</p><p>Such standards are just as important as those of ATLS.</p><p>We need to develop guidelines regarding organizational models to address diseases requiring urgent surgical intervention.</p><p>This is an integral component in the mission of the World Journal of Emergency Surgery and of the World Society of Emergency Surgery.</p><p>We must be uniformly prepared all around the world, similar to the uniform emergency protocols for airplanes and airports.</p><p>If we fail to meet this objective, we will continue to witness preventable complications and deaths affecting both the famous and the non-famous alike.</p><p>This is a dream, but it needn't be a broken one.</p><p>In 2010 we will have the 1<sup>st </sup>World Congress of WSES. If we can successfully develop solid guidelines for surgeons from all around the world we will have accomplished a small yet important "humanitarian mission."</p><p>These guidelines would be freely available on the WJES web site and surgeons all around the world could reference them.</p><p>You can call it emergency surgery or acute care surgery, but not the "Boulevard of Broken Dreams".</p></body></article>