<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18980952</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639018</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ern257</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Leaf cold acclimation and freezing injury in C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> grasses of the Mongolian Plateau</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Mei-Zhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>Colin P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>State Key Laboratory of Vegetation and Environmental Change, Institute of Botany, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100093, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Animal and Plant Sciences, University of Sheffield, Sheffield S10 2TN, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>c.p.osborne@sheffield.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><!--Fake ppub date generated  by PMC from publisher pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>59</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>4161</fpage><lpage>4170</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2008 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><p>This paper is available online free of all access charges (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html">http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html</ext-link> for further details)</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The scarcity of C<sub>4</sub> plants in cool climates is usually attributed to their lower photosynthetic efficiency than C<sub>3</sub> species at low temperatures. However, a lower freezing resistance may also decrease the competitive advantage of C<sub>4</sub> plants by reducing canopy duration, especially in continental steppe grasslands, where a short, hot growing season is bracketed by frost events. This paper reports an experimental test of the hypothesis that cold acclimation is negligible in C<sub>4</sub> grasses, leading to greater frost damage than in C<sub>3</sub> species. The experiments exposed six C<sub>3</sub> and three C<sub>4</sub> Mongolian steppe grasses to 20&#x02009;d chilling or control pre-treatments, followed by a high-light freezing event. Leaf resistance to freezing injury was independent of photosynthetic type. Three C<sub>3</sub> species showed constitutive freezing resistance characterized by &#x0003c;20% leaf mortality, associated with high photosynthetic carbon fixation and electron transport rates and low leaf osmotic potential. One freezing-sensitive C<sub>4</sub> species showed the expected pattern of chilling-induced damage to photosynthesis and &#x0003e;95% leaf mortality after the freezing event. However, three C<sub>3</sub> and two C<sub>4</sub> species displayed a cold acclimation response, showing significant decreases in osmotic potential and photosynthesis after exposure to chilling, and a 30&#x02013;72% reduction of leaf freezing injury. This result suggested that down-regulation of osmotic potential may be involved in the cold acclimation process, and demonstrated that there is no inherent barrier to the development of cold acclimation in C<sub>4</sub> species from this ecosystem. Cold acclimation via osmoregulation represents a previously undescribed mechanism to explain the persistence of C<sub>4</sub> plants in cool climates.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>C<sub>3</sub> photosynthesis</kwd><kwd>C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis</kwd><kwd>chilling</kwd><kwd>cold acclimation</kwd><kwd>electron transport rate</kwd><kwd>freezing injury</kwd><kwd>leaf mortality</kwd><kwd>Mongolian Plateau</kwd><kwd>osmotic potential</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>C<sub>4</sub> grasses dominate the tropical and subtropical savannas, but the diversity and abundance of these species decline with temperature at higher latitudes and elevations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Sage <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). This geographic distribution pattern is matched by temporal patterns within temperate grassland communities, where C<sub>3</sub> plants have superior growth during cool springs, whereas C<sub>4</sub> grasses dominate during mid-summer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kemp and Williams, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Monson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1983</xref>). Mechanistic explanations of these patterns focus on the efficiency and chilling sensitivity of photosynthesis. Photosynthetic efficiency is greater in the C<sub>4</sub> than in the C<sub>3</sub> type at temperatures &#x0003e;20&#x02013;25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, where photorespiration accounts for a significant fraction of assimilated carbon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Ehleringer and Bj&#x000f6;rkman, 1977</xref>). However, when photorespiration is limited by lower temperatures, the energetic requirements of the C<sub>4</sub> cycle make it less efficient than the C<sub>3</sub> type. Photosynthesis and growth of C<sub>4</sub> species may also be directly impaired by low temperatures in the chilling range (&#x0003c;15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C), especially under high light fluxes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Long, 1983</xref>), when carbon assimilation is constrained by cold-labile enzymes such as pyruvate phosphate dikinase (PPDK; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Sugiyama <italic>et al.</italic>, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Potvin <italic>et al.</italic>, 1986</xref>), and the low capacity of Rubisco (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Pittermann and Sage, 2000</xref>). This diminishes the photochemical sink for absorbed energy, increasing &#x02018;excitation pressure&#x02019; on photosystem II (PSII; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Huner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), and making C<sub>4</sub> leaves vulnerable to photoinhibition in cold, high-light conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Baker <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>).</p><p>Freezing resistance represents an additional potential difference between C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species, but has been considered less often in studies over the past 30 years (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Larcher, 2001</xref>). Recent experiments with C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> subspecies of the African grass <italic>Alloteropsis semialata</italic> showed that the C<sub>4</sub> subspecies suffers from freezing-induced mortality of its leaves during winter, which the C<sub>3</sub> subspecies avoids via cold acclimation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Ibrahim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Osborne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Cold acclimation in the C<sub>3</sub> subspecies is associated with changes in the pattern of moisture release at low water potentials, compared with the C<sub>4</sub> type, indicating the possible involvement of water relations in the acclimation response. These data suggested that climatic extremes such as frost events, rather than photosynthetic responses to average climate conditions, may advantage the C<sub>3</sub> over the C<sub>4</sub> subspecies in cool climatic regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Ibrahim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Osborne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p><p>Injury to leaves caused by late spring and early autumn frosts significantly limits the growing season length, and exerts a strong influence over plant production and distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Woodward, 1987</xref>). Late spring frosts are particularly damaging, because they occur at a time when most plants have broken dormancy, and introduce significant costs for leaf replacement. Freezing injury is caused primarily by the physical disruption of cellular structures by ice crystals, and desiccation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Pearce, 2001</xref>), resulting from the higher water potential of cellular contents than extracellular ice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Larcher, 2001</xref>). Previous studies have suggested that only a few C<sub>4</sub> grass species have the capability for developing cold acclimation during exposure to chilling, thereby increasing leaf resistance to subsequent freezing events (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Rowley, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Stair <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), but the underlying mechanisms of this response have not been reported. Despite its operation in some C<sub>4</sub> grass species, most do not develop cold acclimation and have minimal resistance to freezing. The reasons for this remain poorly understood, although they may be linked to the high energetic costs of freezing resistance, incurred via the synthesis of compatible osmolytes, membrane lipids, cell wall components, and cryoprotective proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Smallwood and Bowles, 2002</xref>).</p><p>Freezing events are critical to the ecology of the Mongolian steppe during springtime. The extreme continental climate of this region leads to an annual freeze-free period in Inner Mongolia of only 90&#x02013;100&#x02009;d, and significant diurnal temperature fluctuations during spring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Chen, 2000</xref>). During this season, daytime temperatures often exceed 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C after a night-time frost event, and leaf survival of freezing may therefore bring significant advantages for photosynthesis. However, C<sub>3</sub> grasses in Inner Mongolia usually begin to grow in early May, whilst their C<sub>4</sub> competitors do not initiate growth until early June (MZL, personal observations). Since the last freezing event generally occurs during May, these observations suggest that C<sub>4</sub> plants may be more sensitive than C<sub>3</sub> species to late spring frosts.</p><p>In the present study, controlled environment experiments with Mongolian steppe grasses were used to test the hypothesis that C<sub>4</sub> members of this plant community are inherently less resistant to freezing than co-occurring C<sub>3</sub> species. Four linked questions were addressed. (i) Does chilling cause a reduction in photosynthesis and greater photoinhibition in C<sub>4</sub> than C<sub>3</sub> species? (ii) Does osmotic adjustment accompany acclimation to chilling in C<sub>3</sub> but not C<sub>4</sub> grasses? (iii) Do freezing temperatures cause higher leaf mortality in C<sub>4</sub> than C<sub>3</sub> grasses? (iv) If the plants undergo a chilling treatment prior to freezing exposure, does this reduce leaf mortality?</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Plant materials</title><p>The experiments used steppe grasses of the Mongolian Plateau, an area occupied by Mongolia in the north and Inner Mongolia (an autonomous region of China) in the south (elevation 900&#x02013;1500&#x02009;m). Seeds of nine species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>) were collected in autumn 2005 from the southern steppe of Inner Mongolia (42&#x000ba;39&#x02032;&#x02013;43&#x000b0;56&#x02032;N, 116&#x000b0;08&#x02032;&#x02013;116&#x000ba;55&#x02032;E). All frequently co-occur in this ecosystem, allowing direct, ecologically meaningful comparisons between C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species. <italic>Lolium perenne</italic> and <italic>Pennisetum clandestinum</italic> were introduced as exotic pasture species in the 1980s, but the other species are indigenous.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Species involved in current experiments, and their photosynthetic subtypes and general habitats in the steppe ecosystem of Inner Mongolia</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abbreviation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Common habitats</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lolium perenne</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naturalized exotic species, grown in pastures</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Festuca pratense</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meadow, forest edges</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bromus inermis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meadows, riverine, along roadsides</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Poa pratensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meadow, in thin forests</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Leymus chinensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steppe, in saline meadows, sand beds of river valleys.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Achnatherum splendens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">As</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saline meadows in arid/semi-arid regions</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Eragrostis minor</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Em</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAD-ME</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sand and pebble riverbeds, often as a weed in oases, along roadsides, wasteland</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pennisetum clandestinum</italic> cv &#x02018;Whittet&#x02019;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADP-ME</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naturalized exotic species, grown in pastures</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cleistogenes squarrosa</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAD-ME</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Desert steppes, especially in sandy and loamy soils; also found scattered in rocky habitats.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>a</label><p>Commonly referred to as &#x02018;<italic>P. clandesti</italic>&#x02019; in China.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Seeds were germinated in sterile nutrient agar for 1 week, and 12 plants of each species transferred to pots (18 cm&#x000d7;13 cm, height&#x000d7;diameter) containing four parts high nutrient compost (Levington M3, Scotts UK Professional, Suffolk, UK) to one part sand (Play Sand, William Sinclair Horticulture Ltd, Lincoln UK) and one part Perlite (Esoteric Hydroponics, Guildford, UK). Plants were watered daily with 40% Long Ashton Solution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Hewitt, 1966</xref>), to provide a nutrient-rich, moist soil environment. The plants were grown in a controlled environment chamber (Conviron BDR 16; Conviron Controlled Environments Ltd, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada) at the University of Sheffield and maintained under a 14&#x02009;h photoperiod with a photon flux density (PFD) of 600&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> measured at plant height, day/night temperature of 25/15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and relative humidity of 60/80% for 12 weeks prior to the experiment.</p><p>At the initiation of the experiment, six plants of each species were maintained under these conditions for a further 20&#x02009;d (control pre-treatment). The other half were transferred to an identical growth chamber with a day/night temperature of 15/5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;d (chilling pre-treatment). The pre-treatments and plants were exchanged between cabinets mid-way through the experiment to minimize the confounding effects of cabinet and pre-treatment. Temperature regimes were designed to match the average daily maximum/minimum temperatures of May (chilling pre-treatment) and July (control pre-treatment) in the field. Measurements of leaf gas exchange, chlorophyll fluorescence, and leaf osmotic potential were made at the end of the 20&#x02009;d pre-treatments.</p></sec><sec><title>Gas exchange and chlorophyll fluorescence</title><p>Photosynthesis and chlorophyll fluorescence were measured on 2&#x02013;4 tillers from a single plant, and four replicate plants in each pre-treatment. All measurements were made on the youngest fully expanded leaf on each tiller which, in the chilling plants, was completely developed under the control temperature regime.</p><p>Chlorophyll fluorescence was first measured using an integrated open gas-exchange and chlorophyll fluorescence system (LI-6400-40, LI-COR Biosciences, Inc., Lincoln, NE, USA). After dark adaptation overnight, the leaves were exposed to a weak modulated beam to determine the zero fluorescence level (<italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>), and then a saturating pulse to obtain the maximum fluorescence level (<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>). Variable fluorescence (<italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>) is the difference between <italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> and <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>, and was used to calculate <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>, the maximum quantum efficiency of PSII.</p><p>Steady-state measurements of CO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>O exchange were made on the same part of the leaf, at the growth temperature of either 15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (chilling pre-treatment) or 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (control pre-treatment), a leaf-to-air vapour pressure deficit of 1.0&#x02013;1.2&#x02009;kPa, <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> of 38&#x02009;Pa, and a PFD of 600&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to simulate the growth environment. The steady-state value of fluorescence (<italic>F</italic><sub>t</sub>) was obtained next, followed by a saturating pulse to obtain the fluorescence maximum in the light (<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>&#x02032;), and these were used to estimate the quantum yield of PSII (&#x003a6;<sub>PSII</sub>) and photochemical quenching (qP). The minimum fluorescence emission of light-adapted leaves (<italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>&#x02032;) was assessed by rapidly darkening the leaf in the presence of far-red light.</p><p>PFD was then increased to 1200&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, which ensured light saturation in these plants and, after reaching a new steady-state value, the response of net CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) to intercellular <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>) was used to estimate the Rubisco-limited photosynthetic capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Farquhar <italic>et al.</italic>, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">von Caemmerer, 2000</xref>). These measurements differed between C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species. For the C<sub>3</sub> plants, four <italic>A&#x02013;C</italic><sub>i</sub> points were obtained using a range of <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> between 38 and 5&#x02009;Pa. However, for the C<sub>4</sub> plants, only a single measurement of CO<sub>2</sub>-saturated photosynthesis was made at 150&#x02009;Pa. Gas exchange parameters were calculated according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">von Caemmerer and Farquhar (1981)</xref>.</p><p>Following these measurements of <italic>A</italic> and chlorophyll fluorescence, leaf absorptance was measured using an imaging technique (Imaging-PAM Chlorophyll Fluorometer, Heinz Walz GmbH, Eichenring, Germany), based on the difference in leaf absorptance of red and near-infrared photons. The apparent photosynthetic electron transport rate (ETR) was then estimated using &#x003a6;<sub>PSII</sub>, PFD, and absorptance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Genty <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>), making the simplifying assumption of equal energy partitioning between PSII and PSI. Excitation pressure on PSII was defined as the fraction of PSII reaction centres that are closed under ambient conditions (1&#x02013;qP; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Huner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), and non-photochemical quenching (NPQ) was calculated using <italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>&#x02032; and <italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bilger and Bj&#x000f6;rkman, 1990</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Maximum rate of carboxylation</title><p>In order to test the hypothesis that Rubisco capacity <italic>in vivo</italic> (<italic>V</italic><sub>c,max</sub>) exerts a higher degree of control over the C<sub>4</sub> than the C<sub>3</sub> photosynthetic rate at low temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Pittermann and Sage, 2000</xref>), <italic>V</italic><sub>c,max</sub> was approximated by fitting a biochemical model of C<sub>3</sub> photosynthesis to <italic>A</italic>&#x02013;<italic>C<sub>i</sub></italic> curves at low values of <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>, and then used to calculate the potential Rubisco-limited CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate for each C<sub>3</sub> species, based on the <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> at light saturation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Farquhar <italic>et al.</italic>, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Long and Bernacchi, 2003</xref>). For the C<sub>4</sub> species, it was assumed that Rubisco limitation of CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation would be indicated by a decrease in the CO<sub>2</sub>-saturated value of photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>), recognizing that <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> may also be limited by the capacity for ribulose bisphosphate (RuBP) or phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP) regeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">von Caemmerer, 2000</xref>). To investigate the limitation of <italic>A</italic> by Rubisco in the control and chilling pre-treatments, the modelled values of Rubisco-limited <italic>A</italic> for C<sub>3</sub> plants, and measured <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> for C<sub>4</sub> plants, were therefore plotted against the observed light-saturated value of <italic>A</italic> (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) at the ambient CO<sub>2</sub> concentration.</p></sec><sec><title>Leaf water potential and osmotic potential</title><p>The leaf water potential (&#x003a8;<sub>leaf</sub>) and osmotic potential (&#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub>) were measured using psychrometry (C-30-SF chambers, Wescor Inc., Logan, UT, USA) following the principles outlined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Koide <italic>et al.</italic> (1989)</xref>. All of the psychrometer chambers were calibrated with a series of known NaCl solutions prior to measurements. The plants were watered on the evening before sampling to allow leaf hydration overnight, and samples were taken at dawn (prior to the controlled-environment lights coming on). &#x003a8;<sub>leaf</sub> was first measured by equilibrating cut leaves in the psychrometer chambers for 60&#x02009;min in an insulated box. The chambers were then flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen for 10&#x02009;min to destroy cell integrity, and measurements repeated for an estimate of &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub>. Four replicates were measured for each species and pre-treatment combination.</p></sec><sec><title>Freezing injury</title><p>After leaf physiology measurements, all plants were exposed to a high-light freezing treatment to test for constitutive freezing resistance (control plants) and to investigate whether cold acclimation had developed (chilled plants). The freezing treatment was designed to simulate a frost in the natural environment, and was applied using a walk-in controlled-environment cabinet (BDW 40, Conviron Controlled Environments Ltd). The treatment was applied to a single block of plants (one of each species&#x000d7;pre-treatment combination=18 plants), and replicated on six consecutive days.</p><p>The protocol for each freezing event followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Osborne <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>. Briefly, the root system of each plant was prevented from freezing by wrapping each pot in polythene, and immersing it in a water bath held at 15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The plants were put into the cabinet at 14:00&#x02009;h and exposed to 15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in the light until 19:00&#x02009;h. The lights were then turned off, and the temperature was lowered gradually overnight to reach a minimum of &#x02013;5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C before dawn. The temperature was held constant at this level for 1&#x02009;h, then the lights were turned on at 08:00&#x02009;h to deliver a PFD of 400&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and both temperature and PFD were then ramped gradually upwards to reach 15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and 1200&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at 13:30&#x02009;h.</p><p>The light regime used for this freezing treatment represented a compromise between: (i) ensuring that the PFD was high enough to allow differential photodamage in C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> leaves; whilst (ii) not exposing the plants to a PFD too far from the value experienced during growth. The growth PFD was constrained by the type of controlled environment cabinets available, and PFD for the freezing treatment was therefore chosen as the minimum value required to saturate photosynthesis at 15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in these plants, based on prior gas exchange measurements. The remainder of this paper therefore refers to the &#x02018;high-light freezing treatment&#x02019;, recognizing that it had the potential to cause both freezing injury and light-mediated oxidative stress to the leaves.</p><p>The extent of leaf injury within the canopy was assessed for all of the plants exposed to this high-light freezing treatment. All dead leaves were cut off before the treatment, and the plants were returned to the control growth conditions after freezing. Over the subsequent 3&#x02013;7&#x02009;d, the total numbers of dead (&#x0003e;67% necrotic) and green leaves were counted, and used to calculate leaf mortality as the number of dead leaves divided by the total number of leaves.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data for <italic>A</italic>, <italic>V</italic><sub>c,max</sub>, <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>, <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>, &#x003a6;<sub>PSII</sub>, qP, NPQ, ETR, &#x003a8;<sub>leaf</sub>, and &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> were taken from four replicates. For freezing injury, the data from six replicates were transformed by taking their natural logarithms to stabilize heterogeneous variances for statistic analysis. A linear mixed effects model (SPSS 14.0.1, Chicago, IL, USA) was used to examine the main effects and interactions of photosynthetic type and pre-treatment, with species included as a random effect. &#x003a8;<sub>leaf</sub> was added as a co-variate to the model for &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub>. Variables were compared by least significant difference to determine whether they were significant at the 0.05 level.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Photosynthesis</title><p>Values of <italic>A</italic> in the chilling pre-treatment were significantly lower than in controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). However, there were no differences between C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species, and no differential effects of the chilling pre-treatment on plants with different photosynthetic types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Results of ANOVA (<italic>F</italic>-values and degree of freedom) testing the effects of photosynthetic type, chilling pre-treatment, &#x02018;freezing strategy&#x02019;, and their interactions on leaf mortality, CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation (<italic>A</italic>), the maximum carboxylation rate of Rubisco (<italic>V</italic><sub>c,max</sub>)(&#x0223c;<italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> in the C<sub>4</sub> species), electron transport rate (ETR), PSII excitation pressure (1&#x02013;qP), non-photochemical quenching (NPQ), the maximum quantum yield of PSII (<italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>), and leaf osmotic potential (&#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photosynthetic type</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chilling pre-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chilling pre-treatment &#x000d7; photosynthetic type</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Freezing strategy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chilling pre-treatment &#x000d7;freezing strategy</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A</italic></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (1, 64)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.46 (1, 64)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 (1, 64)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.88 (2, 64)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (2, 64)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V</italic><sub>c,max</sub></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (1, 4)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.68 (1, 40)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.35 (1, 40)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80 (2, 4)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (2, 40)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42 (1, 5)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.17 (1, 59)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00 (1, 59)*</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 (2, 5)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88 (2, 59)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;qP</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (1, 5)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.65 (1, 59)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 (1, 59)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57 (2, 5)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 (2, 59)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPQ</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99 (1, 5)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.95 (1, 59)**</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (1, 59)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.01 (2, 5)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.24 (2, 59)**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETR</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (1, 64)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.92(1, 64)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (1, 64)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.93 (2, 64)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (2, 64)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 (1, 5)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.63 (1, 59)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69 (1, 59)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 (2, 5)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.12 (2, 59)*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf mortality</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46 (1, 100)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 (1, 100)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (1, 100)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.21 (2, 100)***</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.51 (2,100)***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Analyses of leaf mortality were performed on log<sub>e</sub>-transformed values.</p></fn><fn><p>Significance level: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.1; *, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05; **, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.01; ***, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Net leaf CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate (<italic>A</italic>) for C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species on the 20th day of chilling (filled bars) or control (open bars) pre-treatments. Species are grouped according to hypothesized freezing resistance strategies (see Results), and abbreviations for species names are defined in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>. Each point represents the mean (&#x000b1;SE) of measurements on sets of leaves from four individual plants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern257f01_lw"/></fig><p>In C<sub>3</sub> leaves from the control pre-treatment, the modelled CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate was always equal to the observed value (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2a</xref>), suggesting that Rubisco exerted significant control over light-saturated photosynthesis. The data indicated a similar relationship in the chilling pre-treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2a</xref>), mediated by a significant decrease in <italic>V</italic><sub>c,max</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). These results suggest that the observed reductions in photosynthetic rates were due to temperature-related decreases in Rubisco activity or close coordination between the activity of this enzyme and another limiting process.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Comparison of the light-saturated leaf CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) with: (a) the modelled Rubisco-limited CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate of C<sub>3</sub> species; and (b) the measured CO<sub>2</sub>-saturated rate of <italic>A</italic> (<italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>) for C<sub>4</sub> species. Each point represents the mean (&#x000b1;SE) of measurements on sets of leaves from four individual plants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern257f02_lw"/></fig><p>Values of <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> always exceeded <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> in C<sub>4</sub> plants from the control pre-treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2b</xref>), demonstrating that photosynthesis was not completely saturated with CO<sub>2</sub>, and suggesting that Rubisco activity exceeded that of the C<sub>4</sub> cycle at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. However, the close correspondence of <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> for <italic>Eragrostis minor</italic> and <italic>P. clandestinum</italic> in the chilling pre-treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2b</xref>) indicated greater control of photosynthesis by the enzyme or the capacities for RuBP or PEP regeneration. Conversely, the greater value of <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> than <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> for <italic>Cleistogenes squarrosa</italic> in the chilling pre-treatment suggests limitation of photosynthesis by the C<sub>4</sub> cycle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2b</xref>). Overall, the chilling pre-treatment led to smaller decreases in <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> for the C<sub>4</sub> species than <italic>V</italic><sub>c,max</sub> for the C<sub>3</sub> species, resulting in a significant interaction of photosynthetic type and pre-treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Electron transport</title><p>Photosynthetic type did not affect the excitation pressure, <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>, or ETR, but the effects of chilling pre-treatment were statistically significant for all (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). After 20&#x02009;d growth at 15/5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, pre-dawn <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> of <italic>E. minor</italic> for the chilled plants decreased from 0.79&#x000b1;0.006 in the control to 0.74&#x000b1;0.002, while there were no significant decreases in the other species (Fig. 3a). As with <italic>A</italic>, there was no significant interaction between photosynthetic type and pre-treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Effects of the chilling pre-treatment on (a) maximum quantum yield of PSII (<italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>); (b) PSII electron transport rate (ETR); (c) excitation pressure (1&#x02013;qP); and (d) non-photochemical quenching (NPQ) for C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species on the 20th day of chilling (filled bars) or control (open bars) pre-treatments. Species are grouped according to hypothesized freezing resistance strategies (see Results), and abbreviations for species names are defined in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>. Each point represents the mean (&#x000b1;SE) of measurements on sets of leaves from four individual plants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern257f03_lw"/></fig><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> shows the chilling-induced increase in excitation pressure and decrease in ETR relative to controls, plotted against the parallel decrease in <italic>A</italic> for each species. These plots represent the degree of coordination between photochemistry and CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation at low temperature. Chilling-induced decreases in CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation, increases in excitation pressure, and decreases in photosynthetic electron transport were typically coordinated, as indicated by the linear relationships between these variables across most of the species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). However, excitation pressure in <italic>E. minor</italic> and <italic>Bromus inermis</italic> showed a smaller than expected increase under the chilling pre-treatment relative to the other species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). A smaller than expected decrease in ETR was also observed for the cold-acclimating species <italic>B. inermis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). These results could be explained in terms of decreasing <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub><italic>/F</italic><sub>m</sub> for <italic>E. minor</italic>, but not <italic>B. inermis</italic>, where the data are consistent with a high alternative electron sink capacity.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Comparison of the increase in excitation pressure (1&#x02013;qP) (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.82; <italic>n</italic>=7; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.01) and decrease of PSII electron transport rate (ETR) (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.87; <italic>n</italic>=7; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.01) with the decrease of CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate (<italic>A</italic>) for plants in the chilling compared with the control pre-treatment (mean &#x000b1;SE, <italic>n</italic>=4). The values for Em and Bi are excluded for both relationships.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern257f04_lw"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Osmotic potential</title><p>Values of &#x003a8;<sub>leaf</sub> and &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> for each species showed significant co-variation, and plants from the chilling pre-treatment had more negative values than controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5a</xref>). Relative to plants grown at 25/15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, the &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> was significantly depressed by 4&#x02013;43% in the chilling pre-treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5a</xref>), indicating osmoregulation in these leaves. There was no significant effect of photosynthetic type on &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Relationships of: (a) pre-dawn leaf osmotic potential (&#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub>) and water potential (&#x003a8;<sub>leaf</sub>) (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.55; <italic>n</italic>=16; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01); (b) leaf mortality and &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> for constitutive freezing resistance species (filled squares, chilling; open squares, control), cold-acclimated species (filled circles, chilling; open circles, control), and freezing-sensitive species (filled triangles, chilling; open triangles, control) (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.53; <italic>n</italic>=16; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.01). The values for Em are excluded from both relationships. Each value represents the mean (&#x000b1;SE) of measurement from four individual plants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern257f05_lw"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Leaf freezing injury</title><p>The high-light freezing treatment caused high leaf mortality in only one C<sub>4</sub> grass species, <italic>E. minor</italic>, killing &#x0003e;95% of the leaf canopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). In contrast, leaves of the C<sub>4</sub> <italic>P. clandestinum</italic> and <italic>C. squarrosa</italic> exhibited significant resistance to this treatment, and cold acclimation responses more than halved leaf mortality in the chilling pre-treatment compared with controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). Leaf mortality in these C<sub>4</sub> species was in the middle of the range observed for the C<sub>3</sub> grasses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>), meaning that neither the effects of photosynthetic type nor its interaction with pre-treatment were significant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). If the values for <italic>E. minor</italic> were excluded, there was a negative correlation between leaf freezing injury and &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> across both the control and chilling pre-treatments, with &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> explaining &#x0003e;50% of the variance in freezing mortality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5b</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Leaf mortality of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants after 20&#x02009;d of chilling (filled bars) or control (open bars) pre-treatments followed by a high-light &#x02013;5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C freezing event. Species are grouped according to hypothesized freezing resistance strategies, and abbreviations for species names are defined in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>. Each value represents the mean (&#x000b1;SE) of measurements from six individual plants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern257f06_lw"/></fig><p>Based on a visual inspection of the data, it was hypothesized that &#x02018;freezing strategies&#x02019; might provide a better explanation of the observed patterns than photosynthetic pathway, with species displaying either: sensitivity to the high-light freezing treatment (=&#x02018;freezing sensitivity&#x02019;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>, Em); cold acclimation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>, Lp, Fp, Bi, Pc, and Cs); or constitutive resistance to the treatment (=&#x02018;freezing resistance&#x02019;), with no cold acclimation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>, Pp, Lc, and As). This <italic>post hoc</italic> hypothesis was supported by a statistical analysis incorporating &#x02018;freezing strategy&#x02019; as a main effect, which demonstrated highly significant impacts of freezing strategy and its interaction with pre-treatment on leaf mortality, regardless of the photosynthetic type (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). This result showed that the <italic>post hoc</italic> hypothesis was consistent with the data, and explained a significant amount of the variance.</p><p>Cold acclimation was observed in three C<sub>3</sub> and two C<sub>4</sub> species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). The largest effect was in the C<sub>3</sub> <italic>B. inermis</italic>, where plants in the chilling pre-treatment suffered leaf freezing mortality of only 1%, i.e. a 96% decrease compared with control plants. Mortality in the freezing treatment was 30% and 47% less in the chilling pre-treatment relative to the control of for the C<sub>3</sub> plants <italic>L. perenne</italic> and <italic>Festuca pretense</italic>, and 60% and 72% lower in the C<sub>4</sub> species <italic>P</italic>. <italic>clandestinum</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>squarrosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). For the C<sub>3</sub> species where the data suggested constitutive resistance to the high-light freezing treatment, the chilling pre-treatment had no effect on leaf mortality, and both the chilling and control plants displayed low leaf mortality after the freezing treatment, which varied from 5% to 22% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Freezing strategy</title><p>The factor &#x02018;freezing strategy&#x02019; (based solely on the observed patterns of freezing injury) explained a highly significant amount of the variance in <italic>A</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). In other words, <italic>A</italic> measured prior to the freezing treatment emerged as a strong correlate of subsequent leaf injury patterns.</p><p>Values of <italic>A</italic> were the lowest in the &#x02018;freezing-sensitive&#x02019; species, intermediate in the &#x02018;cold-acclimated&#x02019; species, and highest in the species with &#x02018;constitutive freezing resistance&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). The freezing-sensitive species <italic>E</italic>. <italic>minor</italic> showed a significant, 50% depression of <italic>A</italic> in the chilling pre-treatment compared with controls (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Values of <italic>A</italic> in the cold-acclimated group of plants were also depressed by the chilling pre-treatment compared with controls: by 27% in <italic>L</italic>. <italic>perenne</italic>, 32% in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>inermis</italic>, 21% in <italic>F. pretense</italic>, 17% in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>squarrosa</italic>, and 24% in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>clandestinum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). In contrast, <italic>A</italic> showed a tendency to be limited less by chilling in the species with constitutive resistance; <italic>Achnatherum splendens</italic> showed a slight (15%) decrease of <italic>A</italic> in the chilling pre-treatment, while no major change was observed for <italic>L</italic>. <italic>chinensis</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>pratensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). However, there was no significant interaction between &#x02018;freezing strategy&#x02019; and the chilling pre-treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>&#x02018;Freezing strategy&#x02019; also explained a significant amount of the variance in ETR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). Species that displayed constitutive resistance to the high-light freezing treatment maintained the highest ETR under the chilling pre-treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3b</xref>), and the lowest excitation pressure (Fig.3c). As with <italic>A</italic>, there was no significant interaction between the chilling pre-treatment and freezing strategy (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>The magnitudes of &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> responses to the chilling pre-treatment were also consistent with the <italic>post hoc</italic> &#x02018;freezing strategies&#x02019; hypothesis. The interaction of chilling pre-treatment and freezing strategy on &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> was highly significant, and independent of &#x003a8;<sub>leaf</sub>, which was included in the statistical analysis as a co-variate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). The effects of chilling were minimal for the freezing-sensitive species, decreasing the value of &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> by 9% relative to controls, and those with constitutive freezing resistance, where &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> was depressed by 4&#x02013;16% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5b</xref>). In contrast, &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> in the cold-acclimating species decreased by 8&#x02013;43% in the chilling pre-treatment compared with controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5b</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Freezing injury and osmoregulation</title><p>Two out of the three C<sub>4</sub> species in this experiment (<italic>C</italic>. <italic>squarrosa</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>clandestinum</italic>) developed significant cold acclimation under the chilling pre-treatment, manifested as a decrease in leaf osmotic potential, which reduced leaf mortality during a consequent high-light freezing event. These cold acclimation responses of C<sub>4</sub> grasses fell within the range observed for C<sub>3</sub> grass species from the same steppe ecosystem. This suggests that the photosynthetic pathway presents no inherent barrier to the survival of freezing followed by high light. This oxidative shock to leaves is typical of natural frost events, since low night-time temperatures are commonly associated with clear sky conditions.</p><p>The development of cold acclimation in this experiment is atypical of C<sub>4</sub> species, which occur in tropical grass lineages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Edwards and Still, 2008</xref>), and have not usually evolved the complex set of genetic pathways required for frost protection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Beck, 2007</xref>). A mechanistic link between freezing sensitivity and the C<sub>4</sub> pathway is also suggested by the occurrence of cold acclimation in the C<sub>3</sub> but not in the C<sub>4</sub> subspecies of <italic>A. semialata</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Ibrahim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Osborne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). However, cold acclimation has been observed previously in a minority of C<sub>4</sub> species. A study in New Zealand showed that only two out of 11 C<sub>4</sub> species, <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic> and <italic>Eragrostis curvula</italic>, markedly increased leaf freezing resistance when the growth temperature was decreased gradually (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Rowley, 1976</xref>). These two species, introduced from Africa, frequently occur in lawns or on roadsides and are drought-tolerant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Percival 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Robinson and Whalley 1991</xref>). Similar results were reported in winter-hardy genotypes of C<sub>4</sub> species in the southern USA; leaves of <italic>Pennisetum ciliare</italic>, <italic>Pennisetum flaccidum</italic>, and <italic>Pennisetum mezianum</italic>, which are very drought-tolerant perennials and can spread in dry years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Tellman, 2002</xref>), displayed increasing freezing resistance when they were grown in a low-temperature chamber of 10/5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 4 weeks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Stair <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). The results reported here demonstrate that some C<sub>4</sub> grass species from the Mongolian Plateau, which are drought tolerant and frequently occur in roadside or dry, rocky habitats (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>), also have the potential to acclimate to frost during the growing season.</p><p>Drawing upon these data, two complementary hypotheses may be put forward. First, that frost injury in the leaves of C<sub>4</sub> plants is the outcome of an adaptive trade-off between the energetic costs of cold acclimation and the photosynthetic benefits for a C<sub>4</sub> plant of leaf survival during freezing events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Sage and Pearcy, 2000</xref>). Since recent studies suggest that cold acclimation may be less effective or more costly in C<sub>4</sub> than in C<sub>3</sub> leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sage and McKown, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Osborne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), such a trade-off is most likely to favour cold acclimation in continental or high elevation environments experiencing large diurnal temperature ranges. Here, freezing temperatures at dawn are succeeded by daytime temperatures of &#x0003e;20&#x02013;25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The diurnal temperature range experienced by C<sub>4</sub> plants at high altitudes is further increased by the absorption of direct solar radiation, which may raise leaf temperature by 10&#x02013;20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C over that of the air (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Sage and Sage, 2002</xref>). This adaptive interpretation is consistent with the evidence reported here and recent reports of freezing injury thresholds below &#x02013;10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in C<sub>4</sub> grasses from high elevations in the Venezuelan Andes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">M&#x000e1;rquez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) and Californian White Mountains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Sage and Sage, 2002</xref>).</p><p>A second hypothesis, involving a linkage between frost and drought sensitivity, is also suggested by the results of previous studies and the data reported here. Frost injury in freezing-sensitive species is induced mainly through extracellular ice formation, which dehydrates mesophyll tissues by extracting symplastic water, but may directly disrupt the bundle sheath cells of C<sub>4</sub> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Ashworth and Pearce, 2002</xref>). However, by altering their biochemical composition under chilling temperatures, cold-acclimated plants can accumulate compatible osmolytes in cells, which cause a decline in water potential and increase resistance to dehydration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Goldstein <italic>et al.</italic>, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Ani&#x0015b;ko and Lindstrom, 1996</xref>), also improving their resistance to freezing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Smallwood and Bowles, 2002</xref>). The data reported here are consistent with this mechanism, showing that values of &#x003a8;<sub>leaf</sub> and &#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub> decreased in plants exposed to the chilling pre-treatment, indicating significant osmoregulation, especially for those in the cold-acclimating group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5a, b</xref>). This was correlated with freezing resistance strategies that were defined via an independent method.</p><p>Leaf survival of high water deficits in drought environments is facilitated via similar desiccation protection mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Turner and Begg, 1981</xref>), which can directly improve the cold acclimation of species via biochemical changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Mantyla <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kacperska, 2004</xref>). Based on these results and the habitat requirements of individual species, it is hypothesized that cold acclimation in the C<sub>4</sub> steppe grass species from the Mongolian Plateau may be associated with drought adaptations. This inferred linkage is consistent with the observed cold acclimation responses in the C<sub>4</sub> grasses <italic>C</italic>. <italic>squarrosa</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>clandestinum</italic>, which occur in open grassland and desert steppe habitats (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Liang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), and the freezing sensitivity and failure to cold-acclimate in <italic>E. minor.</italic> The latter C<sub>4</sub> grass is confined to moist habitats of the Mongolian Plateau, including riverbeds and disturbed areas (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Ma, 1998</xref>), suggesting an obligate requirement for wet growth conditions. Furthermore, the three C<sub>3</sub> species showing the greatest constitutive freezing resistance are also those occupying the driest habitats in the steppe ecosystem (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>): <italic>L</italic>. <italic>chinensis</italic> is broadly distributed in the dry steppe regions of East Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Zhu, 2004</xref>), <italic>P</italic>. <italic>pratensis</italic> naturally occupies the open and high land, and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>splendens</italic> occurs naturally on saline soils where it survives low soil water potentials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Ma 1998</xref>). Clearly, the small sample of species used here precludes generalizations, but these observations suggest that the potential association of drought and frost resistance in steppe grasses could be a useful avenue for future research.</p></sec><sec><title>Photosynthesis under chilling conditions</title><p>At high temperatures, C<sub>4</sub> species have the potential to achieve a higher photosynthetic rate than their C<sub>3</sub> counterparts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Pearcy and Ehleringer, 1984</xref>). However, under the environmental conditions applied in this experiment, constitutive freezing-tolerant C<sub>3</sub> species showed the highest rates of photosynthesis, followed by the cold-acclimating C<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>3</sub> species. This may be because of the PFD used, which limited rates of C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis under the growth conditions. Despite the relatively low PFD (600&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), the chilling pre-treatment still caused a 50% decrease in the CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate in the freezing-sensitive C<sub>4</sub> species <italic>E. minor</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), a decline in the pre-dawn <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub><italic>/F</italic><sub>m</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3a</xref>), and a small increase of excitation pressure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3c</xref>), despite increased NPQ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3d</xref>). Decreases of <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub><italic>/F</italic><sub>m</sub> and PSII photochemical efficiency following chilling have been noted previously for C<sub>4</sub> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Baker <italic>et al.</italic>, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Demmig <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>). The results for <italic>E. minor</italic> suggest the operation of slow-relaxing (&#x0003e;10&#x02009;h) quenching mechanisms, indicative of photodamage, correlated with a greater excess energy flux through PSII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3c</xref>) and high leaf mortality after the subsequent high-light freezing event (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p><p>The inference of photodamage in <italic>E. minor</italic> is consistent with previous experiments applying similar PFD conditions to the tropical C<sub>4</sub> plants <italic>Zea mays</italic> and <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Taylor and Rowley, 1971</xref>). Interpretation of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref> using a biochemical model of C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">von Caemmerer, 2000</xref>) suggests a high degree of control by the capacities of Rubisco or components of the PEP regeneration pathway such as PPDK. Both have been implicated previously in the photoinhibition of C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Long, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Sage and Kubien, 2007</xref>), and represent key limitations that must be overcome in cold-tolerant C<sub>4</sub> species by dynamic quenching mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Ensminger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Sage and Kubien, 2007</xref>) or repair processes mediated by protein expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p><p>Chilling-induced photodamage did not occur in all of the C<sub>4</sub> species in the experiment. In the cold-acclimating species, the chilling pre-treatment lowered photosynthetic rates equally in C<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>3</sub> species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), and this was associated with lower, rather than higher, leaf mortality after the subsequent freezing event (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). Photodamage was avoided in these species by coordinated decreases in the PSII electron flux and CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation, despite an increase in the excitation pressure on PSII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3c</xref>). This acclimation response is common in C<sub>3</sub> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Sage and Kubien, 2007</xref>), and suggests the operation of effective non-photochemical quenching mechanisms together with protective down-regulation of PSII efficiency in the cold-tolerant C<sub>4</sub> species studied here (Fig. 3d).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Resistance to a high-light freezing treatment was independent of photosynthetic pathway in the grasses of the Mongolian Plateau studied in this experiment, but differed among species according to ecological traits. The depression of osmotic potential was associated with the acquisition of cold acclimation in some C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species, and represents a previously undescribed mechanism to explain the persistence of C<sub>4</sub> plants in cool climate habitats. The one freezing-sensitive C<sub>4</sub> species in this experiment did not adjust osmotic potential, and was also susceptible to chilling-induced photodamage. Based on the habitat requirements of individual species in the natural ecosystem, it is hypothesized that freezing resistance in Mongolian steppe grasses may be more closely allied to the capacity for drought resistance than the photosynthetic pathway.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term><italic>A</italic></term><def><p>net leaf CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate (&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub></term><def><p>the CO<sub>2</sub>-saturated value of <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> (&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub></term><def><p>the light-saturated value of <italic>A</italic> (&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub></term><def><p>intercellular <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> (Pa)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ETR</term><def><p>photosynthetic electron transport rate (&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub></term><def><p>the maximum quantum efficiency of photosystem II after overnight dark adaptation (dimensionless)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NPQ</term><def><p>fast-relaxing non-photochemical quenching (dimensionless)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PFD</term><def><p>photon flux density (&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSII</term><def><p>photosystem II</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qP</term><def><p>photochemical quenching, the fraction of <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> realized under growth conditions (dimensionless)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>1&#x02013;qP</term><def><p>excitation pressure on photosystem II, the fraction of PSII reaction centres that are closed under ambient conditions</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>V</italic><sub>c,max</sub></term><def><p>the apparent maximum carboxylation activity of Rubisco <italic>in vivo</italic> (&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>&#x003a6;<sub>PSII</sub></term><def><p>quantum yield of PSII, the operating efficiency of photosystem II under growth conditions (dimensionless)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>&#x003a8;<sub>leaf</sub></term><def><p>leaf water potential (MPa)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>&#x003a8;<sub>osmotic</sub></term><def><p>leaf osmotic potential (MPa)</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><p>We wish to thank Mr Jian-Cai Du, Dr Zheng-Wen Wang, and Dr Hai-Dong Liu for providing seeds for this study, Timo Blake and Stuart Pearce for their help in setting up growth chambers, Andrew Beckerman for advice on the statistics, and Brad Ripley for his critical comments on the manuscript. This work was funded by an International China Fellowship and a University Research Fellowship from The Royal Society, the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 40501009), and National Scientific and Technological Support Projects (2008BADB0B05).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ani&#x0015b;ko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cold hardiness and water relations parameters in <italic>Rhododendron</italic> cv. <italic>Catawbiense Boursault</italic> subjected to drought episodes</article-title><source>Physiologia Plantarum</source><year>1996</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>155</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular freezing in leaves of freezing-sensitive species</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2002</year><volume>214</volume><fpage>798</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11882950</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>East</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chilling damage to photosynthesis in young <italic>Zea mays</italic>. II. Photochemical function of thylakoids <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>1983</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farage</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurements of the quantum yield of carbon assimilation and chlorophyll fluorescence for assessment of photosynthetic performance of crops in the field</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>1989</year><volume>323</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>308</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fettig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Knake</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattarai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specific and unspecific responses of plants to cold and drought stress</article-title><source>Journal of Biosciences</source><year>2007</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17536169</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of the xanthophylls cycle in photoprotection elucidated by measurements of light-induced absorbance changes, fluorescence and photosynthesis in <italic>Hedera canariensis</italic></article-title><source>Photosynthesis Research</source><year>1990</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>185</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Steppe ecosystems in China</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Beijing, China</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Science Publishing (in Chinese)</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demmig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Czygan</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photoinhibition and zeaxanthin formation in intact leaves: a possible role of the xanthophylls cycle in the dissipation of excess light energy</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>1987</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16665420</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Still</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate, phylogeny and the ecological distribution of C<sub>4</sub> grasses</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18201200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehleringer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantum yields for CO<sub>2</sub> uptake in C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants. Dependence on temperature, CO<sub>2</sub>, and O<sub>2</sub> concentration</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>1977</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16659794</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ensminger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huner</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photostasis and cold acclimation: sensing low temperature through photosynthesis</article-title><source>Physiologia Plantarum</source><year>2006</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farquhar</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>von Caemmerer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A biochemical model of photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation in the leaves of C<sub>3</sub> species</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1980</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Briantais</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between quantum yield of photosynthetic electron transport and quenching of chlorophyll fluorescence</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source><year>1989</year><volume>990</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rada</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Azocar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cold hardiness and supercooling along an altitudinal gradient in Andean giant rosette species</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1985</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>152</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Sand and water culture methods used in the study of plant nutrition</source><year>1966</year><publisher-loc>Buckingham, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Commonwealth Agricultural Bureau</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huner</surname><given-names>NPA</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00150;quist</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarhan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Energy balance and acclimation to light and cold</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>230</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripley</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal differences in photosynthesis between the C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> subspecies of <italic>Alloteropsis semialata</italic> are offset by frost and drought</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>2008</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1038</fpage><lpage>1050</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kacperska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensor types in signal transduction pathways in plant cells responding to abiotic stressors: do they depend on stress intensity?</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2004</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>168</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>A physiological basis for niche separation between <italic>Agropyron smithii</italic> (C<sub>3</sub>) and <italic>Bouteloua gracillis</italic> (C<sub>4</sub>)</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1980</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>846</fpage><lpage>858</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koide</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Robichaux</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pearcy</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehleringer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rundel</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant water status, hydraulic resistance and capacitance</article-title><source>Plant physiological ecology. Field methods and instrumentation</source><year>1989</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>183</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larcher</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><source>Physiological plant ecology</source><year>2001</year><edition>4th edn</edition><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Michalk</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ecology and growth patterns of <italic>Cleistogenes</italic> species in degraded grasslands of eastern Inner Mongolia, China</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source><year>2002</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>594</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis at low-temperatures</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>1983</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>363</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernacchi</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gas exchange measurements, what can they tell us about the underlying limitations of photosynthesis? Procedures and sources of error</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2003</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>2393</fpage><lpage>2401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14512377</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inner Mongolia flora</source><year>1998</year><volume>Vol. 3</volume><publisher-loc>Huhhot, China</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Inner Mongolia People's Publishing House</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantyla</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Palva</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of abscisic acid in drought-induced freezing tolerance, cold acclimation, and accumulation of LTI78 and RAB18 proteins in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>1995</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228349</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000e1;rquez</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rada</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Freezing tolerance in grasses along an altitudinal gradient in the Venezuelan Andes</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2006</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17024382</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Littlejohn</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Photosynthetic adaptation to temperature in four species from the Colorado shortgrass steppe: a physiological model for coexistence</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1983</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wythe</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripley</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low temperature effects on leaf physiology and survivorship in the C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> subspecies of <italic>Alloteropsis semialata</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1743</fpage><lpage>1754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18403381</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant freezing and damage</article-title><source>Annals of Botany</source><year>2001</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>424</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearcy</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehleringer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative ecophysiology of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>1984</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Percival</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survey of <italic>Paspalum</italic> in New Zealand pastures</article-title><source>New Zealand Journal of Experimental Agriculture</source><year>1977</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>226</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pittermann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photosynthetic performance at low temperature of <italic>Bouteloua gracilis</italic> Lag., a high-altitude C<sub>4</sub> grass from the Rocky Mountains, USA</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>2000</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>823</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potvin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of low temperature on the photosynthetic metabolism of the C<sub>4</sub> grass <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic></article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1986</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>506</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Whalley</surname><given-names>RDB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competition among three agronomic types of the <italic>Eragrostis curvula</italic> (Schrad.) Nees complex and three temperate pasture grasses on the Northern Tablelands of New South Wales (Australia)</article-title><source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source><year>1991</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>316</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of freezing tolerance in leaves of C<sub>4</sub> grasses</article-title><source>Australian Journal of Plant Physiology</source><year>1976</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>603</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubien</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The temperature response of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>2007</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1086</fpage><lpage>1106</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>McKown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis less phenotypically plastic than C<sub>3</sub> photosynthesis?</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364950</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearcy</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Leegood</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>von Caemmerer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The physiological ecology of C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis</article-title><source>Photosynthesis: physiology and metabolism</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>The Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kluwer</publisher-name><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>532</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsite characteristics of <italic>Muhlenbergia richardsonis</italic> (Trin.) Rydb., an alpine C<sub>4</sub> grass from the White Mountains, California</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2002</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>508</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Monson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biogeography of C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis: patterns and controlling factors</article-title><source>C<sub>4</sub> plant biology</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>356</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smallwood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowles</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants in a cold climate</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2002</year><volume>357</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>847</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stair</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahmer</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Bashaw</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussey</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Freezing tolerance of selected <italic>Pennisetum</italic> species</article-title><source>International Journal of Plant Sciences</source><year>1998</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>605</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in cold lability of pyruvate, Pi dikinase among C<sub>4</sub> species</article-title><source>Plant and Cell Physiology</source><year>1979</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>965</fpage><lpage>971</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants under climate stress. I. Low temperature, high light effects on photosynthesis</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>1971</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>718</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16657691</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tellman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Invasive exotic species in the Sonoran Desert region</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Arizona</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Arizona Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant&#x02013;water relations and adaptation to stress</article-title><source>Plant and Soil</source><year>1981</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Caemmerer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biochemical models of leaf photosynthesis</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Victoria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CSIRO Publishing</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Caemmerer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Farquhar</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some relationships between the biochemistry of photosynthesis and the gas exchange of leaves</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1981</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>387</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Portis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An increase in expression of pyruvate Pi dikinase and its high activation energy correspond to cold-tolerant C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis of <italic>Miscanthus&#x000d7;giganteus</italic></article-title><source>Photosynthesis Research</source><year>2007</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>225</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>FI</given-names></name></person-group><source>Climate and plant distribution</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><source>The biology and ecology of Leymus chinensis</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Shenyang, China</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Jilin Scientific and Technology Publishing</publisher-name></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>