<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Cell Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2121</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19068119</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639384</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2121-9-66</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2121-9-66</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Valproic acid induces differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in neural progenitor cells via the beta-catenin-Ras-ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Gyung-Ah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>assam76@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>Ju-Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>surcamus@yonsei.ac.kr</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>Byoung-San</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>iloveyoumoon@hanmail.net</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Dong-Hwa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>y2d2h2@hanmail.net</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Hyun-Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>gtype79@empal.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Sang-Hun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>leesh@hanyang.ac.kr</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bryja</surname><given-names>Vitezslav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>bryja@sci.muni.cz</email></contrib><contrib id="A8" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>Ernest</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>ernest.arenas@ki.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A9" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Kang-Yell</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kychoi@yonsei.ac.kr</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>National  Research  Laboratory  of Molecular  Complex  Control, Department of Biotechnology, College  of  Life Science and Biotechnology, Yonsei University, Seoul, 120-752, Korea</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Biochemistry, College of Medicine, Hanyang University, Seoul, 133-791, Korea</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Laboratory of Molecular Neurobiology, Department of Medical Biochemistry and Biophysics, Karolinska Institutet, S1-171 77 Stockholm, Sweden</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2121/9/66"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Jung et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Jung et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Jung               Gyung-Ah                              assam76@gmail.com            </dc:author><dc:title>            Valproic acid induces differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in neural progenitor cells via the beta-catenin-Ras-ERK-p21Cip/WAF1 pathway         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Cell Biology 9(1): 66-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2121(2008)9:1&#x0003c;66&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2121</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Valproic acid (VPA), a commonly used mood stabilizer that promotes neuronal differentiation, regulates multiple signaling pathways involving extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) and glycogen synthase kinase3&#x003b2; (GSK3&#x003b2;). However, the mechanism by which VPA promotes differentiation is not understood.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We report here that 1 mM VPA simultaneously induces differentiation and reduces proliferation of basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF)-treated embryonic day 14 (E14) rat cerebral cortex neural progenitor cells (NPCs). The effects of VPA on the regulation of differentiation and inhibition of proliferation occur via the ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway. These effects, however, are not mediated by the pathway involving the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) but via the pathway which stabilizes Ras through &#x003b2;-catenin signaling. Stimulation of differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in NPCs by VPA occur independently and the &#x003b2;-catenin-Ras-ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway is involved in both processes. The independent regulation of differentiation and proliferation in NPCs by VPA was also demonstrated <italic>in vivo </italic>in the cerebral cortex of developing rat embryos.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We propose that this mechanism of VPA action may contribute to an explanation of its anti-tumor and neuroprotective effects, as well as elucidate its role in the independent regulation of differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in the cerebral cortex of developing rat embryos.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Valproic acid (VPA; 2-propyl-pentanoic acid) has been used for mood stabilization and the treatment of epilepsy for several decades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. VPA also exhibits potent <italic>in vitro </italic>and <italic>in vivo </italic>anti-tumor effects in leukemic cells, neuroblastomas, and gliomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. VPA is a histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitor and plays a role in modifying chromatin structure and gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. VPA has also been found to affect various signaling systems, including the extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK), protein kinase C (PKC), and the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. VPA alters the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling by directly or indirectly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] inhibiting the activity of glycogen synthase kinase 3&#x003b2; (GSK3&#x003b2;).</p><p>VPA has been reported to regulate the differentiation and proliferation of various cells, including mesenchymal and hematopoietic stem cells, neuroblastoma cells, primary neurons, and neural progenitor cells (NPCs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. VPA can also reduce the proliferation of neuroblastoma cells by induction of the cell cycle regulator p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], which is also known to be involved in the VPA-induced differentiation of hematopoietic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. However, the mechanism by which VPA regulates differentiation and proliferation is not understood.</p><p>We report here that 1 mM VPA induces differentiation and inhibits proliferation of NPCs by overcoming the effect of basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), a factor which inhibits the differentiation of NPCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. VPA-induced activation of the ERK- p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway did not occur via the common pathway involving epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR), an upstream component of the ERK pathway, as indicated by significant reduction in the level of EGFR in the presence of VPA. The level of Ras protein, another upstream component of the ERK pathway, was significantly increased by VPA treatment. This observation led us to conclude that VPA-induced ERK pathway activation occurs via an increase in the stability of Ras, mediated by Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. We also found that the common Ras-ERK-p21<sup>Cip//WAF1 </sup>pathway is involved in generating the mutually exclusive phenotypes of differentiation and proliferation in NPCs and in brain tissue of the cerebral cortex of developing embryos.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>VPA overcomes the effects of bFGF on differentiation and proliferation in multipotent NPCs</title><p>Basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF) is necessary for the maintenance of multipotency in neural progenitor cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] and is involved in the regulation of differentiation and growth in neuronal cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. In agreement with earlier reports, we found that NPCs isolated from the cerebral cortex of E14 rat embryos underwent morphologic differentiation when grown in N2 medium alone (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>, upper left panel). The NPCs retain the capacity for self-renewal, as shown by their ability to form neurospheres, by a process of dissociation and reformation, for several passages in culture (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). The NPCs also retain the property of multipotency, as shown by their capacity to differentiate into primary neurons, oligodendrocytes, and astrocytes (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). The NPCs maintained an undifferentiated morphology when grown in the presence of 10 ng/ml bFGF (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>, lower left panel). The differentiation-suppressing and proliferative effects of bFGF were partly overcome by treatment with 1 mM VPA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>, lower right panel). Cells treated with VPA and bFGF also exhibited more pronounced neurite outgrowth compared to cells treated with bFGF alone. The effect of VPA on morphologic differentiation in the presence of bFGF was dose-dependent (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>). No evidence of cell toxicity was detected in the presence of 1 mM VPA and this concentration was used in the remaining experiments. Not only do NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF for 48 h remain morphologically undifferentiated, but the cells also had a high proliferation rate, as indicated by a five-fold increase in total cell number compared to untreated cultures (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). In contrast, co-treatment with 1 mM VPA for 48 h reduced cell number by 60% compared to cells treated with bFGF alone (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). VPA did not alter cell number in cultures grown in the absence of bFGF. Therefore, VPA induced both differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in NPCs by overcoming the anti-differentiation and pro-growth effects of bFGF.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of VPA on morphology and proliferation of NPCs</bold>. NPCs were treated with 1 mM VPA for 48 h in the presence or absence of 10 ng/ml bFGF. (A) Micrographs were taken at a magnification of 200&#x000d7;. (B) Cells were harvested and then counted using a hemocytometer. In three independent experiments, cells within the 230-&#x003bc;m square were counted and expressed as percent of the total number of cells in bFGF-treated cultures. Data represent mean &#x000b1; SD of three separate experiments. P*** &#x0003c; 0.001 by one-way ANOVA followed by Newman-Keuls test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>VPA induces both p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>and Tuj1 via the Raf-MEK-ERK cascade in NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF</title><p>The ERK pathway is involved in both positive and negative regulations of cell growth depending upon the intensity and duration of the signals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] and VPA can activate the ERK pathway in primary neurons in culture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. To investigate the potential involvement of the ERK pathway in VPA-induced differentiation and growth inhibition in bFGF-treated NPCs, the activation status of Raf-1, MEK, and ERK was examined. Immunoblot analysis revealed that VPA treatment elicited an increase in ERK activity, as indicated by an increase in the levels of phosphorylated ERK (p-ERK), in NPCs grown in bFGF. The levels of phosphorylated MEK (p-MEK) and Raf-1 (p-Raf-1) were also increased in NPCs in which differentiation had been induced and proliferation had been inhibited by treatment with VPA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Induction of the cell cycle regulator p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>is an important indicator of ERK pathway-induced inhibition of proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. In accordance with its anti-proliferative effect, VPA elicited an increase in p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>levels in NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Immunocytochemical analysis of NPCs revealed that the induction of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>by VPA was accompanied by accumulation of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>in the cell nuclei (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>; left panel). The number of cells containing positive nuclear staining of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>increased from 5% to 87.5% in response to VPA treatment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>, right panel). In contrast, the percentage of proliferating cells, which incorporated BrdU into their nuclei, was reduced from 73% to 15% in response to treatment with 1 mM VPA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). Immunoblot analysis revealed that the level of Tuj1, a specific marker of immature neurons, increased in NPCs grown in the presence of VPA and bFGF (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Immunocytochemical analysis confirmed these findings and also showed marked, enhanced neurite outgrowth in cells showing significantly increased levels of Tuj1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of VPA on activities of ERK pathway components and on expression of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>and Tuj1</bold>. NPCs grown in 10 ng/ml bFGF were treated with 1 mM VPA for 48 h. (A) Whole-cell lysates were subjected to immunoblotting for analysis of the presence of p-ERK, p-MEK, p-Raf-1, p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>, Tuj1, or &#x003b2;-actin. Alternatively, NPCs were processed for immunofluorescent labeling of (B) p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>(green), (C) BrdU (red), or (D) Tuj1 (green). Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI (blue). All images are 200&#x000d7; magnifications. The percentage of cells that exhibited nuclear p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>in the presence and absence of VPA is presented, along with the percentage of BrdU-positive and Tuj1-positive cells. Error bars indicate the standard deviations of three independent experiments. Data represent mean &#x000b1; SD of three separate experiments. P*** &#x0003c; 0.001, P** &#x0003c; 0.01 by Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. (B-C). Effects of inhibition of ERK pathway on p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>and Tuj1 induction by VPA. (E) NPCs grown in the presence of 10 ng/ml bFGF were treated with different combinations of 20 &#x003bc;M PD98059 and 1 mM VPA. (F) NPCs grown in the presence of 10 ng/ml bFGF were treated as in (E). In three independent experiments, cells within the 230-&#x003bc;m square were counted and expressed as a percentage of the total number of cells. Values represent the mean &#x000b1; SD of three separate experiments. P** &#x0003c; 0.01, P*** &#x0003c; 0.001 by one-way ANOVA followed by Newman-Keuls test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-2"/></fig><p>To ascertain whether the ERK pathway mediates p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>induction and neuronal differentiation in response to VPA, we measured the effect of inhibition of the Ras-ERK pathway on the induction of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>and Tuj1 by VPA. Induction of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>by VPA was significantly reduced when ERK activation was inhibited by the MEK inhibitor PD98059 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>). Induction of Tuj1 by VPA was also reduced by PD98059. The VPA-induced activation of the ERK pathway in the inhibition of growth of NPCs in the presence of bFGF was confirmed by the observation of re-increase of cell numbers by treatment with PD98059 in the presence of VPA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>). We did not observe any growth-stimulatory effect of PD98059 when NPCs were grown in the absence of bFGF; rather, cell number was somewhat reduced by PD98059 treatment (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). In summary, VPA induces differentiation and inhibition of proliferation via the Ras&#x02192;MEK&#x02192;ERK pathway in NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF.</p></sec><sec><title>p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>mediates VPA-induced differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF</title><p>VPA-induced ERK activation and p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>induction were not observed in the Tuj1-induced, differentiated NPCs grown in the absence of bFGF, as shown by both biochemical (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>) and immunocytochemical (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>) analyses. In these cultures, the number of BrdU-positive cells was relatively low and was not changed by VPA treatment (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). To determine the role of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>in VPA-induced differentiation and inhibition of proliferation, we analyzed the effect of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>siRNA. Stimulation of neuronal differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in NPCs by VPA treatment were diminished by p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>siRNA as shown by both biochemical (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>) and immunocytochemical (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>) analyses. Inhibition of proliferation, one of the effects of VPA on NPCs as assessed by BrdU incorporation, was also released after treatment with p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>siRNA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>; quantitative data are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>). The majority of cells exhibiting nuclear accumulation of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>after VPA treatment were also BrdU-negative, underscoring the important anti-proliferative role of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of bFGF and p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>siRNA on regulation of the VPA-induced differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in NPCs (A-B)</bold>. NPCs were treated with 1 mM VPA for 48 h in the presence or absence of 10 ng/ml bFGF. (C-D) NPCs were transfected with 100 nM p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>siRNA prior to treatment with 1 mM VPA for 48 h in the presence of 10 ng/ml bFGF. Whole-cell lysates were subjected to immunoblotting to detect p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>, Tuj1, or &#x003b2;-actin. Alternatively, cells were processed for immunofluorescent labeling to detect the presence of Tuj1 (green), p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>(green), or BrdU (red). Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI. Images are 400&#x000d7; magnifications. (E) NPCs were treated with 1 mM VPA for 48 h in the presence of 10 ng/ml bFGF. Cells were processed for immunofluorescent labeling to detect the presence of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>(green) or BrdU (red). Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI. Magnification is 1200&#x000d7;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>VPA activates the ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway and induces differentiation and inhibition of proliferation via &#x003b2;-catenin-mediated accumulation of Ras in NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF</title><p>The epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) most often mediates activation of the ERK pathway by extracellular stimuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. Although, in this study, the ERK pathway was activated by VPA, we were surprised to find that EGFR levels were reduced by VPA treatment in NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). The VPA-induced decrease in EGFR levels was convincingly seen in the time course of VPA treatment after treatment with 1 mM VPA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). VPA regulates the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin pathway by direct binding and inhibition of GSK3&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. In this study, we also observed an increase in the level of phospho-Ser-9-GSK3 (p-GSK3&#x003b2;), an inactive form of GSK3&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], and &#x003b2;-catenin following VPA treatment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). It is also known that Ras protein levels are subject to regulation by the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin pathway in several cell types, including primary hepatocytes, and &#x003b2;-catenin has been identified as a mediator in that process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Here, we found that the level of Ras protein was significantly up-regulated in NPCs treated with VPA, leading to an increase in p-GSK3&#x003b2; and its target, &#x003b2;-catenin (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). The role of &#x003b2;-catenin in the regulation of Ras was further indicated by similar patterns of increase in Ras and &#x003b2;-catenin levels during the time course of VPA treatment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of VPA or &#x003b2;-catenin on EGFR, &#x003b2;-catenin, and Ras regulation</bold>. (A-B) NPCs grown in 10 ng/ml bFGF were treated with 1 mM VPA for 48 h or different periods of time. (C-D) NPCs were transfected with pcDNA3.0 or Flag-&#x003b2;-catenin-pcDNA3.0 and grown in the presence of 10 ng/ml bFGF. (A-C) Whole-cell lysates were then subjected to immunoblotting for detection of p-GSK3&#x003b2; (Ser-9), &#x003b2;-catenin, Pan-Ras, p-ERK, p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>, Tuj1, EGFR, or &#x003b2;-actin. (D) Immunofluorescent labeling was performed for Flag or BrdU. Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-4"/></fig><p>To identify the role of &#x003b2;-catenin in the regulation of the Ras-ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway and subsequent stimulation of differentiation and inhibition of proliferation induced by VPA in NPCs, we measured the effect of overexpression of &#x003b2;-catenin. Overexpression of &#x003b2;-catenin increased ERK activity and Ras protein level and induced expression of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>and Tuj1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). Cells overexpressing &#x003b2;-catenin were morphologically differentiated and BrdU-negative (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref>). Therefore, &#x003b2;-catenin is an important factor for both differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in cortical E14 NPCs and those physiological responses are simultaneously and independently controlled by &#x003b2;-catenin.</p><p>The role of &#x003b2;-catenin in the VPA-induced expression of Tuj1 and p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>in NPCs was further investigated by measurement of the effects of &#x003b2;-catenin siRNA. We observed that the VPA-induced increase in Ras was reduced following &#x003b2;-catenin knockdown (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). ERK activation, and subsequent induction of Tuj1 and p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>, was also reduced by &#x003b2;-catenin knockdown (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>), indicating that &#x003b2;-catenin, at least in part, mediates the effect of VPA on the activation of the ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>-Tuj1 pathway via stabilization of Ras. VPA-induced reduction in EGFR levels was not affected by &#x003b2;-catenin knockdown. The role of &#x003b2;-catenin in VPA-induced differentiation and inhibition of proliferation was also examined (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). Immunocytochemical analysis revealed that &#x003b2;-catenin siRNA significantly reduced VPA-mediated induction of Tuj1 in NPCs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). In contrast, the number of BrdU-positive cells, which initially decreased in the presence of VPA, was marginally increased by VPA treatment following silencing of &#x003b2;-catenin (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>; quantitative data are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of &#x003b2;-catenin knockdown on Ras-ERK pathway activation and VPA-induced differentiation and inhibition of proliferation</bold>. NPCs were transfected with 100 nM control siRNA or &#x003b2;-catenin siRNA prior to treatment with 1 mM VPA for 48 h. (A) Whole-cell lysates were subjected to immunoblotting to detect presence of &#x003b2;-catenin, Pan-Ras, p-ERK, p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>, Tuj1, EGFR, or &#x003b2;-actin. (B-C) Immunofluorescent labeling of Tuj1or BrdU. Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>VPA independently induces differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in NPCs in the developing rat brain</title><p>To understand the physiological relevance of the effects of VPA observed <italic>in vitro</italic>, we administered VPA to E13.5 rat embryos and examined the effect on differentiation and proliferation in the cerebral cortex. In the absence of VPA, the immunofluorescent labeling patterns of proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) and Tuj1 in the cerebral cortex of the developing rat embryo were distinct and non-overlapping (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). In control embryos injected with PBS alone, Tuj1 staining was predominantly localized to the cortical plate (CP) area, where differentiated neuronal cells reside. However, PCNA staining was primarily localized to the subventricular zone (SVZ) and the intermediate zone (IMZ), where neural stem/progenitor cells reside (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>; left panel). The number of cells that had differentiated into neurons was significantly increased by VPA, to the extent that both the area occupied by Tuj1-positive cells and the intensity of the Tuj1 staining were significantly increased in the CP region (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). In contrast, the intensity and number of PCNA-positive cells were significantly reduced by VPA in the SVZ and IMZ of the cerebral cortex (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>); of the cerebral cortical cells induced to differentiate by VPA treatment, none were PCNA-positive. Demonstration of differentiation and proliferation in cells of the VPA-treated cerebral cortex was also carried out <italic>in vitro</italic>, and similar distinct patterns of Tuj1 and BrdU staining were observed in the VPA-treated NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of VPA on differentiation and proliferation in cerebral cortex of the developing embryo</bold>. (A) Coronal sections of E15.5 rat embryo cerebral cortex immunofluorescently labelled for Tuj1 (green) and PCNA (red). (B) Rats at E13.5 of gestation were intravenously injected with 200 mg/kg VPA or PBS at 0 and 24 h and sacrificed. Immunofluorescence labeling of Tuj1 (green) and PCNA (red) was performed on coronal sections of embryonic brains of the E15.5 rat. The three layers of the cerebral cortex &#x02013; the cortical plate (CP), the intermediate zone (IMZ), and the subventricular zone (SVZ) above the lateral ventricle (LV)- can be distinguished. The white arrow indicates the direction of migration of the differentiating cells (bar = 25 &#x003bc;m). (C) NPCs from E14 embryos were incubated in the presence of 10 ng/ml bFGF in the presence or absence of 1 mM VPA for 48 h. Immunofluorescence labeling was performed with anti-Tuj1 and anti-BrdU. Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-6"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In the present study, we found that NPCs undergo neuronal differentiation and inhibition of proliferation following treatment with 1 mM of the commonly prescribed antiepileptic drug VPA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. We chose 1 mM VPA because this concentration is non-toxic to the NPCs in our current study and to hippocampal neuronal progenitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The VPA amount applied to the animals, 200 mg/kg, is identical to that used to achieve whole-brain levels of 1.0&#x02013;1.5 mM by chronic application [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>We investigated the mechanism by which VPA regulates differentiation and inhibition of proliferation. The role of VPA in the exclusive <italic>in vivo </italic>regulation of differentiation and proliferation of NPCs suggest an application for VPA in the production of functional neurons for therapeutic use in patients. Our study also provides a mechanism that may aid in validating the proposed use of VPA as an anti-tumor and neuroprotective agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. VPA induced both differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in NPCs by overcoming the effect of bFGF, a factor which promotes growth/proliferation and suppresses differentiation, through the common ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway. The VPA-induced inhibition of proliferation was suppressed by the MEK inhibitor PD98059, indicating a role for activation of the ERK pathway in the inhibition of proliferation by VPA. Participation of the ERK pathway in inhibition of proliferation is frequently accompanied by induction of the cell cycle inhibitory factor p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]; p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>was also induced in the VPA-treated NPCs. The role of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>in inhibition of proliferation by VPA is also shown by release of the VPA-induced inhibition of proliferation by p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>siRNA. The role of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>as a potent anti-proliferation factor was further shown by loss of BrdU incorporation in most cells in which p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>had been induced by VPA.</p><p>A significant decrease in the level of Tuj1 following siRNA-mediated p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>knockdown, demonstrated by both biochemical and immunocytochemical analyses, suggests that p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>may also be involved in the regulation of differentiation and inhibition of proliferation. It is clear that both inhibition of proliferation and differentiation of NPCs stimulated by VPA occur through the ERK pathway-dependent induction of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>.</p><p>We have shown that activation of the ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway by VPA did not occur via the segment of the pathway involving EGFR but via the segment involving &#x003b2;-catenin. Although EGFR has been identified as a target of Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin in liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>], EGFR was reduced by VPA in NPCs. The mechanism by which <italic>EGFR </italic>transcription is inhibited by VPA is unknown; however, it has been established that <italic>EGFR </italic>transcription is repressed by bone morphogenetic protein 4 (BMP4), an alternative transcription target of &#x003b2;-catenin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>], in NPCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. We observed significant induction of BMP4 in the VPA-treated NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF (data not shown). These data suggest that the VPA-induced decrease in EGFR in NPCs may be acquired through induction of BMP4.</p><p>VPA directly inhibits GSK3&#x003b2; resulting in activation of the &#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] and &#x003b2;-catenin is, in turn, involved in regulation of the ERK pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Evidence for the role of &#x003b2;-catenin in VPA-induced activation of the ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway, and subsequent effects on differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in NPCs, was seen in the reduction of the effects of VPA, including ERK activation and induction of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>and Tuj1, following siRNA-mediated &#x003b2;-catenin knockdown. The &#x003b2;-catenin-mediated activation of the ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway following VPA treatment may be attributed to upregulation of Ras, suggested by the increase in the level of Ras seen after &#x003b2;-catenin overexpression. The VPA-induced increase in the level of Ras may be due to the stabilization of &#x003b2;-catenin as a result of inhibition of GSK3?. Increases in Ras following modulation of the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway have been demonstrated in various cell types, including primary hepatocytes, and &#x003b2;-catenin has been identified as an important mediator of that process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Regulation of Ras protein levels by the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin system is mediated by polyubiquitination and proteasomal degradation [Kim et al., 2008, Journal of Cell Science, In print]. Differentiation and proliferation occur independently in the cerebellar cortex of the developing embryo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]; however, the mechanism(s) underlying the differential regulation of the two processes has not been described. In this study, we found that differentiation and proliferation occurred independently in regions of the developing brain of embryos treated with VPA. We saw no BrdU-positive cells among Tuj1-positive NPCs following VPA treatment. We also did not observe any proliferating cells among differentiated NPCs stimulated to differentiate by &#x003b2;-catenin overexpression or by VPA treatment to express increased levels of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>. These results indicate that mutually exclusive patterns of differentiation and proliferation during neuronal differentiation and development may be regulated via the common Ras-ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>pathway involving &#x003b2;-catenin.</p><p>However, the effects of VPA, particularly its effect on proliferation, were modest or only partially inhibited by increases in p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>or siRNA-mediated &#x003b2;-catenin knockdown in several different cases. These results indicate the possibility that VPA-induced differentiation and inhibition of proliferation occur in part via different routes, including, e.g., the pathway affected by inhibition of HDAC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Although we improved the efficiency of transfection by making modifications to the standard method, the limited effectiveness of siRNAs in general may also be a contributing factor in the weak effects seen on differentiation and inhibition of proliferation (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). The concomitant stimulation of differentiation and inhibition of proliferation in NPCs and the developing rat embryo by VPA treatment indicate potential utility for VPA in the treatment of neuroblastomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] and/or in neuronal regeneration.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our results suggest that VPA induces neuronal differentiation and inhibition of proliferation of cortical NPCs at least partly via the Ras-ERK-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>-pathway mediated by &#x003b2;-catenin. We propose that this mechanism of VPA action may contribute to an explanation of its anti-tumor and neuroprotective effects, as well as elucidate its role in the independent regulation of differentiation and proliferation in the cerebral cortex of developing rat embryos. Regulation of Ras stability in neuronal differentiation and inhibition of proliferation may indicate a new role of the protooncoprotein Ras in the differentiation of stem cells and in development.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Primary cerebral cortical progenitor cell culture, transfection, and VPA treatment</title><p>Sprague-Dawley (SD) rats were purchased from KOATECH (Gyeonggi Do, Korea). All animal procedures were approved by the Institutional Review Board of Severance Hospital, Yonsei University College of Medicine. NPCs were isolated from the cerebral cortex of E14 SD rats as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. The isolated cortical cells were plated in dishes coated with 15 &#x003bc;g/ml poly-L-ornithine and 10 &#x003bc;g/ml fibronectin (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) and cultured in N2 medium [DMEM:F12 (1:1) (Invitrogen) containing 100 &#x003bc;M putrescine, 30 nM selenite, 20 nM progesterone, 1.55 mg/ml D-(+)-glucose, 25 &#x003bc;g/ml insulin, 0.1 &#x003bc;g/ml apo-transferrin (Sigma-Aldrich), 0.5 mM Glutamax, 100 IU/ml penicillin, and 100 &#x003bc;g/ml streptomycin] containing 10 ng/ml bFGF (basic Fibroblast Growth Factor; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) in a humidified atmosphere of 95% air/5% CO<sub>2 </sub>at 37&#x000b0;C. NPCs were plated at 4 &#x02013; 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>cells per dish in a 60-mm culture dish and grown to 40% confluence, cells were treated with 0.5 &#x02013; 10 mM (most often 1 mM) VPA for 48 h. To observe the effect of inhibition of MEK, some cultures were co-treated with 20 &#x003bc;M PD98059 (2'-amino-3'-methoxyflavone) (A G. Scientific Inc, San Diego, CA) in addition to VPA. To test the effects of overexpression or knockdown, vectors or siRNAs were transfected into NPCs using Lipofectamine TM 2000 (Invitrogen). Transfections were performed in N2 medium without antibiotics, followed by growth in N2 medium containing 50 IU/ml penicillin and 50 &#x003bc;g/ml streptomycin, prior to treatment with VPA. Cultures were photographed using the ECLIPS TE2000-U Fluorescent microscope (Nikon, Tokyo, Japan) equipped with a digital CCD camera (Diagnostic Instruments, Inc., Sterling Heights, MI).</p></sec><sec><title>VPA Treatment of embryos</title><p>Beginning on embryonic day 13.5 (E13.5) of gestation, rats were intravenously injected with 200 mg/kg VPA (Acros Organics, Belgium) or phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) twice at 24 h intervals, and provided with water containing 15 g/l VPA for 48 h. On day15.5 embryos were collected for subsequent immunohistochemical analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoblot Analysis</title><p>Cells were rinsed with ice-cold PBS and lysed in 1&#x000d7; Laemmli buffer (0.14 M Tris, pH 6.8, containing 2.4 M glycerol, 0.21 M sodium dodecyl sulfate, and 0.3 mM bromophenol blue). Cell lysates were heated at 100&#x000b0;C for 10 min and separated by electrophoresis through 8 &#x02013; 12% SDS-polyacrylamide gels. Following electrophoretic transfer of proteins to nitrocellulose, membranes were blocked in 5% nonfat dry milk in PBS containing 0.1% (v/v) Tween 20 for 30 min at 25&#x000b0;C followed by incubation with anti-p-ERK, anti-p-MEK, anti-p-GSK3&#x003b2; (Ser-9) (Cell Signaling Biotechnology, Beverly, MA), anti-&#x003b2;-catenin (rabbit polyclonal antibody produced in this laboratory), anti-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>, anti-EGFR (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA), anti-p-Raf-1 (Ser-338), anti-pan-Ras (Upstate Biotechnology, Lake Placid, NY), anti-Tuj1 (Covance, Princeton, NJ), or anti-&#x003b2;-actin (Abcam Ltd, MA) antibody followed by horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary anti-rabbit, anti-rat (Calbiochem, La Jolla, CA), or anti-mouse IgG (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA). Protein bands were visualized using enhanced chemiluminescence (ECL; Amersham, Inc, UK) and the LAS-3000 imaging system (Fujifilm, Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunocytochemistry and Immunohistochemistry</title><p>For immunocytochemistry, NPCs were plated on coverslips coated with poly-L-ornithine and fibronectin in 24-well plates at a density of 2 &#x02013; 2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>cells/well. When cultures reached 30% confluence VPA was added to the medium. Where indicated, the cells had been transfected with 100 nM p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>siRNA or &#x003b2;-catenin siRNA for 12 h before VPA treatment. For the proliferation assay, cultures were incubated with 25 &#x003bc;M BrdU (Sigma-Aldrich) for 2.5 h before fixation. Cells were fixed in 70% ethanol for 30 min, washed three times with PBS, and permeabilized by incubation in 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS for 30 min. To measure BrdU incorporation, cells were incubated in 2 M HCl for 30 min and washed three times with PBS. The cells were incubated in blocking solution (10% normal goat serum in PBS) for 30 min followed by incubation with anti-Tuj1, anti-BrdU (Dako Co., Carpinteria, CA), anti-Flag (Sigma-Aldrich), or anti-p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>in blocking solution at 4&#x000b0;C overnight. Cells were washed three times in PBS and incubated with Alexa Fluor 488- or Alexa Fluor 555-conjugated IgG secondary antibody (Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR) at room temperature for 1 h. Nuclei were counterstained by incubation in 1 &#x003bc;g/ml DAPI (4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole; Boehringer Mannheim, Mannheim, Germany) for 10 min followed by exhaustive washing in distilled water. Coverslips were mounted in GelMount (Biomeda, Foster City, CA). Fluorescent labeling was observed using a Radiance 2100 multi-photon imaging system (Bio-Rad Laboratories) and LSM510META (Carl Zeiss, Germany) at excitation wavelengths of 488 nm (Alexa Fluor 488), 543 nm (Alexa Fluor 555), or 405 nm (DAPI). Approximately 300&#x02013;400 cells were counted in each of three independent experiments to quantify relative p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>-, Tuj1-, or BrdU- positive cells. For histological analyses, embryos were fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin for 48 h, dehydrated by serial immersion in alcohols, cleared in xylene, and embedded in paraffin. Four-micron sections were cut using a RM2245 microtome (Leica Microsystems Wetzlar, Germany). Immunohistochemical analysis was performed using Alexa Fluor 555- and 488-conjugated IgG secondary antibodies. Antigen retrieval was performed using citrate buffer, pH 6.0. All incubations were carried out in humidified chambers in the dark. Immunofluorescent labeling of tissue sections was performed using the staining procedure described above.</p></sec><sec><title>Vector and siRNAs</title><p>Flag-&#x003b2;-catenin-pcDNA3.0 was obtained from Dr. Eric R. Fearon of the University of Michigan School of Medicine. Small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) targeting rat p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>(GenBank accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NM_080782">NM_080782</ext-link>) and &#x003b2;-catenin (GenBank accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NM_053357">NM_053357</ext-link>) mRNAs were designed using the template design tool (Ambion, Austin, TX). The <italic>p21</italic><sup><italic>Cip/WAF1 </italic></sup>target sequences are 5'-AGACCAGCCUAACAGATTTTT-3' (431&#x02013;459) and 5'-GAACGGTGGAACTTTGACTTT-3' (136&#x02013;154). <italic>&#x003b2;-catenin </italic>target sequences are 5'-AAGGCTTTTCCCAGTCCTTCA-3' (203&#x02013;223) and 5'-AAGATGATGGTGTGCCAAGTG-3' (1303&#x02013;1323). &#x003b2;-catenin and p21<sup>Cip/WAF1</sup>siRNAs were synthesized by Samchully Pharm Co., LTD (Gyeonggi do, Korea).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>bFGF: basic fibroblast growth factor; BMP4: bone morphogenetic protein 4; CP: cortical plate; ERK: extracellular signal-regulated kinase; GSK3&#x003b2;: glycogen synthase kinase3&#x003b2;; HDAC: histone deacetylase; IMZ: intermediate zone; NPC: neural progenitor cells; Tuj1: class III &#x003b2;-tubulin; PCNA: proliferating cell nuclear antigen; SVZ: subventricular zone; siRNA: small interfering RNA; VPA: valproic acid, 2-propyl-pentanoic acid.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>GAJ, JYY, BSM, DHY, and HYK carried out the experiments. KYC coordinated and wrote the manuscript. SHL, VB, and EA provided reagents and techniques and approved the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>NPCs isolated from E14 embryos retain the capacity to form neurospheres and to differentiate into primary neurons, oligodendrocytes, and astrocytes</bold>. NPCs were isolated as described in Methods. (A) Neurospheres were established as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] and maintained in N2 medium containing bFGF (10 ng/ml) and epidermal growth factor (EGF, 20 ng/ml). Neurospheres were dissociated and re-formed for two passages (P1 and P2, respectively). Neurospheres were subjected to immunocytochemical analyses using anti-Tuj1, anti-glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP), or anti-O4 (oligodendrocyte marker O4) to detect primary neurons, astrocytes, and oligodendrocytes, respectively.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-S1.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>Effects of different concentrations of VPA on morphological differentiation and proliferation of NPCs. NSCs were isolated from rat cerebral cortex at embryonic day 14 (E14) and cultured in N2 medium supplemented with 10 ng/ml bFGF as described in Methods</bold>. At 40% confluence, the cultures were treated with 0, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, or 10 mM VPA and incubated for an additional 48 h. Micrographs were taken using a Nikon ECLIPSE TE2000-U fluorescence microscope at 200&#x000d7; magnification.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-S2.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>Effects of MEK inhibitor PD98059 on the morphological differentiation and proliferation of NPCs. NPCs were grown in medium containing 10 ng/ml bFGF</bold>. Medium was then replaced with fresh medium containing 10 ng/ml bFGF, 20 &#x003bc;M PD98059, and/or 1 mM VPA, as indicated, and cultures were incubated for an additional 48 h. Cultures were photographed and relative numbers of cells were estimated as described in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-S3.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p><bold>Effects of bFGF and VPA on proliferation of NPCs</bold>. This experiment is similar to that shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>. Cells were processed for immunofluorescent labeling of BrdU (red). Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI (blue). Images are 100&#x000d7; magnifications. Right panel: Estimate of the percentage of BrdU-positive cells. Error bars indicate the standard deviation of three independent experiments.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-S4.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional file 5</title><p><bold>Effects of p21<sup>Cip/WAF1 </sup>siRNA on VPA-induced inhibition of proliferation of NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF</bold>. This figure shows the quantitative data for Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref> (lower panel). Relative numbers of BrdU-positive cells were quantified. Error bars indicate the standard deviation of three independent experiments.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-S5.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6"><caption><title>Additional file 6</title><p><bold>Effects of &#x000df;-catenin siRNA on VPA-induced proliferation of NPCs grown in the presence of bFGF</bold>. This  figure  shows  the  quantitative  data  for  Figure  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>.    Relative numbers of BrdU-positive cells were quantified.    Error bars indicate the standard deviation of three independent experiments. </p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-S6.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7"><caption><title>Additional file 7</title><p><bold>Measurements of NPC transfection efficiencies.     </bold> NPCs were  grown  in N2 medium  containing bFGF  (10 ng/ml),  and transfected  with  0,  0.5,  1,  2,  or  3  &#x000b5;g  pEGFP-C1  (Clontech)  as  described  in Methods.    Percentages  of  GFP-positive  cells  were  estimated  24  h  after transfection.    Error  bars  indicate  the  standard  deviation  of  three  independent experiments.  </p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-9-66-S7.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by a Korea Science and Engineering Foundation (KOSEF) grant funded by Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (MIST) of Korea (No. 2005-01564; 2006-02681; R112000078010020). JY Yoon, BS Moon, DW Yang, and HY Kim were supported by a BK21 studentship from the MEST.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perucca</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacological and therapeutic properties of valproate: a summary after 35 years of clinical experience</article-title><source>CNS Drugs</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12269862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00023210-200216100-00004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Haughey</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Regan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiproliferative action of valproate is associated with aberrant expression and nuclear translocation of cyclin D3 during the C6 glioma G1 phase</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2002</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12358724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2002.01081.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaheta</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaelis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cinatl</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Valproate and valproate-analogues: potent tools to fight against cancer</article-title><source>Curr Med Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1417</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12173980</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuendgen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlenk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Knipp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hildebrandt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Steidl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Germing</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gattermann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitor valproic acid as monotherapy or in combination with all-trans retinoic acid in patients with acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16323176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.21552</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlaky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaney</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Valproic acid induces growth arrest, apoptosis, and senescence in medulloblastomas by increasing histone hyperacetylation and regulating expression of p21Cip1, CDK4, and CMYC</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Ther</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1912</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16373706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-05-0184</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rocchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Camerin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Purgato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fronza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianucci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pession</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreri</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p21Waf1/Cip1 is a common target induced by short-chain fatty acid HDAC inhibitors (valproic acid, tributyrin and sodium butyrate) in neuroblastoma cells</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2005</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1139</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15870934</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>PX</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutkind</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Manji</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mood stabilizer valproic acid activates mitogen-activated protein kinases and promotes neurite growth</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>31674</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11418608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M104309200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwabara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mejia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone deacetylase inhibition-mediated neuronal differentiation of multipotent adult neural progenitor cells</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>16659</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15537713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0407643101</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenuwein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Allis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translating the histone code</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>293</volume><fpage>1074</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11498575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1063127</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurvich</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lithium and valproic acid: parallels and contrasts in diverse signaling contexts</article-title><source>Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2002</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12441177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0163-7258(02)00299-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mechanisms of action of valproate in neuropsychiatric disorders: can we see the forest for the trees?</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>2090</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17514356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-007-7079-x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Manji</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo evidence in the brain for lithium inhibition of glycogen synthase kinase-3</article-title><source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12942141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.npp.1300283</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Manji</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Wnt signaling pathway in bipolar disorder</article-title><source>Neuroscientist</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12374432</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bug</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kampfmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Beissert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boehrer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoelzer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottmann</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Valproic acid stimulates proliferation and self-renewal of hematopoietic stem cells</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>2537</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-3011</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chondrogenic differentiation of human mesenchymal stem cells using a thermosensitive poly(N-isopropylacrylamide) and water-soluble chitosan copolymer</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>5743</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15147820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2004.01.051</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phiel</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Guenther</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone deacetylase is a direct target of valproic acid, a potent anticonvulsant, mood stabilizer, and teratogen</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>36734</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11473107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M101287200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Casaccia-Bonnefil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone modifications affect timing of oligodendrocyte progenitor differentiation in the developing rat brain</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15897262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200412101</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurvich</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsygankova</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinkoth</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone deacetylase is a target of valproic acid-mediated cellular differentiation</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14871841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-03-0799</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mione</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnavelas</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic fibroblast growth factor prolongs the proliferation of rat cortical progenitor cells in vitro without altering their cell cycle parameters</article-title><source>Cereb Cortex</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9177761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/7.4.293</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian neural stem cells</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>1433</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.287.5457.1433</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahk</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmen</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Surh</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>APC inhibits ERK pathway activation and cellular proliferation induced by RAS</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16478791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.02779</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jho</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Surh</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Axin inhibits extracellular signal-regulated kinase pathway by Ras degradation via beta-catenin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>14482</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17374607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M611129200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukaszewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Savatier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contrasting effects of basic fibroblast growth factor and neurotrophin 3 on cell cycle kinetics of mouse cortical stem cells</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>6610</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12151540</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maric</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Maric</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prospective cell sorting of embryonic rat neural stem cells and neuronal and glial progenitors reveals selective effects of basic fibroblast growth factor and epidermal growth factor on self-renewal and differentiation</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12514221</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raballo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyn-Cook</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leckman</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccarino</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic fibroblast growth factor (Fgf2) is necessary for cell proliferation and neurogenesis in the developing cerebral cortex</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>5012</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10864959</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enarsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Erlandsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsberg-Nilsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular signal-regulated protein kinase signaling is uncoupled from initial differentiation of central nervous system stem cells to neurons</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12496361</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Juliano</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct mechanisms mediate the initial and sustained phases of integrin-mediated activation of the Raf/MEK/mitogen-activated protein kinase cascade</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>27268</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9765250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.42.27268</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ERK pathway involves positive and negative regulations of HT-29 colorectal cancer cell growth by extracellular zinc</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>G1181</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12816758</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Creson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Manji</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mood stabilizer valproate promotes ERK pathway-dependent cortical neuronal growth and neurogenesis</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>6590</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15269271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5747-03.2004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Both ERK and Wnt/beta-catenin pathways are involved in Wnt3a-induced proliferation</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15615777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.01601</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherwinski</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Raf-induced proliferation or cell cycle arrest is determined by the level of Raf activity with arrest mediated by p21Cip1</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>5598</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9271435</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCubrey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steelman</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Terrian</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Milella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tafuri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Roles of the Raf/MEK/ERK pathway in cell growth, malignant transformation and drug resistance</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2007</year><volume>1773</volume><fpage>1263</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17126425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2006.10.001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marinova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Leeds</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic neuroprotective effects of lithium and valproic acid or other histone deacetylase inhibitors in neurons: roles of glycogen synthase kinase-3 inhibition</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2576</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5467-07.2008</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okano</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Okano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of Hu and heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein K in neuronal differentiation through p21 mRNA post-transcriptional regulation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>12690</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15671036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M411119200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Seong</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular zinc stimulates ERK-dependent activation of p21(Cip/WAF1) and inhibits proliferation of colorectal cancer cells</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>2002</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12381673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjp.0704909</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Apte</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Micsenyi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotsagrelos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranganathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Monga</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Michalopoulos</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Monga</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidermal growth factor receptor: a novel target of the Wnt/beta-catenin pathway in liver</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2005</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16012954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2005.04.013</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Beddington</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Harland</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wnt signaling in Xenopus embryos inhibits bmp4 expression and activates neural development</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>3149</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10601040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.13.23.3149</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcion</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Halilagic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Faissner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>ffrench-Constant</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Generation of an environmental niche for neural stem cell development by the extracellular matrix molecule tenascin C</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2004</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>3423</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15226258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01202</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lillien</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Raphael</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BMP and FGF regulate the development of EGF-responsive neural progenitor cells</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2000</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>4993</fpage><lpage>5005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11044412</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Manji</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mood-stabilizing agent valproate inhibits the activity of glycogen synthase kinase-3</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>1999</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1327</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10037507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2000.0721327.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jope</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CREB DNA binding activity is inhibited by glycogen synthase kinase-3 beta and facilitated by lithium</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2001</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1219</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11579131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2001.00495.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nadarajah</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Alifragis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnavelas</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ventricle-directed migration in the developing cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11850632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn813</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nadarajah</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnavelas</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modes of neuronal migration in the developing cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12042877</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chopp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proliferation and differentiation of progenitor cells in the cortex and the subventricular zone in the adult rat after focal cerebral ischemia</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2001</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(01)00117-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaelis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suhan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cinatl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Driever</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cinatl</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Valproic acid and interferon-alpha synergistically inhibit neuroblastoma cell growth in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Int J Oncol</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1795</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15547719</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thyroid hormone stimulates gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase in the developing rat cerebra and in astroglial cultures</article-title><source>J Neurosci Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16302185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jnr.20657</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>