<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238242</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639665</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">003800032008</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Hypothesis</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of regulatory elements in 16S rRNA gene of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> species isolated from water sample</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>Shipra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Vijai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Vipin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>Praveen Chandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>Rajeev</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>Vaishali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Vijayta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>Anil Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Biotechnology and Bioinformatics Division, BIOBRAINZ, 566/29 J, Jai Prakash Nagar, Alambagh, Lucknow 226005, U.P., India</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Biotechnology, Madhav Institute of Technology and Science, Gwaliar</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Present address: National Botanical Research Institute, Rana Pratap Marg, Lucknow, U.P. India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Anil Kumar Rawat: <email>akrbz@rediffmail.com</email>Phone: 91 0522 4042284</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open-access article, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium,for non-commercial purposes, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A bacterial strain, designated AcBz01, was isolated from a water sample collected from Gomti River, Lucknow, India,and identified using a molecular approach. On the basis of the bacterial 16S rRNA gene sequence phylogeny and comparison of thisgene sequence with sequences in Ribosomal Database project II, evidence given in this study, it is proposed that isolate isclosely related to members of the genus <italic>Acinetobacter</italic>. Identification and annotation of regulatory elements in the 16S rRNA geneand characterization of their interaction with the respective transcription factor can provide basis for better understanding ofthe mechanism of network of gene interaction of functionally related genes. The identification of such sites is relevant forlocating promoter boundary of a gene and it also allows the prediction of specific gene expression pattern and response todisturbances in a known signaling pathway. Computational identification of regulatory elements and Transcription Factor withtheir binding sites in 16S rRNA gene of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. was performed using BPROM tool. We predicted the regulatory elementsare TSS, -10 box, -35 box and three Transcription Factor (narP, ompR and fadR) with their binding sites in the upstream regionof 16S rRNA gene of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. AcBz01. The GenBank accession number for 16S rRNA gene of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. AcBz01 is<bold>EU931637</bold>.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>RNA polymerase binding site</kwd><kwd>16S ribosomal RNA gene</kwd><kwd>transcription factor</kwd><kwd>promoter region</kwd><kwd><italic>Acinetobacter</italic></kwd><kwd>PCR</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>Gomti, one of the rivers in India, represents a unique niche for many animals and plants in Lucknow, which is one of the cities of India. In recent years, it has received great attention from the public, due to its potential for biodiversity and biological conservation. We initiated a systematic screening programme to catalogue the microbial composition of Gomti river water in Lucknow. The traditional identification of bacteria on the basis of phenotypic characteristics is generally not as accurate as identification based on genotypic methods. Comparison of the bacterial 16S rRNA gene sequence has emerged as a preferred genetic technique [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>]. In this work, we reported the isolation and identification of a previously unknown bacterium from Gomti, for which the name <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. AcBz01 is proposed with the help of 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis.</p><p><italic>Acinetobacter</italic> species have been attracting interest in both environmental and biotechnological applications: they are known to be involved in biodegradation of a number of different pollutants and in the extra and intracellular production of a number of economically valuable products [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>]. In 16S ribosomal gene, transcription process begins with binding of RNA polymerase to DNA sequence in the promoter region, which is located immediate upstream of the transcription start site (TSS). A typical prokaryotic promoter region is thought to comprise of two hexameric motifs TATAAT and TTGACA centered at or near -10 and -35 positions relative to the TSS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. These sequence motifs were identified based on the analysis of a large number of promoter sequences and represent consensus sequences. It has been seen that a wide variety of sequences similar to these representative motifs are present in promoter. Today, how RNA polymerase locates these binding sites in the non-promoter DNA region remains a field of intensive investigation.</p><p>Several computational approaches have been reported for the identification of regulatory elements during the last decade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>]. The regulatory elements TSS, -10 box, -35 box and known Transcription Factor (TF) with their binding sites in the upstream sequence of bacterial 16S rRNA gene of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic>r sp. AcBz01 were predicted by using BPROM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>] tool sited at Softberry.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methodology</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Culturing of bacteria</title><p>Water sample collected from Gomti River in Lucknow, India was serially diluted and spread onto peptone/Beef extract/Nacl/Agar-Agar palates and kept for incubation at 30&#x000b0;C under anaerobic conditions. Different single colonies of bacterial strains were picked and further grown and subcultured several times to obtain a pure culture.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>DNA isolation of bacteria</title><p>Pure culture of the target bacteria was grown overnight in liquid NB medium for the isolation of genomic DNA, which was done as per the method described by Hiney and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>] with some modification.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>PCR amplification 16S rDNA gene</title><p>PCR reaction was performed in a gradient thermal cycler (Eppendorf, Germany). The universal primers (Forward primer 5'- AGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG -3' and reverse primer 5'- CTTGTGCGGGCCCCCGTCAATTC-3') were used for the amplification of the 16S rDNA gene fragment. The reaction mixture of 50 &#x003bc;l consisted of 10 ng of genomic DNA, 2.5 U of Taq DNA polymerase, 5 &#x003bc;l of 10 X PCR amplification buffer (100 mM Tris-HCl, 500 mM KCl pH-8.3) , 200&#x003bc;M dNTP, 10 p moles each of the two universal primers and 1.5mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. Amplification was done by initial denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 3 minutes, followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 940C for 30 second, annealing temperature of primers was 55&#x000b0;C for 30 second and extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 1 minute. Final extension was at 72&#x000b0;C for 10 minutes</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Agarose gel electrophoresis</title><p>10 &#x003bc;l of the reaction mixture was then analyzed by submarine gel electrophoresis using 1.0 % agarose with ethidium bromide at 8V/cm and the reaction product was visualized under Gel doc/UV transilluminator</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Purification of PCR product</title><p>PCR product was purified by Qiagen gel extraction kit using the following protocol: Excise the DNA fragment from the agarose gel with a clean sharp scalpel. Weigh the gel slice in an eppendorf. Add 3 volumes of buffer QG to 1 volume of gel (100 mg &#x0223c; 100 &#x003bc;l). Incubate at 50&#x000b0;C for 10 minutes. To help dissolve gel, mix by vortexing the tube every 2-3 min during the incubation. After the gel slice has dissolved completely, check that the colour of the mixture is yellow. Add 1 gel volume of Iso-propanol to the sample and mix. Place a QIAquick spin column in a provided 2 ml collection tube. To make the DNA bind to the column bind, apply the sample to the QIAquick column, and centrifuge for one minute. Discard flow-through and place QIAquick column back in the same collection tube. To wash, add 0.75 ml of buffer PE to QIAquick column and centrifuge for 1 minute. Discard the flow-through and centrifuge the QIAquick column for an additional 1 minute at 10,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>. Place QIAquick column into a clean 1.5 ml eppendorf. To elute DNA, add 50 &#x003bc;l of buffer EB (10mM Tris-Cl, pH 8.5) to the center of the QIAquick membrane and centrifuge the column for 1 min.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>DNA sequencing of the 16S rDNA fragment</title><p>A total 100ng concentration of 16S rDNA amplified PCR product was used for the sequencing with the single 16S rDNA 27F Forward primer: 5'- AGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG-3` by ABI DNA sequencer (Applied Biosystem Inc).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Computational analysis</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Identification of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic>r sp.</title><p>A comparison of the 16S rRNA sequence of test strain with sequences in the non-redundant collection (Genbank, DDBJ, EMBL &#x00026; PDB) using BLAST [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>] and Ribosomal Database Project II [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>] databases, has been done. The 16S rRNA gene sequence of the test strain was aligned with selected members of the genus <italic>Acinetobacter</italic>; sequences were obtained from BLAST hits, using multiple sequence alignment programme ClustalW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. A phylogenetic tree was drawn, using neighbor-joining method for this alignment by using ClustalW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Regulatory elements analysis</title><p>We identified upstream DNA sequence region (17883 nt to 18443 nt) of 16S rRNA gene from the complete genome of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. strain ADP1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>] as a input sequence for the regulatory elements analysis because this strain has maximum similarity (99% identity) with proposed <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. AcBz01 at 16S rRNA gene sequence level. Bacterial promoter prediction program, BPROM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>] identified position of promoter i.e. Transcription start site (TSS), -10 box and -35 box in input sequence as well as predicts know Transcription Factor (TF) with their binding sites.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>rRNA-based analysis is a central method in microbiology, used not only to explore microbial diversity but also as a method for bacterial strain identification. The genomic DNA was extracted from isolated bacterial strain AcBz01 and universal primers 27F and 939R were used for the amplification and sequencing of the 16S rRNA gene fragment. A total of 805 bp of the 16S rRNA gene was sequenced and used for the identification of isolated bacterial strain. Ribosomal Database Project II (RDP) Classifier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>] tool with confidence threshold of 95% has classified that the test strain belongs to genus <italic>Acinetobacter</italic>. A 16S rRNA based phylogenetic tree showing the relationships between strain AcBz01 and representatives of the family <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. It is evident from phylogenetic analysis of 16S rRNA gene that isolate AcBz01 represents a novel genomic species in the genus <italic>Acinetobacter</italic>.</p><p>Genomic regulatory elements are frequently represented by DNA motifs. As such these representations are general and can be used to describe any class of short DNA sequence elements. Here we primarily discuss the transcriptional regulatory elements, more specifically, promoter elements and DNA binding sites that are bound by the TFs. In the non coding upstream sequences of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. AcBz01, the 16s rRNA gene promoter contains three signals, Transcription Start Site (TSS), -10 box (GAGTAACAT) and -35 box (TTGACT) at 321 bp, 306 bp, 287 bp and three TF binding sites at 302 bp, 308 bp, 317 bp relative to the start position of the input sequence, respectively shown in Figure 2 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary material</xref>). The detail of the three known TF narP, ompR and fadR are listed in table 1 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary material</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>All bacterial species possess at least one copy of the 16S rRNA gene, which contains highly conserved as well as hyper variable nucleic acid sequences. Therefore the PCR targeting conserved nucleic acid sequence of 16S rRNA gene of bacterial isolate as a molecular tool is used to identify the presence of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. in water sample from Gomti River. Sequencing of 16S rRNA gene may also explain the discrepancy between phenotypic identification and the antibiotic susceptibility profile of a microorganism. Upstream region of 16S rRNA gene of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. AcBz01 containing promoter region, have three signals, TSS, -10box (GAGTAACAT), -35box (TTGACT) and three known TF narP, ompR and fadR with their binding sites.</p><p>It can be stated that these data provide a backbone to understand the basis of transcription regulation mechanism of 16S rRNA gene in <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> Sp. AcBz01.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><caption><title>Data 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="97320630003173S1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e372" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The present work was supported by a joint venture of the laboratory facilities at Chromous Biotech Pvt. Ltd. Bangalore, India and Biotechnology and Bioinformatics Division, BIOBRAINZ, Lucknow, U.P., India.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>III</surname><given-names>Clarridge</given-names></name></person-group><source>Clinical Microbiology Reviews</source><year>2004</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>840</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15489351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-El-Haleem</surname><given-names>Desouky</given-names></name></person-group><source>African Journal of Biotechnology</source><year>2003</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>71</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Nucleic Acid Res</source><year>1987</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2343</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3550697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><source>Methods Cell Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>337</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18485306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.softberry.com/berry.html">http://www.softberry.com/berry.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1575477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J Comput Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>203</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10890397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>5261</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/">http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/clustalW">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/clustalW</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>5766</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15514110</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>A Cladogram, using neighbor-joining method of selected 16S rRNA gene sequences of the genus <italic>Acinetobacter</italic>, obtained from BLAST hits, showing relationships between strain AcBz01 and some closely related representative members.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="97320630003173F1"/></fig></floats-group></article>