<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238254</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639686</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">003000032008</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Database</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A database of natural products and chemical entities from marine habitat</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>Padavala Ajay</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Puppala</surname><given-names>Suma Sree</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aswini</surname><given-names>Satyavarapu Lakshmi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vani</surname><given-names>Metta Ramya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Chinta Narasimha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prasanna</surname><given-names>Tallapragada</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>ProGene Biosciences, Institute of Bioinformatics and Research Centre, 103, Bharat Towers, Dwaraka Nagar, Visakhapatnam - 530 016, India</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Biotechnology, Godavari Institute of Engineering and Technology, Rajahmundry, India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Padavala Ajay Babu: <email>ajay_pgb@progenebio.in</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>11</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open-access article, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, 		for non-commercial purposes, provided the original author and source are credited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>					Marine compound database consists of marine natural products and chemical entities, collected from various literature sources,            which are known to possess bioactivity against human diseases. The database is constructed using html code. The 12 categories            of 182 compounds are provided with the source, compound name, 2-dimensional structure, bioactivity and clinical trial            information. The database is freely available online and can be accessed at             <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.progenebio.in/mcdb/index.htm">http://www.progenebio.in/mcdb/index.htm</ext-link>                  </p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>database</kwd><kwd>marine compounds</kwd><kwd>natural products</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>It is a known fact that water occupies at least three-quarters (3/4ths) of the earth's surface. Of this, more than 70&#x000a2; is themarine water. Hence, marine waters form the reservoirs for a large variety of number of organisms. Different species oforganisms produce various metabolites. Several thousands of these compounds have been claimed to possess medicinalproperties. Metabolites used to treat cancer or other dreadful diseases are of considerable interest for the scientificcommunities. The active metabolites are isolated from different marine organisms and can be used directly as drugsor as pharmaceutical agents. Several of these metabolites might offer a natural key to unlock the complications ofseveral diseases. Because of the immense biological diversity in the sea, it has been recognized that a variety of naturalproducts and novel chemical entities exist in oceans and that they possess biological activities with greater efficacy andspecificity against human diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>].</p><p>Diseases like cancer, malaria, tuberculosis and several other disorders are affecting large number of people world wide.Many of the marine organism derived compounds are known to exhibit therapeutic potential and are more potent againstvarious disorders. For example, it has been reported that cone snail venoms are highly potent and act as selective peptideantagonists or agonists of ligand or voltage-gated ion channels and G-protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>]. Similarly, &#x003b1;- and &#x003b1;A-conotoxins, are known to competitivelyinhibit nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChR) whereas &#x003c8;-conotoxins show noncompetitive inhibition of this family ofreceptors. Several such studies have been reported in literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>]. Information on marine compounds is of prime interest to researchers involved in drug discovery, natural products isolation, purification and characterization, or marine biology research. Hence, initially, we created adatabase of 182 natural products and chemical entities from marine habitat that contains information related to theorganism, derived compound, the disease against which the compound is active and the status of clinical trials, if any.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methodology</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Construction of Marine Compound Database</title><p>The database hereafter referred as MCDB (Marine Compound Database), is constructed using html and can be accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.progenebio.in/mcdb/index.htm"> http://www.progenebio.in/mcdb/index.htm</ext-link>. Data has been collected from various literature sources like NCBI (National Centre for Biotechnology Information) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>], Google Scholar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>], ScienceDirect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>] etc.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Features of Marine Compound Database</title><p>MCDB contains about 182 compounds known to exhibit biological activity against human diseases are kept conveniently under 12 different categories (Table 1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary material</xref>) with number of entries under eachcategory, given in parentheses. The additional advantage of MCDB is that the compounds from MCDB can be utilized for various scientific purposes and that these compounds, reported at a single place, could be useful in testing other diseases apart from the mentioned disease in the database, thus indicating the importance of medicinal values of the compounds. A screen-shot of the database is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. The database architecture contains source of the compound, trade name, 2-dimensional structure, respective biological activity, clinical trial information and literature references, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Utility</title><p>The database finds utility in the scientific community for a quick review of the marine organisms and their compoundsfor drug discovery and treatment. MCDB also contains information on clinical trials; therefore, the user shall have aquick look on the compounds that entered in any phase of clinical trials. References are provided for each compound soas to track the published data.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The main objective of MCDB is to provide an easy access of marine compounds to researchers working in marinelaboratories for novel drug discovery and to other users of scientific discipline. Database categorization reveals a clearmechanism of data access, and is more user-friendly. The database shall be updated periodically and released with thecontinuous updates of new compounds</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><caption><title>Data 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="97320630003142S1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x1d46020N0x406ba00" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Proksch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2002</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12111137</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulaj</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>Curr Pharm Des</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1249</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10903392</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haefner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Drug Discov Today</source><year>2003</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>536</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12821301</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kijjoa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawangwong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mar Drugs</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>73</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">     http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.scholar.google.com">     www.scholar.google.com</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.sciencedirect.com">     www.sciencedirect.com</ext-link></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Screenshot image of &#x02019;Marine Compounds from Tunicates&#x02018; page of MCDB</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="97320630003142F1"/></fig></floats-wrap></article>