<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Reprod Biol Endocrinol</journal-id><journal-title>Reproductive Biology and Endocrinology : RB&#x00026;E</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1477-7827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19077325</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639581</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1477-7827-6-63</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7827-6-63</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Changes in the reproductive function and developmental phenotypes in mice following intramuscular injection of an activin betaA-expressing plasmid</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Mi-Nyeu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>beautymn@hanmail.net</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Moon Nyeo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>moon0817@empal.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Hoi Kyung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>hoikyung77@hanmail.net</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Chunghee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>choch@gist.ac.kr</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>Kelly E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>k-mayo@northwestern.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Byung-Nam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ocean@catholic.ac.kr</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Life Science/Research Center for Biopharmaceutical Lead Molecule, The Catholic University of Korea, Bucheon, 420-743, Korea</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Life Science, Kwangju Institute of Science and Technology (K-JIST), Kwangju, Korea</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Biochemistry, Molecular Biology and Cell Biology, Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois 60208, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rbej.com/content/6/1/63"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Kim et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kim et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Kim               Mi-Nyeu                              beautymn@hanmail.net            </dc:author><dc:title>            Changes in the reproductive function and developmental phenotypes in mice following intramuscular injection of an activin betaA-expressing plasmid         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Reproductive Biology and Endocrinology 6(1): 63-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1477-7827(2008)6:1&#x0003c;63&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1477-7827</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The TGF-beta family protein activin has numerous reported activities with some uncertainty in the reproductive axis and development. The precise roles of activin in in vivo system were investigated using a transient gain of function model.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>To this end, an expression plasmid, pCMV-rAct, with the activin betaA cDNA fused to the cytomegalovirus promoter, was introduced into muscle of the female adult mice by direct injection.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Activin betaA mRNA was detected in the muscle by RT-PCR and subsequent Southern blot analysis. Activin betaA was also detected, and western blot analysis revealed a relatively high level of serum activin with correspondingly increased FSH. In the pCMV-rAct-injected female mice, estrus stage within the estrous cycle was extended. Moreover, increased numbers of corpora lutea and a thickened granulosa cell layer with a small antrum in tertiary follicles within the ovary were observed. When injected female mice were mated with males of proven fertility, a subset of embryos died in utero, and most of those that survived exhibited increased body weight.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Taken together, our data reveal that activin betaA can directly influence the estrous cycle, an integral part of the reproduction in female mice and activin betaA can also influence the embryo development as an endocrine fashion.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Activin and inhibin were first identified as gonadal protein hormones that regulate the synthesis and secretion of follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) in the pituitary gland which in turn controls the gonadal function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. They are members of the transforming growth factor-&#x003b2; superfamily of proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Activin and inhibin are generated through the combinatorial assembly of an &#x003b1; subunit and two highly related &#x003b2; subunits, &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>or &#x003b2;<sub>B </sub>to generate inhibin A (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>), inhibin B (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>B</sub>), activin A (&#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>&#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>), activin B (&#x003b2;<sub>B</sub>&#x003b2;<sub>B</sub>), and activin AB (&#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>&#x003b2;<sub>B</sub>). Recently, activin &#x003b2;<sub>C</sub>, &#x003b2;<sub>D</sub>, &#x003b2;<sub>E </sub>chains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], and partially characterized activin AC (&#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>: &#x003b2;<sub>C</sub>) and activin BC (&#x003b2;<sub>B</sub>: &#x003b2;<sub>C</sub>) proteins have been reported, although they are not expressed in the gonad [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Outside the gonad, activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>was reported to be expressed in early pre- and postimplantation mouse embryos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], and to be involved in the formation of mesoderm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], and in secondary body axis formation in chick [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], zebrafish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], and amphibians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>is also expressed in the pituitary, placenta, bone marrow, brain, and spinal cord although precise functions of extragonadal activin are unclear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p><p>In the reproductive axis, it has been recognized that activin potentially has an endocrine and paracrine (or autocrine) functions. The endocrine function of activin was inferred from the fact that correlation between high activin and high FSH in the mid cycle and luteo-follicular transition period was observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The paracrine function of activin was inferred from the fact that antibodies to activin B suppressed FSH secretion from cultured rat pituitary cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Another paracrine role of activin related to the reproduction is controversially reported in the ovary within which activin inhibited follicular development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] whereas activin induced proliferation of the granulosa cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Relating with the pregnancy, activin has been reported to have effects on embryonic development. Activin A increased the rate of morula formation and the velocity of embryonic cleavage in mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. And activin also influenced body axis formation in chick [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], zebrafish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], and amphibian [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] during embryo development as explained above. Our comprehensive understanding of the activin function which is mainly based on the in vitro experiment, however, is still uncertain in the context of individual organism. Thus, we need to reinvestigate the actual functions in the in vivo system. Transgenic animal is a good model for this.</p><p>As to the actual functions of activin, previous studies have attempted in the intact organism through gene disruption or transgenic overexpression approaches. However, perinatal or early embryonic lethality is observed in these cases, so further studies for the activin functions are limited in adult organ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Recent conditional knockout of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>which revealed that activin influenced ovarian growth and differentiation have extended the studies in specific organ of an early stage of adult mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. These approaches, however, essentially do not permit the role of activin in the adult animal. In order to overcome this limitation and to investigate the actual function of activin in the adult, we adopted an alternative approach as described in our previous report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Briefly, we transiently expressed activin, a secreted factor, in muscle under the control of the cytomegalovirus (CMV) promoter and assessed its impact on peripheral physiology at specific stage of female mice. The expression of foreign genes using CMV promoter is reported to persist for at least 22 weeks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] which is thought to be enough period for hormone to exert its action. Our result revealed that activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>colud directly influence the estrous cycle in female mice and the embryo development as an endocrine fashion.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Animals and experimental design</title><p>ICR mice at 2 months of age were purchased from the Daehan Animal Center and maintained under light under 14 h light, 10 h dark illumination at 23&#x000b0;C, with food and water available <italic>ad libitum</italic>. Plasmid DNA was purified and injected as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. To measure activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>mRNA and activin protein, a single injection of 300 &#x003bc;g pCMV-rAct in 50 &#x003bc;l of 10% sucrose in saline was performed at 10:00 A.M. and tissues were harvested 4 days after injection (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). For the detection of activin and FSH in serum, a single injection of 300 &#x003bc;g pCMV-rAct in 50 &#x003bc;l of 10% sucrose in saline was performed at 10:00 A.M. on diestrus II after confirmation of the two consecutive normal estrous cycles and serum was harvested 4 days later that is the diestrus II of the next cycle which normally reveals lower level of FSH in mice. Estrous cycle stages were determined by daily examination of vaginal cytology at 9:30 A.M. (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). For the reproductive studies, the first injection of 300 &#x003bc;g pCMV-rAct was performed at 10:00 A.M. on diestrus II and the second followed 4 days later. After the first injection of plasmid, estrous cycle stages were determined at 9:30 A.M. until next fifth cycle (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). For the ovarian histology, female mice at diestrus I of the third cycle after injection of plasmid were sacrificed. For the testicular histology, the first injection was done and followed the second 4 days later. Then the mice were sacrificed 7 days later after the second (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). For the developmental studies, the first injection was performed 1 day before mating, and the second 6 days after pregnancy was confirmed. Control mice were injected with the same amount of pcDNA3 vector (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). All the experiments were performed at least four times if not otherwise noted, and representative results are shown.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>pCMV-rAct structure and activin expression</bold>. (A) Diagram of the pCMV-rAct construct. Functional elements include the cytomegalovirus (CMV) promoter, the activin cDNA, and the human growth hormone (hGH) poly(A) signal. (B) RT-PCR and (C) Southern blot analysis were performed as described in methods. Marker of pGEM3Z/infI was loaded in lane 1. RNA from the pCMV-rAct-injected mice was loaded in lane 3 after treatment with DNase I, reverse transcriptase, and PCR. RNAs from control mice and from the pCMV-rAct-injected mice without reverse transcription were used as a normal (lane 2) and an internal control (lane 4), respectively. pCMV-rAct plasmid was used as a positive control (lane 5). RT: reverse transcription, pCMV-rAct: pCMV-rAct-injected mice. +: treated (or reacted), -: not treated (or not reacted).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-6-63-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Activin and FSH</bold>. Western blot analysis was performed as described in methods. (A) Proteins from control muscle, ovary, and liver were used as a normal sample, a positive control, and a negative control, respectively. (B) One microliter of serum was obtained from the pCMV-rAct-injected mice, electrophoresed, and performed to western blot as described in methods. The western blot shown is representative of results obtained from three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-6-63-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Change in the estrous cycle</bold>. (A) Each stage of the estrous cycle was identified by daily examination of vaginal cytology at 9:30 A.M. at a 100 &#x000d7; magnification. The first injection was carried out after confirming at least two normal estrous cycles and the second injection followed 4 days later. Note that the third estrous cycle was extended in the pCMV-rAct-injected female. The number of mice sacrificed is seven in each group (n = 7). Asterisks denote values that are significantly different from the mean control value (Student's <italic>t</italic>-test, *, <italic>p </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01). Values shown are mean &#x000b1; standard deviation. (B) A photograph of one example. Of note is that extended estrus stage up to six days was observed. Control: vehicle-injected female mouse, pCMV-rAct: pCMV-rAct-injected female mouse. DI: diestrus I, DII(1): diestrus II day 1, DII(2): diestrus II day 2, P: proestrus, E: estrus, E(1&#x02013;6): estrus day 1&#x02013;6.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-6-63-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Histology of the gonad</bold>. The ovaries (A) and testis (B) were prepared as described in methods and observed at 40 &#x000d7; (A; Above, B) and 120 &#x000d7; (A; Below) magnification. Of note is that follicle revealed a thickened granulosa cell layer with a small antrum and increased numbers of corpora lutea were observed in the pCMV-rAct-injected female mouse. Asterisks indicate antra in the follicles of control mice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-6-63-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Embryos from the pCMV-rAct-injected mice</bold>. (A) The two surgically isolated embryos at left were obtained at E15.5 from a pCMV-rAct-injected female mouse, one of which was dead (pCMV-rAct 1) and the other of which was atypically large (pCMV-rAct 2). Tissues of the embryos were observed at 6&#x000d7; magnification under the stereomicroscope (Leica ME Apo). (B) The embryos were weighted at E15.5. The number of embryos from control and the pCMV-rAct-injected female mice is 48 (N = 48), and 100 (N = 100), respectively. Asterisks denote values that were significantly different from control mean values (Student's <italic>t</italic>-test, *, <italic>p </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-6-63-5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Growth rates of offspring from the pCMV-rAct-injected mice</bold>. Body weights of the offspring that were obtained from control and pCMV-rAct-injected mice are shown for the first 6 weeks after birth. The number of offspring used for control and pCMV-rAct-injected mice is 32 (N = 32) and 42 (N = 42), respectively. Asterisks denote values that are significantly different from control mean values (Student's <italic>t</italic>-test at each point, *, <italic>p </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01). Values shown are means &#x000b1; standard deviation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-6-63-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Construction of the pCMV-rAct DNA expression vector</title><p>For the pCMV-rAct (6.9 kb), a 1.5-kb rat activin cDNA digested with EcoR I was cloned into the EcoR I site of a vector pcDNA3 (Invitrogen, USA) which contains a CMV early promoter and a bovine growth hormone polyadenylation site (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). The correct insertion of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>cDNA was confirmed by digestion with Kpn I.</p></sec><sec><title>Reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and Southern blot hybridization</title><p>RT-PCR and Southern blot hybridization were performed as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Briefly, muscles were homogenized with denaturing solution (4 M guanidinium thiocyanate, 25 mM sodium citrate (pH 7), 0.5% N-lauryl sarcosine, and 0.1 M 2-mercaptoethanol). The homogenate was phenol/chloroform extracted, and the RNA precipitated and quantified with a U.V. 2000 spectrophotometer (Pharmacia, USA). A260/A280 ranged from 1.8 to 2.0. Ten micrograms of total RNA were used in duplicate. The RNA was then treated with DNase I (5 U, Promega, USA) at 37&#x000b0;C for 10 min in order to remove genomic and plasmid DNA, and reverse transcribed at 42&#x000b0;C with random hexamer primers and AMV reverse transcriptase (Promega, USA) in a 20 &#x003bc;l reaction. A mixture of oligonucleotide primers (500 ng each), dNTP, and Taq DNA polymerase (2.5 U) was added to each reaction, the total volume was brought to 100 &#x003bc;l with 1&#x000d7; PCR buffer [10 mM Tris (pH 8.3), 50 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 0.01% gelatin] and the sample was overlaid with light mineral oil. Amplification was performed for 30 cycles using an annealing temperature of 65&#x000b0;C on an Omn-E thermal cycler (Hybaid Limited, UK). For the activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>gene, the primers were designed to generate a 397 bp fragment. The 5' primer was 5'CCACACGACTTTTGCTGCCAG3' and the 3' primer was 5'GGTGATGATCTCCGAGGTCTG3'. After amplification, the samples were chloroform extracted, dried, resuspended in 10 &#x003bc;l TE buffer (10 mM Tris, pH 8.0, 1 mM EDTA), and electrophoresed on a 1.2% agarose gel. The gel was photographed after ethidium bromide staining. The PCR products were then denatured with sodium hydroxide and transferred to Nytran filters (0.45 &#x003bc;m, Schleicher &#x00026; Schuell, Germany) under vacuum. They were hybridized with dixogenein-labeled activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>cDNA, blotted with anti-dixogenein AP (1:1000) (Roche, Germany), washed, and exposed to X-ray film after blotting with CSPD (Roche, Germany).</p></sec><sec><title>Protein blot analysis</title><p>Tissues were removed, homogenized in 400 &#x003bc;l of protein extraction buffer [0.1 M NaCl, 0.01 M Tris-Cl (pH 7.6), 1 mM EDTA (pH 8.0), 0.1% TritonX-100, 1 &#x003bc;g/ml aprotinin, and 100 ng/ml phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride], and centrifuged four times. The homogenates were mixed with an equal volume of 2 &#x000d7; SDS-loading buffer [100 mM Tris-Cl (pH6.8), 200 mM DTT, 4% SDS, 0.2% BPB, 20% glycerol], placed in boiling water for 10 min, and centrifuged. The supernatants were transferred to fresh tubes. Samples of each extract containing 10 &#x003bc;g protein were heated at 70&#x000b0;C for 10 min, electrophoresed on a 12% acrylamide gel and transferred onto Nytran filters in transfer buffer (39 mM glycine, 48 mM Tris base, 0.037% SDS, 20% methanol). The blots were incubated overnight in blocking solution (5% nonfat dried milk, 0.02% sodium azide, 0.02% Tween) with shaking at 4&#x000b0;C, followed by exposure to primary activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>antibodies (1:400) (Serotec, UK) overnight. They were washed in milk-TBS-Tween for 30 min and incubated with secondary anti-rabbit Ig horseradish peroxidase-linked whole donkey antibody (1:100)(Amersham Pharmacia Biotech, USA) in azide-free blocking solution [5% nonfat dried milk, 150 mM NaCl, 50 mM Tris-Cl (pH 7.5)] for 2 h. The secondary antibody-specific signal was detected with an ECL kit (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech, USA). For serum measurement of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>or FSH, one microliter of serum was obtained, electrophoresed, and western blot analysis was performed, using primary activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>antibodies (Serotec, UK) or primary FSH antibodies (1:750) (Serotec, UK).</p></sec><sec><title>Histology and statistical analysis</title><p>The gross appearance of embryos and excised tissues from injected and control mice were examined and the tissues immediately fixed in fresh 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS, pH 7.4. Following overnight fixation, they were dehydrated in ethanol and embedded in paraffin, and seven-micrometer sections were prepared with a microtome (Leica RM2235, Switzerland). The sections were de-paraffinized with xylene, dehydrated in absolute ethanol, and rehydrated in water. Sections were stained with hematoxylin, counterstained with eosin, and observed under a light microscope (Olympus IX70, Japan) or a steromicroscope (Leica ME Apo, Switzerland). For the statistical analysis, Student's <italic>t </italic>test was used for single comparison at &#x003b1; = 0.01. Statistics were performed no less than four independent experiments.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In initial studies, we tested whether intramuscular injection was an effective means of expressing activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>in adult mice. At the transcription level, we investigated the expression of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>. After injection of the pCMV-rAct DNA construct (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), we obtained an expected 397 bp PCR product in mouse muscle using RT-PCR with activin &#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>-specific primers, indicating that it came from activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>mRNA (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref> lane 3). Subsequently, we reconfirmed that the amplified PCR product really came from activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>mRNA by Southern blot analysis with the labelled activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>cDNA (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref> lane 3). At the protein level, western blot analysis revealed that mature activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>protein (14 kDa) was synthesized specifically in muscle from pCMV-rAct-injected mice (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Activin was also detected in the ovary, but not in the liver and control muscle. The level of serum activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>protein was substantially elevated in the pCMV-rAct-injected mice (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref> left). Thus, both activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>mRNA and protein were successfully expressed in muscle and secreted into the serum by this approach.</p><p>Activin was initially described and named for its ability to enhance FSH secretion in the female reproductive axis. To investigate whether the ectopically expressed activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>influences serum FSH, we measured FSH (24 kDa) by western blot analysis and found an increase in serum FSH in the injected mice (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref> right). The induced activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>(14 kDa) in serum was also found high at this time which corresponded to the increased FSH (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref> left). For the detection of FSH in serum, a single injection of pCMV-rAct was performed at 10:00 A.M. on diestrus II after confirmation of the two consecutive normal estrous cycles and serum was harvested 4 days later that is the diestrus II of the next cycle which normally reveals low level of FSH in mice. To examine the consequences of this altered FSH and activin levels, we examined the estrous cycle. The result was that the estrous cycle was extended at the third one after two injection of the plasmid (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Within the estrous cycle, estrus stage was mainly influenced. One case is that estrus stage was extended up to 6 days and diestrus II was extended up to 3 days (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). The seemingly normal epithelial cells were clearly observed during 6 days.</p><p>When we observed the ovary, the size was slightly increased in the pCMV-rAct-injected mice. And the ovary in the pCMV-rAct-injected mice revealed a less cavity across the ovarian section compared to control which had small and numerous cavities. Moreover, increased numbers of corpora lutea were observed in the pCMV-rAct-injected mice, indirectly suggesting the increased ovulation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>, Above). Within the ovaries, the later follicular stages, including tertiary follicles, had a thickened granulosa cell layer with a small antrum. The oocytes appeared normal regardless of the abundant granulosa cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>, Below). Activin&#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>was expressed in the testis (15), implying some role. In order to gain some insight into the role of activin in male reproduction, we also applied our approach to the male mice. However, in case of male mice, any noticeable change in the histology was obtained except a slight increase in the number of seminiferous tubules of the testis in the pCMV-rAct-injected mice (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). We are under further investigation.</p><p>Since activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>belongs to the TGF-&#x003b2; superfamily whose members are mainly involved in embryonic development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], the possible role of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>in embryonic development was investigated. To do this, female mice were injected with pCMV-rAct while pregnant. The resultant offspring proved to be large; day E15.5 embryos were larger than similar aged control embryos (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> pCMV-rAct2). Also offspring revealed a more accelerated development since more advanced vertebrae were observed. In addition, up to 10% of the embryos died (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Histological analysis at embryological day 15.5 (E15.5) revealed severe tissue degradation across the body in the dying embryos (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> pCMV-rAct1). Abortions were often observed within the uterus of the pCMV-rAct-injected pregnant mice. All the prematurely delivered embryos died immediately after delivery (data not shown). The mean body weight of the surviving embryos was about 1.5 times heavier than that of controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). These heavier body weights were maintained until 3 weeks after birth, but converged to control values by 6 weeks after birth (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>To further understand the detailed physiological function of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>in mammalian reproduction and development, we applied a "transient gain of function" mouse model as described in our previous research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], using naked DNA injection as a gene transfer method. Direct injection of DNA into mouse muscle led to the appearance of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>mRNA and protein, and had a variety of consequences, including changes in estrous cycle, ovarian histology, embryo size, and survival. This approach provides a relatively simple means of examining the roles of the activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>subunit in adult females and in development that could be extended to other endocrine genes.</p><p>Activin was first identified as gonadal protein to stimulate FSH in the pituitary gland [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. When we induced activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>through direct DNA injection, FSH in serum of pCMV-rAct-injected female was increased, suggesting that activin can act endocrine factor in addition to the already known paracrine factor. The resultant FSH enhancement also suggests change of the estrous cycle. When we examined the estrous cycle by vaginal smear method, the expected extended estrus stage was observed. In this case, it was presumed that increased FSH by ectopic activin expression induced follicle development in the ovary and subsequently elevated estrogen influenced the uterine tissue, resulting in extended estrus. This mechanism might be different from that of inhibin &#x02013; induced estrus extension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] in that an inhibin &#x003b1;-induced extension was occurred without increase of FSH.</p><p>With respect to the role of activin in reproductive tissues of the female mice, controversial results have been reported. Activin inhibited follicular development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] whereas activin induced proliferation of the granulosa cells with FSH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Our results support the granulose cell proliferation by activin overexpression. It remains, however, unclear whether activin acts solely or in the presence of FSH since FSH levels were significantly increased following activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>overexpression in pCMV-rAct-injected mice (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). The increased numbers of corpora lutea in pCMV-rAct-injected mice was also observed in intraovarian activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>knockout mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. However the inducing mechanism of corpus luteum seemed to be different in that our approach adopted the addition of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>whereas an intraovarian activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>knockout approach did the loss of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>. It was inferred that our addition of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>induced more corpora lutea with normal degeneracy whereas conditional deletion of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>induced normal corpora lutea with blocked degeneracy, both resulting in net increased corpora lutea in number.</p><p>In male mice, the reproductive system seemed not to be influenced by the induced expression of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>. Male fertility was not changed in pCMV-rAct-injected mice. In contrast, male sterility was observed in transgenic mice expressing activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Although the FSH was increased by the excess activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>as it is in the female, the actual amount of FSH might be not enough to influence the testis, either because there is a lesser induction of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>in male compared to female mice with unexplainable reason (under investigation) or because the sensitivity to FSH between the ovary and the testis might be different. Minor changes in the testis could be directly influenced by activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>since the binding site of the activin was observed within the testis and testis cell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p><p>Gene disruption studies suggest an essential role of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>in embryonic development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Our results indicate that overexpression of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>during development also has deleterious effects. In our experiments, some embryos from litters of the pCMV-rAct-injected female mice died during development, and the remaining embryos were observed to be larger than controls at birth. The increased size of the surviving embryos might be explained by their ability to more effectively compete for nutrients once a subset of the embryos die. Alternatively, the increased size of some embryos may limit the nutritional supply to others, contributing to the premature lethality that is observed. Collectively, these data indicate that activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>is essential during development, but it is important that its levels be tightly regulated, and excessive amounts of activin are toxic or lethal. Consistent with the essential role of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>and tight regulation of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>expression, it was reported that both activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>and activin &#x003b2;<sub>B </sub>are needed for development although activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>at least is maintained over a minimum threshold level for normal growth and survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p><p>The larger size of the surviving mice in our study stands in contrast to the small-sized activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>overexpressing transgenic mice observed at 3 weeks of age in another study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. In this case, the cause of the decreased size was presumed to be a thicker tongue and therefore a reduced ability to suckle. Another phenotype reported in activin &#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>-overexpressing mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], replacement of fatty tissue by connective tissue and a thickening of the epidermis, were not observed in pCMV-rAct-injected mice.</p><p>In addition to contributing new information on the consequences of altered activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>expression in the adult female, these studies provide several important technical advances as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Briefly, our approach is a very simple method and can be applied to many different species and to multiple strains of mice. For secreted proteins, our approach can be used effectively to study the phenotypic consequences of protein overexpression without the time-consuming production of transgenic mice. Moreover, the certain function of the protein in adult which was blocked by the deleterious effect during growth period in the overexpressing transgenic animal such as activin &#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>-transgenic animal can be overcome by this transient expression method.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our data revealed that activin betaA could directly influence the estrous cycle, an integral part of the reproduction in female mice and activin betaA also could influence the embryo development as an endocrine fashion. Moreover, our approach was proved to be efficient for functional analysis of the secreted proteins as a transient gain of function model.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>BNC designed the study and drafted the manuscript. MNK performed experiments related to the gene construction and subsequent gene expression. MNP participated in investigating the estrouc cycle. HKJ participated in investigating embryo. CC and KEM helped to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Young il Kim, Mi Young Kim, and Oye-Sun Seok for their technical assistance and Jun-Hyk Kim for his help in preparation of the manuscript. We thank Drs. Teresa Woodruff and Daniel Linzer for their helpful discussion. This work was supported by a grant from the "GRRC" Project of Gyeonggi Provincial Government (to Cho, BN), Republic of Korea.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Esch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Denoroy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillemin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and partial characterization of a Mr 32,000 protein with inhibin activity from follicular fluid</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1985</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>7217</fpage><lpage>7221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3864157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.82.21.7217</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimasaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Esch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillemin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pituitary FSH is released by a heterodimer of the &#x003b2;-subunits from the two forms of inhibin</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1986</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3086749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/321779a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilezikjian</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Knobil E, Neill JD, Greenswald GS, Markert CL, Pfaff DW</surname></name></person-group><source>Reproductive and other roles of inhibins and activins</source><year>1994</year><publisher-name>The Physiology of Reproduction Raven NY</publisher-name><fpage>1861</fpage><lpage>1878</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotten</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidhardt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning of a new member of the TGF-&#x003b2; family: a putative new activin &#x003b2;<sub>C </sub>chain</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1995</year><volume>206</volume><fpage>608</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7826378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1995.1086</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimatsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of a new activin &#x003b2; subunit: A dorsal mesoderm-inducing activity in Xenopus</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1995</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7755637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1995.1699</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Smiley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonadio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning of the mouse activin beta(e) subunit gene</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1996</year><volume>228</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8941337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1996.1715</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mellor</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cranfield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ries</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cancilia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>de Kretser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Groome</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Risbridger</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Localization of activin &#x003b2;<sub>A</sub>-, &#x003b2;<sub>B</sub>-, and &#x003b2;<sub>C</sub>-subunits in human prostate and evidence for formation of new activin heterodimers of &#x003b2;<sub>C</sub>-subunit</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2000</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>4851</fpage><lpage>4858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11134153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.85.12.4851</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Paynton</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachvarova</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of activins and TGF&#x003b2;<sub>1 </sub>and &#x003b2;<sub>2 </sub>RNAs in early postimplantation mouse embryos and uterine decidua</article-title><source>Mech Dev</source><year>1992</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1373953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0925-4773(92)90065-R</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albano</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Groome</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activins are expressed in preimplantation mouse embryos and in ES and EC cells and are regulated on their differentiation</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1993</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8330535</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feijen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goumans</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eijden-van Raaij</surname><given-names>AJ van den</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of activin subunits, activin receptors and follistatin in postimplantation mouse embryos suggests specific developmental functions for different activins</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1994</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>3621</fpage><lpage>3637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7821227</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activins are expressed early in Xenopus embryogenesis and can induce axial mesoderm and anterior structures</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1990</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2225062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(90)90445-K</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitrani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziv</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimonin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bril</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activin can induce the formation of axial structures and is expressed in the hypoblast of the chick</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1990</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(90)90446-L</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulte-Merker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusslein-Volhard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The protein product of the zebrafish homologue of the mouse T gene is expressed in nuclei of the germ ring and the notochord of the early embryo</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1992</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1295726</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hormonal regulation of embryogenesis: The formation of mesoderm in Xenopus laevis</article-title><source>Endocr Rev</source><year>1994</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8076585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/er.15.3.326</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gonadal and extragonadal expression of inhibin &#x003b1;, &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>and &#x003b2;<sub>B</sub> subunits in various tissues predicts diverse functions</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1988</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2829170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.85.1.247</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muttukrishna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Groome</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in peripheral serum levels of total activin A during the human menstrual cycle and pregnancy</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1996</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>3328</fpage><lpage>3334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8784092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.81.9.3328</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corrigan</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilezikjian</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bald</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmelzer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fendly</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwall</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for an autocrine role of activin B within rat anterior pituitary cultures</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1991</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>1682</fpage><lpage>1684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1900235</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodruff</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mather</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibin and activin locally regulate rat ovarian folliculogenesis</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1990</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>3196</fpage><lpage>3205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2123449</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mather</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activin promotes ovarian follicle development in vitro</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1995</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7867593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.136.3.849</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of granulosa cell deoxyribonucleic acid synthesis and differentiation by activin</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1996</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8593790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.137.2.464</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orimo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Taga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Minaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of activin-A on the development of mouse preimplantation embryos in vitro</article-title><source>J Assist Reprod Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8897128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02069647</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matzuk</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bickenbach</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Roop</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaenish</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of activins during mammalian development</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1995</year><volume>374</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7885473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/374354a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Horiguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukamizu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Male sterility in transgenic mice expressing activin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>subunit gene in testis</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1999</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10364482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1999.0833</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pangas</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgez</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Agno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Matzuk</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intraovarian activins are required for female fertility</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>2458</fpage><lpage>2471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17609433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/me.2007-0146</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiogenesis and white blood cell proliferation induced in mice by injection of a prolactin-expressing plasmid into muscle</article-title><source>Mol Cells</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>262</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12803491</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Herweijer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Latendresse</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High expression of naked plasmid DNA in muscles of young rodents</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1435</fpage><lpage>1443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9285779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/6.9.1435</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproductive deficiencies in transgenic mice expressing the rat inhibin &#x003b1;-subunit gene</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>2001</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>4994</fpage><lpage>5004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11606468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.142.11.4994</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in the reproductive functions of mice due to injection of a plasmid expressing an inhibin &#x003b1;-subunit into muscle: a transient transgenic model</article-title><source>Mol Cells</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15359127</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krummen</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodruff</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Covello</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Working</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Matler</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Localization of inhibin and activin binding sites in the testis during development by in situ ligand binding</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>1994</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>734</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8199254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1095/biolreprod50.4.734</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Husgafvel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Syvala</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuohimaa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ylikomi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a nuclear localization signal in activin/inhibin &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>subunit; Intranuclear &#x003b2;<sub>A </sub>in rat spermatogenic cells</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>1999</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>588</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10026103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1095/biolreprod60.3.588</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Houston-Hawkins</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Matzuk</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activins are critical modulators of growth and survival</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2404</fpage><lpage>2417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14551263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/me.2003-0051</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Smola</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleuel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brauchle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lein</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Huylebroeck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Balling</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of activin A in the skin of transgenic mice reveals new activities of activin in epidermal morphogenesis, dermal fibrosis and wound repair</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>5205</fpage><lpage>5215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/18.19.5205</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>