<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238195</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639673</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">001900032008</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Current Trends</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mitochondrial gene rearrangements: new paradigm in the evolutionary biology and systematics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raj Singh</surname><given-names>Tiratha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Bioinformatics, Maulana Azad National Institute of Technology (MANIT), Bhopal, India</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Zoology, Faculty of Life Sciences, Tel-Aviv University, Tel-Aviv, Israel</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Tiratha Raj Singh: <email>tiratharaj@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open-access article, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, 		for non-commercial purposes, provided the original author and source are credited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>					Mitochondrial (mt) genomic study may reveal significant insight into the molecular evolution and several other aspects of 			genome evolution such as gene rearrangements evolution, gene regulation, and replication mechanisms. Other questions such as 			patterns of gene expression mechanism evolution, genomic variation and its correlation with physiology, and other molecular 			and biochemical mechanisms can be addressed by the mt genomics. Rare genomic changes have attracted evolutionary biology 			community for providing homoplasy free evidence of phylogenetic relationships. Gene rearrangements are considered to be rare 			evolutionary events and are being used to reconstruct the phylogeny of diverse group of organisms. Mt gene rearrangements 			have been established as a hotspot for the phylogenetic and evolutionary analysis of closely as well as distantly related 			organisms.                  </p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>gene expression</kwd><kwd>evolution</kwd><kwd>mitochondrial gene</kwd><kwd>genomic variation</kwd><kwd>replication</kwd><kwd>gene regulation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>Genes and genomes are the product of complex processes of evolution, influenced by mutation, random drift, and naturalselection. The inference of genome rearrangement events such as duplication, inversion, and translocation, is crucial inmultiple genome comparisons. During the past three decades, DNA and protein sequence data has increasingly become themain asset to infer the general phylogeny; however, certain difficulties and limits have been found with the use ofnucleotide sequences in phylogeny, in particular evolutionary rate differences between taxa, non-homogenous basecomposition, and multiple substitutions. &#x0201c;Rare genomic changes&#x0201d; have attracted great interest because of theirpotential to provide homoplasy free evidence of phylogenetic relationships [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>]. Gene rearrangements are considered to be rare evolutionary events, and as such the existence of a shared derived gene order between taxa is often indicative of common ancestry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>].</p><p>Enormous numbers of phylogenetic studies using mt gene sequences have been carried out and reported, some dealingwith the use of mitochondrial genes in the establishment of different levels of phylogenetic relationships. The success ofmt DNA in molecular systematics lies in its prevalent characteristics, such as maternal inheritance, rapid rate ofevolution, and haploid nature. Different parts of mt genome with different functional constraints are expected to evolve atdifferent rates. Thus, comparative mt genomics promises to offer a comprehensive study of distinct patterns and processes of molecular evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Description</title><p>Mitochondria are the power house of the cell. They are present in virtually every cell in body. They play animperative role in metabolism, apoptosis, disease and aging. They are the site of oxidative phosphorylation, essential forthe production of ATP, as well as for other biochemical functions. Mitochondria have a genome separate from thenuclear genome referred to as mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA). Animal mt DNA is a small (~16 kb), compact,economically-organized circular molecule, composed of 37 genes coding for 22 tRNAs, 2 rRNAs and 13 proteins, withfew exceptions specifically in invertebrates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>]b The thirteenproteins are mainly involved in electron transport and oxidative phosphorylation of the mitochondria.</p><p>Recent advances in sequencing techniques have made available a great deal of data on whole genome basis.Complete mt genome sequences are available for thousands of organisms. The order of the genes in the mitochondrialDNA molecule in a wide variety of organisms has begun to be disclosed during last two decades. The gene order ishighly conserved in vertebrates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>) except for the region around the control region (D-loop), which is more prone to gene rearrangement. Maximum variability has been found in the gene order in invertebrates. The control region of the mitochondrial genome is frequently used in population studies due to the high variability in its nucleotide sequence,while protein-coding genes, such as cytochrome <italic>b</italic> (Cyt <italic>b</italic>), are generally used for phylogenetic analysis of taxa above the species level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>]b.</p><p>Genome level character comparison can address a large number of evolutionary branch points. A small number of such comparisons have provided strong resolution of some evolutionary relationships which were controversial earlier. This suggests the reliability and confidence in their usage as markers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>]. Mitochondrial gene rearrangements are considered to be rare evolutionary events. In principle, &#x02019;rare genomic changes&#x02018; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>], such as changes in gene order, can retain phylogenetic information for long periods of time, even when primary sequence data must have become randomized due to the involvement of long time periods.</p><p>Differences in mitochondrial gene order have been useful for phylogenetic resolution of some groups of species, forexample Arthropoda being monophyletic, and within this Crustacea grouping with Hexapoda to the exclusion ofMyriapoda and Onychophora. The &#x02019;universal&#x02018; gene order for living vertebrates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>) is not followed by birds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. In some recent studies based on complete mt genomes in birds, it has been suggested that gene orders evolved independently more than once. Also mapping of these gene orders on theavian phylogenetic tree suggested that one of these gene orders is an ancestral while the other is a derived form. Themost acceptable model for the mt gene rearrangements till date is the tandem duplication followed by the deletion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Conclusion</title><p>With the increasing amount of mt and nuclear sequence data there will be new outcomes for phylogenetic studies atseveral levels and will soon emerge as the knowledge base for molecular evolution. As the understanding of thesecondary structure of the control region, non coding region and ribosomal genes and their role in the mt genome willimprove, these sequences will be helpful for use in phylogeny. Several studies and debate are still in progress onthe structure of tRNAs and their specific role in gene regulation and evolution. Gene regulation may also serve as asubstrate for evolutionary change, since control of the timing, location, and amount of gene expression can have aninsightful effect on the functions and existence of the genes in the organism. Mt gene rearrangements are likely to revealstructural, functional and evolutionary aspects of the biology distinct from those evident from homologous sequencecomparisons. It will also help in the prediction and reconstruction of homoplasy free phylogenetic relationships,and will also be used to develop models for the phylogenetic analysis of remotely related organisms and to betterunderstand the evolutionary history of organisms.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rokas</surname></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>PWH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><year>2000</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>454</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11050348</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boore</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1767</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10101183</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumazawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1995</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>759</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7476123</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mindell</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>10693</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9724766</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nachman</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><source>Genetica</source><year>1998</year><volume>102/103</volume><fpage>61</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9725852</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><year>2001</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1114613</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boore</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><year>2006</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>439</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16762445</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desjardins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>599</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2329578</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bensch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e4;rlid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>107</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10666710</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2007</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16854605</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>475</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178969</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawlings</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2001</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1604</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470854</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dowton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>2003</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>517</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12698290</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1993</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>545</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8350349</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boore</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Nature</source><year>1995</year><volume>376</volume><fpage>163</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7603565</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2003</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>171</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12878457</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zardoya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Genetics</source><year>1996</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>1249</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8846902</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of mt genome, mt gene order and its narrative role in elucidating evolutionary information.(a) Circular animal mt genome. (b) Universal mt gene order in vertebrates and one derived form in birds as ancestral gene order.The gene order near CR (control region) are shown which is the characteristics of higher organisms and more prone to generearrangements. (c) A schematic phylogenetic tree to indicate the generation of evolutionary information form mt gene order andits rearrangements.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="97320630003095F1"/></fig></floats-wrap></article>