<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238250</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639687</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">002600032008</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Prediction Model</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Colon cancer prediction with genetic profiles using intelligent techniques</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alladi</surname><given-names>Subha Mahadevi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>P</surname><given-names>Shinde Santosh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>Vadlamani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>Upadhyayula Suryanarayana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Bioinformatics Group, Biology Division, Indian Institute of Chemical Technology, Tarnaka, Hyderabad 500007, Andhra Pradesh, India</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Institute for Development and Research in Banking Technology, Castle Hills Road, Masab Tank, Hyderabad 500057, India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Vadlamani Ravi: <email>rav_padma@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open-access article, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, 		for non-commercial purposes, provided the original author and source are credited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Micro array data provides information of expression levels of thousands of genes in a cell in a single experiment. 		Numerous efforts have been made to use gene expression profiles to improve precision of tumor classification. In our present 		study we have used the benchmark colon cancer data set for analysis. Feature selection is done using t&#x02010;statistic. Comparative 		study of class prediction accuracy of 3 different classifiers viz., support vector machine (SVM), neural nets and logistic 		regression was performed using the top 10 genes ranked by the t&#x02010;statistic. SVM turned out to be the best classifier for this 		dataset based on area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC) and total accuracy. Logistic Regression ranks 		as the next best classifier followed by Multi Layer Perceptron (MLP). The top 10 genes selected by us for classification are all 		well documented for their variable expression in colon cancer. We conclude that SVM together with t-statistic based feature        selection is an efficient and viable alternative to popular techniques.           </p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>gene expression</kwd><kwd>tumor classification</kwd><kwd>t-statistic</kwd><kwd>feature selection</kwd><kwd>SVM neural network</kwd><kwd>logistic regression</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>DNA micro arrays have enabled researchers to monitor thousands of genes simultaneously. The role of micro arrayexpression data in cancer diagnosis is very significant. Mining for useful information from such micro array dataconsisting of thousands of genes and a small number of samples is often a tough task. Colon cancer is the secondmost common cause of cancer mortality in Western countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>]. According to the WHO 2006 report colorectal cancer causes 655,000 deaths worldwide per year. Precise predictions of tumors are very important fortreatment and diagnosis.</p><p>All the genes used in the expression profile are not informative; also many of them are redundant. Reducingthe number of genes by feature selection and still retaining best class prediction accuracy for the classifier is vital incase of tumor classification. The emphasis in cancer classification is both on methods of gene selection and onchoice of classifier. Towards the objective of selecting the features important for colon cancer classification severalmethods like t&#x02010;statistic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>], Fisher's F statistic, Principalcomponent analysis, SVM-RFE are in use. Several machine learning techniques have also been successfullyapplied, for example decision trees, na&#x000ef;ve Bayesian methods and support vector machines.</p><p>Furey and colleagues have used signal to noise ratio for feature selection and SVM as classifier resulting in 90.3&#x000a2;accuracy in prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. Li and colleagues have madeuse of an approach combining GA and KNN to identify genes that can jointly discriminate between the tumor andnormal classes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>]. It is a stochastic supervised patternrecognition method and they have achieved 94.1&#x000a2; accuracy with it. Sun and colleagues have used wavelettransformation to reduce feature space to a lower dimension and classified colon cancer data with PNN toobtain 92&#x000a2; accuracy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Chen and colleagues used multiple kernel support vector machine (MK-SVM)scheme, consisting of feature selection, rule extraction and prediction modeling to improve the explanation capacity of SVM. They used two gene expression datasets viz., leukemia dataset and colon tumor dataset to demonstratethe performance of this approach. Using the small number of selected genes, MK-SVM achieves encouragingclassification accuracy of more than 90&#x000a2; for both two datasets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>]. Kim and colleagues have used information gain and tested evolutionary neural networks for their prediction model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>]. Mahata and colleagues have ranked genes depending on the minimum probability of classification errors (MPE) for each gene and classification accuracy was obtained using SVM and a modified na&#x000ef;veBayes classifier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>].</p><p>In our study, we have worked on the prediction of colon cancer, based on gene expression data. We have used thebenchmark colon cancer dataset having expression pattern for 40 tumor and 22 normal colon tissue samples analyzedwith Affymetrix Oligonucleotide array [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>] to compare 3different classifiers. Feature extraction is done using t&#x02010;statistic. SVM, Neural nets and Logistic Regression areemployed and their performance in terms of classification accuracy on the micro array data was compared.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methodology</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Dataset</title><p>The colon cancer data set was taken from Kent Ridge Biomedical Data Repository [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. It has gene expression samples that were analyzed with an Affymetrix Oligonucleotide array complementary to more than 6500human genes. The data set contains 62 samples collected from colon-cancer patients. Among them, 40 tumor biopsies are from tumors (labeled as &#x0201c;negative&#x0201d;) and 22 normal (labeled as &#x0201c;positive&#x0201d;) biopsies are from healthy parts of the colons of the same patients. Two thousand out of around 6500 genes were selected based on the confidence in the measured expression levels. The source of the dataset did not mention the number for the confidence of the expression levels. The data of all samples in a micro array are presented in a table constructing the gene expression matrix. The rows of the matrix correspond to the single genes and the columns to the single samples.This gene expression matrix is the input to a classification system.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Data preparation</title><p>The first step in the analysis of micro array experiments is the normalization of the data. The purpose of normalizationis to adjust for any bias arising from the variation in microarray technology rather than from biological differencesbetween the RNA samples or the printed probes. The microarray expression data is also highly heterogeneous. We have standardized the data in order to reduce the range over which calculations need to be made. We have taken the normal samples as class 0 and tumor samples as class 1. The equation for the standardized value is: Z=[X-&#x003bc;]/&#x003c3;, where X is the attribute to be standardized, &#x003bc; is thearithmetic mean of the attribute and &#x003c3; is its standard deviation.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Feature selection</title><p>Feature selection is the technique commonly used in machine learning, to select a subset of relevant features forbuilding robust learning models. When applied in biology domain, the technique is also called discriminative geneselection which detects influential genes based on DNA micro array experiments. By removing most irrelevant andredundant features from the data, feature selection helps improve the performance of learning models. Featureselection identifies the subset of differentially expressed genes that are potentially relevant for distinguishing theclasses of samples. The aim is to reduce the initial gene pool from 7,000&#x02010;10,000 to 100&#x02010;200.</p><p>We have used t&#x02010;statistic for selecting the top genes to be used by the classifiers. Each sample belongs to one class 0(normal) or 1 (tumor). For each gene we have calculated the mean and standard deviation for both the classes.Assuming unequal variances a score <bold>t</bold> is given by the formula in equation 1 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary material</xref>). Thetop 50 genes are identified on the basis of t statistic of each of the 2000 genes originally considered and used forclassification.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>KNIME and Lib-SVM software</title><p>For analyzing the classification efficiency of Logistic regression and neural nets we have used the LR, MLP andRBF options available in the software tool KNIME (a freely available software package) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. For analyzing colon cancer dataset with SVM we used the Lib-SVM 2.85 tool (a freely available software package). [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Class prediction procedure</title><p>The dataset was split into training and test set in the ratio 80:20, 70:30, 65:35 and 60:40. We obtained best predictionaccuracy with the 65:35 split. Consequently, we continued training and prediction using the classifiers with the 65:35data sets. Five different 65:35 data sets were generated set1, set2, set3, set4, set5) and used to predict the averageclassification accuracy of the models. We applied Logistic Regression, neural net (MLP, RBF) and SVM to the coloncancer data. 10 fold cross validation was performed with SVM.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Specificity, sensitivity and ROC curve</title><p>The different classifiers are compared against one another on the basis of specificity, sensitivity, total accuracy andthe value of area under the ROC curve (AUC). Sensitivity of each classifier was calculated using the formula(TP/TP+FN) where TP is number of true positives and FN is number of false negative cases. Specificity is measuredby the formula (TN/TN+FP) where TN is number of true negatives tested and FP is the number of false positive cases.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The top 50 genes are identified on the basis of t&#x02010;statistic of each of the 2000 genes originally considered. Wecompared the average prediction accuracy using 10 and 50 genes and found less error in prediction using 10 genes.The top 10 genes are ranked in ascending order and their GenBank Accession numbers are H08393, X63629, M22382, J05032, H40095, M63391, M26697, T56604, X12671, T47377. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref> represents the Table comparing SVM classifier performance with different classifiers.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref> presents the results of 10 fold cross validation for SVM and finally <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1c</xref> depicts the ROC Plot.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref> presents the comparison of classifier performance with different number of features selected. 10 fold cross validation was performed on the full data set with out splitting it and used in Lib-SVM. This was donewith each of the five sets and an average cross validation percentage was generated, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>.Specificity and sensitivity of the different classifiers are evaluated for the colon cancer data set with 10 genes. The results obtained are used to plot an ROC curve in the <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1c</xref>. The results have shown the performance of SVM to be better than that of Logistic Regression and Neural net (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1b</xref>). The area under the ROC curve shows significantly better results for SVM with a radial basis function indicating good sensitivity and specificity.</p><p>Further, it is worth noticing that five out of 10 discriminating genes are present in the genes which wereselected by using information gain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>] as a method for feature selection, four are present in the list selected using MPE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>]. M63391 DES gene has been discovered to be down regulated in colon cancer patient samples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>]. This has also been verified by biological experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]. HSP D1 whose gene accession number is M22382 is expressed in both primary tumor and lymph node metastasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>As reported (3,6) in earlier literature and as shown by our study, the potential of applying machine learningtechniques is very high for classification of malignancy in tumors on the basis of variation in gene expression. Wealso demonstrate the superior prediction accuracy of SVM over neural net and logistic regression classifiers in case ofthe colon cancer data set. An important point is the question regarding what the significant features or patternsmean from a biological perspective. We can point out the genes, which give best prediction accuracy in case ofclassification, correlating them to their biological significance with respect to the disease. Developing moresophisticated methods of feature selection coupled with SVM would yield more insights into defining a betterbinary classification model for this biological problem.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><caption><title>Data 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="97320630003130S1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x1ce47b0N0x1e6ab40" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rew</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Euro J Surg Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>504</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Genomic Informatics</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>51</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furey</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2000</year><volume>906</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11120680</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751221</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Neurocomputing</source><year>2006</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>387</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Artif Intell Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>161</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17851055</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Neurocomputing</source><year>2004</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>361</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahata</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biomedical Informatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>775</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17950675</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alon</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>6745</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10359783</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://datam.i2r.astar.edu.sg/datastes/krbd/ColonTumor/ColonTumor.html">	http://datam.i2r.astar.edu.sg/datastes/krbd/ColonTumor/ColonTumor.html</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.knime.org/downloads.html">	http://www.knime.org/downloads.html</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.csie.ntu.edu.tw/~cjlin/libsvm">	http://www.csie.ntu.edu.tw/~cjlin/libsvm</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groisman</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Histopathology</source><year>2006</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>43</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16487365</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cappello</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2005</year><volume>5</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16253146</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(a) Table comparing classifier performance with different number of genes; (b) 10 fold cross validation for SVM;(c) ROC plot.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="97320630003130F1"/></fig></floats-wrap></article>