<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">eid</journal-id><journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8903209</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639829</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The infectious diseases impact statement: a mechanism for addressing emerging diseases.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McSweegan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><email>em8p@nih.gov</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland 20892-7630, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><abstract><p>The use of an Infectious Diseases Impact Statement (IDIS) is proposed for predictive assessments of local changes in infectious diseases arising from human-engineered activities. IDIS is intended to be analogous to an Environmental Impact Statement. The drafting of an IDIS for specific activities, particularly in developing nations, would provide a formal mechanism for examining potential changes in local health conditions, including infected and susceptible populations, diseases likely to fluctuate in response to development, existing control measures, and vectors likely to be affected by human activities. The resulting survey data could provide a rational basis and direction for development, surveillance, and prevention measures. An IDIS process that balances environmental alterations, local human health, and economic growth could substantially alter the nature of international development efforts and infectious disease outbreaks.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>