<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">molbiolevol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">molbev</journal-id><journal-title>Molecular Biology and Evolution</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0737-4038</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1537-1719</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033257</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2639113</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msn272</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Estimating Translational Selection in Eukaryotic Genomes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>dos Reis</surname><given-names>Mario</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wernisch</surname><given-names>Lorenz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">&#x02021;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>*</label>School of Crystallography, Birkbeck College, London, UK</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02020;</label>Mathematical Biology, National Institute for Medical Research, Mill Hill, London, UK</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x02021;</label>MRC Biostatistics Unit, Institute of Public Health, Cambridge, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp>E-mail: <email>mdosrei@nimr.mrc.ac.uk</email>.</corresp><fn><p>Manolo Gouy, Associate Editor</p></fn></author-notes><!--Fake ppub date generated  by PMC from publisher pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2008 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Natural selection on codon usage is a pervasive force that acts on a large variety of prokaryotic and eukaryotic genomes. Despite this, obtaining reliable estimates of selection on codon usage has proved complicated, perhaps due to the fact that the selection coefficients involved are very small. In this work, a population genetics model is used to measure the strength of selected codon usage bias, <italic>S</italic>, in 10 eukaryotic genomes. It is shown that the strength of selection is closely linked to expression and that reliable estimates of selection coefficients can only be obtained for genes with very similar expression levels. We compare the strength of selected codon usage for orthologous genes across all 10 genomes classified according to expression categories. Fungi genomes present the largest <italic>S</italic> values (2.24&#x02013;2.56), whereas multicellular invertebrate and plant genomes present more moderate values (0.61&#x02013;1.91). The large mammalian genomes (human and mouse) show low <italic>S</italic> values (0.22&#x02013;0.51) for the most highly expressed genes. This might not be evidence for selection in these organisms as the technique used here to estimate <italic>S</italic> does not properly account for nucleotide composition heterogeneity along such genomes. The relationship between estimated <italic>S</italic> values and empirical estimates of population size is presented here for the first time. It is shown, as theoretically expected, that population size has an important role in the operativity of translational selection.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>translational selection</kwd><kwd>tAI</kwd><kwd>tRNA</kwd><kwd>codon usage bias</kwd><kwd>population size</kwd><kwd>eukaryotes</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Different codons are used to different extents, and every genome shows particular codon preferences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Grantham et al. 1980</xref>). It is generally acknowledged that the pattern of codon usage in a given genome is given by a balance between mutational bias, random genetic drift, and the action of natural selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Sharp et al. 1995</xref>). In highly expressed genes of fast-growing organisms, preferred codons are favorably selected to match the most abundant cognate transfer tRNAs (tRNAs), thus improving translational efficiency and accuracy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bennetzen and Hall 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Ikemura 1985</xref>). A selection&#x02013;mutation balance theory of codon usage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Bulmer 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">McVean and Charlesworth 1999</xref>) has been developed to explain the forces that shape codon usage in different genomes. Organisms like the bacterium <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> show codon usage patterns that can be explained mainly by mutational biases and drift (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lafay et al. 2000</xref>), whereas organisms like the fast-growing bacterium <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> show patterns of codon usage that are consistent with a coadaptation to the intracellular tRNA levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Ikemura 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">dos Reis et al. 2003</xref>). Natural selection acting at the codon level for translational optimization is usually referred to as translational selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Akashi and Eyre-Walker 1998</xref>). Understanding how and why translational selection acts to optimize codon usage in certain organisms is an important and active area of research.</p><p>One of the major limitations of codon usage studies is that measuring translational selection is a complicated matter. Most studies are based on the development or application of codon usage indices that intend to describe general patterns of codon usage, and any evidence of selection is indirect, with selection rarely being measured directly (see, e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sharp and Li 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Wright 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Knight et al. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Chen et al. 2004</xref>). Perhaps, the only group of organisms where several serious attempts to estimate selection have been made are <italic>Drosophila</italic> spp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Akashi 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Akashi and Schaeffer 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Maside et al. 2004</xref>) with some estimates in other organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hartl et al. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Cutter and Charlesworth 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Yang and Nielsen 2008</xref>). These studies have shown that the selection coefficients affecting codon usage are very small, roughly ranging between 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> and 10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup>. Only fairly recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sharp et al. (2005)</xref> conducted an extensive study of codon usage in prokaryotic organisms, utilizing a population genetic model developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Bulmer (1991)</xref> to obtain appropriate estimates of translational selection. These workers estimated the population parameter <italic>S</italic>, which is the confounded product of the effective population size and the actual selection coefficient acting at the codon level. Regrettably, their study was not extended to eukaryotic organisms.</p><p>Because the selection coefficients affecting codon usage are so small, translational selection is expected to be operative only in large populations. In small populations, random drift effects largely determine the fate of new mutants in a population even if they are slightly advantageous (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kimura 1983</xref>). The role of effective population size on the evolution of codon usage has been well discussed in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Sharp et al. 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chamary et al. 2006</xref>). However, it seems no researchers have actually compared estimates of selection and population size from actual data. Perhaps, the only exception is the work by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Akashi (1997)</xref>, where the differences in effective population sizes and the degree of codon usage in two <italic>Drosophila</italic> species were discussed.</p><p>The objective of the present work is to utilize <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Bulmer's (1991)</xref> model of codon evolution as implemented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sharp et al. (2005)</xref> to study codon selection in a small set of eukaryotic genomes, with particular emphasis on the baker's yeast, <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. The relationship between estimates of translational selection and expression levels is studied in detail. Furthermore, we use published estimates of effective population sizes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Lynch and Conery 2003</xref>) to show, perhaps for the first time, the relationship between effective population size and estimates of translational selection in eukaryotic organisms.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Estimating Selection on Codon Usage</title><p>This work follows Bulmer's model of codon evolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Bulmer 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">McVean and Charlesworth 1999</xref>). Let us consider a diploid model with an amino acid that is encoded by only two synonymous codons, <italic>c</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>c</italic><sub>2</sub>. The mutation rate from <italic>c</italic><sub>1</sub> to <italic>c</italic><sub>2</sub> is <italic>u</italic> and from <italic>c</italic><sub>2</sub> to <italic>c</italic><sub>1</sub> is <italic>v</italic>. The model assumes that selection acts independently at all sites and that there is genic selection, this is, <italic>c</italic><sub>1</sub> has selective advantage <italic>s</italic> in single dose and <italic>2s</italic> in double dose. The frequency (<italic>P</italic>) of <italic>c</italic><sub>1</sub>, at equilibrium, will be determined by the mutation pattern, the selection strength in favor of <italic>c</italic><sub>1</sub>, and the effect of random drift. <italic>P</italic> is approximately given by<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx1_ht.jpg"/></disp-formula>where <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub> is the effective population size. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> shows the expected theoretical relationship between <italic>P</italic> and <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub> for a constant selective pressure <italic>s</italic>.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>F<sc>IG</sc>. 1.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Theoretical expected equilibrium frequency (<italic>P</italic>) of an optimal codon versus effective population size (<italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>). The curve represented in the figure is from rearranging equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd1">(1)</xref>. The gray rectangles show estimated effective population size intervals for some eukaryotic groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Sherry et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Harpending et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Lynch and Conery 2003</xref>). Estimates of selection on codon usage are in the order of 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> to 10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hartl et al. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Maside et al. 2004</xref>). A value of <italic>s</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup> was chosen for illustrative purposes only. The dashed line shows the equilibrium frequency of the codon under no selection when <italic>u</italic>/<italic>v</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272f01_ht"/></fig><p>In practical terms, the selection coefficient (<italic>s</italic>) cannot be estimated independently because it is confounded with the effective population number. The confounded parameter <italic>S&#x02009;=&#x02009;4N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>s</italic> (for haploid organisms <italic>S&#x02009;=&#x02009;2N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>s</italic>) can be estimated from the previous equation as<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx2_ht.jpg"/></disp-formula>where <italic>k&#x02009;=&#x02009;u/v</italic> and <italic>Q</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 &#x02013; <italic>P</italic> is the frequency of the suboptimal codon (<italic>c</italic><sub>2</sub>). If selection is absent (<italic>s&#x02009;=&#x02009;0</italic>), equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd1">(1)</xref> is reduced to<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx3_ht.jpg"/></disp-formula>Rearranging this <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd3">equation (3)</xref> gives <italic>k</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;(1 &#x02013; <italic>P</italic>)/<italic>P</italic>. From a practical point of view, in any given genome, a value of <italic>k</italic> can be estimated from a set of genes where selection is either absent or very weak. This value of <italic>k</italic> can then be used to estimate <italic>S</italic> for a set of highly expressed genes in such genome. Formally, the estimated value of <italic>S</italic> can be expressed as<disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx4_ht.jpg"/></disp-formula> where the caret is used to distinguish the estimate from the model parameter and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx5_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula><sub>hx</sub> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx5_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula><sub>ref</sub> are the observed frequencies of optimal codons in the highly expressed and reference gene sets. Please note that the estimated <italic>k</italic> is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx6_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd4">(4)</xref> was used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sharp et al. (2005)</xref> to estimate <italic>S</italic> values in 80 bacterial genomes. Formally, this equation is simply the log-odds ratio of the relative codon frequencies of optimal over nonoptimal codons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Eyre-Walker and Bulmer 1995</xref>). If the value of <italic>k</italic> is nonhomogeneous throughout a given genome, then equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd4">(4)</xref> cannot be used to estimate <italic>S</italic> correctly as the log-odds ratio would simply reflect different mutational patterns in different genes and not selection. This is an important issue that must be kept in mind. The crucial point is to choose the gene sets carefully and to verify that mutational patterns in both sets are similar.</p><p>All nine amino acids encoded by only two synonymous codons were analyzed in this study. Values of <italic>k</italic> were estimated for each of the nine codon pairs from a suitably determined reference gene set. These <italic>k</italic> values were then used to estimate <italic>S</italic> values for each one of the nine optimal codons in genes expressed at different levels. Overall, <italic>S</italic> values for all nine amino acids were calculated as the average weighted according to the number of codons present. Bootstrap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Efron and Tibshirani 1993</xref>) confidence intervals for estimated <italic>S</italic> values were obtained by sampling with replacement codons within amino acids and expression categories. The confidence intervals are then the 2.5% and 97.5% quantiles of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula><sub>b</sub> values obtained from 1,000 bootstrap samples.</p><p>The technique used here to estimate <italic>S</italic> is symmetrical for amino acids encoded by two codons. This means that if a codon <italic>c</italic><sub>1</sub> has a selective value <italic>S</italic><sub>1</sub>, then the selective value against the complementary codon <italic>c</italic><sub>2</sub> is simply <italic>S</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02013;<italic>S</italic><sub>1</sub>. This property allows the estimation of <italic>S</italic> irrespective of whether we know beforehand which codon is the optimal one. In fact, it allows the identification of the optimal codon by computing <italic>S</italic> itself. If a negative value is obtained, then the optimal codon is the complementary one. The only exception to this rule is when <italic>S</italic> is zero, which can easily be determined by bootstrapping. Optimal codons determined this way for baker's yeast are the same as those reported in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bennetzen and Hall 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Percudani et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kanaya et al. 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence Data and Analysis</title><p>Sequence data for all open reading frames (ORFs) recognized in the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome were downloaded from the National Center of Biotechnology Information ftp site (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genomes/Saccharomyces_cerevisiae">ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genomes/Saccharomyces_cerevisiae</ext-link>). Expression data for this organism were obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.wi.mit.edu/young/expression/">http://web.wi.mit.edu/young/expression/</ext-link> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Holstege et al. 1998</xref>). This data set contains estimates of mRNA abundance for 5,460 genes as number of transcripts per cell, obtained from duplicated high-density oligonucleotide array experiments. This data set has already been used to study codon usage in at least three separate publications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Coghlan and Wolfe 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Akashi 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">2003</xref>). A total of 119 genes were excluded for analysis in this work because they present name discrepancies with the downloaded yeast genome or present duplicated expression values in the set. Genes were ranked according to their expression level and binned in groups containing at least 6,000 codons. Genes with the same expression level were binned together. Seventy-seven bins were obtained containing between 8 and 523 genes (there is a disproportionate amount of genes with very low expression values). This binning scheme is very similar to that used previously by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Akashi (2003)</xref> for the same yeast data. Two hundred and eighty genes are depicted in the data set as having only 0.1 transcripts per cell. This represents the lowest detectable value in the array experiments. In this study, these genes were assumed to be under no translational selection, so this group was taken as the reference gene set in order to calculate codon frequencies under mutational equilibrium.</p><p>Nine more eukaryotic genomes were also analyzed: the orange bread mold (<italic>Neurospora crassa</italic>), the cryptococcosis agent (<italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>), the malaria parasite (<italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>), the mouse-ear cress (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), the fruit fly (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>), a microsporidian parasite (<italic>Encephalitozoon cuniculi</italic>), a nematode worm (<italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>), the common mouse (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>), and human (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>). The 77 gene expression bins identified in the baker's yeast were collapsed into 11 expression categories sorted according to increasing expression levels. The observed number of optimal codons in a sequence is a binomial variable, and so the proportion of optimal codons has a variance inversely proportional to the total number of codons in question. Because of this, relatively large bins containing thousands of codons are desirable to obtain reliable estimates of <italic>S</italic>. These expression categories, and the genes contained within them, were used as a reference to find the corresponding orthologs in the other genomes. Best reciprocal matches obtained with BLAT (Kent J, unpublished data) were used to identify orthologous pairs of protein sequences between the baker's yeast and the nine other eukaryotic genomes. BLAT was designed to find closely related sequences and will fail to identify more distant homologs. In this sense, our approach is rather conservative as only well-conserved homologs were considered here. For general advice on the identification of orthologous sets of genes, the reader is encouraged to read <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Koonin (2005)</xref>. If the orthologous genes are assumed to have conserved relative expression levels across species, then the technique described above can be used to estimate translational selection (<italic>S</italic>) in any of the other nine genomes given a sufficiently large number of orthologous genes can be identified. We used microarray expression data for 79 physiologically normal human tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Su et al. 2004</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://symatlas.gnf.org">http://symatlas.gnf.org</ext-link>) to assess the assumption of conserved expressivity for our set of orthologs.</p><p>R scripts to calculate <italic>S</italic> with bootstrap intervals and the sets of orthologous genes analyzed here are available for download at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://people.cryst.bbk.ac.uk/&#x0223c;fdosr01/Nes/">http://people.cryst.bbk.ac.uk/&#x0223c;fdosr01/Nes/</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Estimates of <italic>S</italic> in the Baker's Yeast</title><p>There are approximately 15,000 transcripts in a yeast cell, with individual transcript species ranging from 0.1 to 80 transcripts per cell. The estimated <italic>S</italic> values ranged from 0 to 2.5 for the most highly expressed genes. As expected, there is a strong positive correlation between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values and expression levels for the yeast transcriptome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">fig. 2</xref>), with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values showing an asymptotic relationship with expression level for the highest expression values. Individual amino acids showed <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values for their optimal codons ranging from 1.04 for cysteine's TGT to 4.53 for glutamine's CAA in the three most highly expressed gene bins (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">table 1</xref>). Interestingly, genes expressed at over one transcript per cell show noticeable, albeit small, signs of selection on codon usage. Because about 40% of yeast ORFs present more than one transcript per cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">fig. 3</xref>), this percentage of the transcriptome seems to be under the action of translational selection. All optimal codons showed the same relationship of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> value to expression level when all bins are taken into account (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">fig. 3</xref>). The trend observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">figure 2</xref> was first noticed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Coghlan and Wolfe (2000)</xref> using the codon adaptation index (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sharp and Li 1987</xref>) compared against unbinned expression levels. This was later studied in more detail by Akashi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Akashi and Eyre-Walker 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Akashi 2003</xref>), comparing the relative frequency of optimal codons against binned expression data. However, our study seems to be the first comparing a formal measure of translational selection, namely <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula>, with expression levels in any organism.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Estimated <italic>S</italic> Values Partitioned according to the Optimal Codons Analyzed for the Two Bins with Highest Expression in the Yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Codon</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx5_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula><sub>ref</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx5_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula><sub>hx</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx8_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> (2.5%, 97.5%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TTC</bold></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34 (2.08, 2.63)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tyr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TAC</bold></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78 (2.32, 3.43)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cys</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TGT</bold></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.50, 2.23)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">His</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CAC</bold></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 (1.59, 2.26)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gln</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CAA</bold></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.53 (3.69, 5.27)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Asn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AAC</bold></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79 (2.44, 3.16)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Lys</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AAG</bold></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39 (2.19, 2.58)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Asp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GAC</bold></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.87, 1.27)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Glu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GAA</bold></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43 (3.03, 4.06)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57 (2.36, 2.78)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>N<sc>OTE</sc>.&#x02014;Optimal codons are shown in boldtype face.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>F<sc>IG</sc>. 2.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Expression levels versus average <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values on codon usage for the yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. Vertical bars are the bootstrap nonparametric 95% confidence intervals.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272f02_ht"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>F<sc>IG</sc>. 3.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Expression levels versus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values for each of the codons analyzed in this study for the baker's yeast. Vertical bars are the bootstrap nonparametric 95% confidence intervals. The right bottom corner depicts the frequency histogram for the expression levels of the yeast transcriptome.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272f03_lw"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Estimates of <italic>S</italic> in Other Eukaryotic Genomes</title><p>The following analysis of selection on codon usage in the nine other eukaryotic genomes is rather exploratory in nature. Because some of the assumptions of the analysis might be violated (specially the homogeneity of <italic>k</italic>), these results should be taken with care. They are presented here mainly to illustrate the problems faced when estimating selection. However, it is hoped that these results will help clear a path toward future research on this topic.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> shows average estimated <italic>S</italic> values for all the genomes studied across expression categories. As expected, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> is positively correlated with increasing expression category. What is surprising though is that the trend is strikingly similar for all species. Furthermore, orthologs belonging to the highest expression category also show the larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values across all genomes analyzed. It must be stressed here again that this analysis assumes that expression levels are conserved across all species. Also it is assumed that mutation patterns between highly and lowly expressed genes are very similar, so a meaningful estimate of <italic>S</italic> can be obtained. This is why this analysis should be regarded with care. However, the results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">figure 4</xref> are very suggestive, and further work will be needed to confirm them.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>F<sc>IG</sc>. 4.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Estimated <italic>S</italic> values across expression categories for several eukaryotic genomes. Organism codes are: mmus, <italic>Mus musculus</italic>; hsap, <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>; pfal, <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>; atha, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>; cele, <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>; ecun, <italic>Encephalitozoon cuniculi</italic>; dmel, <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>; ncra, <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic>; scer, <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>; and cneo, <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>. The values on the upper left corner of each panel are the number of orthologous genes analyzed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272f04_ht"/></fig><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref> shows estimated <italic>S</italic> values for all the optimal codons in each of the nine amino acids being considered. The two most highly expressed bins from the original yeast analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">fig. 2</xref>) were collapsed into one putatively highly expressed orthologous category to compute the values shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">table 2</xref>. All genomes analyzed, except mouse, show <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values for the most highly expressed genes that are statistically different from zero, even after correcting for multiple testing (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">table 2</xref>). It is interesting to note that optimal codons are not always the same across the genomes analyzed. For example, codon CAA coding for glutamine is preferred in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and <italic>P. falciparum</italic>, whereas its counterpart CAG seems to be consistently preferred by the other genomes. Estimates of <italic>S</italic> are statistically different from zero for most amino acids in most genomes. For those cases where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> is indistinguishable from zero, the optimal codon was arbitrarily chosen as the one with a positive <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> value. This did not cause noticeable biases in the estimation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> for the genomes analyzed.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Estimated <italic>S</italic> Values for Several Eukaryotes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic><hr/></td><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>Neurospora crassa</italic><hr/></td><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic><hr/></td><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic><hr/></td><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aa</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Codon</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tyr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cys</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.35</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.22</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">His</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gln</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAA</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.67</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAG</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.89</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.64</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Asn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Lys</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAA</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAG</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.58</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Asp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Glu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAA</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.93</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAG</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Totals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic><hr/></td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic>Encephalitozoon cuniculi</italic><hr/></td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic><hr/></td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic>Mus musculus</italic><hr/></td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic>Homo sapiens</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aa<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Codon<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic><hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic><hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic><hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic><hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x0015c;</italic><hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%<hr/></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5%<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.37</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.93</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tyr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.35</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.08</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cys</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.03</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.39</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.25</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">His</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.26</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.21</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gln</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAA</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAG</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.04</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.29</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.40</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Asn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.08</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Lys</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAA</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAG</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Asp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.21</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Glu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAA</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAG</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.20</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Totals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>N<sc>OTE</sc>.<bold>&#x02014;</bold>Aa, amino acid; tRNA, number of cognate tRNA gene copies for the given codon present in the genome (as identified with tRNAscan-SE; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lowe and Eddy 1997</xref>); 2.5% and 97.5%, are the quantiles from 1,000 bootstrap samples on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula>; and *, indicates that the mean <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> is statistically different from zero after using Bonferroni's correction for multiple testing (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The results indicated above assume that expression levels are conserved for orthologous genes across the genomes studied. There are two problems with this. First, identifying sets of orthologous genes is a complicated matter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Koonin 2005</xref>). The organisms studied here have suffered several genome expansions during their evolutionary histories (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Friedman and Hughes 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Maere et al. 2005</xref>). Groups of orthologous genes have led to the origin of sets of paralogous gene families through genome duplications across these genomes. For example, a single yeast gene might have several homologs in the corresponding mammalian genomes that could be considered true orthologs. The reciprocal BLAT search approach we used would simply find one of those several possible orthologous pairs. For example, once a yeast gene was matched with BLAT against the human RefSeq transcriptome (&#x0223c;17,000 genes), the newly found, best match human sequence was then matched back to the yeast transcriptome. If the best reciprocal match was the original yeast sequence, then this was considered a suitable orthologous pair and was kept for further analysis, otherwise, it was discarded. Of course, each one of the selected human&#x02013;yeast orthologous pairs is simply one out of several arbitrary possible pairs. It is important to note that out of &#x0223c;5,000 yeast and &#x0223c;17,000 human genes, only 1,079 were considered as suitable orthologous pairs for further analysis, so our approach attempted to be as conservative as possible. The other problem is that, even after obtaining such suitable sets of close orthologs, it is not guaranteed that their expression levels will also be conserved. We tested this for the yeast and human expression data. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref> shows that, for the particular set of orthologs analyzed for these two genomes, expression levels are relatively well conserved despite 1,500 My of evolutionary divergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Wang et al. 1999</xref>). Plotting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values versus expression for human produces essentially the same trends observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">figure 4</xref> for this organism (data not shown). These results are encouraging and suggest that a well-conserved core of eukaryotic genes exists across the genomes analyzed with conserved expression values.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>F<sc>IG</sc>. 5.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Average expression levels within orthologous gene categories for <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> and <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. The full 77 orthologous categories were used. The Spearman rank correlation between the two data sets is 0.76. This shows that the orthologous genes analyzed here for these organisms have reasonably conserved expression levels despite over 1,500 My of evolutionary divergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Wang et al. 1999</xref>). Using maximum expression levels for human transcripts (i.e., the highest observed value in any tissue) leads to very similar results as reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Urrutia and Hurst 2003</xref>). The human expression data were standardized so the median value per tissue equals 100 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Su et al. 2004</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272f05_lw"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Selection on Codon Usage and tRNA Adaptation</title><p>As mentioned above, estimated <italic>S</italic> values from a given genome simply reflect the log-odds values of codon frequencies between highly and lowly expressed genes. If the observed differences in codon frequencies are due to different mutational biases in both gene sets (e.g., if <italic>k</italic> is not constant throughout the genome), then misleading (and statistically different from zero) <italic>S</italic> values might be obtained. A good example of this was reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sharp et al. (2005)</xref> for the genomes of <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> and <italic>Nitrosomonas europaea</italic>, where peculiar base compositions bias the estimation of <italic>S</italic> values. To help decide whether estimated <italic>S</italic> values are caused by translational selection and not spurious artifacts, the <italic>S</italic> values can be compared with the <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> values suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">dos Reis et al. (2004)</xref>. The <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> test is based on the relationship between the tRNA adaptation index (tAI) and the effective number of codons (<italic>N</italic>c) used in a gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Wright 1990</xref>). tAI quantifies how well a protein-coding sequence is adapted to the genomic tRNA pool of an organism, based on the codon frequencies observed in the gene, and how well different tRNAs recognize each codon. If a gene presents a high tAI value, it is assumed that the gene in question is finely tuned to match the tRNA composition of the genome. The correlation (<italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic>) between tAI values for a suitably chosen set of genes and their corresponding (corrected) <italic>N</italic>c values gives an idea of how well codon usage and tRNA usage are coadapted in a given genome. Because selection for translational optimization acts through codon&#x02013;tRNA coadaptation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bulmer 1987</xref>), a high <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> value suggests that translational selection has been operative in the genome in question. Organisms presenting high <italic>S</italic> values averaged for highly expressed genes should also present high <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> values. It has been shown that <italic>S</italic> and <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> are moderately correlated in bacterial genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sharp et al. 2005</xref>). This correlation can be substantially improved if only highly expressed genes are used to compute <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> (dos Reis M, unpublished data). Both, <italic>S</italic> and <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> values, are complementary measures that can give insight into whether true translational selection is operative or not in a given genome. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref> shows that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> values for the 10 genomes analyzed are indeed correlated. This suggests that adaptation to the genomic tRNA configuration, and not mutational patterns, drives the trends observed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">table 2</xref>.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>F<sc>IG</sc>. 6.&#x02014;</label><caption><p><italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> versus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values for several eukaryotic genomes. Organism codes as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">figure 4</xref>. <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> values were calculated as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">dos Reis et al. (2004)</xref>. The correlation between phylogenetically independent contrasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Felsenstein 1985</xref>) for the two variables is 0.95. The contrasts were calculated for hsap, dmel, cele, scer, and atha based on a phylogeny published for these organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Wang et al. 1999</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272f06_lw"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Relationship between <italic>S</italic> and Effective Population Size</title><p>Random drift causes the nonpreferential fixation of certain alleles in a population and the elimination of others. Because the time it takes for an allele to become fixed is proportional to the population size, new mutants at individual sites tend to become fixed relatively quickly in small populations, whereas individual sites tend to remain polymorphic in larger populations. Thus, random drift causes a reduction of genetic diversity, or polymorphism, in small populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kimura 1983</xref>). This provides a way to use molecular data to estimate population size. Using polymorphism levels from gene alignments, it is possible to estimate the quantity <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic>, which is the product between the effective population size (<italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>) and the mutation rate per base pair per generation (<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>). If the mutation rate is known, then it can be factored out to obtain an estimate of <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>. Recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Lynch and Conery (2003)</xref> used this idea and gathered estimates of <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic> for several eukaryotic and prokaryotic genomes. This provides us with a unique opportunity to compare those values with estimates of selection on codon usage. This will tell us whether, as should be expected, organisms with small population sizes show signs of reduced selected codon usage bias. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref> shows the estimated <italic>S</italic> values for the most putatively highly expressed orthologs in the 10 eukaryotic genomes analyzed (these are equivalent to the three most highly expressed bins out of 77 in the yeast analysis), plotted against Lynch and Conery <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic> values. As expected, there is a positive correlation between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic>. The large mammalian genomes (<italic>M. musculus</italic> and <italic>H. sapiens</italic>) with low <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic> values show, as expected, low <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values. On the other hand, the fast-growing fungal genomes (<italic>N. crassa</italic>, <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, and <italic>C. neoformans</italic>) show the largest values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic>. The two multicellular invertebrates (<italic>C. elegans</italic> and <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>) and the plant genome (<italic>A. thaliana</italic>) present intermediate <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values with large variances. The two intracellular parasites (<italic>E. cuniculi</italic> and <italic>P. falciparum</italic>) show relatively low values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> despite intermediate <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic> values.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>F<sc>IG</sc>. 7.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Estimated <italic>S</italic> values for several eukaryotic genomes versus <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic>. Organism codes as in figure 4. The horizontal bars are the mean values, and the vertical bars are the 95% nonparametric bootstrap intervals. The Spearman rank correlation for the phylogenetically independent contrasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Felsenstein 1985</xref>) for the two variables is 0.8. The contrasts were calculated as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">figure 6</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272f07_lw"/></fig><p>The presence of selected codon bias in mammals has been contentious, with reports in favor and against the presence of translational selection (see, e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Eyre-Walker 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Urrutia and Hurst 2001</xref>). Recent works by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Urrutia and Hurst (2003)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Comeron (2004)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Yang and Nielsen (2008)</xref> have shown evidence of selected codon usage in humans and other mammals. The results presented here are compatible with the findings of these authors; however, with our current analysis we cannot assert that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values are statistically different from zero in this group of organisms, until the problem of heterogeneity in <italic>k</italic> values is addressed. In any case, the general consensus seems to be that translational selection in mammals is either nonexistent or weak. This suffices to show that selection on codon bias is correlated with effective population size as displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">figure 7</xref>. In fact, this correlation would even be stronger if the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="molbiolevolmsn272fx7_ht.jpg"/></inline-formula> values for mouse and human were completely on the zero line at the bottom right-hand side of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">figure 7</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study highlights several important issues regarding the estimation of selection on codon usage. On the first hand, which genes are selected and how they are pooled together might have dramatic effects on selection estimates. If a cutoff of 10 transcripts per cell is used to define highly expressed genes, then overall estimates of <italic>S</italic> in the baker's yeast can range anywhere from 0.75 to 2.6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">fig. 2</xref>); because many studies use a few dozen highly expressed genes for these estimates, a lot of variation should be expected. This has important implications when comparisons between different works are made. If different studies on the same organism are based on different genes, estimates of selection could differ substantially from one another despite the fact that both studies analyzed genes that could be considered highly expressed. Recently, there has been some controversy regarding estimates of <italic>s</italic> in various species of <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Maside et al. 2004</xref>), and part of the discrepancy in the estimated <italic>s</italic> values in these studies could be explained by the fact that substantially different sets of genes were analyzed. Controlling for intragenomic heterogeneity in translational selection is of great importance in comparative studies. Furthermore, studies comparing estimates of translational selection between distant species are meaningless unless orthologous gene sets are compared. It is hoped that the approach taken in this work of using orthologous sequences to estimate <italic>S</italic> in distant species will be taken up by other workers.</p><p>An important issue is the selection of the reference (i.e., under no selection) gene set in order to estimate the relative mutational bias (<italic>k</italic>). In their work on translational selection in prokaryotic genomes, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sharp et al. (2005)</xref> used all of a genome's ORF to estimate <italic>k</italic> and then <italic>S</italic> was estimated for a small subset of 40 highly expressed genes. It is clear that if selection has been widespread in a genome, the above procedure would result in an underestimation of <italic>S</italic> in highly expressed genes. We repeated Sharp's approach to the yeast genome and found an average value of <italic>S</italic> for the two most highly expressed bins equal to 2.47, a small underestimation when compared with the value of 2.57 obtained when only the lowest expressed genes are used to estimate <italic>k</italic>. In an organism like <italic>E. coli</italic>, where the proportion of genes under selection is substantially higher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">dos Reis et al. 2003</xref>), the above approach could lead to a larger error. Another problem with the estimation of <italic>k</italic> is the heterogeneity in mutational bias along genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Lynch 2007</xref>). In this work, it was assumed that mutational biases are homogeneous along the baker's yeast chromosomes. This is a reasonable assumption given the narrow distribution of G + C content in this genome. However, for some of the other eukaryotes analyzed, such as worm, fly, and human, the estimates of <italic>S</italic> are less reliable due to the larger variation in G + C content observed in these genomes (<italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">C. elegans Sequencing Consortium 1998</xref></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adams et al. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lander et al. 2001</xref>).</p><p>This issue seems to be particularly important for the mammalian genomes, where the variation in genomic G + C composition is more pronounced (isochores), reflecting dramatic differences in local mutational patterns. Biased gene conversion and transcriptionally coupled mutation in these genomes could be correlated to expression levels and might produce directional biases in the estimation of <italic>S</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Birdsell 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Duret 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Comeron 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Lynch 2007</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Urrutia and Hurst (2003)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Comeron (2004)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Yang and Nielsen (2008)</xref> have attempted, in various ways, to analyze the effect of expression levels on selected codon usage after taking into account various mutational effects. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Urrutia and Hurst (2003)</xref> showed that expression levels in human are correlated with codon bias after correcting for local nucleotide composition, however, is not clear whether their method would account for biased gene conversion or transcriptionally coupled mutation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Comeron (2004)</xref> performed a similar analysis of human expression and codon usage and found that transcription-associated mutational bias (TAMB) is a major factor determining codon usage in humans, however, for genes expressed in tissues with no evidence for TAMB, this worker found a definite preference for a set of optimal codons. Finally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Yang and Nielsen (2008)</xref> extended well-known codon substitution models to include population genetic parameters and selection on codon usage. Their model implicitly takes into account the local nucleotide composition of a gene, and it uses the phylogenetic relationship among a set of orthologous genes to estimate the substitution parameters. They tested the model on a set of 5,639 orthologs from five mammalian genomes and found, under a likelihood ratio test, that the null hypothesis of no selection on codon bias could be readily rejected. It is not the objective of this work to present a detailed analysis of translational selection in mammals. The estimated <italic>S</italic> values we report here for human and mouse simply reflect the log-odds ratio of codon usage in lowly versus highly expressed genes. Whether the relatively modest positive deviation we observe in this ratio is due to selection as suggested by the authors above or is due to other forces such as biased gene conversion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Lynch 2007</xref>) or TAMB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Comeron 2004</xref>) is a contentious topic that requires more research.</p><p>Another issue is the meaning of <italic>S</italic>. This is a confounded parameter that contains a numerical constant (2 or 4), the effective population size (<italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>), and the actual selection coefficient (<italic>s</italic>). The value of the numerical constant depends on whether the organism is haploid or diploid and, in the case of diploidy, on the selection model being considered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Crow and Kimura 1970</xref>). Nearly all studies seem to assume genic selection, if this assumption does not hold, then the exact form of <italic>S</italic> cannot be known unless a different model is explicitly specified. Furthermore, some organisms like the baker's yeast present alternating haploid and diploid phases, which could arguably lead to oscillations between 2<italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>s</italic> and 4<italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>s</italic>, with the estimated value of <italic>S</italic> being an average over the variable numerical constant. However, it is important to note that <italic>S</italic>, as defined in this work, is simply the log-odds ratio between the relative frequencies of the optimal codon in highly versus lowly expressed genes. This is, nonetheless, a useful comparative measure of selected codon usage in disparate organisms such as eubacteria, unicellular eukaryotes, or metazoans.</p><p>The results presented here show that population size has an important role affecting the operativity of translational selection. The organisms analyzed that presented the largest <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic> values also showed the largest selected codon usage bias. Although this fact was expected, this is the first time it is confirmed by empirical data. Further problems though need to be addressed before a fully clear picture can emerge. Mutation rate per base pair per generation varies from about 1 to 100&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup> in eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lynch 2006</xref>), with the lowest rates observed in free living unicellular eukaryotes and the highest rates in vertebrates. This presupposes a negative correlation between <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub> and <italic>&#x003bc;</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Lynch 2007</xref>), which, after being taken into account in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">figure 7</xref>, implies that the actual selection coefficient for codon usage, <italic>s</italic>, would be unusually high for genomes with low <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>. Another striking issue is that <italic>S</italic> for bacterial genomes ranges from 0 to 2.6 for the fastest dividing genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sharp et al. 2005</xref>), which is about the same range observed here (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">fig. 7</xref>). Giving that average population numbers for bacteria are on the order of 10<sup>8</sup>, this suggests that <italic>s</italic> would be substantially smaller for prokaryotes than eukaryotes. This paradox has been reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Lynch (2007)</xref>, and he has proposed that biased gene conversion in eukaryotes might have a substantial role in the overestimation of <italic>s</italic> in this group. Whether this is the case, it can only be confirmed with a more thorough analysis of mutational patterns in highly expressed genes. Yet another problem is the estimation of <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic> itself. Usually, silent sites in protein-coding gene alignments are used for this, and if translational selection has been widespread in a genome (as seems to be the case for unicellular eukaryotes and eubacteria), then <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>&#x003bc;</italic> itself would be underestimated. All these problems highlight the challenges that a more thorough analysis on <italic>S</italic> extended to a larger set of eukaryotic genomes will have to face.</p><p>A final future issue will be to try to understand what ecological factors or lifestyle choices affect population numbers in the organisms studied and hence their degree of selected codon bias. It is interesting to note that among the organisms studied, those with the largest genomes showed the lowest population numbers. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Lynch and Conery (2003)</xref> have proposed that although prokaryotes evolved toward multicellular eukaryotes, the consequent increase in organism size was linked to a dramatic reduction in population size due to ecological constrains. Because random genetic drift is stronger in smaller populations, this allowed the accumulation of genomic features that would have been eliminated by the action of natural selection in larger populations. These features include the evolution and expansion of introns, gene duplication, and the accumulation of repetitive DNA, mechanisms that account for genome size expansion. Lynch and Conery present convincing evidence showing that indeed population size and genome size are inversely correlated from prokaryotes to eukaryotes. These findings suggest that any form of weak selection tends to be overridden by random drift in organisms with large genomes, and this must include selection on codon usage. Lynch and Conery ideas are very appealing and could provide a nice framework onto which the action of translational selection in eukaryotes could be understood. Why translational selection behaves so idiosyncratically as to optimize codon usage in certain genomes while ignoring others is a puzzling question. Achieving reliable and consistent ways to test for selection in eukaryotes is of paramount importance in order to solve this issue and to gain a deeper understanding of the processes of molecular evolution.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was partially supported by a studentship grant to M.d.R. by the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council, UK, and by the Medical Research Council, UK. Thanks to Paul M. Sharp and Adam Eyre-Walker for valuable comments.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Celniker</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/><collab>(195 co-authors)</collab></person-group><article-title>The genome sequence of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>2185</fpage><lpage>2195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731132</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring weak selection from patterns of polymorphism and divergence at &#x0201c;silent&#x0201d; sites in Drosophila DNA</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1995</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7713409</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Codon bias evolution in Drosophila. Population genetics of mutation-selection drift</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1997</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9461401</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression and molecular evolution</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11682310</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational selection and yeast proteome evolution</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2003</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>1303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12930740</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational selection and molecular evolution</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><year>1998</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9914211</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural selection and the frequency distributions of &#x0201c;silent&#x0201d; DNA polymorphism in Drosophila</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1997</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9136019</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennetzen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Codon selection in yeast</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1982</year><volume>257</volume><fpage>3026</fpage><lpage>3031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7037777</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birdsell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrating genomics, bioinformatics, and classical genetics to study the effects of recombination on genome evolution</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2002</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>1197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12082137</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coevolution of codon usage and transfer RNA abundance</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1987</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>728</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2434856</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The selection-mutation-drift theory of synonymous codon usage</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1991</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>897</fpage><lpage>907</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1752426</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><collab><italic>C. elegans</italic> Sequencing Consortium</collab><article-title>Genome sequence of the nematode <italic>C. elegans</italic>: a platform for investigating biology</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>2012</fpage><lpage>2018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9851916</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chamary</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hearing silence: non-neutral evolution at synonymous sites in mammals</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418745</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hottes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Codon usage between genomes is constrained by genome-wide mutational processes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>3480</fpage><lpage>3485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14990797</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coghlan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship of codon bias to mRNA concentration and protein length in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10953085</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Comeron</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective and mutational patterns associated with gene expression in humans: influences on synonymous composition and intron presence</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>1304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15280243</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>An introduction to population genetics theory</source><year>1970</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harper and Row</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutter</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection intensity on preferred codons correlates with overall codon usage bias in <italic>Caenorhabditis remanei</italic></article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2053</fpage><lpage>2057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17055986</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>dos Reis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Savva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wernisch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solving the riddle of codon usage preferences: a test for translational selection</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>5036</fpage><lpage>5044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15448185</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>dos Reis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wernisch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Savva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unexpected correlations between gene expression and codon usage bias from microarray data for the whole <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 genome</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>6976</fpage><lpage>6985</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14627830</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duret</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of synonymous codon usage in metazoans</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>640</fpage><lpage>649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12433576</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Efron</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>An introduction to the bootstrap</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synonymous substitution rates in enterobacteria</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1995</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>1407</fpage><lpage>1412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7498779</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An analysis of codon usage in mammals: selection or mutation bias?</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1991</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1960741</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenies and the comparative method</article-title><source>Am Nat</source><year>1985</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene duplication and the structure of eukaryotic genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11230161</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grantham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pave</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Codon catalog usage and the genome hypothesis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1980</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>r49</fpage><lpage>r62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6986610</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harpending</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Batzer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorde</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherry</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic traces of ancient demography</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1961</fpage><lpage>1967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9465125</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moriyama</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection intensity for codon bias</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1994</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8001789</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holstege</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyrick</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hengartner</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissecting the regulatory circuitry of a eukaryotic genome</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9845373</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between the abundance of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> transfer RNAs and the occurrence of the respective codons in its protein genes: a proposal for a synonymous codon choice that is optimal for the <italic>E. coli</italic> translational system</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1981</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6175758</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Codon usage and tRNA content in unicellular and multicellular organisms</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1985</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3916708</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinouchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Codon usage and tRNA genes in eukaryotes: correlation of codon usage diversity with translation efficiency and with CG-dinucleotide usage as assessed by multivariate analysis</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>2001</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11675589</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>The neutral theory of molecular evolution</source><year>1983</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Landweber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple model based on mutation and selection explains trends in codon and amino-acid usage and GC composition within and across genomes</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><comment>research0010.1&#x02013;0010.13</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orthologs, paralogs, and evolutionary genomics</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genet</source><year>2005</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16285863</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lafay</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Atherton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Absence of translationally selected synonymous codon usage bias in <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic></article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10784043</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Linton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Birren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/><collab>(255 co-authors)</collab></person-group><article-title>Initial sequencing and analysis of the human genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>409</volume><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11237011</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>tRNAscan-SE: a program for improved detection of transfer RNA genes in genomic sequence</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9023104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origins of eukaryotic gene structure</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16280547</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>The origins of genome architecture</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Sunderland (MA)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sinauer Assoc</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Conery</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origins of genome complexity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>302</volume><fpage>1401</fpage><lpage>1404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14631042</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bodt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Raes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Casneuf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Montagu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Peer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling gene and genome duplications in eukaryotes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>5454</fpage><lpage>5459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15800040</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maside</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection on codon usage in <italic>Drosophila americana</italic></article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14738738</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McVean</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A population genetic model for the evolution of synonymous codon usage: patterns and predictions</article-title><source>Genet Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>148</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Percudani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavesi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottonello</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transfer RNA gene redundancy and translational selection in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9159473</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Averof</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Matassi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peden</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA sequence evolution: the sounds of silence</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><year>1995</year><volume>349</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8577834</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grocock</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peden</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sockett</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in the strength of selected codon usage bias among bacteria</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>1153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728743</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The codon adaptation index&#x02014;a measure of directional synonymous codon usage bias, and its potential applications</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1987</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1281</fpage><lpage>1295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3547335</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherry</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Harpending</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Batzer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoneking</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alu evolution in human populations: using the coalescent to estimate effective population size</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1997</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>1977</fpage><lpage>1982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9409852</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiltshire</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Batalov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/><collab>(13 co-authors)</collab></person-group><article-title>A gene atlas of the mouse and human protein-encoding transcriptomes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>6062</fpage><lpage>6067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15075390</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urrutia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Codon usage bias covaries with expression breadth and the rate of synonymous evolution in humans, but this is not evidence for selection</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2001</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>1191</fpage><lpage>1199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11729162</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urrutia</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The signature of selection mediated by expression on human genes</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2260</fpage><lpage>2264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12975314</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergence time estimates for the early history of animal phyla and the origin of plants, animals and fungi</article-title><source>Proc Biol Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>266</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10097391</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The &#x02018;effective number of codons&#x02019; used in a gene</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1990</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2110097</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutation-selection models of codon substitution and their use to estimate selective strengths on codon usage</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>568</fpage><lpage>579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178545</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>