<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">eid</journal-id><journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9621199</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2640124</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Emergence of the M phenotype of erythromycin-resistant pneumococci in South Africa.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Widdowson</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><email>174carol@chiron.wits.ac.za</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klugman</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>South African Institute for Medical Research, Johannesburg, South Africa.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><abstract><p>Erythromycin-resistant pneumococci have been isolated in South Africa since 1978; however, from 1987 to 1996, resistance to macrolides was only detected in 270 (2.7%) of 9,868 blood or cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) pneumococcal isolates, most of which were obtained from the public sector. In South Africa, macrolide use in the public sector is estimated at 56% of that in the private sector. Most erythromycin-resistant strains (89%) exhibited resistance to erythromycin and clindamycin (macrolide-lincosamide-streptogramin B phenotype). In the United States, most erythromycin-resistant pneumococci exhibit the newly described M phenotype (resistance to erythromycin alone), associated with the mefE gene. The M phenotype in South Africa increased significantly in the last 10 years, from 1 of 5,115 to 28 of 4,735 of blood and CSF isolates received from 1987 to 1991 compared with 1992 to 1996 (p = 5 x 10(-7)). These data suggest that, although macrolide resistance in pneumococci remains low in the public sector, the mefE gene is rapidly emerging in South Africa.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>