<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">eid</journal-id><journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9866735</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2640252</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genetic epidemiology of infectious diseases in humans: design of population-based studies.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><email>abel@biomath.jussieu.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dessein</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Institut National de la Sant&#x000e9; et de la Recherche M&#x000e9;dicale Unit 436, Mathematical and Statistical Modeling in Biology and Medicine, CHU Piti&#x000e9;-Salp&#x000ea;tri&#x000e8;re, Paris, France.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Oct-Dec</season><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><abstract><p>The spread and clinical manifestations of an infection in human populations depend on a variety of factors, among them host genetics. Familial linkage studies used in genetic epidemiology to identify host genes test for nonrandom segregation of a trait with a few candidate chromosomal regions or any regions in the genome (genomewide search). When a clear major gene model can be inferred and reliable epidemiologic information is collected (e.g., in schistosomiasis), parametric linkage studies are used. When the genetic model cannot be defined (e.g., in leprosy and malaria), nonparametric linkage studies (e.g., sibling-pair studies) are recommended. Once evidence of linkage is obtained, the gene can be identified by polymorphisms strongly associated with the trait. When the tested polymorphism is in strong linkage disequilibrium with the disease allele or is the disease allele itself (e.g., in HIV infection and malaria), association studies can directly identify the disease gene. Finally, the role of the detected polymorphism in causing the trait is validated by functional studies.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>