<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">eid</journal-id><journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9621192</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2640135</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Agricultural use of Burkholderia (Pseudomonas) cepacia: a threat to human health?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><email>aholmes@rpms.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Govan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Imperial College School of Medicine, Hammersmith Hospital, London, United Kingdom.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><abstract><p>In the past 2 decades, Burkholderia cepacia has emerged as a human pathogen causing numerous outbreaks, particularly among cystic fibrosis (CF) patients. One highly transmissible strain has spread across North America and Britain, and another between hospitalized CF and non-CF patients. Meanwhile, the organism has been developed as a biopesticide for protecting crops against fungal diseases and has potential as a bioremediation agent for breaking down recalcitrant herbicides and pesticides. However, B. cepacia is inherently resistant to multiple antibiotics; selection of strains "safe" for environmental application is not at present possible phenotypically or genotypically; molecular epidemiology and phylogenetic studies demonstrate that highly transmissible strains emerge randomly; and the organism has a capacity for rapid mutation and adaptation (facilitated by numerous insertion sequences), and a large, complex genome divided into separate chromosomes. Therefore, the widespread agricultural use of B. cepacia should be approached with caution.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>