<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">eid</journal-id><journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10221876</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2640682</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Air evacuation under high-level biosafety containment: the aeromedical isolation team.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Christopher</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name><email>Army Medical Research Institute of Infectious Diseases, Fort Detrick, Maryland 21702-5011, USA.george_christopher@detrick.army.mil</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eitzen</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>U.S. Army Medical Research Institute of Infectious Diseases, Fort Detrick, Maryland 21702-5011,</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Mar-Apr</season><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><abstract><p>Military contingency operations in tropical environments and potential use of biological weapons by adversaries may place troops at risk for potentially lethal contagious infections (e.g., viral hemorrhagic fevers, plague, and zoonotic poxvirus infections). Diagnosis and treatment of such infections would be expedited by evacuating a limited number of patients to a facility with containment laboratories. To safely evacuate such patients by military aircraft and minimize the risk for transmission to air crews, caregivers, and civilians, the U.S. Army Medical Research Institute of Infectious Diseases maintains an aeromedical isolation team. This rapid response team, which has worldwide airlift capability designed to evacuate and manage patients under high-level containment, also offers a portable containment laboratory, limited environmental decontamination, and specialized consultative expertise. This article also examines technical aspects of the team's equipment, training, capabilities, and deployments.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>