<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmj</journal-id><journal-title>BMJ : British Medical Journal</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0959-8138</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1468-5833</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19204035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2640114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">kent583211</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.b128</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Preserving professional credibility: grounded theory study of medical                    trainees&#x02019; requests for clinical support</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>Tara J T</given-names></name><role>research fellow</role><role>developmental paediatrician</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name><surname>Regehr</surname><given-names>Glenn</given-names></name><role>Richard and Elizabeth Currie chair in health professions education                        research and professor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><role>scientist</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><role>associate director</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>G Ross</given-names></name><role>professor of health policy, management and evaluation</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name><surname>Lingard</surname><given-names>Lorelei</given-names></name><role>scientist</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref><role>associate professor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref><role>BMO financial group professor and education scientist</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Wilson Centre for Research in Education, Toronto, ON,                    Canada </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Bloorview Kids Rehab, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Stan Cassidy Centre for Rehabilitation, Fredericton,                    NB, Canada</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto,                    ON,&#x000a0;Canada</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Toronto General Research Institute, University Health                    Network, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>SickKids Learning Institute, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Paediatrics, University of Toronto,                    Toronto, ON, Canada </aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>University Health Network, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence to: T Kennedy                <email>tara.kennedy@utoronto.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><!--For BMJ, both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing starting July 2008 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>338</volume><elocation-id>b128</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Kennedy et al 2009</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kennedy et al</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative                        Commons Attribution Non-commercial License, which permits unrestricted use,                        distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is                        properly cited.</p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmj.b128.pdf"/><abstract><p><bold>Objective</bold> To develop a conceptual framework of the influences on                    medical trainees&#x02019; decisions regarding requests for clinical support from a                    supervisor.</p><p><bold>Design</bold> Phase 1: members of teaching teams in internal and emergency                    medicine were observed during regular clinical activities (216 hours) and                    subsequently completed brief interviews. Phase 2: 36 in depth interviews were                    conducted using videotaped vignettes to probe tacit influences on decisions to                    request support. Data collection and analysis used grounded theory methods.</p><p><bold>Setting</bold> Three teaching hospitals in an urban setting in Canada.</p><p><bold>Participants</bold> 124 members of teaching teams on general internal                    medicine wards and in the emergency department, comprising 31 attending                    physicians, 57 junior and senior residents, 28 medical students, and eight                    nurses. Purposeful sampling to saturation was conducted.</p><p><bold>Results</bold> Trainees&#x02019; decisions about whether or not to seek clinical                    support were influenced by three issues: the clinical question (clinical                    importance, scope of practice), supervisor factors (availability,                    approachability), and trainee factors (skill, desire for independence,                    evaluation). Trainees perceived that requesting frequent/inappropriate support                    threatened their credibility and used rhetorical strategies to preserve                    credibility. These strategies included building a case for the importance of                    requests, saving requests for opportune moments, making a plan before requesting                    support, and targeting requests to specific team members.</p><p><bold>Conclusions</bold> Trainees consider not only clinical implications but                    also professional credibility when requesting support from clinical supervisors.                    Exposing the complexity of this process provides the opportunity to make changes                    to training programmes to promote timely supervision and provides a framework                    for further exploration of the impact of clinical training on quality of care of                    patients.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>A central tenet of medical education is that trainees must progressively assume more                responsibility for care of patients to become independent practitioners.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> In the course of assuming responsibility                for such care, trainees regularly encounter situations that &#x0201c;exceed their confidence                or skill to handle alone.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> In such                situations, they have an &#x0201c;obligation to secure direct assistance from faculty or                appropriately experienced residents.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> Thus                quality of care in clinical training depends, to a large part, on communication                between trainees and supervisors in the form of requests for clinical help when                required.</p><p>This reliance on trainees&#x02019; requests works much of the time, but when it doesn&#x02019;t the                results can be devastating. One infamous example of a breakdown in the supervision                request process is the 2001 case at Boston Children&#x02019;s Hospital, where a state review                determined that a 5 year old boy who died after a prolonged seizure did not receive                optimal medical treatment.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Two postgraduate                medical trainees arrived soon after the seizure began, but a senior physician was                not called to the bedside until an hour into the episode.</p><p>This case shows the link between quality of care and timely requests for clinical                help. It is potentially dangerous to assume that trainees&#x02019; requests for support                arise directly from clinical need, without complication. Ethnographic studies of                medical education and research on case presentations have suggested that                communication between trainees and their supervisors is not a straightforward                transmission of clinical information but rather is complicated by issues such as                evaluation, learning agendas, and professional socialisation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></p><p>If we are to continue to provide the educational benefit of clinical independence to                    trainees,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> a critical examination of                the process of requesting clinical support is required. We developed a conceptual                framework of the influences on trainees&#x02019; decisions to request clinical help from a                supervisor through exploration of teaching team practices.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>We designed the study using grounded theory,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref> a research method intended to develop a                theoretical explanation of a social phenomenon that is &#x0201c;grounded in&#x0201d; (that is,                derived from) naturalistic data.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>                Participants in the study were 124 members of clinical teaching teams in general                internal medicine and emergency medicine, including attending physicians (n=31),                junior and senior residents (n=57), medical students (n=28), and nurses (n=8). We                used purposeful sampling<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> to ensure                inclusion of participants of both sexes and of different levels of experience.                Sampling continued until saturation of the data was reached (the point at which                further sampling ceases to yield any new analytical concepts).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></p><p>In the Canadian medical education system, students complete an undergraduate                university degree before entering medical school. Medical school programmes last                three to four years, the final two years of which are spent training primarily in                clinical settings. The medical students in this study were all in their third or                fourth year of medical school. Graduates of Canadian medical schools then enter                postgraduate training programmes, commonly called residencies, before undertaking                the certification examinations required to practise as independent physicians. These                last from two to five or more years, depending on the degree of subspecialisation                undertaken. The junior resident participants were in their first or second year of                postgraduate training. The senior residents were all late in their second year of                specialty training after medical school or beyond.</p><p>The project took place in three academic health sciences centres associated with a                Canadian medical school in a large urban setting. Sampling from the three centres                was performed to provide a broad range of relevant perspectives and practices and to                increase transferability of resultant analytic concepts. Settings included the                emergency departments and the general internal medicine inpatient teaching wards of                the three centres. We chose these areas of intense clinical teaching to represent                different clinical supervisory structures. In the emergency medicine settings, all                trainees, regardless of seniority, assessed patients on their own and then reported                back to an in house attending physician. On the general internal medicine wards,                trainees worked in teams with at least one medical student, one or two junior                residents, a senior resident, and an attending physician. The attending physicians                and senior trainees provided supervision for junior trainees in a hierarchical                supervisory structure, with the senior resident running the day to day clinical                activities. On the general internal medicine wards, the senior resident was                generally the senior in house physician at night, while the attending physician                could be contacted at home for support. In both settings, the amount of direct                contact between attending physicians and trainees was determined by the individual                attending physician (and depended on several variables in the specific clinical                    context).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref> Throughout the course of                clinical training in Canada, attending physicians provide evaluation and feedback                for all trainees under their supervision (with input from senior trainees when they                are working in teams like in general internal medicine).</p><sec><title>Phases of study</title><p>The study was designed in two phases. Phase 1 consisted of non-participant                    observations and brief interviews. Phase 2 consisted of in depth interviews with                    video vignette prompts. The principal investigator and a research assistant                    collected all data; neither had any affiliation with the study sites or previous                    knowledge of the participants.</p><p>Phase 1 involved non-participant observation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref> of 12 teaching teams (seven in general internal medicine and five in                    emergency medicine, with a total of 88 team members observed). Each team was                    observed on six occasions over the course of one month (total of 216 hours of                    observation). Observations were scheduled to sample the maximum possible variety                    of clinical activities for each team. Detailed structured field notes were                        kept.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref> Observers initially                    recorded, in as much detail as possible, any observed interactions between                    supervising physicians and trainees (including the content of conversations, the                    context, participants and intended audience for relevant comments, and the                    non-verbal nuances involved in the interactions). In accordance with grounded                    theory principles, the structure of the field notes evolved as the study                    progressed to reflect emergent analytical concepts.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> As a source of triangulating data, 65 members of                    teaching teams also completed a brief (15 minute) interview near the end of the                    month of observations (we did not interview trainees whose rotation with the                    team finished before the end of the observation period). The interviews were                    used to explore the authenticity<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref> of                    the observational data and to probe the intentions and rationales behind                    observed behaviours. The interviews were audiotaped and were anonymised during                    transcription.</p><p>We analysed the field notes, reflective notes, and interview transcripts for                    emergent themes using grounded theory methods.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> Data collection and analysis proceeded simultaneously in an                    iterative fashion, in which the results of the ongoing data analysis informed                    subsequent data collection. Two researchers recursively read the dataset to                    develop a preliminary coding structure.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> The research team, which included a paediatric clinician educator                    (who had recently finished training), a qualitative education scientist, a                    cognitive psychologist, and a health policy researcher, discussed, refined, and                    confirmed this coding structure. Confirmability was ensured by maintaining an                    audit trail of all analytical memos, minutes of the meetings, and revisions to                    the coding structure. One coder applied the final coding structure to the                    complete dataset, using NVivo software to facilitate cross referencing.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref> Phase 1 generated a model of                    supervision practices and an exploration of how supervisors make decisions about                    the nature of the supervision to be provided to clinical trainees, which has                    been published elsewhere.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref> Phase 1                    also produced a preliminary conceptual framework regarding decisions to request                    supervision that was expanded in phase 2.</p><p>Phase 2 was designed to refine and expand the emerging conceptual framework,                    through in depth interviews with video prompts (a technique effective at probing                    unspoken behavioural influences).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref> We developed a series of 10                    videotaped vignettes (five set in general internal medicine and five in                    emergency medicine), each crafted to present a dilemma relevant to decisions                    about supervision. The vignettes were based on events that occurred during the                    observations (with details altered to render the original participants                    unidentifiable). For example, one vignette portrayed a junior resident                    deliberating about whether or not she should call her attending physician before                    giving a patient heparin in the middle of the night.</p><p>Phase 2 participants included 19 attending physicians, 13 residents, and four                    medical students. Although the interviews with attending physicians provided                    some contextual and confirmatory data that were relevant, we report here mainly                    on phase 1 data and the trainee interviews from phase 2. During the interviews,                    we asked participants to discuss their opinion of the appropriate response to                    the dilemma presented in each video vignette and to articulate other possible                    responses and their reasons for rejecting these (the discourse based interview                        method).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref> We analysed anonymised                    interview transcripts for both emergent themes and pre-selected themes that had                    emerged from the phase 1 data. We used an iterative and constant comparative                    method, in the grounded theory tradition,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> in analysis as described above.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Trainees&#x02019; decisions about whether or not to seek clinical support were influenced, as                one would expect, by the nature of the clinical situation in question, but also by                factors related to supervisors and to the trainees themselves (tables 1-3<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1"/>                <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2"/>                <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3"/>). The more urgent the clinical situation or the                more important the implications of the clinical decision to be made, the more likely                trainees were to seek support from their supervisors. As one junior resident said:                &#x0201c;I&#x02019;ll use as an example chest pain . . . if chest pain is getting to a point where                the patient might need a higher level of care then I&#x02019;ll always ask for help earlier                rather than later&#x0201d; (junior resident 14, general internal medicine). Trainees also                considered whether or not the clinical question fell within the scope of practice                that was expected of them at their level of training. They expressed reluctance to                ask for help if the clinical situation was one that they perceived they should have                mastered at their level. A senior resident explained: &#x0201c;If I want [attending                physician] to watch me suture, then he probably would laugh at me because that is                expected of me to know that&#x0201d; (senior resident 1, emergency medicine). On the other                hand, trainees seemed to have an impression of the types of clinical situation that                always warranted their contacting a supervisor. For example, one medical student                relayed a situation where there was a question about a patient&#x02019;s discharge status:                &#x0201c;I contacted [attending physician] because . . . obviously I cannot make the call of                whether or not [patient&#x02019;s name] can stay in the hospital&#x0201d; (medical student 8,                general internal medicine).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p> Clinical factors affecting requests from medical trainees for clinical                        support</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Themes and                                definitions</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Representative transcript excerpts</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top" content-type="TableSubHead"><bold>Clinical situation</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Refers to                                influence of nature of clinical situation (such as urgency,                                importance) on decisions about requests for clinical support</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;The other day                                when this guy came in short of breath . . . he just didn&#x02019;t look                                good, he was working so hard to breathe and I started to talk to                                him, and at that point I was like &#x02018;this guy could get really sick                                really fast,&#x02019; so I just ran out and called the fifth year emerg                                resident&#x0201d; (junior resident 13, emergency medicine)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top" content-type="TableSubHead"><bold>Scope of practice</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Refers to way                                trainees&#x02019; judgments about whether or not required clinical action is                                outside expected knowledge or responsibility for their programme and                                level of training influences decisions about asking for clinical                                support related to that action</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;You are expected                                to make certain decisions by yourself at a certain stage of training                                and that you are really inconveniencing someone else by asking them,                                that would be used to judge your level of competence I guess&#x0201d;                                (medical student 4, emergency medicine)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p> Supervisor factors affecting requests from medical trainees for clinical                        support</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Themes and                                definitions</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Representative transcript excerpts</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top" content-type="TableSubHead"><bold>Availability</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Refers to examples                                of how physical proximity of supervisor and timing of clinical                                situation affect likelihood that trainees will ask for clinical                                support</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;Especially if                                they&#x02019;re busy, if they&#x02019;re running around, answering pages,                                reassessing people, trying to deal with EMS calling on the patch                                phone for example . . . it can make it tough to sort of stick your                                head in and say &#x02018;can we review a case&#x02019; or &#x02018;I have a question&#x02019;&#x0201d;                                (junior resident 9, emergency medicine)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top" content-type="TableSubHead"><bold>Approachability</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Refers to                                influence of trainees&#x02019; perceptions of their relationship with                                supervisor on decisions about whether or not to ask for clinical                                support</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;There are certain                                staff that are known for . . . they don&#x02019;t like to be bothered, you                                feel that if you call them they&#x02019;ll feel it&#x02019;s just a petty problem,                                why didn&#x02019;t you look after it yourself. They&#x02019;ll think less of you as                                a resident&#x0201d; (junior resident 14, general internal medicine)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>EMS=emergency medical services (dispatching service for ambulances, etc).                    </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p> Trainee factors affecting requests from medical trainees for clinical                        support</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Themes and                                definitions</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Representative transcript excerpts</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top" content-type="TableSubHead"><bold>Expertise</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Refers to                                situations where trainees&#x02019; level of expertise has an impact on their                                ability to know when it would be appropriate to ask for clinical                                support</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;I guess one of my                                pet-peeves . . . there were sort of a bunch of things last year                                where it wasn&#x02019;t so much a problem of people didn&#x02019;t know how to                                manage patients, but they just didn&#x02019;t know how or when to call for                                help. And that&#x02019;s sort of when bad things can happen&#x0201d; (senior                                resident 8, general internal medicine)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top" content-type="TableSubHead"><bold>Desire for independence</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Refers to                                instances where trainees&#x02019; desire to take on responsibility and                                perform clinical activities independently might influence decisions                                about requesting clinical support</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;I think there is                                some personal . . . satisfaction of getting a procedure done by                                yourself especially when you are a junior, you know it is really                                satisfying, so you might try not to ask for help&#x0201d; (senior resident                                3, emergency medicine)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top" content-type="TableSubHead"><bold>Evaluation and assessment</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Refers to                                instances where trainees make decisions about requesting clinical                                support for evaluative or educational purposes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;I want to look                                like I&#x02019;m independent and I can handle questions on my own and I                                don&#x02019;t need to go to the attending for every little thing unless it&#x02019;s                                big . . . [because] you want to impress and you want to have good                                things said about you at the end of your rotations&#x0201d; (junior resident                                5, emergency medicine)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Decisions about whether or not to seek clinical support were affected not only by the                clinical implications of their question. Trainees also considered issues related to                their supervisors (table 2).<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2"/> At a practical                level, they considered their supervisor&#x02019;s proximity and availability. When                supervisors were perceived to be busy, or were not physically present and therefore                potentially busy with something else, trainees thought that their clinical question                had to be sufficiently important to warrant a call for help. One senior resident                said: &#x0201c;it&#x02019;s not so hard to ask anything if the staff is standing right there, but if                it is 1.30 in the morning and your resident is asleep . . . I think that has a big                impact&#x0201d; (senior resident 3, emergency medicine). The trainees also considered their                relationship with the supervisor when deciding whether or not to ask for                supervision. Trainees often used the term approachability to refer to their                perception of the ease with which they could ask a particular supervisor for                support. As a senior resident explained: &#x0201c;You get a vibe from your staff very                quickly on when or when you shouldn&#x02019;t ask for help. And some staff are very open and                up-front: &#x02018;call me for anything&#x02019;&#x02014;very approachable. And some staff you get the                impression that if you call them in the middle of the night it&#x02019;s going to be a huge                deal and they&#x02019;ll be talking in the morning and be sort of like &#x02018;I can&#x02019;t believe him.                He called in the middle of the night&#x02019; . . .&#x0201d; (senior resident 10, general internal                medicine).</p><p>Finally, trainees&#x02019; decisions about whether or not to seek clinical support were                influenced by factors related to the trainees themselves (table 3).<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3"/> For example, trainees described how their desire                for independence in clinical skills affected their decisions about seeking help from                supervisors. As a junior resident said: &#x0201c;It is empowering when you know you can do                that, empowering when you have a question and then you think about it and you make a                decision and then you find out later if it is right&#x0201d; (junior resident 5, general                internal medicine).</p><p>Trainees also discussed how their concern about evaluation and assessment could                affect decisions, as in the following excerpt from an interview with a senior                resident in general internal medicine: &#x0201c;Evaluations. They figure into it. To get                into med school everyone has to love you and you have to have straight As. To get                into a residency programme of your choice, everyone has to love you and you have to                have straight As. And so when you go through residency you&#x02019;re figuring you&#x02019;re still                in that mode: &#x02018;Everyone has to love me and I have to get super high marks.&#x02019; And                evaluations are all subjective right? So you piss off the guy by waking him up and                he&#x02019;s going to give you a bad evaluation. If that matters to you, you won&#x02019;t wake him                up&#x0201d; (senior resident 6, emergency medicine).</p><p>Trainees also realise that they might, in some cases, lack the expertise required to                recognise when they cannot cope and need support from their supervisors. As one                medical student put it: &#x0201c;Generally I won&#x02019;t ask for advice unless it seems urgent,                which I&#x02019;m not sure if I&#x02019;m the best judge of that&#x0201d; (medical student 1, general                internal medicine).</p><p>Many factors other than the clinical implications are therefore involved in decisions                about requests for clinical support. Furthermore, we saw that trainees struggle with                (and sometimes, particularly in the middle of the night, agonise over) the decision                of whether or not to call their supervisor to ask for help. What makes these                decisions so difficult and so complicated? The issue of credibility emerged from our                data as central to this question. Trainees perceive that their professional                credibility could be at risk when they admit to a supervisor that they need help.                Trainees perceive that asking for &#x0201c;appropriate&#x0201d; support aids credibility (akin to                &#x0201c;knowing one&#x02019;s limits&#x0201d;), but that asking too often or for too much support threatens                their credibility as a practitioner. The fact that trainees use rhetorical                strategies (persuasive arguments)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref> to                preserve their credibility when making requests for help supports this theory. We                have used the term &#x0201c;rhetorical strategy&#x0201d; here in the theoretical sense to indicate                language strategies that are purposeful, are targeted towards a particular audience,                and serve a persuasive function.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref> We do                not intend to invoke the derogatory lay meaning of rhetoric involving artificiality                or deception. Trainees used four main rhetorical strategies to preserve their                credibility when requesting clinical support from a supervisor.</p><sec><title>Building a case</title><p>Along with their request for help, trainees often emphasise details that support                    the urgency or the importance of their clinical situation as a type of                    justification for making the request. For example, in the following excerpt from                    our observation field notes (box 1), a junior resident working in the emergency                    department asked her attending physician to see a patient before she finished                    taking the history, emphasising the patient&#x02019;s level of pain.</p><boxed-text position="float" content-type="style2"><sec><title>Box 1 Transcript from field notes</title><p>JR [junior resident] comes in to the nursing station&#x02014;AP [attending                            physician] is talking to a nurse.</p><p>JR &#x0201c;Sorry . . . would you come see the guy in 12 with me? He&#x02019;s in really                            a lot of pain, writhing around on the bed, I didn&#x02019;t think I should                            wait.&#x0201d;</p><p>JR presents the case in a couple of sentences as they walk down the                            hallway.</p></sec></boxed-text></sec><sec><title>Saving questions</title><p>Trainees saved questions and asked them at times convenient to their supervisor.                    Disturbing a supervisor for an &#x0201c;insignificant&#x0201d; question was perceived as a                    threat to credibility, while asking the same question of a supervisor who was                    close by and available did not have the same implications. Consider the excerpt                    shown in box 2 from our observation notes, in which a trainee&#x02019;s decision to                    &#x0201c;save&#x0201d; her request for help in interpreting imaging results leads to a difficult                    situation.</p><boxed-text position="float" content-type="style2"><sec><title>Box 2 Transcript from field notes</title><p> JR3 [junior resident 3]: &#x0201c;Can we review some imaging? All mine are back                            now.&#x0201d;</p><p>AP [attending physician] and JR3 look at a CXR [chest x ray picture].                            They then review the old x ray together.</p><p>Nurse comes up and asks for nausea meds for the patient with                            post-concussion syndrome.</p><p>JR3: &#x0201c;That&#x02019;s my patient&#x02014;I was going to order Gravol [dimenhydrinate] and                            I forgot . . . I&#x02019;ll do that [writes orders on the chart]. I got the x                            ray of the spine and then the CT head.&#x0201d;</p><p>AP: &#x0201c;We were going to see the c-spine [cervical spine] x ray before the                            CT to decide if we needed a CT [computed tomogram] of the spine.&#x0201d;</p><p>Junior resident 3: &#x0201c;Oops . . .&#x0201d; [with grimace].</p><p>AP looks at the c-spine xrays for a long time. (There is a sense that                            they are on the borderline of being adequate to rule out a spine injury                            and that AP might have gotten the CT spine if the patient hadn&#x02019;t already                            gone up for CT head).</p><p>Attending physician: &#x0201c;I think they&#x02019;re OK.&#x0201d;</p><p>Junior resident 3: &#x0201c;Sorry I jumped the gun on the CT.&#x0201d;</p></sec></boxed-text></sec><sec><title>Making a plan</title><p>Trainees preserved credibility by making plans and then checking with a                    supervisor, rather than asking an open ended question about what to do. A senior                    resident explained: &#x0201c;Sometimes when I&#x02019;ve had questions, and really not been                    familiar with the area that my question is on, I will often try to gather some                    information before I approach my supervisor so I don&#x02019;t seem like I don&#x02019;t know                    anything&#x0201d; (senior resident 3, emergency medicine).</p><p>Attending physicians confirmed the impact of this strategy on a trainee&#x02019;s                    assessment, as in the following representative excerpt: &#x0201c;A good trainee will say                    &#x02018;Here&#x02019;s the information. Here&#x02019;s my impression and my plan. Can you check this                    before I implement it?&#x02019; And that&#x02019;s the optimal trainee. That&#x02019;s someone who&#x02019;s                    said &#x02018;Here I go, I&#x02019;ve made an effort to do everything I can, but because I&#x02019;m not                    100% comfortable I would like you to check and see if you agree.&#x02019; But not                    everybody does. Some people either go ahead and do it and then ask you, and you                    find out after or you see in the ward or written on the chart that they&#x02019;ve done                    something potentially dangerous. Or you have someone who doesn&#x02019;t even make an                    effort to come up with any plan, but just wants you to make a plan&#x0201d; (attending                    physician 15, general internal medicine).</p></sec><sec><title>Targeted questions</title><p>Trainees often targeted questions to less &#x0201c;powerful&#x0201d; members of the team, such as                    junior residents or allied health professionals, to avoid exposing a lack of                    clinical knowledge or skill to a supervisor. In this example (box 3), a junior                    resident asked for clinical information from a peer before speaking with her                    senior resident.</p><boxed-text position="float" content-type="style2"><sec><title>Box 3 Transcript from field notes</title><p>As they are waiting for SR [senior resident], JR1 and JR2 discuss a lab                            result from a patient on the floor (INR [international normalised ratio]                            is very high). JR1 mentions that she will obviously hold the Coumadin                            [warfarin] (the medication that caused the ratio to be raised) and asks                            JR2 what else he would do. JR2 suggests giving vitamin K. They agree                            that they would not give FFP [fresh frozen plasma] unless the patient                            was bleeding actively. . . JR2 then leaves to go see his patient, and                            JR1 waits for SR.</p><p>JR1: &#x0201c;The INR is 10.99.&#x0201d;</p><p>SR: &#x0201c;Wow!&#x0201d;</p><p>JR1 gives a couple of other pertinent lab results.</p><p>JR1: &#x0201c;I&#x02019;ll hold the Coumadin.&#x0201d;</p><p>SR: &#x0201c;And my next question is . . .&#x0201d;</p><p>JR1: &#x0201c;Is she bleeding&#x02014;no. I would give her vitamin K.&#x0201d;</p><p>SR: &#x0201c;Yes. I wouldn&#x02019;t give FFP unless she bleeds.&#x0201d;</p><p>JR1 goes to take care of the situation.</p></sec></boxed-text></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>During clinical training, when trainees experience progressive independence in the                care of patients, one of the main safety mechanisms is the trainees&#x02019; obligation to                ask for clinical help from a supervisor when faced with problems that exceed their                clinical knowledge and skills. We have shown the complexity of the process of                requesting support and the strategies trainees use to maintain professional                credibility when making such requests. Trainees consider the preservation of their                professional credibility along with the clinical implications of their situation                when deciding about whether and how to ask for support. Training programmes and                clinical educators should not take for granted timely requests for clinical support.</p><p>The fact that trainees are concerned about their professional credibility during                communication with their supervisors does not indicate that they are unconcerned                about patients&#x02019; wellbeing. In fact, many trainees said that concerns about patients&#x02019;                care would trump concerns about credibility. As one junior resident in general                internal medicine said: &#x0201c;you realise that if you make the wrong decision you can                cause serious harm to someone. So you get over looking stupid really quickly and                just ask for help&#x0201d; (junior resident 4, general internal medicine). Trainees&#x02019; concern                about professional credibility also involves important learning issues. The desire                to develop independence in clinical reasoning and the desire to promote an evolving                identity as an independent clinician are both appropriate educational pursuits. Thus                trainees&#x02019; consideration of professional credibility when making decisions about                asking for help is not necessarily inappropriate, but it does raise issues of                practical importance to the safety of patients on clinical teaching teams.</p><sec><title>Implications for medical education practice</title><p>Many of our participants believed that patients&#x02019; safety in clinical teaching                    situations could be improved by explicitly addressing the link between                    credibility and asking for help. One attending physician stated: &#x0201c;I have to                    break them . . . it&#x02019;s hard, but by the end of the rotation they are getting it.                    I say over and over, it&#x02019;s ok to say I don&#x02019;t know. . .&#x0201d; (attending physician 12,                    emergency medicine).</p><p>We have provided a framework for several interventions that might improve                    transparency in supervisor-trainee communication about supervision. Trainees                    could be explicitly taught rhetorical strategies such as &#x0201c;planning before                    asking&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;targeting questions&#x0201d; to increase their comfort with requesting                    support from a supervisor. An explicit &#x0201c;scope of practice&#x0201d; could be defined for                    trainees in a given context to promote a shared understanding of the types of                    situation that would always warrant contacting a supervisor (such as end of life                    discussions for junior trainees) or warrant seeking expert help (such as                    clinical criteria for accessing a rapid response team).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref> Requests for assistance could be                    explicitly included in the clinical evaluation process, with feedback provided                    on performance of this skill. The impact of such interventions on the teaching                    team environment and quality of patients&#x02019; care will be important to evaluate.</p><p>Our results are also important for clinical supervisors who want to maximise the                    quality of the clinical care provided by their teaching teams. An understanding                    of the factors involved in trainees&#x02019; decisions about requesting support allows                    the management of these factors to promote clinical supervision. To give a                    simple example, consider the issue of availability of a supervisor. Our dataset                    was filled with instances where trainees reported that they considered asking                    for help but decided against it because their supervisor wasn&#x02019;t close by, and                    they thought that their question wasn&#x02019;t important enough to warrant a phone call                    to someone who might be busy with something else. Addressing the issue of                    supervisor proximity by increasing the number of times supervisors and trainees                    meet during the day might promote timely discussion about trainees&#x02019; clinical                    concerns. An evaluation of the effects of such changes to supervision practices                    on care outcomes would lay the groundwork for the necessary, but as yet largely                    neglected, study of the links between supervision practices and quality of                        care.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></p><p>Our study shows that asking for help from a supervisor involves a complex                    decision making process for medical trainees. This leads to a question of key                    importance to medical educators: how and why has a medical training culture                    evolved in which asking for help can be so difficult? Medical anthropologists                    such as Bosk<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref> and Sinclair<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> have described how factors like                    professional responses to error<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref> and                    evaluation processes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> can contribute                    to a lack of transparency in communication between medical trainees and their                    supervisors. Further exploration of this phenomenon from a sociocultural                    perspective will be required better to understand, and ultimately influence, the                    multifactorial contributors to the generation of a medical training culture in                    which asking for help is sometimes problematic for trainees.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>Our results should be interpreted with observer effect<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref> and transferability in mind.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref> We took two important measures to minimise the impact                    of observer effect on the results. Firstly, a consistent researcher (the                    principal investigator or a research assistant, both unknown to participants                    before the study) conducted observations for periods of three hours or more, so                    that team members could get used to the observer&#x02019;s presence. Secondly,                    participants were not made aware of the specific focus on supervision until                    after the observations were completed (participants consented to having all                    discussions between attending physicians and trainees recorded) to prevent them                    from altering this specific aspect of their work. With respect to                    transferability, it is important to consider that these data were collected in                    an urban setting and on medical services. The fact that the reported themes were                    common across the two distinct clinical settings (general internal medicine and                    emergency medicine), the three separate institutions with different supervision                    policies and practices, and the broad range of participants within each setting                    supports the transferability of the analysis. It remains to be tested, however,                    whether the theory of credibility will be relevant in different settings (such                    as surgical services or rural teaching practices).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Medical trainees consider not only clinical implications but many other factors                    when requesting support from a supervisor. Requests for support are perceived by                    trainees as potential threats to their professional credibility, and trainees                    thus use several rhetorical strategies to preserve credibility during these                    requests. The exposure of the complexity of this taken for granted process                    provides the opportunity to make changes to training programmes that might                    promote timely discussion of trainees&#x02019; clinical concerns and also provides a                    framework for necessary further exploration of the impact of clinical training                    practices on quality of patient care. </p><boxed-text position="float" content-type="style3"><sec><title>What is already known on this topic</title><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>The quality of clinical care provided to patients by medical                                    trainees depends on the assumption that trainees can and will                                    request clinical support from their supervisors when                                required</p></list-item><list-item><p>Communication between medical trainees and their supervisors is                                    complicated by issues such as evaluations and learning                                agendas</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>What this study adds</title><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Interview and observational data from clinical teaching teams                                    showed that trainees&#x02019; decisions about requesting support from                                    clinical supervisors are complex</p></list-item><list-item><p>Trainees consider not only clinical implications but also                                    personal credibility when making requests for clinical                                support</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exposure of factors affecting medical trainees&#x02019; requests for                                    clinical support provides the opportunity to make changes to                                    clinical training programmes to promote timely clinical                                    oversight by supervisors</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text></sec></sec></body><back><notes><fn-group><fn><p>We thank Douglas Buller of the Wilson Centre, University of Toronto, for his                        technical expertise in the production of the videos, and Lisa Kitchen of the                        University of Ontario Institute of Technology for her invaluable work in                        data collection and study coordination.</p></fn><fn fn-type="participating-researchers"><p>Contributors: All authors contributed to the conception and design of the                        study, the analysis and interpretation of the data, critical revision of the                        manuscript, and obtaining funding for the study. They are all guarantors.                        TJTK acquired the data and drafted the manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>Funding: This study was supported by an operating grant from the Canadian                        Institutes of Health Research (CIHR), which had no involvement in the                        research process. LL is supported by a CIHR New Investigators Award.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Competing interests: None declared.</p></fn><fn><p>Ethical approval: This study was approved by the institutional review board,                        and informed consent was given by all participants.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Field notes, emergency medicine team 5, day 1</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Field notes, emergency medicine team 5, day 4</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p> Field notes, general internal medicine team 7, day 5</p></fn></fn-group></notes><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other">American Association of Medical Colleges.                        <source>Compact between resident physicians and their teachers</source>                        <year>2006</year> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aamc.org/meded/residentcompact/">www.aamc.org/meded/residentcompact/</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal">AAMC policy guidance on graduate medical                    education: assuring quality patient care and quality education. <source>Acad                        Med</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>-6.</citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other">Royal College of Physicians and Surgeons of Canada.                        <source>General standards of accreditation</source> <year>2002</year>                        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rcpsc.medical.org/publications/index.php">http://rcpsc.medical.org/publications/index.php</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="other">General Medical Council. <source>The new                    doctor</source> London: GMC, <year>1997</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="other">General Medical Council. <source>Standards of                        training for the foundation programme</source> <year>2007</year> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gmc-uk.org/education/documents/Standards_for_Training_270307.pdf">www.gmc-uk.org/education/documents/Standards_for_Training_270307.pdf</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="other">Australian Medical Association. <source>AMA position                        statement: prevocational medical education and training</source>                    <year>2005</year> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ama.com.au/web.nsf/doc/WEEN-6JVTW2">www.ama.com.au/web.nsf/doc/WEEN-6JVTW2</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="other">Pope J. Even top hospitals make mistakes.                        <source>CBS News</source><year>2003</year>, September 29. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2003/09/29/health/main575546.shtml">www.cbsnews.com/stories/2003/09/29/health/main575546.shtml</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lingard L, Garwood K, Schryer CF, Spafford MM. A                    certain art of uncertainty: case presentation and the development of                    professional identity. <source>Soc Sci                        Med</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>603</fpage>-16.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12570977</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal">Sommers PS, Muller JH, Saba GW, Draisin JA, Shore                    WB. Reflections-on-action: medical students&#x02019; accounts of their implicit beliefs                    and strategies in the context of one-to-one clinical teaching. <source>Acad                        Med</source><year>1994</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>S84</fpage>-6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7916839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="other">Konner M. <source>Becoming a doctor</source> New                    York: Viking Penguin, <year>1987</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="other">Sinclair S. <source>Making doctors</source> Oxford:                    Oxford International Publishers, <year>1997</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kennedy TJ, Regehr G, Baker GR, Lingard LA.                    Progressive independence in clinical training: a tradition worth defending?                        <source>Acad                    Med</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>S106</fpage>-11.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199447</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other">Glaser B, Strauss A. <source>The discovery of                        grounded theory: strategies for qualitative research</source> Chicago:                    Aldine, <year>1967</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kennedy TJ, Lingard LA. Making sense of grounded                    theory in medical education. <source>Med                        Educ</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16451236</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="other">Charmaz K. Grounded theory: objectivist and                    constructivist methods. In: Denzin N, Lincoln Y, eds. <source>Handbook of                        qualitative research</source> Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage,                    <year>2000</year>:509-35.</citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="other">Charmaz K. Grounded theory in the 21st century:                    applications for advancing social justice studies. In: Denzin N, Lincoln Y, eds.                        <source>The Sage handbook of qualitative research</source> Thousand Oaks,                    CA: Sage, <year>2005</year>:507-36.</citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="other">Strauss A, Corbin J. <source>Basics of qualitative                        research</source> Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications,                <year>1998</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal">Morse JM. The significance of saturation.                        <source>Qual Health                        Res</source><year>1995</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>-9.</citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kennedy TJ, Lingard L, Baker GR, Kitchen L, Regehr                    G. Clinical oversight: conceptualizing the relationship between supervision and                    safety. <source>J Gen Intern                        Med</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1080</fpage>-5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17557190</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="other">Hammersley M, Atkinson P. <source>Ethnography:                        principles in practice</source>, London: Routledge,                <year>1995</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="other">Denzin N, Lincoln Y. Introduction: the discipline                    and practice of qualitative research. In: Denzin N, Lincoln Y, eds. <source>The                        Sage handbook of qualitative research</source> Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage,                        <year>2005</year>:1-32.</citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="other">Kelle U. <source>Computer-aided qualitative data                        analysis: theory, methods, and practice</source> Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage,                        <year>2002</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ginsburg S, Regehr G, Lingard L. To be and not to                    be: the paradox of the emerging professional stance. <source>Med                        Educ</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>350</fpage>-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12654120</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ginsburg S, Regehr G, Stern D, Lingard L. The                    anatomy of the professional lapse: bridging the gap between traditional                    frameworks and students&#x02019; perceptions. <source>Acad                        Med</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>516</fpage>-22.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12063195</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="other">Odell L, Goswami D, Herrington A. The                    discourse-based interview: a procedure for exploring the tacit knowledge of                    writers in nonacademic settings. In: Odell L, Goswami D, eds. <source>Writing in                        nonacademic settings</source>, New York: Guilford Press,                <year>1985</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="other">Burke K. <source>Language as symbolic action: essays                        on life, literature, and method</source> Berkeley, CA: University of                    California Press, <year>1966</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lingard L, Haber RJ. Teaching and learning                    communication in medicine: a rhetorical approach. <source>Acad                        Medcine</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>507</fpage>-10.</citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal">King E, Horvath R, Shulkin DJ. Establishing a                    rapid response team (RRT) in an academic hospital: one year&#x02019;s experience.                        <source>J Hosp                    Med</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>296</fpage>-305.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17219515</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal">Devita MA, Bellomo R, Hillman K, Kellum J, Rotondi                    A, Teres D, et al. Findings of the first consensus conference on medical                    emergency teams. <source>Crit Care                        Med</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>2463</fpage>-78.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16878033</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="other">Bosk CL. <source>Forgive and remember: managing                        medical failure</source> Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press,                        <year>2003</year></citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal">Holden JD. Hawthorne effects and research into                    professional practice. <source>J Eval Clin                        Pract</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>-70.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11240840</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="other">Lincoln Y, Guba EG. <source>Naturalistic                    inquiry</source> Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage, <year>1985</year></citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="citation-text"><p><bold>Cite this as:</bold>                <italic>BMJ</italic> 2009;338:b128</p></notes><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Field notes, emergency medicine team 5, day 1</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Field notes, emergency medicine team 5, day 4</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p> Field notes, general internal medicine team 7, day 5</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>