<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Case Reports</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Medical Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1752-1947</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19183441</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2642857</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1752-1947-3-42</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-1947-3-42</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Two-dimensional power Doppler-three-dimensional ultrasound imaging of a cesarean section dehiscence with utero-peritoneal fistula: a case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Royo</surname><given-names>Pedro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>proyo@alumni.unav.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Manero</surname><given-names>Manuel Garc&#x000ed;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mgmanero@unav.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Olartecoechea</surname><given-names>Bego&#x000f1;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>bolarteco@unav.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Alc&#x000e1;zar</surname><given-names>Juan Luis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jlalcazar@unav.es</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Clinica Universitaria de Navarra, Avenida Pio XII, 36, 31008 Pamplona, Spain</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>7</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2009 Royo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Royo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jmedicalcasereports.com/content/3/1/42"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>An imaging diagnosis after an iterative cesarean delivery is reviewed demonstrating a fine ultrasound-pathologic correlation.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 33-year-old woman (G3, P3) presented referring intense dysmenorrhea and intermenstrual spotting since her third cesarean delivery, 1 year before. A cesarean section dehiscence with utero-peritoneal fistula was diagnosed by transvaginal ultrasound.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We can conclude that transvaginal two-dimensional power Doppler and three-dimensional ultrasound are highly accurate in detecting cesarean section dehiscence and uterine fistula.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The uterine fistula is a known and uncommon entity as a possible result of gynecological surgery or other pathologic conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The lower segment type of cesarean section has increased the prevalence of these uterine fistulous processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. An imaging diagnosis after an iterative cesarean delivery is reviewed demonstrating a fine ultrasound-pathologic correlation. Our objective is to report an unusual case of utero-peritoneal fistula in cesarean scar defect diagnosed by color Doppler hysterosonography and three-dimensional ultrasound.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 33-year-old woman (G3, P3) presented referring intense dysmenorrhea and intermenstrual spotting since her third cesarean delivery, 1 year earlier. The patient's medical history and physical examination did not reveal any relevant finding. Two-dimensional-three-dimensional transvaginal ultrasound scans were performed with a Voluson 730 Expert system (GE Healthcare, Milwaukee, WI, USA) and IC5&#x02013;9 (5&#x02013;9 MHz) wide band Convex probe. Power Doppler settings were set to achieve maximum sensitivity to detect low velocity flow without noise (frequency, 5 MHz; power Doppler gain, -7.4; dynamic range, 20&#x02013;40 dB; edge, 1; persistence, 2; color map, 5; gate, 2; filter, L1; and pulse repetition frequency, 0.6 kHz). The scan showed a hematoma (5.3 cm<sup>3</sup>) between the cesarean section scar and the bladder peritoneum. The bladder wall was not involved (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The lower uterine segment had a 9 &#x000d7; 12 mm wall defect and an anechoic track that seemed to communicate the blood collection with the endometrial cavity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Afterwards, the power Doppler examination demonstrated the presence of active blood flow across the myometrium (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). Finally, the treatment performed was an abdominal hysterectomy and the pathologic study confirmed the process as being of ischemic origin (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Three-dimensional transvaginal ultrasound scan (in multiplane acquisition mode) of the uterus-hematoma-bladder complex (UT, HM, BD respectively)</bold>. Please note that the white pixel (placed in the center of each image) always correspond with the same space point of the three orthogonal planes, and is located referring HM, between UT (at the level of the uterine scar) and just beneath BD. Defect's surface three-dimensional reconstruction (of the coronal plane) correspond with bottom right picture, and is framed with a white arrow (instead of white pixel).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-1947-3-42-1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Two-dimensional transvaginal uterine (UT) ultrasound on longitudinal plane showing the communication (arrow) of the hematoma (HM) with the endometrial cavity (EC)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-1947-3-42-2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Intra-operative picture showing the defect on the lower uterine segment after dissection (arrow)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-1947-3-42-3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Pathological image of the uterus showing the defect</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-1947-3-42-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Uterine fistulas are infrequent pathologic entities and are characterized by abnormal communication of the uterus with any other organ or structure through a perforation due to traumatic or infectious conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The lower segment type of cesarean section has increased the prevalence of these uterine fistulous processes, which account for 83% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Rarely, it could be related to long labor, forceps delivery, vaginal birth after cesarean section, gynecological injuries, tuberculosis of the genital tract or intrauterine contraceptive devices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Our patient could not be considered as having Youseff's syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] because the bladder wall was not involved and, in addition, the three types of vesico-uterine fistulas defined by Jozwik and Jozwik were also ruled out [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. This case must be considered as an utero-peritoneal fistula, because the uterovesical pouch of peritoneum that covers the ventral surface of the uterus (separated from the bladder) was not affected.</p><p>The presence of the fistula can explain the symptoms referred by the patient during her menstrual cycle, with the passage of blood to the peritoneal cavity (causing peritoneal irritation with pelvic pain) and the vagina (causing intermenstrual spotting) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Transvaginal ultrasound and color Doppler hysterosonography have been used successfully in many cases to allow direct visualization of the uterine fistulae. It has been demonstrated that the normal sonographic appearance of the uterine incision as distinguishable from the abnormal appearance in patients who were symptomatic after cesarean section [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Benacerraf <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] showed three sonographic patterns for the uterine scar, including a dense, echogenic area; a fluid-filled area anterior to the site of the wound between the uterus and the bladder (our case); and a sonolucent area at the site of the wound between the external surface of the lower uterine segment and the lumen of the uterus. Transvaginal ultrasound is highly accurate in detecting cesarean hysterotomy scars. The cesarean scar defect, defined by the presence of fluid within the incision site, is more common when labor precedes cesarean delivery and with multiple cesarean deliveries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>The advantage of three-dimensional gynecological ultrasound (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) is the possibility of obtaining coronal planes and their surface reconstruction which provides new image features which are not possible to obtain with conventional two-dimensional ultrasound [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>As non-invasive alternative procedures, magnetic resonance imaging with heavily T2-weighted images may show a bright fluid-filled tract, and computed tomography can also be diagnostic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p><p>Conservative management may be attempted, especially for patients with few symptoms, as the tract may spontaneously close [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The pregnancy rate after repair is 31.25% with a rate of term deliveries of 25% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. After dehiscence repair, due to the high risk of uterine rupture or dehiscence, a new delivery should be performed by repeating a cesarean section [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Transvaginal two-dimensional power Doppler and three-dimensional ultrasound are highly accurate in detecting cesarean section dehiscence and uterine fistula.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>PR (as corresponding author) and BO took intraoperatory photos, reviewed the literature and drafted the case description and discussion. MGM, a specialist in obstetrics and gynecology, revised and corrected all areas in the text covering this field. JLA, a specialist in obstetric and gynecology imaging, acquired and interpreted the sonographic images and revised and corrected all relevant areas of the text.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional File 1</title><p><bold>Video</bold>. Real-time B-mode and power Doppler video showing the blood moving between the hematoma and the endometrial cavity and which demonstrates the utero-peritoneal fistula.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-1947-3-42-S1.avi" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="x-msvideo"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr Guillermo L&#x000f3;pez Garc&#x000ed;a for his valuable suggestions.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guimar&#x000e3;es Filho</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>da Costa</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanforlin Filho</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nardozza</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Diagnosis of uteroperitoneal fistula through color Doppler hysterosonography</article-title><source>Arch Gynecol Obstet</source><year>2007</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00404-006-0306-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17219161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Porcaro</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zicari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zecchini Antoniolli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pianon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Migliorini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Comunale</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Vesicouterine fistulas following cesarean section: report on a case, review and update of the literature</article-title><source>Int Urol Nephrol</source><year>2002</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1024443822378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12899224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><article-title>Menouria following lower segment Caesarean section. A syndrome</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><year>1957</year><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13411039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jozwik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jozwik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Clinical classification of vesicouterine fistula</article-title><source>Int J Gynaecol Obstet</source><year>2000</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0020-7292(00)00247-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10967170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bromley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitcher</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Klapholz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Benacerraf</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><article-title>Sonographic appearance of uterine scar dehiscence</article-title><source>Int J Gynaecol Obstet</source><year>1995</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0020-7292(95)80009-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8582519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andreotti</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischer</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>LE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><article-title>Three-dimensional sonography of the endometrium and adjacent myometrium: preliminary observations</article-title><source>J Ultrasound Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1313</fpage><lpage>1319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16998104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbaric</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><article-title>Fistulas of the genitourinary tract: a radiologic review</article-title><source>Radiographics</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1331</fpage><lpage>1352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/rg.245035219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15371612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bashiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burstein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheiner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Clinical significance of uterine scar dehiscence in women with previous cesarean delivery: prevalence and independent risk factors</article-title><source>J Reprod Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18251354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>