<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="article-commentary" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19266021</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2643474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PLGE-PV-0005R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000370</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspective</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Cell Biology/Microbial Growth and Development</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Chromosome Biology</subject><subject>Microbiology/Microbial Evolution and Genomics</subject><subject>Molecular Biology/Centromeres</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Neocentromeres Come of Age</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>Owen J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>K. H. Andy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Chromosome and Chromatin Research, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, Parkville, Victoria, Australia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Paediatrics, University of Melbourne, Parkville, Victoria, Australia</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Copenhaver</surname><given-names>Gregory P.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>andy.choo@mcri.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><!-- Fake ppub added to accomodate plos workflow change from 03/2008 --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e1000370</elocation-id><copyright-statement>Marshall, Choo. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" vol="5" page="e400" id="N0x1c72ff0N0x1fd71f0" ext-link-type="pmc"><article-title>Neocentromeres Form Efficiently at Multiple Possible Loci in Candida albicans</article-title></related-article><counts><page-count count="3"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Sixteen years ago, the discovery of a newly formed, ectopic centromere in a human <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Voullaire1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-duSart1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref> was a turning point for centromere research. Whereas previously centromeres had been thought of as immovable and unchanging, embedded in vast tracts of tandemly repeated DNA, this new centromere&#x02014;or neocentromere&#x02014;lacked any characteristic centromeric DNA sequences and had formed in a gene-rich area of the genome. Essentially, a fully functional centromere had spontaneously arisen where no centromere had any right to be, complete with all the necessary centromere proteins and epigenetic marks required for the creation of a complex DNA/protein structure. Neocentromere formation remains one of the most astonishing examples of epigenetic change within the genome.</p><p>Since this discovery, neocentromeres (not to be confused with the &#x0201c;classical&#x0201d; facultative neocentromeres, which were originally described in maize (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Dawe1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>) have been shown to be a means of centromere repositioning during karyotype evolution and speciation in vertebrates, with evidence suggesting a similar role in plants (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Marshall1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>). Clearly, there is an evolutionary advantage in being able to form new centromeres, and this process has been conserved. However, an understanding of the mechanisms of neocentromere formation remains elusive.</p><p>It was this question that Ketel et al., in this issue of <italic>PLoS Genetics</italic>, set out to answer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Ketel1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>. The authors based their study on the pathogenic fungus <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, which has small, simple, regional centromeres flanked by inverted repeats, and extremely high rates of homologous recombination. Their approach was to specifically remove the centromeric DNA on Chromosome V by replacing it with <italic>URA3</italic>, a selectable marker gene, and observe the positioning and frequency of neocentromeres that resulted via chromatin immunoprecipitation for the fundamental centromere marker protein CENP-A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000370-g001">Figure 1A</xref>).</p><fig id="pgen-1000370-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000370.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Formation of neocentromeres in <italic>C. albicans</italic>.</title><p>(A) The existing centromere on Chromosome V, together with the surrounding inverted repeats, is replaced with the <italic>URA3</italic> gene via homologous recombination, resulting in neocentromere formation either proximal (B) or distal (C) to the original centromere. Selection against <italic>URA3</italic> expression results in either chromosome loss (E) or silencing of <italic>URA3</italic> through centromere shifting (D). If resistant colonies from the latter case are again grown on uridine-deficient media, a second shift in the position of the centromere restores <italic>URA3</italic> expression (F).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000370.g001"/></fig><p>The results were striking: the authors found an extremely high frequency of neocentromere formation (with neocentromeres forming in all transformants) at multiple possible locations along Chromosome V. Essentially, these neocentromeres fell into two distinct classes: proximal neocentromeres, which formed close to the location of the original, excised centromere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000370-g001">Figure 1B</xref>); and distal neocentromeres, which formed at all other locations on the chromosome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000370-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). Although experimentally induced neocentromere formation has been previously investigated in flies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Williams1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Maggert1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>, plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Nasuda1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, and other fungi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Ishii1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, this is the first example, to our knowledge, where neocentromeres have been found to form at seemingly random chromosomal locations, similar to human neocentromeres (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000370-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pgen-1000370-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000370.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Organisms in which neocentromere formation has been reported.</title><p>From left to right are: humans (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Marshall1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>), flies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Williams1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Maggert1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>, wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Nasuda1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Ishii1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, and <italic>C. albicans</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Ketel1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000370.g002"/></fig><p>In most cases, the size of the neocentromeres was similar to a normal <italic>C. albicans</italic> centromere, albeit with reduced quantities of CENP-A. Would the resulting neocentromeres be less stable during mitosis? To find out, Ketel et al. used a standard assay to gauge chromosome stability, growing the transformant strains on 5-FOA media, which is toxic to Ura&#x0002b; cells. Those transformants with distal neocentromeres became resistant through loss of the neocentric chromosome at a rate comparable to control strains, suggesting that <italic>Candida</italic> neocentromeres suffered no loss of mitotic stability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000370-g001">Figure 1E</xref>).</p><p>However, transformants with proximal neocentromeres (near the selectable marker gene) became FOA-resistant at a much higher rate. Astonishingly, though, this was not due to higher rates of chromosome loss. In these strains the neocentromere had shifted onto the <italic>URA3</italic> gene, thereby silencing <italic>URA3</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000370-g001">Figure 1D</xref>). Furthermore, moving the resistant strains back onto media selective for uridine synthesis resulted in the neocentromere shifting away from the gene and <italic>URA3</italic> expression being restored (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000370-g001">Figure 1F</xref>).</p><p>Does this mean, then, that centromeres are incompatible with gene expression? Experiments such as the current work and recent reports in fission yeast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Castillo1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02014;where genes inserted within centromeric chromatin were similarly down-regulated&#x02014;would suggest that this is the case. But these results are somewhat contradicted by results in human cells, where at both a neocentromere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Saffery1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref> and artificially generated chromosomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Nakashima1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Lam1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref> gene expression has been demonstrated despite the presence of CENP-A. Such observations may point to a different chromatin environment between humans and fungi at centromeres. Alternatively, it is possible that centromeric chromatin is merely impermissible to high levels of gene transcription&#x02014;both experiments in fungi reported very low levels of reporter gene transcription still occurring. But such observations are intriguing considering recent reports of transcription at centromeres <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-BouzinbaSegard1">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>, and investigation of the precise relationship between centromeric chromatin and transcription is likely to become an important research focus in the future.</p><p>A key question regarding neocentromere formation has been whether there are any DNA sequence motifs required for a new centromere to arise. Using the three distal neocentromeres isolated in this study, Ketel et al. were unable to find any common sequence between the three regions. The only similarity, indeed, seemed to be that all neocentromeres formed within intergenic regions on the chromosome&#x02014;not surprising, perhaps, considering the negative effect that centromeric chromatin appears to have on gene expression in <italic>Candida</italic>. It is unfortunate, though, that so few distal neocentromeres were analysed, making it impossible to tell if <italic>C. albicans</italic> has &#x0201c;hotspots&#x0201d; of neocentromere similar to those found on human chromosomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000370-Marshall1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. And what of the large number of proximal neocentromeres that arose? The high frequency of proximal neocentromere formation makes these neocentromeres difficult to explain through an occasional shifting or spreading of the centromeric signal. Perhaps there are other epigenetic marks conducive to centromere formation that lie outside of the excised <italic>cen5</italic> region.</p><p>So what can we conclude from this research? Clearly, <italic>C. albicans</italic> provides an excellent model system for studying the process of neocentromere formation, and the current work throws up many new questions regarding both the process of centromere formation and its impact upon transcription. What this work undeniably demonstrates, though, is that the ability to form neocentromeres is common from fungi to humans and is clearly an integral part of the genome.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pgen.1000370-Voullaire1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voullaire</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>A functional marker centromere with no detectable alpha-satellite, satellite III, or CENP-B protein: activation of a latent centromere?</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>1163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7684888</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-duSart1"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>du Sart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cancilla</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Earle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Saffery</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>A functional neo-centromere formed through activation of a latent human centromere and consisting of non-alpha-satellite DNA.</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><comment>doi:10.1038/ng0697-144</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9171825</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Dawe1"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawe</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiatt</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Plant neocentromeres: fast, focused, and driven.</article-title><source>Chromosome Res</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><comment>doi:10.1023/B:CHRO.0000036607.74671.db</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289670</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Marshall1"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chueh</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>KHA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Neocentromeres: new insights into centromere structure, disease development, and karyotype evolution.</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><comment>doi:10.1016/j.ajhg.2007.11.009</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18252209</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Ketel1"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ketel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HSW</given-names></name><name><surname>McClellan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchonville</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Selmecki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Neocentromeres form efficiently at multiple possible loci in <italic>Candida albicans</italic>.</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>5(3)</volume><fpage>e1000400</fpage><comment>doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1000400</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Williams1"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Karpen</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Neocentromere activity of structurally acentric mini-chromosomes in Drosophila.</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9425896</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Maggert1"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maggert</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Karpen</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>The activation of a neocentromere in Drosophila requires proximity to an endogenous centromere.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>158</volume><fpage>1615</fpage><lpage>1628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11514450</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Nasuda1"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nasuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudakova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Houben</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Stable barley chromosomes without centromeric repeats.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>9842</fpage><lpage>9847</lpage><comment>doi:10.1073/pnas.0504235102</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15998740</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Ishii1"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogiyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chikashige</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Soejima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Heterochromatin integrity affects chromosome reorganization after centromere dysfunction.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>321</volume><fpage>1088</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><comment>doi:10.1126/science.1158699</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18719285</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Castillo1"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellone</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Plasticity of fission yeast CENP-A chromatin driven by relative levels of histone H3 and H4.</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>e121</fpage><comment>doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.0030121</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17677001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Saffery1"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saffery</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Transcription within a functional human centromere.</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14536089</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Nakashima1"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiraoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Assembly of additional heterochromatin distinct from centromere-kinetochore chromatin is required for de novo formation of human artificial chromosome.</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>5885</fpage><lpage>5898</lpage><comment>doi:10.1242/jcs.02702</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16339970</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-Lam1"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonney</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Human centromeric chromatin is a dynamic chromosomal domain that can spread over noncentromeric DNA.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>4186</fpage><lpage>4191</lpage><comment>doi:10.1073/pnas.0507947103</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16537506</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000370-BouzinbaSegard1"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouzinba-Segard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guais</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Francastel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Accumulation of small murine minor satellite transcripts leads to impaired centromeric architecture and function.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>8709</fpage><lpage>8714</lpage><comment>doi:10.1073/pnas.0508006103</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731634</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>