<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diagn Ther Endosc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DTE</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diagnostic and Therapeutic Endoscopy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1070-3608</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1029-0516</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19229344</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2643052</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2008/721850</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Endoscopic Findings in Loin Pain Hematuria Syndrome: Concentric Clot in Calyceal Fornices</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Canales</surname><given-names>Benjamin K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Windsperger</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lukasewycz</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Monga</surname><given-names>Manoj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Department of Urologic Surgery, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN 55455-0392, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Manoj Monga: <email>monga002@umn.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Recommended by J. Stuart Wolf</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>2008</volume><elocation-id>721850</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Benjamin K. Canales et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The loin pain hematuria syndrome (LPHS) creates a considerable burden, both for patients afflicted with the disease and for those involved in medical management and diagnosis.  To date, the diagnosis of LPHS remains one of exclusion, with some speculation regarding the extent of actual pathology.  We report ureteroscopic findings in 2 cases of LPHS.  These findings provide objective confirmation of underlying pathology in a difficult-to-manage disease process.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="section" id="sec1"><title>1. INTRODUCTION</title><p>Loinpain hematuria syndrome (LPHS) describes  a constellation of clinical featuresincluding recurrent flank pain  and intermittent hematuria without a readilyidentifiable cause [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Historically, LPHS has been associatedwith psychiatric illness and is now widely considered a type of somatoform paindisorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Multidisciplinary pain management strategies include analgesics, nerveblockade, renal denervation, and/or nephrectomy with autotransplantation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Though some studies suggestthat long-term prognosis is usually excellent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], many urologists and patients would contest this.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec2"><title>2. METHODS</title><p>Two patients with severe chronic flank pain punctuated byintermittent gross hematuria were evaluated after laboratory and radiographicevaluation failed to delineate a recognizable pathology, raising the suspicionof a diagnosis of LPHS.  Patientsunderwent ureteroscopic evaluation using a no-touch technique. Ureteroscopicevaluation was performed on the side where the patient reported pain, and/orbloody efflux was noted from the ureteral orifice.</p><p>After informed consent and induction of generalanesthesia, visual inspection of the bladder was performed using a 19 Fr Rigidcystoscope. Subsequently, a 6/7.5 Fr Wolf semirigid ureteroscope was insertedand the ureteral orifice of the symptomatic side cannulated without the use ofa guidewire.  The ureteroscope wasadvanced under direct vision with the use of minimal hand irrigation of saline,utilizing a Boston Scientific single-action pump.  Semirigid ureteroscopy was utilized to thelevel of the proximal ureter.  A BostonScientific sensor guidewire (0.035&#x0201d;) was advanced through the working channelto the tip of the ureteroscope and the ureteroscope was then withdrawn, usingintermittent fluoroscopy to confirm that the guidewire did not advance beyondthe point of ureteroscopic inspection. The Olympus URF-P3 flexible ureteroscope was then backloaded over thefloppy-tip of the sensor wire and advanced under fluoroscopic guidance to thepoint of last inspection, following which the guidewire was removed.  Systematic inspection of the entirecollecting system was then performed with the flexible ureteroscope, takingcare to utilize minimal irrigation throughout the procedure.  A Holmium laser was kept on stand-by in theevent that pathology was to be identified and could be successfully ablated.  Following completion of the procedure, theureter was inspected as the ureteroscope was withdrawn to evaluate for injury,and as none was identified a ureteral stent was not left in place.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec3"><title>3. RESULTS</title><p>Patient1 is a 26-year-old female with a 3-year history of severe right flank pain andgross hematuria beginning in 2003.  Herpain was described as stabbing and located in the lower back and right flankwith radiation to the lower abdomen.  Shereported episodes of intense pain every three to four months that lasted 2&#x02013;4 weeks, with anotable basal level of pain in between exacerbations.  The patient underwent ureteral stentplacement and ureteroscopic extraction of a small stone following a bout ofpain in 2004, and following this, had CT scans with and without contrast thatdid not demonstrate any stones, masses, or hydronephrosis.   The patient presented in early 2005 with arecurrence of symptoms including pain, fever, and microscopic hematuria.  A CT scan with and without IV contrastobtained at this time did not demonstrate any evidence of renal calculi,hydronephrosis, or renal mass.  Withnormal imaging studies, the patient was treated with IV antibiotics witheventual relief of symptoms.  In late2005, the patient was admitted to the hospital with severe right flank pain,fever, and gross hematuria.  Her urinespecimen contained large blood without organisms, signs of infection, orpositive culture or cytology.  Anephrology consult was obtained for a nephritis workup revealing a normal serumcomplement and ANCA screen, a negative Hepatitis C antibody, and negativeantiglomerular basement antibody test. Further studies included an unremarkable CT angiogram of the kidney toevaluate for AV malformation.  Thedecision then made to perform bilateral diagnostic ureteroscopy during this episodeof pain and gross hematuria.  Right rigidand flexible ureteroscopy was performed, using a wireless, no-touch techniquewith minimal irrigation fluid.  Diffusebleeding in a pattern of ring-like clots was noted from each fornix surroundingall calyces of the collecting system, without any identifiable masses orneoplasia (see Supplementary Video in Supplementary Material available online at doi:10.1155/2009/721850).  The patient received aninpatient pain management consultation and was maintained on Neurontin 300 mgthree times daily and Dilaudid 4&#x02013;8 mg every four tosix hours.  The patient is currentlyseeking counseling regarding more aggressive treatments such as nephrectomy orautotransplantation.</p><p>Patient 2 is an 18-year-old female with a 2-year historyof severe left flank pain with intermittent gross hematuria.  The patient presented in 2005 to an outsideinstitution and underwent ureteroscopic evaluation for her flank pain.  A small hemangioma was reportedly identifiedand cauterized during this evaluation. Additionally, the patient was noted to have low-grade vesicoureteralreflux, and a deflux procedure was performed in 2006 with alleviation of painassociated with voiding.  However, painnot associated with voiding persisted, and the patient underwent laparoscopicevaluation by gynecology in 2006.  Thisshowed the presence of a Meckel's diverticulum and several small spots ofendometriosis, and the patient underwent diverticulectomy, intervalappendectomy, and fulguration of the endometriosis.  The patient continued to have intermittentbouts of severe left flank pain, often requiring ER visits and significantamounts of IV narcotics.  The patientunderwent several CT scans with and without IV contrast that did notdemonstrate any evidence of renal calculi, masses, or hydronephrosis.</p><p>An outpatient renal consult was requested, and a fullunremarkable work up for her hematuria was performed, including urinemicroscopy and cytology, CT angiogram, 24-hour urine collection studies, andnegative nephritis work up.  She thenunderwent left ureteroscopic evaluation utilizing the wireless, no-touchtechnique, which again demonstrated a similar pattern of diffuse bleeding in apattern of ring-like clots from each fornix surrounding all calyces of thecollecting system of the left kidney. The patient received an inpatient pain management consultation and wasmaintained on Levsin 0.25 mg every 24 hours, a 50 mcg Fentanyl patch every 72hours, Dilaudid 8 mg every four hours, Neurontin 300 mg three times daily, andFlexeril 10 mg three times daily.  Thepatient eventually elected to undergo left-sided nephrectomy withautotransplantation into the right lower quadrant of her abdomen withresolution of her symptoms.  The patienthas since developed right flank pain suggestive of LPHS in her contralateralkidney, and has undergone intrathecal catheter placement, epidural catheterplacement, and most recently a right lower quandrant fascial pain block.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec4"><title>4. DISCUSSION</title><p>Though some studies suggest that long-term prognosis forLPHS is excellent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], many urologists and LPHS patients would contestthis. Rates of spontaneous resolution of pain symptoms in LPHS have beenreported to typically occur over a 2&#x02013;5-year period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. For those without pain resolution, prognosis can be poor and treatment may involvea multidisciplinary approach with both pain management services (chronic analgesics,nerve blockade, open or laparoscopic renal denervation, and/or nephrectomy withautotransplantation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]) and psychiatric evaluation (LPHS is consideredby some to be a type of somatoform pain disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]).</p><p>Thepathogenesis of flank pain associated with LPHS is thought to be due to glomerularcapillary hemorrhage resulting in tubular obstruction and interstitial edema [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Over time, chronic edema is thought to result in capsular distention, pain, andfurther tubular obstruction and hemorrhage. To our knowledge, we are the firstto report the endoscopic findings of LPHS. Both LPHS patients underwentdiagnostic ureteroscopy using minimal irrigation fluid (to avoid distension ofthe renal pelvis) and a wireless, no-touch technique (to rule out iatrogenic,traumatic cause of bleeding). In both patients, ring-like clots consistent withrecent hemorrhage were identified from each fornix surrounding all calyces ofthe collecting system (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">1(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">1(b)</xref>). Because diagnosis is the first step in understanding pathophysiology, wehypothesize that these endoscopic findings may represent a clinical, endoscopicmanifestation of glomerular hemorrhage and obstruction that has not beenpreviously reported.</p><p>It isimportant to realize that both LPHS patients underwent unremarkable fullwork-up, with CT urogram, CT angiography, nephrology consultation, andlaboratory investigation. All other treatable causes of pain and hematuria mustbe ruled out in these cases. Once excluded, however, upper tract endoscopydemonstrating hematuria and concentric calyceal clots may strengthen thediagnosis of LPHS and confirm the presence of a physiological disorder in thispoorly understood disease.  Thisobjective confirmation of disease may result in more definitive diagnoses ofLPHS, though a larger series is needed to confirm the results.  Such supportive evidence is critical as moreaggressive pain management and/or surgical approaches are considered by thepatient and family.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="supplementary-material-sec"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="f1"><caption><p>The Supplementary Video shows diffuse bleeding in a pattern of ring-like clots that was noted from each fornix surrounding all calyces of the collecting system, without any identifiable masses or neoplasia.</p></caption><media xlink:href="721850.f1.wmv" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="x-ms-wmv"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloper</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wardener</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A syndrome of loin pain and haematuria associated with disease of peripheral renal arteries</article-title><source><italic>The Quarterly Journal of Medicine</italic></source><year>1967</year><volume>36</volume><issue>142</issue><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4227314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leaker</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neild</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loin pain and haematuria syndrome: a somatoform disorder</article-title><source><italic>The Quarterly Journal of Medicine</italic></source><year>1995</year><volume>88</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>709</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mailis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hematuria-loin pain syndrome: its existence as a discrete clinicopathological entity cannot be supported</article-title><source><italic>The Clinical Journal of Pain</italic></source><year>1997</year><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9186025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratner</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasr</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loin pain hematuria syndrome</article-title><source><italic>Kidney International</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>70</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2152</fpage><lpage>2155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17051141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weisberg</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Viner</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loin pain hematuria syndrome</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Nephrology</italic></source><year>1993</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8267018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spetie</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadasdy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadasdy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proposed pathogenesis of idiopathic loin pain-hematuria syndrome</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Kidney Diseases</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>47</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16490620</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Ureteroscopic images demonstrating ring-like clots surrounding each calyx in the collecting system.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DTE2008-721850.001"/></fig></floats-group></article>