<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19240801</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2643479</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PONE-RA-07302R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004598</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Ecology</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subject>Plant Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>How Many Loci Does it Take to DNA Barcode a Crocus?</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Limitations of DNA Barcoding</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seberg</surname><given-names>Ole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>Gitte</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Laboratory of Molecular Systematics, Natural History Museum of Denmark, Copenhagen, Denmark</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>Jane Catherine</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Trinity College Dublin, Ireland</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>oles@snm.ku.dk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: OS GP. Performed the experiments: OS GP. Analyzed the data: OS GP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: OS GP. Wrote the paper: OS GP.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e4598</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Seberg et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>DNA barcoding promises to revolutionize the way taxonomists work, facilitating species identification by using small, standardized portions of the genome as substitutes for morphology. The concept has gained considerable momentum in many animal groups, but the higher plant world has been largely recalcitrant to the effort. In plants, efforts are concentrated on various regions of the plastid genome, but no agreement exists as to what kinds of regions are ideal, though most researchers agree that more than one region is necessary. One reason for this discrepancy is differences in the tests that are used to evaluate the performance of the proposed regions. Most tests have been made in a floristic setting, where the genetic distance and therefore the level of variation of the regions between taxa is large, or in a limited set of congeneric species.</p></sec><sec><title>Methodology and Principal Findings</title><p>Here we present the first in-depth coverage of a large taxonomic group, all 86 known species (except two doubtful ones) of crocus. Even six average-sized barcode regions do not identify all crocus species. This is currently an unrealistic burden in a barcode context. Whereas most proposed regions work well in a floristic context, the majority will &#x02013; as is the case in crocus &#x02013; undoubtedly be less efficient in a taxonomic setting. However, a reasonable but less than perfect level of identification may be reached &#x02013; even in a taxonomic context.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions/Significance</title><p>The time is ripe for selecting barcode regions in plants, and for prudent examination of their utility. Thus, there is no reason for the plant community to hold back the barcoding effort by continued search for the Holy Grail. We must acknowledge that an emerging system will be far from perfect, fraught with problems and work best in a floristic setting.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="6"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The primary aims of DNA barcoding are to identify known specimens and to help flag possible new species, thereby making taxonomy more effective for science and society (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barcoding.si.org">www.barcoding.si.org</ext-link>).</p><p>The majority of DNA barcoding studies in animals have used a small region of the mitochondrial gene, cytochrome c oxidase subunit I (COI), as barcode, and COI is promising, with a few exceptions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Blaxter1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, to be the universal barcode for animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Waugh1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>. The search for a universal barcode in plants has been far more tortuous, but general agreement is emerging that more than one region is needed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref> (for a dissenting view; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Lahaye1">&#x0005b;see 8&#x0005d;</xref>), and that these regions will need to come from the plastid genome, where several different regions have been suggested. The plant mitochondrial genome is usually far too conservative to be of use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Cowan1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Muse1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, whereas the plastid genome shares several of the desirable properties found in the animal mitochondrion. The nuclear multi-copy internal transcribed spacers array (ITS) has also been suggested as a barcode <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Kress1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, but has been discarded due to its peculiar pattern of evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Wendel1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref> and currently the nuclear genome is largely inaccessible for barcoding purposes. However, current advances in sequencing technology and the diminishing expenses promise radically to change the way we do barcoding; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Kane1">&#x0005b;see e.g. 11&#x0005d;</xref>. The majority of plastid regions have been proposed on the basis of comparisons of levels of variation in whole genomes of closely related taxa, e.g. congeneric species, and subsequently tested in taxonomically widely dispersed, randomly chosen species pairs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Kress1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Kress2">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref> and/or in a purely floristic setting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Lahaye1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Taberlet1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>. As a consequence, emphasis is placed on primer universality at the expense of species recognition; see however Fazekas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Chase et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, using data predominantly drawn from GenBank, and acknowledging the imperfect nature of these data, suggested the use of one or two, unspecified, plastid regions plus ITS as potentially useful plant barcodes. Almost simultaneously Kress et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Kress1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref> pointed to the potential value of a combination of ITS and the <italic>trnH-psbA</italic> spacer. The choice of the latter region was based on a combination of comparisons of the complete plastid genomes of deadly nightshade (<italic>Atropa belladonna</italic> L.) and tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> L.), and tests on a small, taxonomically defined set of species and a larger one defined geographically. Using a similar approach, but restricting the search to coding plastid regions only, Chase et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref> selected a number of potentially useful regions (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kew.org/barcoding">www.kew.org/barcoding</ext-link>) that subsequently were tested by a number of research groups worldwide on a limited taxon set. Based on an evaluation of their overall performance in these tests, a smaller set was chosen subsequently, and these favoured regions tested more widely, and two sets were proposed eventually as universal barcodes, <italic>rpoC1</italic> and <italic>matK</italic> plus either <italic>rpoB</italic> or <italic>trnH-psbA</italic>. However, these two triplets were challenged by Kim et al., who preferred a combination of <italic>matK</italic>, <italic>atpF-H</italic>, and <italic>psbI-psbK</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Pennisi1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>On the basis of its ability to distinguish between congeneric species-pairs, Newmaster et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Newmaster1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref> proposed <italic>rbcL</italic> as the first tier in their proposal of a two-tiered approach to barcoding; allowing the next region to be an optional choice. Kress and Erickson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Kress2">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref> refined this proposal by suggesting only the 3&#x02032; end of <italic>rbcL</italic> as their first choice and adding <italic>trnH-psbA</italic> as their preferred second choice, again basing their conclusion on tests involving congeneric species-pairs. However, using a relatively dense taxonomic coverage (35&#x00025; (mobot.mobot.org/W3T/Search/vast.html) of known species in a single genus), Newmaster et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Newmaster1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>, while maintaining their choice of <italic>trnH-psbA</italic>, replaced <italic>rbcL</italic> with <italic>matK</italic>. This conclusion was supported by Lahaye et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Lahaye1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref> on the basis of geographically defined, purely floristic and similarly designed but broader taxonomic studies in a test of all regions suggested by Chase et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Acknowledging the low resolution of the <italic>trnL</italic> intron, even in a floristic context, Taberlet et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Taberlet1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref> none the less suggested its use as a plant barcode, primarily due to the capability of its P6 loop to distinguish species in highly degraded or processed material. Based on a taxonomic study with the hitherto densest taxon sampling, 48&#x00025; of all 278 known species of a single genus, Edwards et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Edwards1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> suggested that at least three regions were necessary to discriminate most of the studied species, including a new region <italic>trnT-trnL</italic> in combination with ITS and &#x0201c;at least one more region with a greater level of variation than <italic>psbA-trnH</italic>&#x0201d; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Edwards1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Even COI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref> and 23S rDNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Presting1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref> have been suggested as barcodes for plants, but have both been proven too invariable to be of general use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results and Discussion</title><p>Here we present the first analysis of the performance of one of the recently proposed barcode sets by Chase et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>, <italic>rpoC1</italic>, <italic>matK</italic>, and <italic>trnH-psbA</italic>, in a large, taxonomically defined, monophyletic group; the genus <italic>Crocus</italic> L. (Iridaceae). We tested these regions on 86 (98&#x00025;) species of the genus <italic>Crocus</italic>, excluding only two species of doubtful taxonomic status. To this set of regions we have added three other regions, two of which have been considered of potential value as barcodes (<italic>rps8-rpl36</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Kress1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref> and <italic>accD</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>), plus <italic>ndhF</italic>, which we have used for phylogenetic purposes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Petersen1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. The taxon sampling was not designed to capture intraspecific variation, but 17 species include more than one accession each (from 2 to 15). Though few studies of plants take intraspecific variation into account, this may be a bigger problem than generally believed, by reducing the barcode gap and consequently the success rate of identification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;see 7&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>The proposed barcode set <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref> is diagnostic for 63 (73&#x00025;) of the included <italic>Crocus</italic>-species, which is only marginally better than the combination <italic>matK</italic> and <italic>psbA-trnH</italic> alone, which identifies 62 (72&#x00025;) species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004598-t001">Table 1</xref>). Substituting <italic>rpoC1</italic> with any of the two other considered regions, <italic>accD</italic> or <italic>rps8-rpl36</italic>, improves species recognition to 67 (78&#x00025;) and 65 (76&#x00025;), respectively. Using the four most variable of these above-mentioned regions (<italic>ndhF</italic>, <italic>matK</italic>, <italic>trnH-psbA</italic>, and <italic>rps8-rpl36</italic>) makes it is possible to identify 79 species (92&#x00025;), a figure that is not changed by adding the two least variable regions (<italic>accD</italic> and <italic>rpoC1</italic>). In all instances the species level resolution is higher than the ones obtained by Fazekas el al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref> using a similar number of loci. This is undoubtedly due to our non-tree based approach, which does not require gene-tree monophyly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. Interestingly, <italic>ndhF</italic>, which has not been suggested as a barcode due to lack of primer universality, has a higher resolving power than <italic>matK</italic>, which is one of the top candidates as a universal barcode. However, in most instances some regions will perform better than others no matter which are chosen as barcodes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. In general, identification success was not influenced by the inclusion of length variation. It is worth mentioning that the two alternative regions proposed by Kim et al. at the Consortium for the Barcode of Life meeting in Taipei, in addition to <italic>matK</italic>, do not behave, in a smaller subset of <italic>Crocus</italic> species (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004598.s002">Tables S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004598.s003">S2</xref>), better than any of those suggested by Chase et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Chase2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0004598-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004598.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Sequence variation and species identification ability of six plastid regions in combinations in 86 species of <italic>Crocus</italic>.</title></caption><graphic id="pone-0004598-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0004598.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0004598-t001-1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique species (&#x00025;)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ndhF</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>matK</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (80&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ndhF</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>trnH-psbA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (77&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>matK</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>trnH-psbA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (72&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ndhF</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>matK</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>trnH-psbA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (87&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>matK</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>trnH-psbA</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>accD</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (78&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>matK</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>trnH-psbA</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>rps8-rpl36</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (76&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>matK</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>trnH-psbA</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>rpoC1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (73&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>ndhF</italic></bold><bold>&#x0002b;</bold><bold><italic>matK</italic></bold><bold>&#x0002b;</bold><bold><italic>trnH-psbA</italic></bold><bold>&#x0002b;</bold><bold><italic>rps8-rpl36</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>79 (92&#x00025;)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ndhF</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>matK</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>trnH-psbA</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>accD</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (90&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ndhF</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>matK</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>trnH-psbA</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>rpoC1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (87&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ndhF</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>matK</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>trnH-psbA</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>rps8-pl36</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>accD</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>rpoC1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (92&#x00025;)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>The best combination, i.e., the combination of the fewest number of sequences yielding the highest number of identified species, is marked in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0004598-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004598.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Sequence variation and species identification ability of six plastid regions individually in 86 species of <italic>Crocus</italic>.</title></caption><graphic id="pone-0004598-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0004598.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0004598-t002-2"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aligned length</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Variable sites</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable sites (excl./incl.gaps)/aligned length</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique species (&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">excl. gaps</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">incl. gaps</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ndhF</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">769</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/19&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (71&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>matK</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">842</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/20&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">&#x0002a;</xref> (58&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>trnH-psbA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">698</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/22&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (49&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rps8-rpl36</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">554</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/18&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (34&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>accD</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/10&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (21&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rpoC1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">575</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (13&#x00025;)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>Of 85 species. DNA was no longer available for <italic>C. hartmannianus</italic> Holmboe.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>With the notable exception of <italic>rbcL</italic>, most of the plastid regions that have been suggested as official barcodes, and hence potentially being the most variable regions, stems from the same limited region, covering approximately &#x0223c;15&#x00025; of the large single-copy region of the plastid, spanning from <italic>rpoB</italic> to <italic>trnH-psbA</italic>. Hence, it is not surprising that &#x0201c;there are multiple multilocus plant DNA barcoding combinations that perform about equally well in resolving species&#x0201d; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004598-g001">figure 1</xref> the relationship between the number of <italic>Crocus</italic> species identified is plotted as a function of the number of basepairs sequenced and the best fitting curve is added. Solving the equation for y&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;86 (the maximum number of species) gives x&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;5859, and it appears reasonable, at least in theory to postulate that it would require approximately 5800 bp from the plastid genome to identify all known species of <italic>Crocus</italic>. This corresponds to 9&#x02013;10 average-sized (&#x0223c;600 bp) barcode genes/regions and is presently not a workable option. Using a differently defined taxon sampling and a different criterion for correct identification a similar relationship between number of barcode regions and discrimination ability was found by Fazekas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0004598-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004598.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The relationship between sequence length and the number of <italic>Crocus</italic> species identified.</title><p>The genus includes 86 known species, and the six regions (five proposed barcode regions plus <italic>ndhF</italic>) used here identify 79 species. The regions are added according to their ability to identify species. The performance of individual genes is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004598-t002">Table 2</xref>. The logarithmic trend line (y&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;12.3 ln(x)&#x02212;21.0) and the R<sup>2</sup> (&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.97) were calculated in Excel&#x000ae; and checked in JMP, Version 7. SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, 1989&#x02013;2007.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004598.g001"/></fig><p>Also, it would be problematic to flag potentially new species using these data because several species, most notably <italic>C. biflorus</italic> Mill. and <italic>C. reticulates</italic> Steven ex Adams, have non-monophyletic sets of plastid genomes (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004598.s001">figure S1</xref>). Disagreement between the evolutionary histories of organellar and nuclear genomes are not uncommon in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Syring1">&#x0005b;see e.g. 19&#x0005d;</xref>) and animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Funk1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>, and it is a controversial point whether reciprocal monophyly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Meyer1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref> is a necessary requirement in barcoding. However, if reciprocal monophyletic species are mandatory this is bound to decrease identification success; see e.g. Fazekas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. Using the same approach as Fazekas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref> and a bootstrap cut-off value of 70&#x00025; only two of the 17 species represented by more than one accession in the present analysis are monophyletic and two paraphyletic.</p><p>In a barcoding context (e.g. Barcode of Life Data System (BOLD); <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.boldsystems.org">www.boldsystems.org</ext-link> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Costa1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>), identification is often conducted by reference to clusters of taxa in a neighbor-joining (NJ) tree using an average Kimura-2-parameter model. If this approach is used on the <italic>Crocus</italic> data set, many of the branch lengths are extremely short, making species assignment of new accessions spurious at best (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004598-g002">figure 2</xref>). To aggravate this, a whole suite of NJ trees may be produced from the same dataset, due to the known input-order sensitivity of NJ. Resampling techniques are occasionally used to justify species monophyly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;see e.g. 7&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Lahaye1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Hajibabaei1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref> or to justify species identification; see e.g. Fazekas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. Due to their innate properties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Hillis1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>} and their very different implementation in different computer programmes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Davies1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref> the use of resampling in this context is ill-advised, and would have made little sense here.</p><fig id="pone-0004598-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004598.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Neighbor-joining tree of <italic>Crocus</italic>.</title><p>The extremely short branches make identification by cluster memberships difficult as does the &#x0201c;non-monophyly&#x0201d; of several species. Species that cannot be identified by any of the sequences used are marked in blue. The NJ tree is rooted with the two <italic>Crocus</italic> species that are sister group to the remaining <italic>Crocus</italic> species in the parsimony based phylogeny (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004598.s001">figure S1</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004598.g002"/></fig><p>As in any other group of species, species circumscription in <italic>Crocus</italic> may be problematic, and this may be one factor underlying the observed lack of resolution. However, there is no reason to believe that taxonomic problems are more severe in <italic>Crocus</italic> than in many other taxa. Even in groups with an almost universally agreed upon species-level taxonomy, e.g., barley (<italic>Hordeum</italic> L.) with 32 species, it is impossible to recognise more than approximately 50&#x00025; of the species using <italic>matK</italic> and <italic>rpoC1</italic> (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004598.s004">Table S3</xref>). Perhaps the worst case scenario is found among the morphologically distinct species of the Gal&#x000e1;pagos sunflower tree, <italic>Scalesia</italic> Arn.(Asteraceae), where no variation has been found (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004598.s005">Table S4</xref>) in the plastid markers, and almost none in nuclear markers.</p><p>Barcode efforts in plants are severely hampered by an obvious lack of agreement about the choice of regions. Opinions are divided on whether two or three regions suffice, whether regions should be coding or non-coding, whether one should or should not use a tiered approach, and ultimately on which regions are to be preferred and how the data are analysed, and the baseline for comparison has been ill-defined <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Lahaye1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Helfenbein1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Kress3">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>. In the most thorough comparison of all suggested regions to date, both with respect to technical and variability issues, it is recommended that three (or even four) regions, one coding (<italic>rbcL</italic>, <italic>rpoB</italic>, <italic>matK</italic>) and two non-coding (<italic>trnH-psbA</italic>, <italic>atpF-atpH</italic>), are selected as official barcodes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref> as this represents a reasonable compromise between effort and species resolution as it is currently implemented in the Barcode of Life Data System.</p><p>Both the present study and the study by Fazekas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Fazekas1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref> show that there is a limit to resolution no matter which region or regions are chosen. The present study shows that in a taxonomic setting and with a reasonable effort it is unlikely that barcoding will enable us to identify more than around 70&#x02013;75&#x00025; of the known species &#x02013; in some instances less, in others more.</p><p>However, the time is ripe for selecting barcode regions in plants, and for prudent examination of their utility. Based on the level of sequence variation alone, an optimal set of regions is not yet known, but <italic>matK</italic> and <italic>trnH &#x02013;psbA</italic> are strong candidates, though other conditions much notably primer universality and sequence quality have to be taken into account. However, we must acknowledge that the emerging system will be far from perfect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Sass1">&#x0005b;see e.g. 29&#x0005d;</xref>), and that it will work best in a floristic setting.</p><p>Thus, there is no reason for the plant community to hold back the barcoding effort by continued search for the Holy Grail <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Rubinoff1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s3"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Taxon sampling</title><p>Taxon sampling was as extensive as possible. Of the 81 species recognized by Mathew <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Mathew1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref> all but one, <italic>Crocus boissieri</italic> Maw, known only from a herbarium specimen, are included, as are six of the seven species described since then. Of the 50 recognized subspecies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Mathew1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref> 48 are included, but only two of the 10 later described ones. A total of 17 species were represented by more than one accession, and the total number of included accessions of <italic>Crocus</italic> is 131. Two species of <italic>Romulea</italic> Maratti, and one species each of <italic>Syringodea</italic> D. Don, <italic>Babiana</italic> Sims, and <italic>Tigridia</italic> Juss. were included as outgroups. Voucher information and GenBank accession numbers may be found in Petersen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Petersen1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Molecular methods</title><p>DNA extractions were performed using the DNeasy Plant Mini Kit (QIAGEN Ltd., Crawley, West Sussex) after tissue disruption in a FastPrep FP-120 bead mill (Qbiogene, Carlsbad, CA). PCR amplifications followed standard procedures except for the addition of 0.1 mg/ml BSA to most reactions. For PCR amplification and sequencing of the five plastid regions the following primers were used: ndhF1318F and ndhF2110R <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Olmstead1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>, accD1F and accD3R (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kew.org/barcoding/protocols.html">http://www.kew.org/barcoding/protocols.html</ext-link>), rpoC1F and rpoC4R (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kew.org/barcoding/protocols.html">http://www.kew.org/barcoding/protocols.html</ext-link>), rpl36F and rps8R <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Kress4">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>, and psbAF and trnH2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Sang1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Tate1">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>. Direct sequencing of purified PCR products was performed using BIGDYE 1.1 (Applied Biosystems, Wellesley, Massachusetts, USA) and purified sequencing products were run on an AB3130xl automated sequencer (Applied Biosystems). Sequence editing was done using Sequencher versions 4.5 to 4.7 (Gene Codes Corporation, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Sequence analysis</title><p>In order to assess the potential value of the six sequence regions as barcodes, the outgroup taxa and the hybrid taxon <italic>C.&#x000d7;jessopae</italic> Bowles were excluded. All variable sites were included, and so was an ambiguously aligned region of <italic>trnH-psbA</italic> previously excluded from phylogenetic analysis. PAUP&#x0002a;, version 4.0b8 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Swofford1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref> provided numbers of variable sites. The number of uniquely identifiable species was checked using MacClade version 4.08 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Maddison1">&#x0005b;37&#x0005d;</xref>. A species is considered uniquely identifiable if all the included specimens/subspecific taxa can be identified. Thus, species monophyly is <italic>not</italic> a requirement. Alignments were done manually and the matrix is available at TreeBase (acc no. M3519, S1912).</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Tree-based analysis</title><p>All phylogenetic analyses were performed using PAUP&#x0002a;, version 4.0b8 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Swofford1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>. Uninformative characters were excluded from the phylogenetic analyses, and informative characters were equally weighted and treated as unordered. Gaps were treated as ambiguous data (?). Analyses were performed using both the default branch collapsing rule (collapse if maximum is zero) and amb- (collapse if minimum length is zero). The latter option was used for facilitating comparison of results from phylogenetic analyses using PAUP&#x0002a; with result from analyses using WinClada <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Nixon1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>. Under the default branch collapsing rule and simple sequence addition the number of equally parsimonious trees was very high (hitting the limit of 637.000 defined by memory allocation) and analyses without an upper limit for the number of saved trees could not be run to completion. Thus, we also used a two step approach first running 1.000 random addition sequences saving no more than 25 trees per replicate. The trees saved in this analysis were used as starting trees for a new analysis with a maximum number of trees saved set to 100.000. Phylogenetic analyses performed using WinClada, version 1.00.08 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Nixon1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>, spawning the matrix to NONA version 2.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004598-Goloboff1">&#x0005b;39&#x0005d;</xref> were executed using heuristic search options hold10000, mult&#x0002a;100, max&#x0002a;, hold/10, and the default branch collapsing rule, amb-.</p><p>Neighbor-joining was also done in PAUP 4.0b8, using the default settings and Kimura-2-parameter distance option.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s4"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004598.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>Strict consensus tree of Crocus and five outgroup taxa.</p><p>(6.33 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004598.s001.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004598.s002"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>Sequence variation and species identification ability of eight plastid regions in Crocus series Crocus. Crocus series Crocus is monophyletic (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004598.s001">figure S1</xref>) and includes nine species (C. sativus L., C. cartwrightianus Herb., C. hadriaticus Herb., C. thomasii Ten., C. oreocreticus B. L. Burtt, C. asumaniae B. Mathew &#x00026; T. Baytop, C. mathewii Kernd. &#x00026; Pasche, C. pallasii Goldb., C. moabiticus Bornm. &#x00026; Dism. ex Bornm). Three species (C. sativus, C. cartwrightianus, C. hadriaticus) cannot be identified be any sequence. The length of the region atpF-H is 570&#x02013;572 bp (573 bp in alignment). atpF-H GenBank acc. nos. EU523361-EU523373. The region psbI-K is very short (ca. 173&#x02013;179 bp), but difficult to sequence due to several longer runs of T's (at least 3 runs of 9&#x02013;10 or more T's).</p><p>(0.03 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004598.s002.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004598.s003"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>Sequence variation and species identification ability of six plastid regions in various combinations in Crocus serie Crocus. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004598.s002">Table S1</xref></p><p>(0.03 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004598.s003.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004598.s004"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p>Sequence variation and species identification ability of two plastid regions in Hordeum (all 32 species). No length variation is observed among the sequences. GenBank acc. nos. EU118371-EU118422, EU118427-EU118478.</p><p>(0.04 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004598.s004.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004598.s005"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p>Sequence variation and species identification ability of six plastid regions in Scalesia (5 of 15 species). No length variation is observed among the sequences. GenBank acc. nos. EU118423-EU118426, EU118479-EU118483, EU118494-EU118498, EU118509-EU118513, EU118524-EU118527, EU118536-EU118539.</p><p>(0.04 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004598.s005.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>Jerry I. Davis, Mark Stoeckle, Dennis Wm. Stevenson, Damon Little, and Finn Borchsenius are thanked for comments that helped improve the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0004598-Blaxter1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The promise of a DNA taxonomy.</article-title><source>Philo Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><volume>359</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>679</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Waugh1"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waugh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>DNA barcoding in animal species: progress, potential and pitfalls.</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17226815</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Chase1"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunwell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesanakurthi</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Land plants and DNA barcodes: short-term and long-term goals.</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><volume>360</volume><fpage>1889</fpage><lpage>1895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16214746</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Kress1"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurdack</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigt</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Use of DNA barcodes to identify flowering plants.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>8369</fpage><lpage>8374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15928076</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Newmaster1"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newmaster</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazekas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragupathy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>DNA barcoding in land plants: evaluation of rbcL in a multigene tiered approach.</article-title><source>Can J Bot</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>341</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Cowan1"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>300,000 species to identify: problems, progress, and prospects in DNA barcoding of land plants.</article-title><source>Taxon</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>616</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Fazekas1"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fazekas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesanakurti</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Newmaster</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Multiple Multilocus DNA Barcodes from the Plastid Genome Discriminate Plant Species Equally Well.</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>e2802</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18665273</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Lahaye1"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lahaye</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Bank</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogarin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pupulin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>DNA barcoding the floras of biodiversity hotspots.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>2923</fpage><lpage>2928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18258745</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Muse1"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muse</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Examining rates and patterns of nucleotide substitution in plants.</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Wendel1"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnabel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seelanan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Bidirctional interlocus concereted eolution following allopolyploid speciciation in cotton (<italic>Gossypium</italic>).</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7816833</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Kane1"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronk</surname><given-names>QCB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Meeting Review: Botany without borders: barcoding in focus.</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>5175</fpage><lpage>5176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19067801</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Kress2"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A Two-Locus Global DNA Barcode for Land Plants: The Coding rbcL Gene Complements the Non-Coding trnH-psbA Spacer Region.</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>e508</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17551588</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Taberlet1"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taberlet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Coissac</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pompanon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gielly</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Miquel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Power and limitations of the chloroplast trnL (UAA) intron for plant DNA barcoding.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>e14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17169982</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Chase2"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollingsworth</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Madri&#x000f1;&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A proposal for a standarised protocol to barcode all land plants.</article-title><source>Taxon</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>299</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Pennisi1"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pennisi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Wanted: A barcode for plants.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>318</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17932267</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Edwards1"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>DNA barcoding of a large genus, <italic>Aspalathus</italic> L. (Fabaceae).</article-title><source>Taxon</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>1317</fpage><lpage>1327</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Presting1"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Presting</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Identification of conserved regions in the plastid genome: implications for DNA barcoding and biological function.</article-title><source>Can J Bot</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>1434</fpage><lpage>1443</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Petersen1"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Seberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Thors&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>A phylogeny of the genus <italic>Crocus</italic> (Iridaceae) based on sequence data from five plastid regions.</article-title><source>Taxon</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>499</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Syring1"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Syring</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Businsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Widespread genealogical nonmonophyly in species of <italic>Pinus</italic> subgenus <italic>Strobus</italic>.</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17454973</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Funk1"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Omland</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Species-Level Paraphyly and Polyphyly: Frequency, Causes, and Consequences, with Insights from Animal Mitochondrial DNA.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Ecol Syst</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>423</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Meyer1"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>DNA Barcoding: Error Rates Based on Comprehensive Sampling.</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>2229</fpage><lpage>2238</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Costa1"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWaard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutillier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratnasingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dooh</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Biological identifications through DNA barcodes: the case of the Crustacea.</article-title><source>Can J Fish Aquat Sci</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>295</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Hajibabaei1"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hajibabaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallwachs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>DNA barcodes distinguish species of tropical Lepidoptera.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>968</fpage><lpage>971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418261</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Hillis1"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>An Empirical Test of Bootstrapping as a Method for Assessing Confidence in Phylogenetic Analysis.</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>192</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Davies1"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barraclough</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Darwin's abominable mystery: Insights from a supertree of the angiosperms.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>1904</fpage><lpage>1909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14766971</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Helfenbein1"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helfenbein</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>DeSalle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Falsifications and corroborations: Karl Popper's influence on systematics.</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15737596</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Little1"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A comparison of algorithms for the identification of specimens using DNA barcodes: examples from gymnosperms.</article-title><source>Cladistics</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Kress3"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>DNA barcodes: Genes, genomics, and bioinformatics.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>2761</fpage><lpage>2762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18287050</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Sass1"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sass</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Specht</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>DNA barcoding in the cycadales: testing the potential of proposed barcoding markers for species identification of cycads.</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>e1154</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17987130</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Rubinoff1"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubinoff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Will</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Are plant DNA barcodes a search for the Holy Grail?</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701459</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Mathew1"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1982</year><source>The Crocus</source><publisher-loc>Portland, OR</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Timber Press</publisher-name><fpage>127</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Olmstead1"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweere</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Combining data in phylogenetic systematics: an empirical approach using three molecular data sets in the Solanaceae.</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>481</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Kress4"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The molecular phylogeny of Alpinia (Zingiberaceae): A complex and polyphyletic genus of gingers.</article-title><source>Amer J Bot</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Sang1"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Evolution of alcohol dehydrogenase genes in peonies (<italic>Paeonia</italic>); phylogenetic relationships of putative nonhybrid species.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>994</fpage><lpage>1007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9335140</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Tate1"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Paraphyly of <italic>Tarasa</italic> (Malvaceae) and diverse origins of the polyploidy species.</article-title><source>Syst Bot</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>737</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Swofford1"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><source>PAUP&#x0002a;. Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony (&#x0002a; and Other Methods), version 4.0b8 &#x0005b;computer program&#x0005d;</source><publisher-loc>Sunderland, Mass.</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sinauer Associates</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Maddison1"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><source>MacClade, version 4.08 &#x0005b;computer program&#x0005d;</source><publisher-loc>Sunderland, Massachusetts</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sinauer Associates</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Nixon1"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><source>WinClada, version 1.00.08 &#x0005b;computer program&#x0005d;</source><publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY.</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Author</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004598-Goloboff1"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goloboff</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><source>NONA (NO NAME), version 2 &#x0005b;computer program&#x0005d;</source><publisher-loc>Tucum&#x000e1;n, Argentina</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Author</publisher-name></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This research was supported by the Danish Natural Sciences Research Council (272-06-0436), the Sloan Foundation, and Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>