<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Community Eye Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Community Eye Health</journal-id><journal-title>Community Eye Health</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0953-6833</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1993-7288</issn><publisher><publisher-name>International Centre for Eye Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19287548</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2643038</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jceh_21_68_067.1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Exchange</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A brief experience of blindness</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>Hessom</given-names></name><aff>Senior House Officer in Ophthalmology, London House, Mecklenburgh Square, London WC1N 2AB, UK. Email: <email>hessom.razavi@gmail.com</email></aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><issue>68</issue><issue-title>Improving eye care</issue-title><fpage seq="1">67</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.cehjournal.org"/><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2008 Hessom Razavi</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></article-meta></front><body><fig id="F1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="jceh_21_68_067.1_f01"/></fig><p>Some months ago, I observed a blind pedestrian negotiating a busy London street with remarkable speed and confidence. &#x0201c;Just how does he do it?&#x0201d;, I thought to myself. I decided that I, as an eye health professional, could benefit from a brief experience of what it was like to be &#x02018;blind&#x02019;. This became the inspiration for a fundraising event, which involved me having my eyes covered for 24 hours, and being effectively &#x02018;blind&#x02019;, under close supervision from a sighted guide.</p><p>Living with sudden and complete visual loss is a high-risk endeavour, and &#x02018;pretending&#x02019; to lose one's sight is no less risky. For this reason, prior to the event, my sighted guide, Puneet Sayal, and I underwent intensive visual awareness training. This involved learning a range of safe coping techniques, both indoors and out, such as opening doors, climbing stairs, and pouring hot drinks. Even the simplest activity could be challenging.</p><p>On the day of the event, with close guidance from my guide, I went about my normal daily routine: getting dressed, preparing and eating breakfast, walking to university, attending classes, etc.</p><p>I quickly noticed that some people treated me differently now that my eyes were covered: they were either more or less attentive than usual, and they sometimes addressed me indirectly by talking to my guide. Some seemed disturbed by my condition, others overeager to help.</p><p>I found I was less confident, found it more difficult to concentrate in class, and was not able to contribute as much as usual. I was completely dependent on my guide and experienced a severe loss of freedom. As the day progressed, I began to feel stressed and became anxious to remove my eye coverings. When they finally came off after 24 hours, the light was actually painful. I also felt quite emotional and remained unsettled for a few hours.</p><sec id="s1"><title>Reflections after the event</title><p>The experience was deeply unsettling, but very valuable to me. Thanks to my guide, I never felt unsafe. I was more disturbed by my diminished confidence, independence, and ability to contribute. I cannot suggest that I now &#x02018;understand&#x02019; what it is like to be blind, but I did learn the following lessons:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Blind people must be treated normally&#x02014;inclusion and dignity are paramount</p></list-item><list-item><p>Efforts to help blind people can both help and hinder them</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ask first before offering help and be precise with instructions</p></list-item><list-item><p>Look at blind people and speak to them directly, using normal language</p></list-item><list-item><p>Leaving a blind person without announcing it is unkind and embarrassing</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ask how and at what pace a blind person would like to be guided</p></list-item><list-item><p>Make sure the person you are guiding is safe, but stay relaxed, and remember not to pull, but to walk with him/her holding your arm</p></list-item><list-item><p>Being blind is a constant challenge</p></list-item><list-item><p>Rehabilitation training is crucial.</p></list-item></list></sec></body></article>