<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xml:lang="EN" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CO</journal-id><journal-title>Current Oncology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1198-0052</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1718-7729</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Multimed Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>66 Martin St. Milton, ON, Canada L9T 2R2</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19229373</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2644626</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">co16-1-59</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Drug Development in Contemporary Oncology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Targeting m<sc>tor</sc>-dependent tumours with specific inhibitors: a model for personalized medicine based on molecular diagnoses</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Furic</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-co16-1-59">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Livingstone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-co16-1-59">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>R.J.O.</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-co16-1-59">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sonenberg</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-co16-1-59"/></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1-co16-1-59">Correspondence to: Nahum Sonenberg, Goodman Cancer Centre and Department of Biochemistry, McGill University, 1160 avenue Des Pins Ouest, Cancer Pavilion, Room 617, Montreal, Quebec H3A 1A3. E-mail:<email>nahum.sonenberg@mcgill.ca</email></corresp><fn id="fn1-co16-1-59"><label>a</label><p>These authors contributed equally to the article.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><copyright-statement>2009 Multimed Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license><abstract><p>Cancer cells are characterized by aberrant growth arising from deregulated signalling pathways. The mammalian target of rapamycin (m<sc>tor</sc>) pathway integrates multiple growth signals coming from both intracellular and extracellular cues. In this short review, we summarize what is known about the efficacy of targeting the m<sc>tor</sc> pathway to treat cancer patients, and we explain the rationale behind promising new inhibitors that could show more potent tumour growth inhibition than did the first generation of these drugs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cell signalling</kwd><kwd>m<sc>tor</sc></kwd><kwd>rapamycin</kwd><kwd>Lkb1</kwd><kwd>Fkbp12</kwd><kwd>tumour growth</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>1. INTRODUCTION</title><p>Signal transduction pathways govern appropriately regulated cell growth, division, and survival in human tissues, but these pathways are often deregulated in aggressive cancers that show seemingly uncontrolled growth. This observation has led to the notion that if the molecular cause of a cancer can be determined, then the aberration on which a particular cancer depends could be directly targeted<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-co16-1-59">1</xref>.</p><p>The mammalian target of rapamycin (m<sc>tor</sc>) signalling pathway has proved to be an excellent model system for exploring this notion of personalized medicine, because numerous mutations resulting in hyperactivation of the pathway have been identified, the hyperactivation is itself demonstrated by multiple downstream biomarkers, and a specific potent m<sc>tor</sc> inhibitor, rapamycin, has a long been safely used to treat humans<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-co16-1-59">2</xref>. In this review, we discuss the mutations and molecular diagnosis of tumours with hyperactivated m<sc>tor</sc> signalling, clinical trials of rapamycin analogues, the rationale behind second-generation non-rapamycin-analogue m<sc>tor</sc> inhibitors, and the ongoing early-phase clinical trials using these agents.</p></sec><sec><title>2. ABERRANT ACTIVATION OF MTOR</title><p>The evolutionarily conserved (yeast to man) m<sc>tor</sc> protein kinase integrates multiple intracellular and extracellular signals representing growth conditions (energy, growth factor, and amino-acid availability, for instance) to control downstream processes, including translation of messenger <sc>rna</sc>, cell growth, and proliferation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-co16-1-59">FIGURE 1</xref>). Numerous mutations of upstream regulators of m<sc>tor</sc> signalling can lead to hyperactivation, thus uncoupling m<sc>tor</sc> activity from the cues that normally modulate its activity, resulting in unconstrained cell growth<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-co16-1-59">3</xref>. For example, the phosphoinositide 3 kinase (PI3K) signalling pathway is normally activated when growth factors bind transmembrane receptors; it is inactivated by <sc>pten</sc> (the protein encoded by the phosphatase and tensin homolog gene) when growth factors are not abundant. Similarly, serine/threonine kinase 11 [Stk11 (Lkb1)] negatively regulates m<sc>tor</sc> activity when cellular energy (adenosine triphosphate) is in low supply, and the tuberous sclerosis complex (Tsc1/Tsc2) negatively regulates both of those signals to m<sc>tor</sc>. Consequently, cells lacking functional <sc>pten</sc>, Stk11 (Lkb1), or Tsc2 exhibit deregulated, constitutive signalling to m<sc>tor</sc>, resulting in multiple types of cancer<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-co16-1-59">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-co16-1-59">4</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>3. RAPAMYCIN ANALOGUES: CLINICAL TRIALS</title><p>Rapamycin, a natural product from soil bacteria, inhibits m<sc>tor</sc> by simultaneously binding to a protein called Fkbp12 and to the Fkbp12 rapamycin-binding (<sc>frb</sc>) domain of m<sc>tor</sc>. Because of its ability to inhibit m<sc>tor</sc>-dependent growth and proliferation of B and T cells, rapamycin has long been used as an immuno-suppressant (sirolimus) to prevent organ rejection, and because of its ability to inhibit the fungal orthologue of m<sc>tor</sc>, it can also be used as an antifungal agent.</p><p>In clinical trials, rapamycin and three rapamycin analogues&#x02014;CCI-779 [temsirolimus (Torisel: Wyeth-Ayerst, Charlotte, NC, U.S.A.)], RAD001 [everolimus (Certican: Novartis Pharmaceuticals, St. Louis, MO, U.S.A.)], and AP23573 (deforolimus: Ariad Pharmaceuticals, Cambridge, MA, U.S.A., and Merck and Co., Whitehouse Station, NJ, U.S.A.)&#x02014;have been assessed for their efficacy as anticancer agents<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-co16-1-59">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-co16-1-59">6</xref>. These compounds have been tested alone and in combination with standard-of-care agents for a wide variety of human cancers.</p><p>Based on preclinical testing, m<sc>tor</sc> inhibitors were predicted to be effective in the treatment of tumours with genetic mutations that lead to overactivation of m<sc>tor</sc> signalling&#x02014;for example, loss of <sc>pten</sc>, Stk11 (Lkb1), or Tsc2. Cells and tumours containing mutations or deletions of these tumour suppressors exhibit uncontrolled m<sc>tor</sc> signalling and an increase in phosphorylation of the downstream targets Eif4Ebp1 (eukaryotic translation initiation factor 4E binding protein 1) and S6 kinase<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-co16-1-59">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-co16-1-59">9</xref>. Data from clinical trials seem to support this hypothesis, because endometrial tumours, which exhibit a high frequency of <sc>pten</sc> inactivation, have responded favourably to treatment with temsirolimus<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-co16-1-59">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-co16-1-59">11</xref>. Renal cell carcinoma also exhibits some sensitivity to m<sc>tor</sc> inhibitors, likely because of the importance of m<sc>tor</sc> signalling in the expression of Hif1A (hypoxia inducible factor 1, alpha subunit), a key player in angiogenesis and the growth of renal tumours<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-co16-1-59">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-co16-1-59">12</xref>. In fact, results from a recent phase <sc>iii</sc> clinical trial involving patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma indicate that everolimus may be an effective option for patients suffering from renal cancer<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-co16-1-59">12</xref>. Furthermore, temsirolimus was approved for the treatment of patients with renal carcinoma in May 2007<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-co16-1-59">5</xref>. This evidence indicates that overactive m<sc>tor</sc> signalling (as a result of genetic mutation, inactivation, or loss of key tumour suppressors) may be used to identify patients who would benefit from treatment with rapamycin analogues. However, although rapamycin analogues have been effective in the treatment of some tumours that lack <sc>pten</sc> (such as those of the endometrium), other cancers have been refractory to the effects of m<sc>tor</sc> inhibitors despite <sc>pten</sc> loss or mutation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-co16-1-59">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14-co16-1-59">14</xref>. In these and other cases, results from clinical trials have been disappointing to some who had high hopes for this rationale-based chemotherapy<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-co16-1-59">15</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>4. SECOND-GENERATION MTOR INHIBITORS</title><p>All of the above-described m<sc>tor</sc> inhibitors undergoing clinical trials are rapamycin analogues, and they therefore inhibit only a portion of m<sc>tor</sc> signalling&#x02014;the portion effected by the rapamycin-sensitive m<sc>tor</sc> complex 1 (m<sc>torc</sc>1)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16-co16-1-59">16</xref>. It has been hypothesized that inhibition of both m<sc>torc</sc>1 and the rapamycin-insensitive m<sc>tor</sc> complex 2 (m<sc>torc</sc>2) would be a more effective means of treating such tumours<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17-co16-1-59">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18-co16-1-59">18</xref>, because inhibition of m<sc>torc</sc>1 with rapamycin actually leads to an upregulation of m<sc>torc</sc>2-dependent survival signalling through the PI3K-Akt pathway by suppressing a negative feedback loop<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19-co16-1-59">19</xref>. Consistent with this reasoning, it has been shown that dual inhibition of m<sc>tor</sc> and PI3K&#x02013;Akt is an effective means to target <sc>pten</sc>-deficient tumours<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20-co16-1-59">20</xref>. Developing m<sc>tor</sc> inhibitors that target the kinase domain has been proposed as an effective means to block the activities of both m<sc>torc</sc>1 and 2 m<sc>torc</sc><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17-co16-1-59">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18-co16-1-59">18</xref>, and a new wave of clinical trials has commenced using a second generation of m<sc>torc</sc>1 and 2 inhibitors. The agent OSI-027 (OSI Pharmaceuticals, Melville, NY, U.S.A.), for example, is an m<sc>torc</sc>1 and 2 inhibitor currently being evaluated (phase <sc>i</sc>) to determine the maximum tolerated dose in patients with lymphoma or solid tumours. Similarly, BEZ235 (Novartis Pharmaceuticals) is being evaluated (phase <sc>i</sc> and <sc>ii</sc>) to determine dosing and effectiveness in treating advanced solid tumours, particularly those in patients with Cowden syndrome (caused by <sc>pten</sc> loss). A third m<sc>torc</sc>1 and 2 inhibitor, XL765 (Exelixis, San Francisco, CA, U.S.A.) is being tested (phase <sc>i</sc>) alone and in combination therapies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>5. SUMMARY</title><p>As a whole, exploiting the m<sc>tor</sc> signalling pathway and its aberrant activation has provided strong proof that the age of personalized medicine based on molecular diagnoses is well underway. Progress to this point indicates that further elucidation of the mechanisms involved in predicting sensitivity to rapamycin and analogues is possible, as is development of new, more potent m<sc>tor</sc> inhibitors for the treatment of cancer. It is important to keep in mind that the signalling pathways inhibited by rapamycin analogues and by m<sc>torc</sc>1 and 2 inhibitors are likely crucial for the growth, proliferation, and survival of possibly all human cells, and therefore such compounds should be effective treatments against most tumours in the same way that traditional chemotherapies are. However, the notion of &#x0201c;oncogene addiction&#x0201d; suggests that, if a particular aberration is driving tumour survival, then it may be possible to selectively target the cancer while merely inducing growth arrest or cytostasis in healthy tissues.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>This scientific paper is the work of the author and was made possible through the support of Merck Frosst Canada Ltd. The opinions and information contained herein are those of the author and do not necessarily reflect the views or opinions of Merck Frosst Canada Ltd.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>6. REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1-co16-1-59"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer. Addiction to oncogenes&#x02014;the Achilles heal of cancer</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12098689</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b2-co16-1-59"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Blenis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>torgeting oncogene addiction for cancer therapy</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16473275</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b3-co16-1-59"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faivre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current development of mtor inhibitors as anticancer agents</article-title><source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16883305</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b4-co16-1-59"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawyers</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Will mtor inhibitors make it as cancer drugs?</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14667501</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b5-co16-1-59"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian target of rapamycin as a therapeutic target in oncology</article-title><source>Expert Opin Ther Targets</source><year>2008</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18208369</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b6-co16-1-59"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petroulakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamane</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bacquer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahbazian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonenberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mtor signaling: implications for cancer and anti-cancer therapy</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2007</year><volume>96</volume><issue>suppl</issue><fpage>R11</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17393579</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b7-co16-1-59"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neshat</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellinghoff</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced sensitivity of pten-deficient tumors to inhibition of frap/mtor</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>10314</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504908</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b8-co16-1-59"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaeschke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartkamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tuberous sclerosis complex tumor suppressor&#x02013;mediated S6 kinase inhibition by phosphatidylinositide-3-OH kinase is mtor independent</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12403809</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b9-co16-1-59"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardeesy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The lkb1 tumor suppressor negatively regulates mtor signaling</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15261145</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b10-co16-1-59"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oza</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elit</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Biagi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular correlates associated with a phase <sc>ii</sc> study of temsirolimus (CCI-779) in patients with metastatic or recurrent endometrial cancer&#x02014;<sc>ncic ind</sc> 160</article-title><source>Proc Am Soc Clin Oncol</source><year>2006</year><volume>24</volume><comment>[Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.asco.org/ASCO/Abstracts+%26+Virtual+Meeting/Abstracts?&#x00026;vmview=abst_detail_view&#x00026;confID=40&#x00026;abstractID=33037">www.asco.org/ASCO/Abstracts+%26+Virtual+Meeting/Abstracts?&#x00026;vmview=abst_detail_view&#x00026;confID=40&#x00026;abstractID=33037</ext-link>; cited January 5, 2009]</comment></citation></ref><ref id="b11-co16-1-59"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Tourneau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Faivre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Serova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mtorC1 inhibitors: is temsirolimus in renal cancer telling us how they really work?</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2008</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18797463</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b12-co16-1-59"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motzer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Escudier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Oudard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><collab>on behalf of the record-1 Study Group</collab><article-title>Efficacy of everolimus in advanced renal cell carcinoma: a double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled phase iii trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2008</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18653228</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b13-co16-1-59"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cloughesy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phase ii study of CCI-779 in patients with recurrent glioblastoma multiforme</article-title><source>Invest New Drugs</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16012795</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b14-co16-1-59"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margolin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Longmate</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baratta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CCI-779 in metastatic melanoma: a phase ii trial of the California Cancer Consortium</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2005</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16007689</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b15-co16-1-59"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>QB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Akt and cancer&#x02014;is it all mtor?</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17045203</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b16-co16-1-59"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarbassov</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rictor, a novel binding partner of mtor, defines a rapamycin-insensitive and raptor-independent pathway that regulates the cytoskeleton</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1296</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15268862</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b17-co16-1-59"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edinger</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Linardic</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of rapamycin on mammalian target of rapamycin signaling functions in mammalian cells</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>8451</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14679009</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b18-co16-1-59"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mtor and cancer: insights into a complex relationship</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>729</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16915295</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b19-co16-1-59"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Um</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Frigerio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Absence of S6K1 protects against age- and diet-induced obesity while enhancing insulin sensitivity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>431</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15306821</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b20-co16-1-59"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>QW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolaides</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A dual phosphoinositide-3-kinase alpha/mtor inhibitor cooperates with blockade of epidermal growth factor receptor in pten-mutant glioma</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>7960</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17804702</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="f1-co16-1-59" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>The phosphoinositide 3 kinase (PI3K)&#x02013;Akt&#x02013;mammalian target of rapamycin (m<sc>tor</sc>) pathway integrates multiple signals emanating from inside and outside the cell. The rapamycin-sensitive m<sc>tor</sc> complex 1 (m<sc>torc</sc>1) responds to energy balance, growth factors, and availability of metabolites. The rapamycin-insensitive m<sc>tor</sc> complex 2 (m<sc>torc</sc>2) promotes cell survival, but its regulation is less well characterized. <sc>atp</sc> = adenosine triphosphate; Lkb1 = serine/threonine kinase 11 (Stk11); Tsc2 = tuberous sclerosis 2 protein; <sc>pten</sc> = protein encoded by the phosphatase and tensin homolog gene; m<sc>rna</sc> = messenger <sc>rna</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="co16-1-59f1"/></fig></floats-wrap></article>