<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8711562</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6325</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncogene</journal-id><journal-title>Oncogene</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0950-9232</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1476-5594</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19079338</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2645484</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2008.435</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS77188</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Menin Interacts with IQGAP1 to Enhance Intercellular Adhesion of &#x003b2; Cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Jizhou</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yuqing</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>Catrina</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>Ho-Man</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Chao-Xing</given-names></name><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>George S</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Xianxin</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Abramson Family Cancer Research Institute and Department of Cancer Biology, University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine, 421 Curie Boulevard, Philadelphia, PA19014</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Biology, University of Virginia; Charlottesville, VA 22903</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Cell Biology, University of Virginia; Charlottesville, VA 22903</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Proteomic Facility: University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine, 421 Curie Boulevard, Philadelphia, PA19014</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Zhongshan Ophthalmic Center, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: phone, 215 746-5565; email: <email>huax@mail.med.upenn.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><abstract><p id="P1">Multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN1) is a dominantly inherited tumor syndrome that results from the mutation of the <italic>MEN1</italic> gene that encodes protein menin. Stable overexpression of <italic>MEN1</italic> has been shown to partially suppress the RAS-mediated morphological changes of NH3 fibroblast cells. Little is known about the molecular mechanisms by which menin decreases the oncogenic effects on cell morphology and other phenotypes. Here we showed that ectopic expression of menin in pretumor beta cells increases islet cell adhesion and reduces cell migration. Our further studies revealed that menin interacts with the scaffold protein, IQGAP1, reduces GTP-Rac1 interaction with IQGAP1 but increases E-cadherin/&#x000df;-catenin interaction with IQGAP1. Consistent with an essential role for menin in regulating &#x000df; cell adhesion in vivo, accumulations of &#x003b2;-catenin and E-cadherin are reduced at cell junctions in the islets from <italic>Men1</italic>-excised mice. Together, these results define a novel menin-IQGAP1 pathway that controls cell migration and cell-cell adhesion in endocrine cells.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>menin</kwd><kwd>IQGAP1</kwd><kwd>intercellular adhesion</kwd><kwd>migration</kwd></kwd-group><contract-num rid="NS1">R01 NS051746-04||NS</contract-num><contract-num rid="NS1">R01 NS051746-03||NS</contract-num><contract-num rid="CA1">R01 CA113962-04||CA</contract-num><contract-sponsor id="NS1">National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke : NINDS</contract-sponsor><contract-sponsor id="CA1">National Cancer Institute : NCI</contract-sponsor></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN1) is a dominantly inherited tumor syndrome that results from the mutation of <italic>Men1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Chandrasekharappa <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>), which encodes menin protein. Menin has been found to interact with mixed lineage leukemia (MLL) protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Hughes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), which is a histone H3 lysine 4 (H3K4) methyltransferase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Milne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Multiple lines of evidence indicate that one of menin&#x02019;s biochemical functions is to promote MLL-dependent H3K4 methylation, leading to enhanced transcription of target genes such as <italic>Hoxa9</italic> and cyclin dependent kinase inhibitors, p18 and p27 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Milne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Yan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Yokoyama <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). However, it is not clear why the attenuated menin expression specifically causes a unique and restricted pattern of endocrine tumors in both humans and mice despite the ubiquitous expression of menin in almost all tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Guru <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>).</p><p id="P3"><italic>Men1</italic><sup>-/-</sup> mice die in mid-gestation (between embryonic day 11.5 to 13.5), while <italic>Men1</italic><sup>+/-</sup> mice develop endocrine tumors later in their life with a spectrum similar to that in MEN1 patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Crabtree <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Heterogeneous expression of <italic>Men1</italic> suggests that attenuation, rather than complete abrogation of <italic>Men1</italic> function, facilitates a tumorigenic signaling pathway in endocrine cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Crabtree <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Although conditional alleles have been generated to allow tissue-specific homozygous deletion of <italic>Men1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Schnepp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), <italic>Men1<sup>+/-</sup></italic> mice, presumably retaining a lower level of menin expression, were used to gain an unbiased assessment of the functional <italic>in vivo</italic> interaction between menin with p18 and p27 proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Bai <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p><p id="P4">An alternate approach to evaluate <italic>Men1</italic>-mutation phenotype is to use neoplastic cells transformed by oncogenes. <italic>Ras</italic> is an oncogene originally identified in rat sarcoma virus. Transforming <italic>Ras</italic> genes cause tumor progression, often accompanied by somatic mutations in tumor suppressor genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Jiang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Through this approach, Kim and colleagues first demonstrated that stable overexpression of <italic>Men1</italic> partially suppressed the <italic>Ras</italic>-mediated tumor phenotype in NH3 fibroblast cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). However, little is known about the molecular mechanisms by which menin decreases the oncogenic effects upon cell morphology.</p><p id="P5">To address menin&#x02019;s role in endocrine cells, we sought to test menin&#x02019;s tumor suppressing function by ectopic expression of menin in &#x003b2;HC9 pretumor beta cells. This cell line was generated from individual hyperplastic pancreatic islets (a tumor precursor stage) of transgenic mice expressing the SV40 large T antigen under control of the rat insulin promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Radvanyi <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>). Using this cell model, we found that ectopic menin expression increased cell adhesion and promoted normal endocrine cell morphology. Menin interacted with a scaffold protein, IQGAP1, and attenuated GTP-Rac1 binding to IQGAP1 but enhanced binding of E-cadherin/&#x000df;-catenin to IQGAP1. Immunostaining showed that E-cadherin and &#x003b2;-catenin were reduced at cell junctions in the islets of <italic>Men1</italic>-excised mice. These results define a novel menin-IQGAP1 pathway that links the cytoskeleton to cell adhesion and migration in endocrine cells.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S2"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Menin enhances aggregation of islet cells</title><p id="P6">To investigate the function of menin in islet &#x000df; cells, we ectopically expressed menin in an insulin-secreting &#x000df; cell line, &#x000df;HC9. More specifically, &#x000df;HC9 cells were infected with either control recombinant retroviruses or retroviruses expressing menin tagged with the TAP (tandem affinity purification) epitopes, SBP (streptavidin binding peptide) and CBP (calmodulin binding peptide) (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplemental data, Fig. S1A</xref>). The resulting pooled and menin-expressing retrovirus-infected cells (Men1-TAP) showed approximately 2-3 fold higher menin expression, with the size of the tagged menin slightly bigger than the endogenous menin, as compared with the vector-infected control cells (Mock) based on immunoblotting (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1C</xref>). High density Men1-TAP cells but not control cells formed multilayers of cell clusters and thus more closely mimicked normal islet morphology (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A, B</xref>). At a low density, control cells were well spread and separated from each other, and readily formed lamellipodia (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref>). In contrast, low-density Men1-TAP cells were relatively round and formed compact clusters, but not lamellipodia (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.1D</xref>). The polarized appearance that distinguished individual control cells from Men1-TAP cells were defined by cell shape index, i.e. 2.5&#x000b1;0.5 vs 1&#x000b1;0.1 (n=10; &#x000b1;S.D.) (see <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.1</xref> legend).</p><p id="P7">To test the possibility that the epitope tags fused with menin, rather than ectopic menin expression, contributed to the morphological changes, we generated an additional stable cell line by infecting &#x000df;HC9 cells with retroviruses expressing untagged menin (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1A</xref>). The resulting cell line (Men1), showed a higher level of menin expression (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1C</xref>, lane 3), and a more compact, clustered phenotype as compared to control, vector-infected cells (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Menin expression changes actin distribution</title><p id="P8">The morphological changes described above were likely to reflect changes in cytoskeletal organization, particularly of actin filaments. Although stress fibers were rarely seen in both cell types, more F-actin patches were found in the cytoplasm of mock-infected control cells than Men1-TAP cells. The other conspicuous difference in actin organization between the two cell types was the accumulations of F-actin surrounding the cell membrane of Men1-TAP versus at the leading edge of control cells (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.1E-H</xref>). The distribution difference was reflected by a ~50% loss of &#x003b2;-actin in menin overexpressing cells, as determined by immunobloting (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig.2D</xref>) and quantitative real-time PCR (data not shown). These results suggest that menin expression promotes actin assembly at cell membrane and negatively regulates steady state levels of &#x003b2;-actin in cytoplasm, possibly due to delocalization of IQGAP1 (see below).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Menin interacts with IQGAP1</title><p id="P9">During our investigation into the role of menin in controlling cell morphology, we tried to identify menin interacting proteins in &#x003b2; cells. To that end, we subjected the mock cells and Men1-TAP cells to sequential affinity purifications, using streptavidin and calmodulin-conjugated beads. One major band at ~180 kD was reproducibly identified during multiple rounds of purification in Men1-TAP cells, but not in the mock cells, indicating specific association with the tagged menin (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). Mass spectrometry identified this band as IQGAP1, a scaffold protein that interacts with a variety of proteins, including Rac1, Cdc42, E-cadherin, &#x003b2;&#x02013;catenin and F-actin to regulate cell motility and adhesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Fukata <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Lambert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Mataraza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p><p id="P10">Physical interaction between menin and IQGAP1 was confirmed by a co-immunoprecipitation (IP) assay. An anti-menin antibody was able to pull down IQGAP1 in both mock-infected and menin overexpressing cells (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>), and more IQGAP1 was present in anti-menin IPs obtained from Men1 cells than from control cells (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>). The latter result suggested that IQGAP1 interacted with both endogenous and ectopically expressed menin. We noticed, however, that the amount of IQGAP1 in IPs obtained from mock and Men1-TAP cells were nearly identical, despite the large presence of menin in the Men1-TAP cells (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig.2B, 2D</xref>). This is likely due to the fact that the immunoprecipitating anti-menin antibody (BL342) was generated using a synthetic peptide corresponding to the C-terminus of human menin and thus may have had a lower affinity for menin modified at its C-terminus with the TAP epitope tag than for unmodified menin. Reciprocal co-IP experiments demonstrated that anti-IQGAP1 could pull down menin (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref>), albeit less effectively than anti-menin pulled down IQGAP1 (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2B</xref>). This result suggests that either a small fraction of menin binds IQGAP1 or the affinity between menin and IQGAP1 is negatively affected by the anti-IQGAP1 antibody. In either case, these collective results indicate that menin and IQGAP1 interact in &#x003b2; cells.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Menin increases IQGAP1 accumulation at the plasma membrane</title><p id="P11">Consistent with our biochemical evidence for an IQGAP1-menin association in cells (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A-C</xref>), we found extensive immunofluorescent co-localization of IQGAP1 with a non-nuclear pool of menin in our &#x003b2; cell lines. However, co-localization around the plasma membrane appeared more extensive in Men1-TAP cultures than in controls, especially at cell-cell junctions (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). The impression that menin overexpression enhanced IQGAP1 localization at the cell surface was further supported by transient transfection studies of IQGAP1-YFP. Cortical enrichment of the fluorescent fusion protein was much more evident in the Men1-TAP cells than in control cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig.3B</xref>). Interestingly, co-expression of mCherry-Rac1 with IQGAP1-YFP prevented the overexpressed menin in Men1-TAP cells from targeting IQGAP1 to the cortex (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref>). As expected, overexpression of mCherry-Rac1 increased the level of Rac1-GTP, an active form to bind IQGAP1 (<xref rid="SD4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S3</xref>). These results suggest that the intracellular distribution of IQGAP1 is controlled by both menin and Rac1, but that Rac1 is dominant.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Menin increases accumulation of E-cadherin/&#x003b2;-catenin at cell-cell contact sites</title><p id="P12">Having established the intracellular distributions of menin and IQGAP1, we next investigated the biological significance of menin-induced IQGAP1 accumulation at intercellular adhesion sites. As determined by cell adhesion assays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Price <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), cells expressing menin (Men1) had strong adhesion, particularly to Fc-E-cadherin (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>). By immunofluorescence, E-cadherin was 2-3 times more concentrated at sites of cell-cell contact in menin-expressing cells than anywhere along the surfaces of mock-infected control cells (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4C</xref>). The distribution of &#x003b2;-catenin was similar to E-cadherin staining in &#x003b2;HC9-derived cells. Menin-expressing cells displayed broader bands of &#x003b2;-catenin staining, reflecting regions of cellular contact (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4C</xref>). In mock cells, however, &#x003b2;-catenin was frequently restricted to a thin line where adjacent mock cells made contact, and showed a 2-3 fold of lower staining intensity than in menin-expressing cells (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4C</xref>). Immunoblots of cell lysates revealed comparable levels of E-cadherin and &#x003b2;-catenin in the mock and Men1-TAP cell lines (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2D</xref>). Together, these results suggest that menin-expression significantly increased intercellular adhesion via E-cadherin pathway.</p><p id="P13">To examine whether distributions of &#x003b2;-catenin and E-cadherin are altered in Men1-associated islet tumors, we immunostained enlarged islets from the Men1-excised mice and control islets from wild type mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Schnepp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D</xref>, the staining intensity of E-cadherin surrounding the cell membrane was much higher in menin-expressing control islets. In the case of &#x003b2;-catenin, staining intensity was very similar in the control and Men1-excised mice, but &#x003b2;-catenin labeling was confined to a narrower band near the surface of Men1 knockout islet cells. These regions of &#x003b2;-catenin immunoreactivity ranged from 0.5-2 &#x003bc;m wide in Men1-deleted islet cells but were 2-4 &#x003bc;m wide in control islets. These results suggest that Men1-deletion leads to reduced distribution of E-cadherin and &#x000df;-catenin at the surface of pancreatic islet cells.</p><p id="P14">To demonstrate the association of menin and IQGAP1 with cadherin complex, Men1 cells and IQGAP1 shRNA-expressing cells were subjected to IP with anti-menin antibody, followed by Western blotting with either anti-&#x000df;-catenin or anti-IQGAP1 antibodies. IQGAP1 and &#x003b2;-catenin were simultaneously immunoprecipitated by menin-specific antibodies. At similar amount of &#x003b2;-catenin input, the levels of &#x003b2;-catenin were reduced by ~60% in IPs obtained from IQGAP1-knock down cells (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4E</xref>). Furthermore, IQGAP1-deficient cells reduced staining intensity of E-cadherin and &#x003b2;-catenin at the cell-cell contacts (<xref rid="SD5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig.S4</xref>), and displayed a weak cell adhesion (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>). Thus, IQGAP1 is crucial to bridge the menin E-cadherin/&#x003b2;-catenin interactions in islet cells.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Menin expression inhibits &#x003b2; cells migration</title><p id="P15">To assess the importance of the menin-IQGAP1 interaction in &#x000df; cell motility, we performed a modified Boyden chamber assay. After 24 hours of migration, virtually all of the Men1-TAP cells remained in the upper chamber, but a small number of mock cells migrated completely through the filter membrane (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>). Because the total number of migratory and non-migratory mock cells was less than that of the seeded cells, we suspected that quite a number of mock cells might be trapped in the filter membrane. We therefore used an alternative approach, the scratch wound assay, to compare the motility of mock versus Men1-TAP cells. As can be seen in <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>, the degree of wound closure achieved by mock cells within 24 hours of wounding was comparable to what was seen after 5 days by the Men1-TAP cells. The dramatic difference between the two cells lines reinforces the impression from the Boyden chamber migration assays that menin overexpression reduces cell motility.</p><p id="P16">To test the effect of Rac1 activity on menin inhibition of cell mobility, we transiently overexpressed constitutively active mutant, RFP-Rac1 (Q61L) in Men1-TAP cells. After 24 hours, Men1-TAP cells reduced the wound gap by 13 % (64 &#x003bc;m of 511 &#x003bc;m) relative to 53% (276 &#x003bc;m out of 519 &#x003bc;m) of mock control cells (<xref rid="SD6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S5</xref>). However, overexpression of active Rac1 (Q61L) increased the migration speed of Men1-TAP cell 2 fold from 64 &#x003bc;m to 122 &#x003bc;m (<xref rid="SD6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S5</xref>). Thus, active Rac1 can abrogate the migratory inhibition caused by Men1 expression in &#x003b2; cell.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Menin modulates IQGAP1 interactions with Rac1</title><p id="P17">IQGAP1 has been reported to promote cell motility via interactions with Rac1 and Cdc42 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Bensenor <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Mataraza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). To test whether menin affects the IQGAP1-Rac1 interaction, we performed affinity pull-down assays to examine associations of menin, IQGAP1 and Rac1 (<xref rid="SD7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S6A</xref>). We precoated Ni-NTA agarose with His-tagged IQGAP1 and then subsequently incubated the coated beads with menin and activated or inactive Rac1. As expected, menin and GTP&#x003b3;S-Rac1 bound independently to IQGAP1 (lanes 4 and 6). The affinity of GDP-Rac1 to IQGAP1 was very low, slightly higher than its background binding to naked Ni-NTA agarose beads (lane 5 vs lane 2). However, GTP&#x003b3;S-Rac1 binding to IQGAP1 was substantially reduced in the presence of menin (lane 7). Thus, activated Rac1 and menin may competitively bind to IQGAP1. This conclusion was fortified by studies of live cells. Mock cells and menin-overexpressing cells were subjected to IPs and immunoblotting. Anti-Rac1 pulled down IQGAP1 but 2.8 fold less effectively in cells that ectopically expressed menin (<xref rid="SD7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S6B, C</xref>).</p><p id="P18">To determine regions in IQGAP1 responsible for menin binding, we tested menin binding to various recombinant fragments of IQGAP1. In these assays, menin showed a weak interaction with N-terminal fragment IQGAP1-N2 (aa 2-522) and strong binding to C-terminal fragments including IQGAP1-C3 (aa 956-1657). However, C3-splited shorter fragment C1(aa 956-1274) and C2 (aa 1276-1657) did not bind or displayed a weak interaction to menin (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A-C</xref>). Together with a previous study showing direct interactions between C1, C2 and N2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Grohmanova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Le Clainche <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), our data suggest that the binding of menin to IQGAP1 depends on the tertiary structure formed between the C-terminal (C3) and N-terminal (N2) domains. Menin-IQGAP1 structural binding may induce IQGAP1 C-terminal conformation affinity toward E-cadherin/&#x003b2;-catenin but against Rac1-GTP (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6E</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Menin expression reduces Rac1-GTP</title><p id="P19">Small GTPases of the Rho family, including Rac1, RhoA, and Cdc42, regulate multiple signaling pathways that affect cell shape and motility, transcription, and cell-cycle progression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Ridley, 2001</xref>). Thus, we sought to determine whether menin affects the activities of these small G proteins using assays to measure their binding to partners that selectively interact with GTP-bound forms of Rac1, RhoA or Cdc42 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Taylor and Shalloway, 1996</xref>). Prior to harvesting the cells for GTPase binding assays, the cells were serum starved and then stimulated with fresh serum. As shown in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6D</xref>, menin overexpression caused a dramatic suppression of Rac1 activation by serum stimulation.</p><p id="P20">RhoA-GTP level was increased but not consistent in mock cells, suggesting that RhoA may play a complicate function in &#x003b2; cells (<xref rid="SD7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig.S6D</xref>). Neither Cdc42-GTP nor total Cdc42 were detected in these cell lines (<xref rid="SD7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig.S6D, S6E</xref>). Collectively, these results indicate that Rac1 is a major Rho family GTPase in the islet cell lines used for this study, and that menin potently prevents Rac1 activation. Inactivation of Rac1 is possibly another mechanism by which menin competitively inhibits Rac1-IQGAP1 interaction in living cells (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig.6E</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S11"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P21">Menin mutations have been known for more than a decade to cause the MEN1 class of multiple endocrine tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Chandrasekharappa <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>), but the oncogenic mechanisms have remained obscure. Until recently, most studies of menin have focused on its role in the nucleus, where it indirectly regulates histone H3 methylation and transcription of at least a few genes that are involved in cell cycle control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Milne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Milne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Schnepp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Although menin is primarily a nuclear protein, it is also detectable in the cytoplasm and on membranes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Guru <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), and its differential distribution between the nucleus and cytoplasm is cell cycle-dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Huang <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Lopez-Egido <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Because little is known about the function of cytoplasmic menin in &#x003b2; cells, we decided to search for cytoplasmic binding partners of menin. We found that a major cytoplasmic binding partner of menin is IQGAP1 (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>), a protein known to be intimately involved in controlling cellular motility and morphogenesis through regulation of actin assembly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Bensenor <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Brandt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Le Clainche <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and intercellular adhesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Kuroda <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). We propose a menin-IQGAP1 pathway, which contrasts and complements the &#x0201c;menin-MLL pathway&#x0201d; in the nucleus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Hughes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Yan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Yokoyama <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p><sec id="S12"><title>Functional interaction between menin and IQGAP1 in endocrine cells</title><p id="P22"><italic>Men1</italic> deletion and mutation causes multiple endocrine tumorigenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Lakhani <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Similarly, IQGAP1 is widely expressed in various tissues. IQGAP1-null mutant mice develop gastric hyperplasia, lung adenoma/adenocarcinoma, and testicular atrophy or mineralization relative to wild-type animals of the same genetic background (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). These observations are consistent with the notion that menin and IQGAP proteins may functionally link to the same pathway in the endocrine cells.</p><p id="P23">IQGAP1 lies in the midst of a complex signal transduction network that regulates cortical microfilaments (MFs) organization, cell motility and cadherin-induced cell adhesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Bashour <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Kuroda <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). Several lines of evidence demonstrate that the interaction of IQGAP1 with menin contributes to the effects on cell adhesion and migration. First, menin increased &#x003b2; cell aggression, which was attenuated by IQGAP1 knockdown (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig.4A-B</xref>). Second, increasing menin concentration leads to a concomitant augmentation of IQGAP1, E-cadherin and &#x003b2;-catenin on the cell surface (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig.3B</xref>, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>). In contrast, menin ablation from islets in vivo decreased the accumulations of E-cadherin and &#x003b2;-catenin at the cell-cell contacts (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D</xref>). Third, menin forms supercomplex with IQGAP1 and &#x003b2;-catenin in &#x003b2;-cells (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D</xref>). Fourth, menin and Rac1 control the subcellular distributions of IQGAP1 in &#x003b2; cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig.3B, C</xref>). They competitively form complex with IQGAP1 in vitro and in cultured cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig.6</xref>, <xref rid="SD7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S6</xref>). This result is in agreement with the previous discovery that reduction of Rac1-GTP level by TPA stimulation could decrease the Rac1-IQGAP1 complexes and increase the IQGAP1-&#x003b2;-catenin complexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Fukata <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="background" id="S13"><title>Regulation of cell motility and cell adhesion through menin-IQGAP1 pathway</title><p id="P24">Menin overexpression led to decreased cellular motility and increased cell-cell adhesion caused by recruitment of IQGAP1, E-cadherin and &#x003b2;-catenin to intercellular junctions. Paralleling these effects of menin overexpression were a reduction in the cytoplasmic levels of activated Rac1 (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6D</xref>), a small G protein whose GTP-bound state and localization at membranes are positively regulated by IQGAP1, and which in turn regulates functional properties of IQGAP1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Fukata <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Hart <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Mataraza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Watanabe <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). On the other hand, association of IQGAP1 with activated Rac1 was attenuated by menin structurally binding to IQGAP1 terminus (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig 6E</xref>). These results implicate menin as an important regulator of IQGAP1 and Rac1, and by extension, the adhesion and motility of endocrine cells.</p><p id="P25">A previous model of intercellular adhesion stipulates specific regulatory roles for activated Rac1 and IQGAP1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Noritake <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). The data on which the model is based on the binding of IQGAP1 to &#x003b2;-catenin abrogates binding of the &#x003b2;-catenin/E-cadherin complex to &#x003b1;-catenin and thus, leads to decreased adhesion. This IQGAP1-mediated inhibition of adhesion can be relieved, however, by binding of Rac1-GTP to IQGAP1, which displaces IQGAP1 from &#x003b2;-catenin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Kuroda <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). Other studies, however, show that activated Rac1 and Cdc42 interact with IQGAP1 and promote cell mobility and polarization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Mataraza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Watanabe <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Watanabe <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). The result presented here indicated that strong adhesion in our &#x003b2; cell lines was correlated with low, basal levels of Rac1-GTP, whereas weak adhesion was correlated with high Rac1-GTP levels and high cell mobility. These results strike us as different mechanisms to modulate IQGAP1 polarity in cell type-specific behavior.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Interplay between menin and IQGAP1 regulates IQGAP1 polarity function</title><p id="P26">Given that IQGAP1 functions in both cell adhesion and mobility, it would be asked what mechanism modulates the two activities in the same cell. IQGAP1 is both a downstream effector and an upstream activator of Cdc42, where active Cdc42 antagonizes IQGAP1 dissociation of the cell-cell contacts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Fukata <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Lambert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Recently Cdc42 has been shown to inhibit IQGAP1&#x02019;s role in polarized secretion in &#x003b2; cells or perhaps migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Rittmeyer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Our results suggest that, at least in the Cdc42-deficient &#x003b2;HC9 cells, menin can replace the active Cdc42 and compete with Rac1 in a complex with IQGAP1, to increase IQGAP1-cadherin association at cell junctions (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6E</xref>). In contrast, activation of Rac1 could increase IQGAP1-Rac1 activity in the cytoplasm and inhibit IQGAP1 association with the E-cadherin-&#x003b2;-catenin complex. Thus, menin and Rac1 competitive interactions with IQGAP1 drive IQGAP1 polarity functions at the cell-cell contacts vs. its polarity functions at the leading edge of migrating cells (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6E</xref>).</p><p id="P27">Since menin represses Ras-mediated transformation in NIH 3T3 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>), and Rac1 is required for Ras-induced development of lung cancer in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Kissil <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), the results of this study may provide a new insight into how menin represses the oncogenic activity of Ras. On the other hand, our model may explain the loose association among islet cells in Men1 insulinoma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Bertolino <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). In epithelial cells, E-cadherin plays a key role in cell-cell adhesion, and loss of E-cadherin is a hallmark of tumor progression, cancer cell invasion and metastasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Andl <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Further work is required to biochemically decipher how menin inhibits Rac1 activation (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig.6E</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S15"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S16"><title>Constructs and cell lines</title><p id="P28">To generate pMX-Men1-TAP construct, the human <italic>Men1</italic> cDNA was subcloned in frame into <italic>Bam-HI-Hind III</italic> restriction sites of a pCTAP vector (Stratagene), and the resulting menin-TAP fragment was excised from this construct and cloned into the <italic>Not1</italic> and <italic>BamH1</italic> sites of retroviral plasmid, pMX-puro (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1A</xref>). pMX-Men1 was constructed by directly inserting human Men1 cDNA fragment into pMX-puro at <italic>Not1</italic> and <italic>BamH1</italic> sites. All the retroviruses were packaged to infect &#x003b2;HC9 cells as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). To stably overexpress wild-type menin, &#x003b2;MX1 cells were reinfected by pcDNA3-Men1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">La <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). A pLKO.1 lentiviral shRNA set targeting mouse IQGAP1 (RMM4534-NM_016721, OpenBiosystem) was used to knockdown IQGAP1. All stable cell lines were created by antibiotic selection (puromycin for pMX-plasmids or G418 for pcDNA3.1-plasmids) (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1</xref>). The cells were grown in Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified Eagle&#x02019;s medium (DMEM) (Mediatech, Inc, Herndon, VA) in the presence of 10% fetal bovine serum, 5% iron-supplemented calf serum (cosmic calf serum) (Hyclone), and 1% penicillin-streptomycin (Invitrogen).</p><p id="P29">The mCherry-Rac1 vector was produced from an eCFP-Rac1 vector obtained from the lab of Dr. Klaus Hahn. The eCFP coding region was excised from the eCFP-Rac1 vector and the mCherry coding region from an mCherry-C1 vector by <italic>NheI</italic> and <italic>BsrGI</italic> digestion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Shaner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). &#x003b2; cell lines were transiently transfected using Lipofectamine&#x02122; 2000 Reagent (Invitrogen).</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Fluorescence microscopy</title><p id="P30">Cells were fixed and stained with indicated antibodies as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Yan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006b</xref>). The primary antibodies used in the study were purchased from companies as described in <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary data</xref>. Texas-Red Phalloidin (Invitrogen) was used to stain F-actin. The fluorescence was examined using a confocal laser scanning microscope (LSM510, Carl Zeiss, Oberkochene, Germany), and a series of images from 1-&#x003bc;m YZ sections were collected. Images were stacked using the LSM510 software and processed by Adobe Photoshop. Genotyping, excision of the floxed <italic>Men1</italic> locus and islet slide staining of mice were performed as describe earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Schnepp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Purification of the tagged-menin complex and Mass Spectrometry analysis of the purified proteins</title><p id="P31">Mock and Men1-TAP cells (1.5&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup>) were separately lysed in cell lysis buffer [250mM NaCL, 1mM MgCL2, 1mM CaCL2, 50mM Tris-HCL at pH 8.0, 0.5% NP-40, 5% glycerol, 2x EDTA-complete protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche)]. The lysates were quickly frozen in dry ice/ethanol slurry for 10 min, followed by incubation for 20 mins in ice-water. Two steps of purification were performed as recommended by the manufacturer (Stratagene). For analysis of protein complexes, a 1/15 volume of sample was separated in NuPAGE 4-12% Bis-Tris gel and visualized by silver stain (Silver staining kit, Invitrogen). The other 1/15 volume was immunoblotted against menin antibody (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S2</xref>). The remaining sample was fractionated in the same SDS gel and stained with colloidal Coommassie blue staining. Bands of interest were excised and analyzed by mass spectrometry.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Adhesion assays</title><p id="P32">Adhesion assays were performed essentially as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Price <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>) with certain modifications. Cells were detached with 1.5mM-EDTA in PBS (without calcium and magnesium) and diluted in serum-free medium. Cells (2&#x000d7;10<sup>5</sup> /well) were seeded to 96-well plates that had been precoated with either PBS, fibronectin (10&#x003bc;g/ml) or goat anti human IgG Fc (20 &#x003bc;g/ml) /Fc-E-cadherin (2&#x003bc;g/ml). After 20 minutes of incubation at room temperature and three washes, the adherent cells were counted from quadruplet wells.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Recombinant binding assay</title><p id="P33">All affinity purification were essentially performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Grohmanova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Le Clainche <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Briefly, GST-tagged IQGAP1 C-terminal fragments were expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (DH5&#x003b1;) and induced with 0.1mM isopropyl 1-thio-&#x003b2;-D-galactopyranoside (IPTG) at 28 &#x000b0;C for 16 hrs. The cells were harvested in lysis buffer (10mM Tris-HCL, pH 8.0, 150mM NaCL, 0.5mM EDTA, 2mM MgCL2, 2mM CaCl2, 0.1% NP40), sonicated and centrifuged at 13,000&#x000d7;g for 20 min. The supernatants were purified on Glutathione Sepharose 4B (GE Healthcare). For menin binding assay, the purified GST-fusion proteins were incubated with 0.2 &#x003bc;g of menin for 1 hr at 4 &#x000b0;C.</p><p id="P34">IP, affinity assays, small G protein affinity binding assays and migration assays are described in <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplemental methods</xref></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S21"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>1</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS77188-supplement-1.doc" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x9e801b0N0xacc8540" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>2</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS77188-supplement-2.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x9e801b0N0xacc8600" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>3</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS77188-supplement-3.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x9e801b0N0xacc86c0" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>4</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS77188-supplement-4.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x9e801b0N0xacc8780" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD6"><label>5</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS77188-supplement-5.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x9e801b0N0xacc8840" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD7"><label>6</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS77188-supplement-6.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x9e801b0N0xacc8900" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="S22" sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures</title><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Menin overexpression induces &#x003b2;HC9 cells to become compact and clustered. Two types of &#x003b2;HC9-derived cell lines are shown: mock (pMX-puro empty vector) and Men1-TAP (overexpressing menin-TAP). Differential interference contrast images of cells are shown at low <bold>(A, B)</bold> and high <bold>(C, D)</bold> magnification. Texas Red-phalloidin staining was used to assess the organization of F-actin. Eleven confocal Z-stacks were taken and projected into one image <bold>(E, F)</bold>, and a single confocal section stained for F-actin and for nuclei with DAPI is also shown <bold>(G-H)</bold>. The morphological polarity of a cell was defined by a seminquantitative index of cell shape as described by Donnadieu and coworkers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Donnadieu <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>). Briefly, the cell was traced as an ellipse using Photoshop software. Two lines were drawn: one along the longest axis of the ellipse; the other perpendicular to the first and bisecting it. The cell shape index was determined by the ratio of the long axis to the short axis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms77188f1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>IQGAP1 is a major cytoplasmic binding partner of menin. Soluble extracts from mock cells and Men1-TAP cells were used for TAP purification. <bold>(A)</bold> The purified products were separated on SDS-PAGE and identified with silver staining. The two most prominent bands in lane 3 were excised from the gel, and their tryptic peptides were identified as menin and IQGAP1 by mass spectrometry (nanoLC/nanospray/MS/MS). <bold>(B)</bold> and <bold>(C)</bold> Physical interactions between menin and IQGAP1 were verified by in vitro reciprocal immunoprecipitation. <bold>(D)</bold> Comparative expression levels of proteins marked by the indicated antibodies in mock and Men1-TAP cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms77188f2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Menin co-localizes with IQGAP1 in &#x003b2; cell lines. The right panel showed quantitative analyses of fluorescence intensity across co-localized areas using Zeiss LSM510 software, underscoring the fluorescence distribution in the membrane and cytoplasm (i.e. peak&#x02019;s breadth). <bold>(A)</bold> Distinct enrichments of menin at the cell-cell contacts in mock and Men1-TAP cells. <bold>(B)</bold> Distinct accumulations of overexpressed IQGAP1-YFP on the cell surface and in the cytoplasm between mock and Men1-TAP cell. <bold>(C)</bold> Overexpressed mCherry-Rac1 delocalizing subcellular distributions of IQGAP1-YFP in Men1-TAP cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms77188f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Menin promotes cell-cell adhesions. <bold>(A)</bold> Cells were detached with 1.5mM EDTA-PBS at 37 &#x000b0;C for either 5min (Mock) or 15min (Men1). The detached cells were diluted and added to wells coated with PBS, Fibronectin (Fn) or Fc-E-cadherin (E-cad). The number of adherent cells/microscopic field is presented (n=5; &#x000b1; S.D). <bold>(B)</bold> IQGAP1 knockdown reduced cell adhesion to E-cadherin in menin overexpression cells. Men1 cells were infected with either IQGAP1 ShRNA or scramble ShRNA lentiviruses, followed by adhesion assays (n=8; &#x000b1;S.D.). Two tailed t-test was used to determine the P value for the difference as shown in the figure. Intercellular junctions marked by E-cadherin and &#x003b2;-catenin in &#x003b2;HC9-derived cell lines <bold>(C)</bold> and paraffin-embedded islets from wild type or <italic>Men1</italic>+/- mice <bold>(D)</bold> were imaged by immunofluorescence. Quantitative analyses of fluorescence intensity across long linear paths that intersect with at least three cell-cell contacts were performed using Zeiss LSM510 software. <bold>(E)</bold> Detection of menin, IQGAP1 and &#x003b2;-catenin complex. IQGAP1 was knocked down with a pool of 5 lentiviral shRNA constructs against murine IQGAP1. The cell lysates from control or IQGAP1 ShRNA knockdown Men1 cells were immunoprecipitated with menin-specific antibodies, followed by Western blotting to determine the association of IQGAP1 and &#x003b2;-catenin with menin. The bottom histogram shows quantification of &#x003b2;-catenin in lysate and menin-IP from control and IQGAP1-deficient cells as in B, normalized by &#x003b2;-catenin level in control lysate. *, paired <italic>t</italic>-test, P&#x0003c;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms77188f4a"/><graphic xlink:href="nihms77188f4b"/><graphic xlink:href="nihms77188f4c"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Menin inhibits migration of &#x000df;HC9-derived cells. <bold>(A)</bold> An equal number of mock cells or Men1-TAP cells were seeded onto the upper chamber and 24 hours later. Cells that remained in the upper chamber and those moved to the lower surface of the filter membrane were photographed and counted. <bold>(B)</bold> Menin overexpression inhibited closure of artificial wounds made in confluent cellular monolayers. One of three assays was shown (n=3; &#x000b1;S.D.).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms77188f5"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig.6</label><caption><p>Menin directly binds to IQGAP1. (A) A schematic diagram of functional domains present in full-length IQGAP1 and seven fragments used for binding assays. (B) Nickel&#x02013;agarose beads were precoated with 2&#x003bc;g of his-tagged IQGAP1 (FL), IQGAP1 (&#x00394;NT), IQGAP1 (522), IQGAP1 (71), or BSA as a negative control. The precoated beads were then incubated 0.2&#x003bc;g of menin. Chemiluminescent immunoblotting was used to detect any menin that may have bound to beads. (C) Precoated GST-fusion C-terminal proteins of IQGAP1 were incubated with menin (0.2&#x003bc;g). Top, anti-menin Western blot of bound menin. Bottom: Coomassie stained gel slices show input of the GST-fusion proteins. Comparison of Western blot and Coomassie staining indicated that all samples of pre-coated GST-fusions were saturated over menin-binding. (D) Menin overexpression reduces cellular levels of activated Rac1. PAK1-PBD agarose and Rhotekin RBD agarose were used to isolate GTP-Rac1 from whole cell lysates from each of the indicated cell lines. The collected complexes were then resolved by SDS-PAGE, and probed with an anti-Rac1 antibody. The amount of Rac1-GTP was quantified by densitometry and normalized by the total input Rac1 protein. Relative to mock cells, Rac1-GTP reduced 2 fold and 6 fold in Men1-TAP and Men1 cells respectively. *, paired <italic>t</italic>-test, P&#x0003c;0.05. (E) A model for menin-regulated IQGAP interaction with the Rac1 and E-cadherin/&#x003b2;-catenin complex. When membrane menin increases, menin inhibits Rac1 activation and binds the tertiary structure by folding the C-terminus (C1 and C2) and N-terminus (N2) of IQGAP1. Their bindings induce IQGAP1 conformation switch to E-cadherin/&#x003b2;-catenin binding (black box, RasGAP domain) at cell-cell contacts and enhance intercellular adhesion. When reduction of menin activity occurs in tumor cells by <italic>Men1</italic> mutation, or increase of Rac1 activity by oncogene, such as Ras, Rac1-GTP interacts with IQGAP1 (blank box, GRD domain) and increases IQGAP1 accumulations in cytoplasm and at the front edge of migrating cells, thereby promoting cell mobility.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms77188f6"/></fig></sec><ack id="S23"><p>The parent clonal &#x003b2;HC9 insulin-secreting cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Radvanyi <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>) were obtained from the cell repository of the Diabetes Research Center at the University of Pennsylvania, with permission of Dr. F.M. Matschinsky. We thank Drs. Faming Zhang for his gifts of purified MBP-tagged menin and non-tagged menin, Martin A. Schwartz for mutant human Rac1 vectors, and Ruth Kroschewski for the IQGAP1 C-terminal constructs (C1-C4). All confocal images and quantitative analyses of fluorescent intensity were conducted at the Biomedical Imaging Core Facility at the University of Pennsylvania. We thank Peter Blessington, Alicia Nelson, Hai Shen, Mercy Gohil and Elena Blagoi for their technical assistance. A special thanks to Drs. Claudia Andl and Margaret Chou for their stimulating discussions. This work was supported in part from NIH grants (R01-CA-100912 and R01-CA-113962 to XH, and R01-NS051746 to GSB), and a grant from the American Diabetes Association (7-07-RA-60 to XH).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="R1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andl</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fargnoli</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Okawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takaoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Coordinated functions of E-cadherin and transforming growth factor beta receptor II in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>9878</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17047049</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>p18Ink4c, but not p27Kip1, collaborates with Men1 to suppress neuroendocrine organ tumors</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>1495</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17145768</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bashour</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fullerton</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>IQGAP1, a Rac- and Cdc42-binding protein, directly binds and cross-links microfilaments</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><volume>137</volume><fpage>1555</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9199170</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bensenor</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallrabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>IQGAP1 regulates cell motility by linking growth factor signaling to actin assembly</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>658</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17264147</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertolino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Casse</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Pancreatic beta-cell-specific ablation of the multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN1) gene causes full penetrance of insulinoma development in mice</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>4836</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12941803</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaibuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Dia1 and IQGAP1 interact in cell migration and phagocytic cup formation</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><volume>178</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17620407</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandrasekharappa</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Guru</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Manickam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Olufemi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmert-Buck</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Positional cloning of the gene for multiple endocrine neoplasia-type 1</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>276</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9103196</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeshan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tubbs</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The tumor suppressor menin regulates hematopoiesis and myeloid transformation by influencing Hox gene expression</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>1018</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16415155</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Scacheri</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett-Beal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmert-Buck</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgemon</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>A mouse model of multiple endocrine neoplasia, type 1, develops multiple endocrine tumors</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>1118</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158604</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Scacheri</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Montagna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Of mice and MEN1: Insulinomas in a conditional mouse knockout</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>6075</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12917331</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donnadieu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cefai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Paresys</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bismuth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Imaging early steps of human T cell activation by antigen-presenting cells</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>148</volume><fpage>2643</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1349319</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawajiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Cdc42 and Rac1 regulate the interaction of IQGAP1 with beta-catenin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>274</volume><fpage>26044</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10473551</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawajiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Involvement of IQGAP1, an effector of Rac1 and Cdc42 GTPases, in cell-cell dissociation during cell scattering</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>2165</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238950</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Noritake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Rac1 and Cdc42 capture microtubules through IQGAP1 and CLIP-170</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12110184</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grohmanova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaepfer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroschewski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Phosphorylation of IQGAP1 modulates its binding to Cdc42, revealing a new type of rho-GTPase regulator</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>48495</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15355962</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guru</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Manickam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Isolation, genomic organization, and expression analysis of Men1, the murine homolog of the MEN1 gene</article-title><source>Mamm Genome</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10341092</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guru</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marx</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Menin, the product of the MEN1 gene, is a nuclear protein</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>1630</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9465067</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Callow</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Polakis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>IQGAP1, a calmodulin-binding protein with a rasGAP-related domain, is a potential effector for cdc42Hs</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>2997</fpage><lpage>3005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8670801</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krutzsch</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Nuclear/cytoplasmic localization of the multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 gene product, menin</article-title><source>Lab Invest</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10092066</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozenblatt-Rosen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Menin associates with a trithorax family histone methyltransferase complex and with the hoxc8 locus</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14992727</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Djeu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Akt mediates Ras downregulation of RhoB, a suppressor of transformation, invasion, and metastasis</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>5565</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15169915</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Heppner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasekharappa</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Stable overexpression of MEN1 suppresses tumorigenicity of RAS</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>5936</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10557080</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kissil</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Walmsley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanlon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Haigis</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender Kim</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweet-Cordero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Requirement for Rac1 in a K-ras induced lung cancer in the mouse</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>8089</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17804720</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ookubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Role of IQGAP1, a target of the small GTPases Cdc42 and Rac1, in regulation of E-cadherin-mediated cell-cell adhesion</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>281</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9694656</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>La</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnepp</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>P</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>S</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Tumor suppressor menin regulates expression of insulin-like growth factor binding protein 2</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>145</volume><fpage>3443</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15044367</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lakhani</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The multiple endocrine neoplasia syndromes</article-title><source>Annu Rev Med</source><volume>58</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17037976</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Choquet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mege</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Dynamics of ligand-induced, Rac1-dependent anchoring of cadherins to the actin cytoskeleton</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><volume>157</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11970959</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Clainche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaepfer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Klingauf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grohmanova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Veligodskiy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>IQGAP1 stimulates actin assembly through the N-WASP-Arp2/3 pathway</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>282</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17085436</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakladar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bronson</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Gastric hyperplasia in mice lacking the putative Cdc42 effector IQGAP1</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10611248</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez-Egido</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongcam-Rudloff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gobl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Menin&#x02019;s interaction with glial fibrillary acidic protein and vimentin suggests a role for the intermediate filament network in regulating menin activity</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169273</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mataraza</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Entwistle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacks</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>IQGAP1 promotes cell motility and invasion</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>41237</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12900413</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mataraza</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacks</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Multiple proteins mediate IQGAP1-stimulated cell migration</article-title><source>Cell Signal</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>1857</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17544257</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mateer</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>McDaniel</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Habermacher</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cromer</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The mechanism for regulation of the F-actin binding activity of IQGAP1 by calcium/calmodulin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>277</volume><fpage>12324</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11809768</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Allis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>MLL targets SET domain methyltransferase activity to Hox gene promoters</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12453418</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozenblatt-Rosen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Menin and MLL cooperatively regulate expression of cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitors</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15640349</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noritake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaibuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>IQGAP1: a key regulator of adhesion and migration</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>2085</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15890984</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajdo-Milasinovic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwartkruis</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collard</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Rap1 regulates E-cadherin-mediated cell-cell adhesion</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>35127</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15166221</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radvanyi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Christgau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baekkeskov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolicoeur</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Pancreatic beta cells cultured from individual preneoplastic foci in a multistage tumorigenesis pathway: a potentially general technique for isolating physiologically representative cell lines</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>4223</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8391634</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Rho family proteins: coordinating cell responses</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719051</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rittmeyer</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>A dual role for IQGAP1 in regulating exocytosis</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216334</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnepp</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cash</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Mutation of tumor suppressor gene Men1 acutely enhances proliferation of pancreatic islet cells</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>5707</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740708</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaner</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbach</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Giepmans</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Improved monomeric red, orange and yellow fluorescent proteins derived from Discosoma sp. red fluorescent protein</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1567</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15558047</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalloway</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Cell cycle-dependent activation of Ras</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1621</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8994826</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Noritake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaibuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Roles of IQGAP1 in cell polarization and migration</article-title><source>Novartis Found Symp</source><volume>269</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><comment>discussion 101-5, 223-30</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16355537</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Noritake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takefuji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Interaction with IQGAP1 links APC to Rac1, Cdc42, and actin filaments during cell polarization and migration</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Desmond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006a</year><article-title>Cdx4 and menin co-regulate hoxa9 expression in hematopoietic cells</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>e47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183676</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006b</year><article-title>The Forkhead Transcription Factor FoxI1 Remains Bound to Condensed Mitotic Chromosomes and Stably Remodels Chromatin Structure</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16354687</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="R48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Somervaille</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozenblatt-Rosen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The Menin Tumor Suppressor Protein Is an Essential Oncogenic Cofactor for MLL-Associated Leukemogenesis</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>123</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16239140</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>