<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Pharm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mp</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">mpohbp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Pharmaceutics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1543-8384</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1543-8392</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18729468</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2646875</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/mp800006e</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Combination Chemotherapy and Photodynamic Therapy with Fab&#x02032; Fragment Targeted HPMA Copolymer Conjugates in Human Ovarian Carcinoma Cells</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Synergism of SOS and Mce<sub>6</sub> against OVCAR-3 Cells</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Hongrapipat</surname><given-names>Jarunee</given-names></name><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Pavla</given-names></name><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jihua</given-names></name><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><name><surname>Prakongpan</surname><given-names>Sompol</given-names></name><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath5"><name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>Jind&#x00159;ich</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="afn3" ref-type="author-notes">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Pharmaceutics and Pharmaceutical Chemistry and Department of Bioengineering, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah 84112, and Department of Pharmacy, Mahidol University, Bangkok 10400, Thailand</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Mailing address: Department of Pharmaceutics and Pharmaceutical Chemistry, University of Utah, 30 S., 2000 E., Rm. 201, Salt Lake City, UT 84112. Phone: <phone>(801) 581-7211</phone>. Fax: <fax>(801) 581-7848</fax>. E-mail: <email>jindrich.kopecek@utah.edu</email>.</corresp><fn id="afn1"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Department of Pharmaceutics and Pharmaceutical Chemistry, University of Utah.</p></fn><fn id="afn2"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>Mahidol University.</p></fn><fn id="afn3"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p>Department of Bioengineering, University of Utah.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>08</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>06</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>709</lpage><history><date date-type="issue-pub"><day>06</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="asap"><day>27</day><month>08</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>01</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>07</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>07</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 American Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>American Chemical Society</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org" license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the ACS AuthorChoice Terms &#x00026; Conditions.  Any use of this article, must conform to the terms of that license which are available at <uri xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org">http://pubs.acs.org</uri>.</license-p></license><license license-type="ccc-price"><license-p>40.75</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp-2008-00006e_0009" id="tgr1"/></p><p>The biological activities of sequential combinations of anticancer drugs, SOS thiophene (SOS) and mesochlorin e<sub>6</sub> monoethylenediamine (Mce<sub>6</sub>), in the form of free drugs, nontargeted <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide (HPMA) copolymer&#x02212;drug conjugates, P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> and P-GFLG-SOS (P is the HPMA copolymer backbone and GFLG is the glycylphenylalanylleucylglycine spacer), and Fab&#x02032;-targeted HPMA copolymer&#x02212;drug conjugates, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; (Fab&#x02032; from OV-TL16 antibodies complementary to CD47), were evaluated against human ovarian carcinoma OVCAR-3 cells. Mce<sub>6</sub>, SOS, P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>, P-GFLG-SOS, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;, and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;, when used as single agents or in binary combination, exhibited cytotoxic activities against OVCAR-3 cells, as determined using a modified MTT assay. The binding and internalization of P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; by OVCAR-3 cells were visualized by confocal microscopy and flow cytometry. The results confirmed an enhanced biorecognition by OVCAR-3 cells of Fab&#x02032;-targeted HPMA copolymer conjugates over nontargeted conjugates. The median-effect analysis and the determination of the combination index (CI) were used to describe the drug interaction and quantify the synergism, antagonism, or additivity in anticancer effects. The sequential combinations of SOS+Mce<sub>6</sub> and P-GFLG-SOS+P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> displayed very strong synergism to synergism in the entire range of cell inhibition levels (<italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> = 0.5 &#x02212; 0.95). The P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;+P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; exhibited a strong synergism for <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> values up to about 0.85, but showed synergistic effect and nearly additive effect at <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> = 0.9 and 0.95, respectively. These observations support the continuation of <italic>in vivo</italic> investigations of these conjugates for the treatment of ovarian cancer.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>N</italic>-(2-Hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide (HPMA) copolymer</kwd><kwd>Fab&#x02032; antibody fragment</kwd><kwd>2,5-<italic>bis</italic>(5-hydroxymethyl-2-thienyl)furan</kwd><kwd>mesochlorin e<sub>6</sub> monoethylenediamine</kwd><kwd>combination index</kwd><kwd>ovarian cancer</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement><funding-source>National Institutes of Health, United States</funding-source></funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>mp800006e</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>mp-2008-00006e</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Polymer&#x02212;drug conjugates are established as one of the first-generation nanomedicines for the treatment of cancer. Their use facilitates the uptake and transport of therapeutic agents and creates a dose-differentiation between the treatment target and the rest of the body, due to the fact that macromolecules can accumulate passively in solid tumor tissue by the phenomenon called &#x0201c;enhanced permeability and retention (EPR) effect&#x0201d;.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>) The enhanced drug accumulation in tumor tissue increases the therapeutic effect while reducing nonspecific side-effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> Moreover, the intracellular trafficking mechanism of polymer&#x02212;drug conjugates renders drug efflux pumps ineffective.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>) To obtain such multifunctional capabilities, polymer&#x02212;drug conjugates have been designed to consist of (a) a nonimmunogenic and biocompatible water-soluble polymer backbone such as poly(ethylene glycol) or <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide (HPMA) copolymers,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>) (b) therapeutically active molecules, (c) linkers between the polymer backbone and the active molecule that are stable in blood circulation and release the free drug at target sites, and (d) a targeting moiety to mediate biomolecular recognition.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup> HPMA copolymers are one of the most frequently evaluated polymer backbones in polymer&#x02212;drug conjugates. The main advantages of HPMA copolymer&#x02212;drug conjugates over their low molecular weight drugs (reviewed in Kope&#x0010d;ek,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>) Putnam and Kope&#x0010d;ek,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>) Kope&#x0010d;ek et al.,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>) Duncan,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>) Cuchelkar and Kope&#x0010d;ek,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>) Pan and Kope&#x0010d;ek(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>)) include the following: (1) enhanced water solubility of poorly soluble or insoluble drugs with concomitant improvement of drug bioavailability; (2) long-lasting circulation in the bloodstream;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup> (3) decreased nonspecific toxicity of the conjugated drug and immunogenicity of the targeting moiety;(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>) (4) increased <italic>passive</italic> and/or <italic>active</italic> accumulation of the drug at the site of its action by the EPR effect and/or by targeting, respectively;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> (5) active uptake by fluid-phase pinocytosis (nontargeted polymer-bound drug) or receptor-mediated endocytosis (targeted polymer bound drug); (6) the potential to overcome efflux pump-mediated mechanism of drug resistance;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> and (7) ability to deliver several active components with different properties to the same target site that enhance the specific activity of the main drug.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup> The incorporation of targeting moieties, such as monoclonal antibody (mAb) or antibody fragment, into HPMA copolymer&#x02212;drug conjugates results in specific delivery and enhancement of the amount of the polymeric conjugate being internalized by receptor-mediated endocytosis.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>) Consequently, the intracellular concentration of the polymeric conjugates is enhanced with concomitant increase in antitumor activity.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>) Moreover, the polymer modification of mAb or antibody fragments reduces their immunogenicity and extends their circulating half-lives.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> The use of antibody fragments provides a better control of the structure of HPMA copolymer conjugates compared to full-length mAb. The unique sulfhydryl group near the C terminus of Fab&#x02032; fragments has provided a convenient way for coupling to HPMA copolymers containing maleimide groups and allow the antigen-binding site to be more approachable.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup></p><p>To improve the therapeutic outcome and reduce the toxicity of anticancer agents, a novel concept of combining chemotherapy and photodynamic therapy (PDT), using HPMA copolymer bound drugs, was developed.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>) The <italic>in vivo</italic> studies on two cancer models, Neuro 2A neuroblastoma induced in A/J mice(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>) and human ovarian carcinoma heterotransplanted in nude mice,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> demonstrated that combination therapy with HPMA copolymer-bound DOX (doxorubicin) and HPMA copolymer-bound Mce<sub>6</sub> (mesochlorin e<sub>6</sub> monoethylenediamine) produced tumor cures which could not be obtained with either chemotherapy or PDT alone. Furthermore, significantly lower nonspecific toxicities were observed when compared to low molecular weight drugs. Previously, <italic>in vitro</italic> studies of the binary combination of free and HPMA copolymer-bound SOS [2,5-bis(5-hydroxymethyl-2-thienyl)furan, NSC 652287], DOX, and Mce<sub>6</sub> in the treatment of human A498 renal carcinoma cells using the median-effect method showed that these combinations displayed synergistic-to-additive effects, depending on the cytotoxic mechanisms of each agent.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>)</p><p>In the present study, Fab&#x02032;-targeted and nontargeted HPMA copolymer&#x02212;drug (SOS and Mce<sub>6</sub>) conjugates for combination chemotherapy and PDT against human ovarian OVCAR-3 carcinoma cells were synthesized. SOS, a dithiophene compound, was used as the chemotherapy agent. Its mechanism of action consists of disrupting the p53-HDM-2 (human double minute-2) interaction, resulting in an increased p53 accumulation, thereby inducing cell cycle arrest and apoptosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> For PDT the second-generation synthetic photosensitizer, Mce<sub>6</sub>, was used. Photosensitizer molecules can be activated by specific wavelength of light and interact with molecular oxygen to produce reactive singlet oxygen, causing irreversible photodamage to cells resulting in cell death.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref>) The antibody Fab&#x02032; fragment was prepared from OV-TL16 antibody, which recognizes the OA-3 surface antigen, also known as CD47 or IAP (integrin-associated protein),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup> overexpressed on most human ovarian carcinoma cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref></sup></p><p>It was hypothesized that a combination of these agents may produce synergistic effects and has higher efficiency than each agent alone. Accordingly, the efficiency of free, nontargeted, and Fab&#x02032; fragment-targeted HPMA copolymer-bound SOS and Mce<sub>6</sub> against OVCAR-3 cells as single agents and in combination was evaluated. The combination index (CI) analysis was used to quantify the synergism, antagonism, and additive effects of drug combinations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref></sup></p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Materials</title><p>Mce<sub>6</sub> was purchased from Porphyrin Products (Logan, UT). SOS was kindly supplied by the Drug Synthesis and Chemistry Branch, Developmental Therapeutics Program, Division of Cancer Treatment and Diagnosis, National Cancer Institute. All other chemicals were purchased from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, MO).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Cell Line</title><p>The human ovarian carcinoma cell line OVCAR-3 was purchased from American type Culture Collection. Cells were cultured in RPMI 1640 medium (Sigma) containing 10 &#x003bc;g/mL insulin (Sigma) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (HyClone Laboratories, Logan, UT), at 37 &#x000b0;C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> (v/v).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>OV-TL16 Antibody Production</title><p>The OV-TL16 antibody was produced as described previously.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>) Briefly, the OV-TL16 antibody was produced by <italic>in vitro</italic> cartridge bioreactor (Cellulosic-MPS, Spectrum Laboratories, Rancho Dominguez, CA) culture of OV-TL16 hybridoma cells with serum free hybridoma medium (Gibco Life Sciences, Carlsbad, CA). The antibody was purified by applying the supernatant of cell suspension harvested from bioreactor to a protein G Sepharose 4 Fast Flow column (Pharmacia, Piscataway, NJ), equilibrated with binding buffer (0.01 M Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 0.15 M NaCl, 0.01 M EDTA pH 7.2). The OV-TL16 antibody was eluted with 0.5 M acetate buffer pH 3.0. The antibody was dialyzed (mol wt cutoff 6&#x02212;8 kDa) against phosphate buffered saline (PBS) overnight at 4 &#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Preparation of Fab&#x02032; Fragment</title><p>The antibody Fab&#x02032; fragment was prepared freshly as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> The OV-TL16 antibody in 0.1 M citric buffer pH 4.0 was digested by 10% (w/w) pepsin (Sigma) for 2.5 h at 37 &#x000b0;C to give F(ab&#x02032;)<sub>2</sub>. The digestion reaction was monitored by size exclusion chromatography on a Superdex 200 column. The F(ab&#x02032;)<sub>2</sub> was reduced to Fab&#x02032; with 20 mM cysteine (Sigma) in 20 mM Tris buffer pH 8.5 for 1 h at 37 &#x000b0;C. Excess cysteine was removed on a Sephadex G-25 (PD-10 column, Pharmacia).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Synthesis of Nontargeted HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub> Conjugate (P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)</title><p>P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> was prepared as described previously.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>) Briefly, the conjugate was synthesized using a polymer analogous reaction in two steps. First, the polymer precursor (P-GFLG-ONp) was prepared by radical precipitation copolymerization of HPMA and <italic>N</italic>-methacryloylglycylphenylalanylleucylglycine <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenyl ester (MA-GFLG-ONp).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref></sup> Second, Mce<sub>6</sub> was bound to P-GFLG-ONp by aminolysis of reactive ONp groups in <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylformamide (DMF). The reaction solution was precipitated into a mixture of acetone:ether (3:2 (v/v)). The dried precipitate was dissolved in methanol and purified on a Sephadex LH-20 column with methanol/0.5% acetic acid as the elution solvent. The polymer band was collected and evaporated to dryness. The product was dissolved in deionized (DI) water, dialyzed overnight and lyophilized. The product yield was 69%. The structure and characterization of nontargeted polymer conjugates are summarized in Scheme <xref rid="sch1" ref-type="scheme">1</xref>A and Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><fig id="sch1" position="float"><label>Scheme 1</label><caption><title>Chemical Structures of (A) Nontargeted and (B) Fab&#x02032;-Targeted HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub> or &#x02212;SOS Conjugates</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp-2008-00006e_0006" id="gs1" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characterization of Nontargeted HPMA Copolymer Conjugates, Polymeric Precursors, and Fluorescently Labeled HPMA Copolymer Conjugates</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">structures</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">mol % of<break/>side chains<xref rid="tbl1-fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">mmol of ligand/<break/>g of polymer<break/>conjugate</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">no. of ligands/<break/>polymer chain<break/>(conjugate)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">apparent<break/><italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> (kDa)<xref rid="tbl1-fn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">2.04</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.125</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">2.9</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">23</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-GFLG-SOS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">1.62</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.106</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">3.4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">32</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-NH<sub>2</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">2.62</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.153&#x02009;(Mce<sub>6</sub>)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">1.7&#x02009;(Mce<sub>6</sub>)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">11</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">8.11<xref rid="tbl1-fn3" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.472&#x02009;(NH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-SOS)-NH<sub>2</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">4.60</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.270&#x02009;(SOS)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">2.7&#x02009;(SOS)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">10</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">4.70<xref rid="tbl1-fn3" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.272&#x02009;(NH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-MAL</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">2.60</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.142&#x02009;(Mce<sub>6</sub>)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">2.0&#x02009;(Mce<sub>6</sub>)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">14</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">6.02<xref rid="tbl1-fn4" ref-type="table-fn">d</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.329&#x02009;(MAL)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-SOS)-MAL</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">4.14</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.236&#x02009;(SOS)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">5.2&#x02009;(SOS)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">22</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">3.36<xref rid="tbl1-fn4" ref-type="table-fn">d</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.192&#x02009;(MAL)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-FITC</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top"><xref rid="tbl1-fn6" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.060<xref rid="tbl1-fn5" ref-type="table-fn">e</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">1.0&#x02009;(FITC)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top"><xref rid="tbl1-fn6" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-SOS)-FITC</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top"><xref rid="tbl1-fn6" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.038<xref rid="tbl1-fn5" ref-type="table-fn">e</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.6&#x02009;(FITC)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top"><xref rid="tbl1-fn6" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC)<xref rid="tbl1-fn7" ref-type="table-fn">g</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top"><xref rid="tbl1-fn6" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.063<xref rid="tbl1-fn5" ref-type="table-fn">e</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">3.1&#x02009;(FITC&#x02009;per&#x02009;conjugate)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top"><xref rid="tbl1-fn6" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-SOS)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC)<xref rid="tbl1-fn7" ref-type="table-fn">g</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top"><xref rid="tbl1-fn6" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">0.050<xref rid="tbl1-fn5" ref-type="table-fn">e</xref></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">2.5&#x02009;(FITC&#x02009;per&#x02009;conjugate)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top"><xref rid="tbl1-fn6" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1-fn1"><label>a</label><p>Determined by UV spectrophotometry in methanol: &#x003b5;<sub>395</sub> = 158000 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for Mce<sub>6</sub>, and &#x003b5;<sub>358</sub> = 33000 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for SOS.</p></fn><fn id="tbl1-fn2"><label>b</label><p>Apparent molecular weight (<italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub>) of polymers was estimated by size exclusion chromatography using AKTA/FPLC (Pharmacia) system equipped with a Superose 6 column, calibrated with polyHPMA fractions. PBS buffer pH 7.3 + 30% (v) acetonitrile and 0.1 M acetate buffer pH 5.5 + 30% (v) acetonitrile were used for polymer conjugates containing Mce<sub>6</sub> and polymer conjugates containing SOS, respectively.</p></fn><fn id="tbl1-fn3"><label>c</label><p>Determined by ninhydrin assay.</p></fn><fn id="tbl1-fn4"><label>d</label><p>Determined by 5-((2-(and-3)-<italic>S</italic>-(acetylmercapto)succinoyl)amino)fluorescein assay (SAMSA assay, Molecular Probes).</p></fn><fn id="tbl1-fn5"><label>e</label><p>Determined by spectrophotometric determination of FITC (&#x003b5;<sub>497</sub> = 73 000 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in 0.1 M sodium borate buffer).</p></fn><fn id="tbl1-fn6"><label>f</label><p>Not determined.</p></fn><fn id="tbl1-fn7"><label>g</label><p>Fluorescently labeled targeted conjugates were prepared by reacting P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; and P- (GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; (Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) with 5-SFX.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>Synthesis of Nontargeted HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;SOS Conjugate (P-GFLG-SOS)</title><p>P-GFLG-SOS (Scheme <xref rid="sch1" ref-type="scheme">1</xref>A) was synthesized by binding of SOS to the P-GFLG-ONp polymer precursor via an ester linkage.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>) Briefly, P-GFLG-ONp was dissolved in DMF and mixed with DMF solution of SOS. 4-Dimethylaminopyridine (DMAP) was added, and the reaction was allowed to proceed for 72 h in the dark at room temperature. The product was isolated, after reduction of volume, by precipitation into a mixture of acetone:ether (3:1 (v/v)). The precipitate was dissolved in methanol and applied to a Sephadex LH-20 column with methanol as the mobile phase. The polymer band was collected, concentrated and reprecipitated. The product was a yellowish powder, with a yield of 61%.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title>Synthesis of HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub> Conjugate Containing Maleimide Groups, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-MAL</title><p>This copolymer precursor was prepared in three steps. The reactions are shown in Scheme <xref rid="sch2" ref-type="scheme">2</xref>. First, a polymerizable derivative of Mce<sub>6</sub>, <italic>N</italic>-methacryloylglycylphenylalanylleucylglycine Mce<sub>6</sub> (MA-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>),(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>) was synthesized by reacting MA-GFLG-ONp (60 mg, 0.103 mmol) with Mce<sub>6</sub> (63.5 mg, 0.093 mmol) in DMF (&#x0223c;2 mL). The reaction solution was stirred at room temperature in the dark for 2 h. <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>&#x02032;-diisopropylethylamine (DIPEA; 18 &#x003bc;L, 0.103 mmol) was added and stirring continued overnight. 1-Amino-2-propanol (&#x0223c;8 &#x003bc;L, 0.103 mmol) and a small amount of <italic>tert</italic>-octylpyrocatechol were added and DMF was removed under reduced pressure. The residue was isolated using a Sephadex LH-20 column with acetone:methanol:acetic acid (2:1:0.1) as the mobile phase. The fractions were collected and checked on TLC. The product fraction was evaporated to dryness, washed with ether, collected by filtration, and dried under vacuum. The molecular weight (<italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub>) of MA-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> was 1083.6 Da as determined by electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (ESI-MS). The product yield was 90 mg (73%). Second, the polymeric precursor P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-NH<sub>2</sub> was prepared by radical copolymerization of HPMA(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref>) (107.6 mg, 0.751 mmol), <italic>N</italic>-(3-aminopropyl)methacrylamide hydrochloride (APMA, 16.27 mg, 0.091 mmol; Polysciences, Warrington, PA), and MA-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> (76.9 mg, 0.068 mmol) in methanol (&#x0223c;1.8 mL) at 50 &#x000b0;C for 48 h, using 2,2&#x02032;-azobisisobutyronitrile (AIBN; 19.27 mg) as the initiator. The polymerization mixture contained 12.5 wt % of monomers and 1.2 wt % of AIBN. The molar ratio of HPMA:APMA:MA-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> was 82.5:10:7.5. The reaction mixture was purified on a Sephadex LH-20 column eluted with methanol. The polymer fraction was collected, and methanol was evaporated. The residue was precipitated in a mixture of acetone:ether (1:2 (v/v)). The precipitate was dissolved in water, dialyzed (mol wt cutoff 6&#x02212;8 kDa) against DI water and lyophilized. The product yield was 65 mg (32%). Third, polymeric precursor P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-MAL was prepared by reacting P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-NH<sub>2</sub> (55 mg, 0.026 mmol NH<sub>2</sub> group) with succinimidyl <italic>trans</italic>-4-(maleimidomethyl)cyclohexane-1-carboxylate (SMCC; 17.36 mg, 0.052 mmol) (Soltec Ventures, Beverly, MA) and DIPEA (&#x0223c;13 &#x003bc;L, 0.078 mmol). The mole ratio of NH<sub>2</sub>:SMCC:DIPEA was 1:2:3. P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-NH<sub>2</sub> was dissolved in 0.3 mL of DMF and SMCC in 0.9 mL of DMF. The polymer solution was added into the SMCC solution. DIPEA was added dropwise. The reaction solution was stirred overnight at room temperature. DMF was removed under reduced pressure to dryness. The residue was dissolved in a small volume of methanol and purified on a Sephadex LH-20 column eluted with a mixture of methanol and 0.1% acetic acid. The copolymer band was collected, evaporated and precipitated into a mixture of acetone:ether (1:1). The characterization of copolymer precursors is shown in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><fig id="sch2" position="float"><label>Scheme 2</label><caption><title>Synthesis and Chemical Structure of HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub>/&#x02212;SOS Conjugates Containing Maleimide Group [P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-MAL and P-(GFLG-SOS)-MAL, Respectively]</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp-2008-00006e_0007" id="gs2" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title>Synthesis of HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;SOS Conjugate Containing Maleimide Groups, P-(GFLG-SOS)-MAL</title><p>This copolymer precursor was also prepared by three-step reaction. The procedure is shown in Scheme <xref rid="sch2" ref-type="scheme">2</xref>. First, MA-GFLG-ONp (278.6 mg, 0.480 mmol) and SOS (200 mg, 0.680 mmol) were dissolved in tetrahydrofuran (THF; &#x0223c;15 mL). DMAP (44.6 mg, 0.370 mmol) was added. The reaction mixture was stirred at room temperature in the dark for 72 h. The mixture was concentrated under reduced pressure. The residue was isolated using silica gel column chromatography. The excess free drug was recovered by elution with acetone:hexane (2:1), and the fractions were collected by eluting with acetone and then with methanol. The fractions were checked on TLC. The product-containing fraction was evaporated and recrystallized with THF/hexane. The <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> of MA-GFLG-SOS was 734.2 Da as determined by ESI-MS. The product yield was 130 mg (27%). Second, polymeric precursor, P-(GFLG-SOS)-NH<sub>2</sub>, was synthesized by copolymerization of HPMA (141.3 mg, 0.987 mmol), APMA (14.2 mg, 0.079 mmol), and MA-GFLG-SOS (50 mg, 0.068 mmol) in DMF (1 mL) and acetone (0.5 mL) at 50 &#x000b0;C for 48 h, using AIBN (19.7 mg) as the initiator. The molar ratio of HPMA:APMA:MA-GFLG-SOS was 87:7:6. The reaction mixture was purified on a Sephadex LH-20 column eluted with methanol. The polymer fraction was collected and evaporated to the viscous residue. The residue was precipitated into acetone:ether (1:1). The product yield was 150 mg (73%). Third, polymeric precursor P-(GFLG-SOS)-MAL was prepared by using the same procedure as for P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-MAL. P-(GFLG-SOS)-NH<sub>2</sub> (145 mg, 0.040 mmol NH<sub>2</sub> groups) and SMCC (26.41 mg, 0.079 mmol) were dissolved separately in DMF (&#x0223c;2.5 mL and &#x0223c;0.5 mL, respectively). DIPEA (&#x0223c;21 &#x003bc;L, 0.119 mmol) was used. The product was applied on a Sephadex LH-20 column and eluted with methanol without acetic acid. The product was precipitated and filtered off, with a yield of 130 mg (76%). The characterization of conjugates is shown in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><title>Preparation of Antibody Fab&#x02032; Fragment-Targeted HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub>/&#x02212;SOS Conjugates, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;</title><p>The targeted conjugates were prepared by dissolving P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-MAL or P-(GFLG-SOS)-MAL precursor in 20 mM MES buffer pH 6.5 and reacting with freshly prepared Fab&#x02032; fragment (polymer:Fab&#x02032; weight ratio = 1:2) overnight in the dark at 4 &#x000b0;C. The product was purified on a DEAE Sepharose Fast Flow ion exchange column (Pharmacia), eluted using 20 mM Bis-Tris buffer pH 6.5 with a gradient NaCl concentration of 0&#x02212;0.5 M. The fraction corresponding to conjugate was confirmed by size exclusion chromatography using Superose 6 (HR 10/30) column. The structure and composition of polymer conjugates are summarized in Scheme <xref rid="sch1" ref-type="scheme">1</xref>B and Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Characterization of Fab&#x02032;-Targeted HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub>/&#x02212;SOS Immunoconjugates</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">structures</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">wt %<break/>drug:polymer:Fab&#x02032;<xref rid="tbl2-fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></th><th style="border:none;" align="center">molecular ratio<break/>drug:polymer:Fab&#x02032;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">mol wt<break/>(kDa)<xref rid="tbl2-fn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">2.1:21.1:76.8</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">2:1:1</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">64</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">1.6:23.5:74.9</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">5:1:1</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">72</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2-fn1"><label>a</label><p>Mce<sub>6</sub> and SOS contents determined by UV spectrophotometry in methanol: &#x003b5;<sub>395</sub> = 158000 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for Mce<sub>6</sub>, &#x003b5;<sub>358</sub> = 33000 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for SOS. Protein content was determined by Lowry assay.</p></fn><fn id="tbl2-fn2"><label>b</label><p>Calculated from the composition of polymer (molecular ratio of drug, polymer, and Fab&#x02032;).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><title>Preparation of Fluorescein-Labeled Nontargeted HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub>/&#x02212;SOS Conjugates, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-FITC and P-(GFLG-SOS)-FITC</title><p>6-(Fluorescein-5-carboxamido)hexanoic acid succinimidyl ester (5-SFX; &#x0223c;0.1 mg, 0.170 &#x003bc;mol) was dissolved in dimethylsulfoxide (25 &#x003bc;L) and DI water (100 &#x003bc;L). The polymer precursor P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-NH<sub>2</sub> or P-(GFLG-SOS)-NH<sub>2</sub> (&#x0223c;3 mg, &#x0223c;1 &#x003bc;mol of NH<sub>2</sub>) was dissolved in DI water (&#x0223c;300 &#x003bc;L). The 5-SFX solution was added into the polymer solution. DIPEA (&#x0223c;1 drop) was added into the reaction solution while stirring. The mixture was stirred at room temperature in the dark for 1 h. Saturated Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> (&#x0223c;20 &#x003bc;L) was added to stop the reaction. The product was separated on a PD-10 column and eluted with PBS.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><title>Preparation of Fluorescein-Labeled Fab&#x02032;-Targeted HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub>/&#x02212;SOS Conjugates, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC) and P-(GFLG-SOS)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC)</title><p>P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; were reacted with 5-SFX. The procedure was as described for P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-FITC and P-(GFLG-SOS)-FITC. The characterization of fluorescently labeled copolymer conjugates is shown in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.12"><title>Drug Stock Solution Preparations</title><p>SOS was dissolved in PBS containing cyclodextrin (5% (w/v) cyclodextrin in PBS/1 mg of SOS) to enhance the solubility of SOS.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref>) P-GFLG-SOS, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;, and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; were prepared in PBS. Other samples (Mce<sub>6</sub> and P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>) were prepared in DI water. All stock solutions were sterile-filtered. Drug contents were determined by UV spectrophotometry. All stock solutions were freshly prepared and gradually diluted with RPMI 1640 culture medium before use.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.13"><title>Confocal Microscopy</title><p>Fifty thousand OVCAR-3 cells were subcultured into an eight-chamber slide and incubated for 2 days at 37 &#x000b0;C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. The cells in each chamber were exposed to fluorescein-labeled copolymer conjugates (at 20 &#x003bc;M FITC equivalent) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 1 h in the dark. Cells were fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde for 20 min at room temperature and washed twice with PBS. The chamber slide was covered with a cover slide utilizing antifade reagent (Molecular Probes). The cell internalization of fluorescently labeled HPMA copolymer conjugates was imaged using a Zeiss (Thornwood, NY) LSM 510 confocal imaging system.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.14"><title>Flow Cytometry</title><p>OVCAR-3 cells (75,000 cells/well) were seeded into a 24-well plate and incubated for 24 h at 37 &#x000b0;C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Cells in each well were exposed to the fluorescein-labeled copolymer conjugates (at 20 &#x003bc;M FITC equivalent) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 1 h in the dark. The medium was removed. The cell monolayer was rinsed twice with ice-cold PBS and detached from the well surface by incubation with TrypLE Express (Gibco) for 2 min. All steps were carried out on ice to minimize efflux of the sample. The cells were suspended with ice-cold PBS containing 0.2% FBS, maintained in suspension on ice in the dark and processed for flow cytometry utilizing FACScan instrument (Becton Dickinson). Twenty thousand events were collected per sample. Control cells were not exposed to the sample to assess the endogenous fluorescence of the cells.</p><p>Additional experiments were performed at 0 &#x000b0;C (on ice) to demonstrate the surface binding of targeted conjugates. OVCAR-3 cells, growth medium and the fluorescein-labeled conjugates (at 10 &#x003bc;M FITC equivalent) were precooled on ice before experiments. The cells were exposed to conjugates for 2 h, then the medium containing conjugates was discarded, and cells were washed extensively with cold PBS and processed for flow cytometry as described above.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.15"><title>Cytotoxicity Bioassays</title><p>The drug concentration that inhibited cell growth by 50% compared with control cells (IC<sub>50</sub>) was determined using a modified 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref>) Cells were seeded in 96-well flat bottom microplates at a density of 10,000 cells/well in 200 &#x003bc;L of RPMI 1640 medium and allowed to grow for &#x0223c;30 h. The cells were then exposed to various concentrations of each free drug alone (Mce<sub>6</sub> and SOS), each nontargeted copolymer conjugate (P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> and P-GFLG-SOS), each targeted copolymer conjugate [P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;], or their sequential combinations (<italic>n</italic> = 6 in single experiment). The different treatment protocols are shown in Scheme <xref rid="sch3" ref-type="scheme">3</xref>. During the cells&#x02019; exposure to drug(s), they were incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and in the dark condition. After 4 days of exposure for SOS and its conjugates or 1 day of exposure for Mce<sub>6</sub> and its conjugates, the drugs were removed, cells were washed with warm PBS and the medium (300 &#x003bc;L) was replaced. For cell growth inhibition studies using Mce<sub>6</sub>, P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>, or P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; (alone or in combinations), the cells were irradiated with three tungsten halogen lamps through a 650 nm band-pass filter at 3.0 mW/cm<sup>2</sup> for 30 min. After an additional 1 day or 4 days in culture for SOS and its conjugates or for Mce<sub>6</sub> and its conjugates, respectively, medium was removed and replaced with 100 &#x003bc;L of fresh medium and 10 &#x003bc;L of sterile-filtered MTT solution (5 mg/mL in PBS). After incubating for 24 h, 150 &#x003bc;L of 20% (w/v) sodium dodecyl sulfate in water was added to each well and incubated overnight. The following day, the absorbance of each well was read at 570 nm with a reference wavelength at 630 nm. Untreated cells served as a 100% cell viability control, and the media served as background reference. Growth inhibition was expressed as the growth of drug-treated cells related to that of untreated control cells.</p><fig id="sch3" position="float"><label>Scheme 3</label><caption><title>Experimental Protocols Used in the Cytotoxicity Study<xref rid="sch3-fn1"/></title><p id="sch3-fn1">(A) Cells were treated with single agents: different concentrations of Mce6, SOS, or their conjugates. (B) Cells were treated with sequential combinations of SOS or HPMA copolymer&#x02212;SOS conjugates, followed by treatment with Mce6 or HPMA copolymer&#x02212;Mce6 conjugates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp-2008-00006e_0008" id="gs3" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2.16"><title>Determination of Drug Interaction and Combination Index</title><p>In combination treatment studies, OVCAR-3 cells were treated with a dose range of SOS for 4 days followed by a dose range of Mce<sub>6</sub> for 1 day, and irradiated for 30 min (<italic>n</italic> = 6 in single experiment), as shown in Scheme <xref rid="sch3" ref-type="scheme">3</xref>. After each step the drug was removed and the cells were washed with warm PBS. Drug interaction and CI were determined using median-effect analysis according to the method of Chou and Talalay.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref></sup> The median-effect equation describes dose&#x02212;effect relationships, which is expressed by <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub>/<italic>f</italic><sub>u</sub> = (<italic>D</italic>/<italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic>)<italic><sup>m</sup></italic> or log(<italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub>/<italic>f<sub>u</sub>)</italic> = <italic>m</italic> log(<italic>D</italic>) &#x02212; <italic>m</italic> log(<italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic>) where <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> and <italic>f</italic><sub>u</sub> are the fraction affected [1 &#x02212; (absorbance of treatment well &#x02212; average of absorbance of blanks)/(average of absorbance of untreated cell wells &#x02212; average of absorbance of blanks)] and unaffected (<italic>f</italic><sub>u</sub> = 1 &#x02212; <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub>) by the dose or concentration <italic>D</italic>, <italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic> is the median-effect dose (IC<sub>50</sub>) that inhibits the cell growth by 50%, and <italic>m</italic> is the coefficient signifying the shape of the dose&#x02212;effect relationship. Based on the logarithmic conversion, the plot of <italic>x</italic> = log(<italic>D</italic>) versus <italic>y</italic> = log(<italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub>/<italic>f</italic><sub>u</sub>) is called the median-effect plot and <italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic> is calculated from the antilog of the <italic>x</italic>-intercept. The CI describes the interaction between two drugs and quantitates the synergism, antagonism or additive effects. The CI is determined by the equation CI = [(<italic>D</italic>)<sub>1</sub>/(<italic>D<sub>x</sub></italic>)<sub>1</sub>] + [(<italic>D</italic>)<sub>2</sub>/(<italic>D<sub>x</sub></italic>)<sub>2</sub>] where (<italic>D<sub>x</sub></italic>)<sub>1</sub> and (<italic>D<sub>x</sub></italic>)<sub>2</sub> are the doses of drug 1 alone and drug 2 alone that inhibit the cell growth <italic>x</italic>%, respectively. (<italic>D</italic>)<sub>1</sub> and (<italic>D</italic>)<sub>2</sub> are for doses in combination that also inhibit <italic>x</italic>%. The CI values were calculated for different values of <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> and plotting the CI values as a function of <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> values, using CompuSyn software (ComboSyn Inc., Paramus, NJ). In the <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub>&#x02212;CI plot, CI &#x0003c; 1, = 1, and &#x0003e; 1 indicate synergism, additivity, and antagonism, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.17"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All mean values are presented as means &#x000b1; standard deviation (<italic>n</italic> = 6 in a single experiment).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Characteristics of HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub>/&#x02212;SOS Conjugates</title><p>The structures of HPMA copolymer conjugates, P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>, P-GFLG-SOS, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;, and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;, are shown in Scheme <xref rid="sch1" ref-type="scheme">1</xref>. The drugs, Mce<sub>6</sub> and SOS, were bound to the HPMA copolymer backbone via a GFLG spacer, stable in the bloodstream, but susceptible to enzymatically catalyzed hydrolysis in the lysosomal compartment of the cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref></sup> For Fab&#x02032; attachment, the amino groups of APMA monomer units in HPMA copolymer precursors were first converted to maleimido groups by reaction with a heterobifunctional agent, SMCC (Scheme <xref rid="sch2" ref-type="scheme">2</xref>), followed by attachment of Fab&#x02032; via thioether bonds. For some experiments, fluorescently labeled conjugates were synthesized. In nontargeted conjugates, the 5-SFX was attached to amino groups of APMA monomer units. The Fab&#x02032;-targeted conjugates were labeled by the reaction of 5-SFX with the final conjugates.</p><p>The characteristics of HPMA copolymer precursors, nontargeted HPMA copolymer conjugates, Fab&#x02032;-targeted HPMA copolymer conjugates, and fluorescently labeled conjugates are summarized in Tables <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>, P-GFLG-SOS, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;, and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; conjugates contained 2.9, 3.4, 2.0, and 5.0 drug molecules per macromolecule, respectively. P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; had drug:polymer:Fab&#x02032; molecular ratios of approximately 2:1:1 and 5:1:1, respectively. The <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> of Fab&#x02032;-targeted copolymer conjugates were 2.2 to 2.8 times higher than those of nontargeted conjugates.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Intracellular Uptake of Fluorescein-Labeled Fab&#x02032;-Targeted HPMA Copolymer Conjugates</title><p>Unlike low molecular weight drugs that enter cells by diffusion through the plasma membrane, macromolecules are internalized within membrane-limited vesicles in the process of endocytosis. Several basic internalization mechanisms, clathrin-mediated endocytosis, caveolae-mediated endocytosis, clathrin- and caveolin-independent endocytosis, and macropinocytosis have been identified.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref></sup> To a greater or lesser extent, two or more distinct mechanisms coexist when a single cell type internalizes macromolecule&#x02212;drug conjugates.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>)</p><p>Studies on the subcellular fate of HPMA copolymer&#x02212;drug conjugates demonstrated that the conjugates are lysosomotropic and will accumulate in the lysosomal compartment of the cell. Tijerina et al., using subcellular fractionation, determined the localization of a considerable fraction of HPMA copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub> conjugates in the lysosomal compartment of human ovarian carcinoma A2780 cells.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>) Omelyanenko et al. used pH dependent fluorescence of FITC to display the lysosomotropism of FITC-labeled HPMA copolymers containing <italic>N</italic>-acylated galactosamine in HepG2 hepatocarcinoma cells.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref>)</p><p>Recently, the uptake mechanism of HPMA copolymer&#x02212;DOX conjugate in human ovarian carcinoma OVCAR-3 cells was studied by confocal fluorescence microscopy and by colocalization experiments with substrates specific for a particular internalization mechanism. The results suggested that the HPMA copolymer&#x02212;DOX conjugate is internalized via both clathrin- and caveolae-mediated endocytosis.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>)</p><p>The biorecognition and cellular uptake of P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC) and P-(GFLG-SOS)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC) was studied using confocal microscopy (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and flow cytometry (Figures <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Nontargeted conjugates, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-FITC and P-(GFLG-SOS)-FITC, served as controls. After a 1 h exposure of OVCAR-3 cells to HPMA copolymer conjugates at 37 &#x000b0;C, the intracellular concentrations of targeted polymer conjugates containing Mce<sub>6</sub> and SOS were significantly higher when compared to nontargeted conjugates. Both confocal microscopy images and flow cytometry profiles displayed very similar results.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Confocal image of fixed OVCAR-3 cells incubated with fluorescein-labeled HPMA copolymer conjugates in RPMI 1640 culture medium for 1 h in the dark. (A) P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-FITC, (B) P-(GFLG-SOS)-FITC, (C) P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC), and (D) P-(GFLG-SOS)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp-2008-00006e_0001" id="gr5" position="float"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Flow cytometry profiles of OVCAR-3 cells incubated with fluorescein-labeled HPMA copolymer conjugates in RPMI 1640 culture medium for 1 h in the dark. (A) Control cells, (B) P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-FITC, (C) P-(GFLG-SOS)-FITC, (D) P-(GFLG-SOS)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC), (E) P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp-2008-00006e_0002" id="gr6" position="float"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Flow cytometry profiles of OVCAR-3 cells incubated with fluorescein-labeled HPMA copolymer conjugates in RPMI 1640 culture medium for 2 h in the dark at 0 &#x000b0;C. (A) Control cells, (B) P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-FITC, (C) P-(GFLG-SOS)-FITC, (D) P-(GFLG-SOS)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC), (E) P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-(Fab&#x02032;-FITC).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp-2008-00006e_0003" id="gr7" position="float"/></fig><p>However, at 37 &#x000b0;C two processes, biorecognition at surface and internalization by endocytosis, are operative. To clearly demonstrate the biorecognition of targeted conjugates by the CD47 antigen, OVCAR-3 cells were exposed to conjugates at 0 &#x000b0;C. Flow cytometry data at 0 &#x000b0;C, at conditions that suppress endocytosis, demonstrated the biorecognition of P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; conjugates by OVCAR-3 cells (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). After incubation of OVCAR-3 cells with targeted and nontargeted conjugates for 2 h, no increase in fluorescent intensity (when compared to controls not exposed to any conjugates) in cells incubated with P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> and P-GFLG-SOS was observed. In contrast, higher fluorescent intensities were detected in cells incubated with targeted (Fab&#x02032; containing) conjugates P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;. Presumably, the fluorescent signals were derived from membrane associated conjugates as a result of Fab&#x02032;&#x02212;CD47 interactions.</p><p>These results indicated the biorecognition of HPMA copolymer conjugates containing the Fab&#x02032; antibody fragment by OVCAR-3 cells. The results of confocal microscopy are consistent with the internalization of targeted HPMA copolymer conjugates via receptor-mediated endocytosis, and of the nontargeted conjugates, containing hydrophobic drugs, by fluid-phase pinocytosis and adsorptive pinocytosis, concurrently.</p><p>The data are consistent with our previous results on the determination of binding constants of OV-TL16 antibody targeted HPMA copolymers toward OVCAR-3 cells.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref>) The affinity constant, <italic>K</italic><sub>a</sub>, of free antibody was 8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, whereas the <italic>K</italic><sub>a</sub> for the P-(GG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; was 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The minor decrease in the affinity may be a result of chemical modification and/or steric hindrance of the polymer chain upon the formation of the antibody&#x02212;antigen complex.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><italic>In Vitro</italic> Inhibition of OVCAR-3 Cell Growth by Drugs as Single Agents</title><p>The growth inhibitory effects of Mce<sub>6</sub>, SOS, P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>, P-GFLG-SOS, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;, and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; as single agents on OVCAR-3 cells were evaluated after drug exposure using the MTT assay. The IC<sub>50</sub> values for the free drugs, nontargeted and targeted HPMA copolymer conjugates are shown in Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. The 1-day Mce<sub>6</sub> exposure and 4-day SOS exposure have been selected based on preliminary experiments on the relationship between exposure time and cell inhibition effect (data not shown). After 1-day Mce<sub>6</sub> exposure and 4-day SOS exposure, the cells were more susceptible to Mce<sub>6</sub> than SOS about 2 times. It is interesting to note the enormous difference in the activity of SOS toward OVCAR-3 cells and toward the human A498 renal cell line.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>) Our previous study on human renal A498 cells demonstrated that free SOS and P-GFLG-SOS conjugates were effective individually and in combination with free DOX and P-GFLG-DOX or free Mce<sub>6</sub> and P-GFLG- Mce<sub>6</sub>, respectively.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>) The IC<sub>50</sub> values for Mce<sub>6</sub> toward both cell types (OVCAR-3 and A498(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>)) were similar. However, SOS was very effective toward A498 cells (IC<sub>50</sub> = 3 nM),(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>) but its activity toward OVCAR-3 was about 670 times lower. These data are consistent with the results of the NCI anticancer drug screen consisting of a panel of 60 human cancer cell lines. Rivera et al. showed that after a 2-day continuous exposure to SOS, OVCAR-3 cells were less sensitive to SOS than the A498 cells.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref>) These results reflect the different p53 status in these cell lines. The inhibitory effect of SOS is mediated through p53; the disruption of the p53-HDM-2 interactions results in increasing p53 accumulation in tumor cells.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>) It was demonstrated that the p53 status of A498 cells and OVCAR-3 cells is wild-type and mutant, respectively.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref>) However, the study of the p53 gene in human ovarian carcinoma cell lines by Yaginuma and Westphal showed that the wild-type p53 protein was detectable in OVCAR-3 cells by immunoprecipitation analysis.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref>) These reports indicated that OVCAR-3 cells can be inhibited by higher concentrations of SOS, but have a considerably lower sensitivity when compared to the A498 cell line.</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>IC<sub>50</sub> Values for Mce<sub>6</sub>, SOS, and HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub>/&#x02212;SOS Conjugates against OVCAR-3 Cells</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">drug</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">incubation<break/>time (days)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">IC<sub>50</sub> or <italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic><break/> (&#x003bc;M)<xref rid="tbl3-fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">Mce<sub>6</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">1</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">3.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.43</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">1</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">12.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.06</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">1</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">1.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">SOS</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">4</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">2.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-GFLG-SOS</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">4</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">32.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.94</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">4</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" valign="top" char=".">43.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.90</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl3-fn1"><label>a</label><p><italic>D</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> is the median-effect dose that inhibits the cell growth by 50%. IC<sub>50</sub> and <italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic> values are the means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 6 in single experiment).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The IC<sub>50</sub> doses of nontargeted conjugates, P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> and P-GFLG-SOS, were higher than those of free Mce<sub>6</sub> and SOS, respectively. These results reflect the different mechanisms of cell entry of free drugs vs copolymer conjugates.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61">61</xref>) In contrast, the targeted P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; conjugate was 2 and 9 times more effective than Mce<sub>6</sub> and P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>, respectively. The cytotoxicity data with Mce<sub>6</sub> conjugates were in agreement with biorecognition data and internalization mechanisms (Figures <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). There was a discrepancy in data obtained for P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;. This conjugate showed faster internalization (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and moderately better biorecognition (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) than P-GFLG-SOS; however, it possessed a slightly weaker inhibitory effect than P-GFLG-SOS (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). One explanation may be in the long drug exposure time. After long exposure times the intracellular drug content of targeted and nontargeted conjugates may be similar.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref62">62</xref>) Furthermore, the efficacies of SOS and its conjugates might be limited by the problem of SOS trafficking to the subcellular compartments where p53 is mainly located, such as nucleus and mitochondria.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref63">63</xref>) Subcellular targeting is very important for some active agents and macromolecular therapeutics that have to be transported to their assigned cell organelles. Once those molecules are delivered to the cytosol, various approaches to locate drugs in a particular subcellular organelle have been performed, such as the use of nuclear localization peptides,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref64">64</xref></sup> cell-penetrating peptides,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref65">65</xref>) lipophilic cationic moieties,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>) and mitochondrial localization agents.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref66">66</xref>)</p><p>The OA-3 surface antigen (CD47 or IAP) was chosen as delivery target in this study because it is overexpressed in about 90% of the ovarian tumors and only weakly expressed in normal tissue.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>) A panel of anti-CD47 mAbs used in the study of Mawby et al., such as NBTS/BRIC-125 (BRIC-125), NBTS/BRIC-126 (BRIC-126) and NBTS/BRIC-154 (BRIC-154), showed an extremely broad tissue distribution, not only in ovarian carcinomas studied, but also in all hematopoietic cells, mesenchyme and epithelia at multiple sites.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>) On the contrary, the tissue distribution of <sup>125</sup>I-labeled OV-TL16 mAb in OVCAR-3 bearing nude mice 48 h after iv injection studied by Boerman et al. demonstrated that <sup>125</sup>I-labeled OV-TL16 mAb possessed tumor/nontumor ratio of about 3&#x02212;15.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>) Furthermore, the mAb OV-TL3 used by Campbell et al. to define OA3 showed little or no reactivity with normal tissues but reacted with most ovarian carcinomas.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref>) Slobbe et al. studied the structure of OV-TL3 and OV-TL16 antibodies and reported that both mAbs are able to bind to same epitopic regions on the ovarian carcinoma membrane antigen OA3, although structurally different in their VH regions.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref67">67</xref>)</p><p>The basis for the difference between mAbs used in the study of Mawby et al. and Boerman et al. or Campbell et al. is unknown and deserves further investigation. One possibility is that an unusual amino acid sequence in the OA3 isoforms is expressed in ovarian cancer cells, and that OV-TL3 and OV-TL16 recognize epitopes in this sequence.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>)</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title><italic>In Vitro</italic> Inhibition of OVCAR-3 Cell Growth with Drug Combinations</title><p>The investigation of possible synergistic, additive, or antagonistic effects of sequential combinations of SOS+Mce<sub>6</sub>, P-GFLG-SOS+P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>, or P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;+P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; against the ovarian carcinoma OVCAR-3 cell line was performed <italic>in vitro</italic> by exposing cells to SOS or its conjugates for 4 days, followed by exposure of cells to Mce<sub>6</sub> or its conjugates for 1 day, and finally, a 30 min irradiation. This sequential combination was chosen because the optimal exposure times of SOS/P-GFLG-SOS/P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; and Mce<sub>6</sub>/P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>/P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; were different (4 days for SOS and 1 day for Mce<sub>6</sub>), as mentioned above. The dose ratios of each combination (Table <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref>) were based on their respective IC<sub>50</sub> concentrations from Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref> as a series of 2-fold dilutions from 4 to 0.03125 times IC<sub>50</sub>. Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the composite dose&#x02212;response curves and median-effect plots of OVCAR-3 cells, indicating the antiproliferative effects of single agents and their combinations. The dose&#x02212;response curves for combined treatment were obtained by plotting % cell viability (<italic>y</italic>) vs the combined dose of two single agents (<italic>x</italic>). The median-effect plots of single agents and combinations were derived from the linear part of dose&#x02212;response curves. All of the combination treatments showed antiproliferative activities toward OVCAR-3 cells. The dose ratio and <italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic> values of the combination treatments are shown in Table <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. The IC<sub>50</sub> dose of each drug in combinations was significantly lower than those of each drug as single agents (compare Tables <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). These results clearly indicate that all of the combination treatments were effective against OVCAR-3 cells.</p><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Dose Ratios and IC<sub>50</sub> Doses in Combinations of Free Drugs (SOS+Mce<sub>6</sub>), Nontargeted Copolymer Conjugates (P-GFLG-SOS+P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>), and Targeted Copolymer Conjugates [P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;+P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;] in OVCAR-3 Cells</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="2" align="center">drug combination<hr/></th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th></tr><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center" valign="bottom">drug A</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" valign="bottom">drug B</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">dose ratio</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic> (&#x003bc;M)<xref rid="tbl4-fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref><break/>(dose A + dose B)<xref rid="tbl4-fn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">SOS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">Mce<sub>6</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">1:1.61</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">0.096&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0077</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">(0.037 + 0.059)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-GFLG-SOS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">1:0.38</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">1.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">(1.22 + 0.47)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">1:0.031</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">1.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.38</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left" valign="top">(1.65 + 0.051)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl4-fn1"><label>a</label><p><italic>D</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> values are the means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 6 in single experiment).</p></fn><fn id="tbl4-fn2"><label>b</label><p>Doses of drug A and drug B were calculated approximately from the <italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic> of each combination and dose ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Dose response curves and median-effect plots of OVCAR-3 cells treated with Mce<sub>6</sub>, SOS, P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>, P-GFLG-SOS, P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;, and P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032; as single agents and sequential combinations at constant ratios of their respective IC<sub>50</sub> concentrations. Bars represent standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 6 in single experiment).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp-2008-00006e_0004" id="gr8" position="float"/></fig><p>The CI analysis was used to assess the drug&#x02212;drug interaction of the sequential combinations of free drugs, nontargeted and targeted copolymer conjugates toward OVCAR-3 cells <italic>in vitro</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref></sup> In the CI analysis, values of CI &#x0003c; 1, CI = 1, and CI &#x0003e; 1 indicate synergy, additivity, and antagonism, respectively. Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> shows the combination index plots (<italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub>&#x02212;CI plots) over all inhibition effect levels (<italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> = 0.05&#x02212;0.95 or 5&#x02212;95% of inhibition effect) in OVCAR-3 cells. The sequential combinations of SOS+Mce<sub>6</sub> and P-GFLG-SOS+P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> yield CI values lower than 1 over the entire range of cytotoxicity, indicating very strong synergistic to synergistic effects. The P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;+P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032; combination also displayed a strong synergism for <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> values up to about 0.85, but showed synergistic effect and nearly additive effect at <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> = 0.9 and 0.95, respectively.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Combination index plots (<italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub>&#x02212;CI plots) obtained from median-effect analysis. Chemotherapeutic drugs and their HPMA copolymer conjugates were gradually diluted at the ratio of their IC<sub>50</sub> values as a series of 2-fold dilutions from 4 to 0.03125 times IC<sub>50</sub> and OVCAR-3 cells exposed to drugs sequentially as described in <xref rid="sec2"/>. CI &#x0003c; 1, = 1 and &#x0003e; 1 indicate synergism, additive effect, and antagonism, respectively. The vertical bars indicate the 95% confidence intervals based on sequential deletion analysis (SDA) and can be generated by using CompuSyn software.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp-2008-00006e_0005" id="gr9" position="float"/></fig><p>The drug interactions may depend on the differences of drugs in the combination, such as physicochemical properties, the mechanisms of action, and the drug exposure schedules. All these differences may result in different antitumor activities. SOS and Mce<sub>6</sub> are hydrophobic low molecular weight molecules, but both have different mechanisms and sites of action. SOS acts on p53 and DNA while Mce<sub>6</sub> can cause damage to biological molecules by generation of reactive oxygen species. In our previous study, we compared the simultaneous combination of P-GFLG-SOS+P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> to SOS+Mce<sub>6</sub> against the human renal A498 carcinoma cell line. After 16 h cell exposure to the combinations, both combinations displayed synergism for <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> up to 0.8, but showed slight antagonism and near additivity at <italic>f</italic><sub>a</sub> = 0.95.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>) Many researchers have studied the antitumor activities following different drug exposure schedules. For example, the simultaneous and sequential exposures of irofulven with oxaliplatin or cisplatin against human breast, colon, and ovarian cancer cell lines showed that the sequence oxaliplatin followed by irofulven displayed better synergistic effect than the other schedules.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref>)</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Combination chemotherapy and PDT with free SOS and Mce<sub>6</sub>, their nontargeted and Fab&#x02032;-targeted HPMA copolymer conjugates in human ovarian carcinoma OVCAR-3 cells was evaluated. Sequential combinations of these therapeutics produced very strong synergism to nearly additivity in the treatment of OVCAR-3 cells. The synergistic effects ranked in the order P-GFLG-SOS+P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub> &#x0003e; SOS+Mce<sub>6</sub> &#x0003e; P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;+P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;. These data support continued <italic>in vivo</italic> investigations of SOS and Mce<sub>6</sub> combinations to determine the antitumor activity for the treatment of ovarian cancer.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Abbreviations Used</title><p>AIBN, 2,2&#x02032;-azobisisobutyronitrile; APMA, <italic>N</italic>-(3-aminopropyl)methacrylamide hydrochloride; CI, combination index; <italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic>, median-effect dose; DI, deionized; DIPEA, <italic>N,N&#x02032;</italic>-diisopropylethylamine; DMAP, 4-dimethylaminopyridine; DMF, <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylformamide; DOX, doxorubicin; EPR, enhanced permeability and retention; GFLG, glycylphenylalanylleucylglycine; HPMA, <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide; IC<sub>50</sub>, concentration that inhibited cell growth by 50% as compared with control cell growth; MA, methacryloyl; mAb, monoclonal antibody; <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub>, weight average molecular weight; Mce<sub>6</sub>, mesochlorin e<sub>6</sub> monoethylenediamine disodium salt; MTT assay, modified 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide assay; ONp, <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenoxy; P, HPMA copolymer backbone; PDT, photodynamic therapy; P-GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>, HPMA copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub> conjugate; P-(GFLG-Mce<sub>6</sub>)-Fab&#x02032;, antibody Fab&#x02032; fragment targeted HPMA copolymer&#x02212;Mce<sub>6</sub> conjugate; P-GFLG-ONp, HPMA copolymer precursor containing reactive <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenyl ester groups at side chain termini; P-GFLG-SOS, HPMA copolymer&#x02212;SOS conjugate; P-(GFLG-SOS)-Fab&#x02032;, antibody Fab&#x02032; fragment targeted HPMA copolymer&#x02212;SOS conjugate; 5-SFX, 6-(fluorescein-5-carboxamido)hexanoic acid succinimidyl ester; SMCC, succinimidyl <italic>trans</italic>-4-(maleimidomethyl)cyclohexane-1-carboxylate; SOS, 2,5-bis(5-hydroxymethyl-2-thienyl)furan; THF, tetrahydrofuran.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank the Drug Synthesis and Chemistry Branch of National Cancer Institute for supplying SOS. The research was supported in part by the NIH grant CA51578 from the National Cancer Institute, and by the Thailand Research Fund (TRF) through the Royal Golden Jubilee Ph.D. Program (Grant No. PHD/0176/2545).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation id="cit1" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> <article-title>Conjugates of anticancer agents and polymers: advantages of macromolecular therapeutics in vivo</article-title>. <source>Bioconjugate Chem.</source> <year>1992</year>, <volume>3</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), 351&#x02013;362.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation id="cit2" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Breunig</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Goepferich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> <article-title>Polymers and nanoparticles: intelligent tools for intracellular targeting?</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Pharm. Biopharm.</source> <year>2008</year>, <volume>68</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 112&#x02013;128.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17804211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation id="cit3" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> <article-title>Polymer conjugates as anticancer nanomedicines</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>6</volume> (<issue>9</issue>), 688&#x02013;701.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16900224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation id="cit4" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kiick</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name> <article-title>Materials science. Polymer therapeutics</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <year>2007</year>, <volume>317</volume> (<issue>5842</issue>), 1182&#x02013;1183.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17761873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation id="cit5" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Minko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> <article-title>HPMA copolymer-anticancer drug conjugates: design, activity, and mechanism of action</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Pharm. Biopharm.</source> <year>2000</year>, <volume>50</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 61&#x02013;81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10840193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation id="cit6" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Soluble biomedical polymers</article-title>. <source>Polim. Med.</source> <year>1977</year>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), 191&#x02013;221.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">593972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation id="cit7" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khandare</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Minko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> <article-title>Polymer&#x02212;drug conjugates: Progress in polymeric prodrugs</article-title>. <source>Prog. Polym. Sci.</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>31</volume>, 359&#x02013;397.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation id="cit8" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Polymer Conjugates with Anticancer Activity</article-title>. <source>Adv. Polym. Sci.</source> <year>1995</year>, <volume>122</volume>, 55&#x02013;123.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation id="cit9" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> <article-title>The dawning era of polymer therapeutics</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discovery</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>2</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), 347&#x02013;360.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit10"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Cuchelkar</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> Polymer&#x02212;Drug Conjugates. In <source>Polymers in Drug Delivery</source>; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Uchegbu</surname><given-names>I. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;tzlein</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, Eds.; <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>, <year>2006</year>; pp <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02212;<lpage>182</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit11"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> Multifunctional Water-Soluble Polymers for Drug Delivery. In <source>Multifunctional Pharmaceutical Nanocarriers</source>; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Torchilin</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, Ed.; <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <year>2008</year>; pp <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02212;<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation id="cit12" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Strohalm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Effect of molecular weight (Mw) of <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide copolymers on body distribution and rate of excretion after subcutaneous, intraperitoneal, and intravenous administration to rats</article-title>. <source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res.</source> <year>1987</year>, <volume>21</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), 1341&#x02013;1358.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3680316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation id="cit13" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ulbrich</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Strohalm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> <article-title>The pharmacokinetics of polymer-bound adriamycin</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Pharmacol.</source> <year>1990</year>, <volume>39</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), 1125&#x02013;1131.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2322298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation id="cit14" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>&#x00158;&#x000ed;hov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Strohalm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rossmann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>V&#x0011b;tvi&#x0010d;ka</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Antibody-directed affinity therapy applied to the immune system: in vivo effectiveness and limited toxicity of daunomycin conjugated to HPMA copolymers and targeting antibody</article-title>. <source>Clin. Immunol. Immunopathol.</source> <year>1988</year>, <volume>46</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 100&#x02013;114.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2891460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation id="cit15" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guo-Shiah</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Z. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Straight</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Cooperativity between free and <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide copolymer bound adriamycin and meso-chlorin e<sub>6</sub> monoethylene diamine induced photodynamic therapy in human epithelial ovarian carcinoma in vitro</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Oncol.</source> <year>1999</year>, <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 5&#x02013;16.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10375588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation id="cit16" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shiah</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dvo&#x00159;&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Biodistribution and antitumour efficacy of long-circulating <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide copolymer-doxorubicin conjugates in nude mice</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Cancer</source> <year>2001</year>, <volume>37</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 131&#x02013;139.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11165140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation id="cit17" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shiah</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Straight</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Combination chemotherapy and photodynamic therapy of targetable <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide copolymer-doxorubicin/mesochlorin e<sub>6</sub> - OV-TL 16 antibody immunoconjugates</article-title>. <source>J. Controlled Release</source> <year>2001</year>, <volume>74</volume> (<issue>1&#x02212;3</issue>), 249&#x02013;253.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation id="cit18" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Minko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Chronic exposure to HPMA copolymer-bound adriamycin does not induce multidrug resistance in a human ovarian carcinoma cell line</article-title>. <source>J. Controlled Release</source> <year>1999</year>, <volume>59</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), 133&#x02013;148.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation id="cit19" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Minko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Efficacy of the chemotherapeutic action of HPMA copolymer-bound doxorubicin in a solid tumor model of ovarian carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Cancer</source> <year>2000</year>, <volume>86</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 108&#x02013;117.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10728603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation id="cit20" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Minko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pozharov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>HPMA copolymer bound adriamycin overcomes MDR1 gene encoded resistance in a human ovarian carcinoma cell line</article-title>. <source>J. Controlled Release</source> <year>1998</year>, <volume>54</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), 223&#x02013;233.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation id="cit21" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vicent</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Penning</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> <article-title>HPMA copolymer-aminoglutethimide conjugates inhibit aromatase in MCF-7 cell lines</article-title>. <source>J. Drug Targeting</source> <year>2005</year>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>8&#x02212;9</issue>), 459&#x02013;470.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation id="cit22" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vicent</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> <article-title>Polymer therapeutics designed for a combination therapy of hormone-dependent cancer</article-title>. <source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source> <year>2005</year>, <volume>44</volume> (<issue>26</issue>), 4061&#x02013;4066.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation id="cit23" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name> <article-title>Ligand-targeted therapeutics in anticancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source> <year>2002</year>, <volume>2</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), 750&#x02013;763.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12360278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation id="cit24" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name> <article-title>PEGylated antibodies and antibody fragments for improved therapy: a review</article-title>. <source>Adv. Drug Delivery Rev.</source> <year>2002</year>, <volume>54</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), 531&#x02013;545.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation id="cit25" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Polymerizable Fab&#x02032; antibody fragments for targeting of anticancer drugs</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source> <year>1999</year>, <volume>17</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), 1101&#x02013;1104.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10545917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation id="cit26" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shiah</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sakuma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Design of novel bioconjugates for targeted drug delivery</article-title>. <source>J. Controlled Release</source> <year>2002</year>, <volume>78</volume> (<issue>1&#x02212;3</issue>), 165&#x02013;173.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="patent" id="cit27"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Krinick</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug delivery system for the simultaneous delivery of drugs activatable by enzymes and light</article-title>. U.S. Patent <patent>5,258,453</patent><comment>(Nov. 2, 1993</comment>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation id="cit28" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krinick</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Joyner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Spikes</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Straight</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>A polymeric drug delivery system for the simultaneous delivery of drugs activatable by enzymes and/or light</article-title>. <source>J. Biomater. Sci. Polym. Ed.</source> <year>1994</year>, <volume>5</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), 303&#x02013;324.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8025029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation id="cit29" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shiah</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Straight</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Combination chemotherapy and photodynamic therapy with <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide copolymer-bound anticancer drugs inhibit human ovarian carcinoma heterotransplanted in nude mice</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source> <year>1996</year>, <volume>56</volume> (<issue>17</issue>), 3980&#x02013;3985.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8752167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation id="cit30" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shiah</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Straight</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Antitumor activity of <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide copolymer-mesochlorin e<sub>6</sub> and adriamycin conjugates in combination treatments</article-title>. <source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source> <year>2000</year>, <volume>6</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), 1008&#x02013;1015.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10741728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation id="cit31" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hongrapipat</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Prakongpan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Enhanced antitumor activity of combinations of free and HPMA copolymer-bound drugs</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Pharm.</source> <year>2008</year>, <volume>351</volume>, 259&#x02013;270.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18029122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation id="cit32" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name> <article-title>Small-molecule inhibitors of the p53 suppressor HDM2: have protein-protein interactions come of age as drug targets</article-title>. <source>Trends Pharmacol. Sci.</source> <year>2004</year>, <volume>25</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), 343&#x02013;346.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15219971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation id="cit33" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Issaeva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bozko</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Enge</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Protopopova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Masucci</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pramanik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Selivanova</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> <article-title>Small molecule RITA binds to p53, blocks p53-HDM-2 interaction and activates p53 function in tumors</article-title>. <source>Nat. Med.</source> <year>2004</year>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), 1321&#x02013;1328.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15558054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation id="cit34" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nieves-Neira</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kohlhagen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hursey</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pourquier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sausville</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pommier</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> <article-title>DNA protein cross-links produced by NSC 652287, a novel thiophene derivative active against human renal cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Mol. Pharmacol.</source> <year>1999</year>, <volume>56</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), 478&#x02013;484.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10462535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation id="cit35" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vistica</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jorden</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kenney</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sausville</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name> <article-title>Selective toxicity of the tricyclic thiophene NSC 652287 in renal carcinoma cell lines: differential accumulation and metabolism</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Pharmacol.</source> <year>1999</year>, <volume>57</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), 1283&#x02013;1295.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10230772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation id="cit36" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> <article-title>Photodynamic therapy: a clinical reality in the treatment of cancer</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol.</source> <year>2000</year>, <volume>1</volume>, 212&#x02013;219.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11905638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation id="cit37" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>K. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Westhoff</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Discher</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name> <article-title>Fractional attachment of CD47 (IAP) to the erythrocyte cytoskeleton and visual colocalization with Rh protein complexes</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>101</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), 1194&#x02013;1199.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12393442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation id="cit38" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mawby</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Anstee</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Spring</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Isolation and characterization of CD47 glycoprotein: a multispanning membrane protein which is the same as integrin-associated protein (IAP) and the ovarian tumour marker OA3</article-title>. <source>Biochem. J.</source> <year>1994</year>, <volume>304</volume> (<issue>Pt 2</issue>), 525&#x02013;530.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7998989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation id="cit39" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boerman</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Massuger</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Makkink</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kenemans</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Poels</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> <article-title>Comparative in vitro binding characteristics and biodistribution in tumor-bearing athymic mice of anti-ovarian carcinoma monoclonal antibodies</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res.</source> <year>1990</year>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>5A</issue>), 1289&#x02013;1295.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2241105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation id="cit40" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>I. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Freemont</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Foulkes</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Trowsdale</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>An ovarian tumor marker with homology to vaccinia virus contains an IgV-like region and multiple transmembrane domains</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source> <year>1992</year>, <volume>52</volume> (<issue>19</issue>), 5416&#x02013;5420.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1394148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation id="cit41" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name> <article-title>Theoretical basis, experimental design, and computerized simulation of synergism and antagonism in drug combination studies</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol. Rev.</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>58</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), 621&#x02013;681.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation id="cit42" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Talalay</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> <article-title>Quantitative analysis of dose-effect relationships: the combined effects of multiple drugs or enzyme inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Adv. Enzyme Regul.</source> <year>1984</year>, <volume>22</volume>, 27&#x02013;55.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6382953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation id="cit43" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wientjes</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Au</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name> <article-title>Evaluation of combination chemotherapy: integration of nonlinear regression, curve shift, isobologram, and combination index analyses</article-title>. <source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source> <year>2004</year>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>23</issue>), 7994&#x02013;8004.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15585635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation id="cit44" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z. R.</given-names></name> <article-title>Polymerizable Fab&#x02032; antibody fragment targeted photodynamic cancer therapy in nude mice</article-title>. <source>S.T.P. Pharma Sci.</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 69&#x02013;75.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="patent" id="cit45"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rejmanov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Strohalm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ulbrich</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>&#x00158;&#x000ed;hov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chytr&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthetic polymeric drugs</article-title>. U.S. <patent>5,037,883</patent><comment>(Aug. 6, 1991)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation id="cit46" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ulbrich</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>&#x00160;ubr</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Strohalm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Plocov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jel&#x000ed;nkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>&#x00158;&#x000ed;hov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> <article-title>Polymeric drugs based on conjugates of synthetic and natural macromolecules. I. Synthesis and physico-chemical characterisation</article-title>. <source>J. Controlled Release</source> <year>2000</year>, <volume>64</volume> (<issue>1&#x02212;3</issue>), 63&#x02013;79.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><mixed-citation id="cit47" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ba&#x0017e;ilov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> <article-title>Poly[<italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide]. I. Radical polymerization and copolymerization</article-title>. <source>Eur. Polym. J.</source> <year>1973</year>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 7&#x02013;14.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit48"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Alley</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hollingshead</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dykes</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Waud</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name></person-group> Human tumor xenograft models in NCI drug development. In <source>Anticancer Drug Development Guide: Preclinical Screening, Clinical Trials, and Approval</source>, <edition>2nd</edition> ed.; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Teicher</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>P. A</given-names></name></person-group>, Eds.; <publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Totowa, NJ</publisher-loc>, <year>2004</year>; pp <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02212;<lpage>152</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><mixed-citation id="cit49" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> <article-title>Re-examination and further development of a precise and rapid dye method for measuring cell growth/cell kill</article-title>. <source>J. Immunol. Methods</source> <year>1989</year>, <volume>119</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), 203&#x02013;210.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2470825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><mixed-citation id="cit50" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Controlled biodegradability of polymers&#x02014;a key to drug delivery systems</article-title>. <source>Biomaterials</source> <year>1984</year>, <volume>5</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 19&#x02013;25.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6375745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit51"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rejmanov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> Enzymatically Degradable Bonds in Synthetic Polymers. In <source>Controlled Drug Delivery</source>; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bruck</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, Ed.; <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>, <year>1983</year>; pp <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02212;<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><mixed-citation id="cit52" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rejmanov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Baudy&#x00161;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kostka</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Polymers containing enzymatically degradable bonds. 8. Degradation of oligopeptide sequences in <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)methacrylamide copolymers by bovine spleen cathepsin B</article-title>. <source>Makromol. Chem.</source> <year>1983</year>, <volume>184</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), 2009&#x02013;2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><mixed-citation id="cit53" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name> <article-title>Clathrin-mediated endocytosis before fluorescent proteins</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 63&#x02013;68.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16365635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><mixed-citation id="cit54" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soldati</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schliwa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> <article-title>Powering membrane traffic in endocytosis and recycling</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), 897&#x02013;908.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17139330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit55"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> Internalization and Subcellular Fate of HPMA Copolymer&#x02212;Doxorubicin Conjugates; International Symposium on Polymer Therapeutics ISPT-07, Berlin, Germany, February 19&#x02212;21, 2007; Proceedings, p <fpage>49</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><mixed-citation id="cit56" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tijerina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Correlation of subcellular compartmentalization of HPMA copolymer-Mce<sub>6</sub> conjugates with therapeutic activity in human ovarian carcinoma cells</article-title>. <source>Pharm. Res.</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>20</volume>, 728&#x02013;737.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12751627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><mixed-citation id="cit57" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Omelyanenko</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Targetable HPMA copolymer-adriamycin conjugates. Recognition, internalization, and subcellular fate</article-title>. <source>J. Controlled Release</source> <year>1998</year>, <volume>53</volume> (<issue>1&#x02212;3</issue>), 25&#x02013;37.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><mixed-citation id="cit58" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Omelyanenko</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shiah</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>HPMA copolymer-anticancer drug-OV-TL16 antibody conjugates. 1. Influence of the method of synthesis on the binding affinity to OVCAR-3 ovarian carcinoma cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>J. Drug Targeting</source> <year>1996</year>, <volume>3</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), 357&#x02013;373.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><mixed-citation id="cit59" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jackman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mutoh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Scudiero</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Monks</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sausville</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Friend</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fornace</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>; <name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name> <article-title>Characterization of the p53 tumor suppressor pathway in cell lines of the National Cancer Institute anticancer drug screen and correlations with the growth-inhibitory potency of 123 anticancer agents</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source> <year>1997</year>, <volume>57</volume> (<issue>19</issue>), 4285&#x02013;4300.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9331090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><mixed-citation id="cit60" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yaginuma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> <article-title>Abnormal structure and expression of the p53 gene in human ovarian carcinoma cell lines</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source> <year>1992</year>, <volume>52</volume> (<issue>15</issue>), 4196&#x02013;4199.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1638534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><mixed-citation id="cit61" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rejmanov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name> <article-title>Pinocytic uptake and intracellular degradation of <italic>N</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)-methacrylamide copolymers. A potential drug delivery system</article-title>. <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source> <year>1981</year>, <volume>678</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 143&#x02013;150.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7306576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><mixed-citation id="cit62" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marecos</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Weissleder</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bogdanov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name> <article-title>Antibody-mediated versus nontargeted delivery in a human small cell lung carcinoma model</article-title>. <source>Bioconjugate Chem.</source> <year>1998</year>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), 184&#x02013;191.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><mixed-citation id="cit63" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shmueli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> <article-title>Regulation of p53 by Mdm2: fate is in the numbers</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source> <year>2004</year>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 4&#x02013;5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14731389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><mixed-citation id="cit64" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tijerina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Mechanisms of cytotoxicity in human ovarian carcinoma cells exposed to free Mce<sub>6</sub> or HPMA copolymer-Mce<sub>6</sub> conjugates</article-title>. <source>Photochem. Photobiol.</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>77</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), 645&#x02013;652.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12870851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><mixed-citation id="cit65" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nori</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tijerina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Tat-conjugated synthetic macromolecules facilitate cytoplasmic drug delivery to human ovarian carcinoma cells</article-title>. <source>Bioconjugate Chem.</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>14</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 44&#x02013;50.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><mixed-citation id="cit66" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kope&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Semitelechelic HPMA copolymers functionalized with triphenylphosphonium as drug carriers for membrane transduction and mitochondrial localization</article-title>. <source>Biomacromolecules</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), 2347&#x02013;2356.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16903681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><mixed-citation id="cit67" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slobbe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Poels</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>ten Dam</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Boerman</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nieland</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Leunissen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ramaekers</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Eys</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> <article-title>Analysis of idiotope structure of ovarian cancer antibodies: recognition of the same epitope by two monoclonal antibodies differing mainly in their heavy chain variable sequences</article-title>. <source>Clin. Exp. Immunol.</source> <year>1994</year>, <volume>98</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 95&#x02013;103.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7523009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><mixed-citation id="cit68" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Serova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lokiec</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Koeppel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Poindessous</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Laar</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cvitkovic</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> <article-title>Characterizations of irofulven cytotoxicity in combination with cisplatin and oxaliplatin in human colon, breast, and ovarian cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Cancer Chemother. Pharmacol.</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>57</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), 491&#x02013;499.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16075278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>