<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="correction" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2646294</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/annotation/7126ab55-ca2a-4202-9e66-fac899bd52ee</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correction</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Correction: Properties and Distribution of Pure GA-Sequences of Mammalian Genomes</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Correction</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Albrecht-Buehler</surname><given-names>Guenter</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>10.1371/annotation/7126ab55-ca2a-4202-9e66-fac899bd52ee</elocation-id><copyright-statement>Public Library of Science. This is an open-access article distributed                under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,                distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><related-article related-article-type="corrected-article" vol="3" page="e3818" id="N0x1c6b3e0N0x20bc0b0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="19043592" ext-link-type="pubmed"><article-title>Properties and Distribution of Pure GA-Sequences of Mammalian Genomes</article-title></related-article></article-meta></front><body><p>In the abstract, the number 160 is incorrect due to a logical flaw in its calculation. The number 160 should be replaced with "many". In addition, the Results section, the second and third paragraphs under the subheading "Example 2" contain a logical flaw. Please consider the following alternate text:</p><p>In short, each point mutation inside a pure GA-sequence would split it into 2 smaller GA-sequences. As a result, one may conclude that pure GA-sequences are conspicuously protected from point mutations based on the following argument.</p><p>My previous study of point mutations in vertebrate genomes [6] suggested that their incidence is proportional to the length of a DNA sequence at a rate of 3.3 point mutations/[Kb]. Thus, the long GA-sequences should become more likely fragmented by point mutations than the short ones. (In quantitative terms, the number of GA-sequences of size L should decay exponentially with increasing numbers M of mutations (Exponent = - r L M )). In contrast, the Pareto-distribution of the sizes of pure GA-sequences (eq. 1 and Fig. 2), is characterized by a conspicuous presence of many, very long sequences. Clearly, many million years of evolution failed to fragment these sequences into many small ones.</p></body></article>