<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="news"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jem</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2646569</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2062iti3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.2062iti3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>In This Issue</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fine-tuning helper Ts</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maxmen</surname><given-names>Amy</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp><email>amaxmen@rockefeller.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>206</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage seq="c">260</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2009 The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="JEM_2062iti.pdf"/></article-meta></front><body><p><fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" position="anchor"><caption><p>Gfi-1 expression (black) blunts Th17 development.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem.2062iti3fig1"/></fig>If the transcriptional repressor Gfi-1 attended a dinner party, it would prevent its host from pairing a heavy red wine with a delicate fish. On page <related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="article-reference" vol="206" page="329" id="d32e68" xlink:href="19188499" ext-link-type="pubmed">329</related-article>, Zhu et al. show how Gfi-1 (growth factor independent 1) stops helper T cells from secreting the wrong type of cytokine.</p><p>What cytokines a T cell produces helps determine the outcome of an infection. Naive CD4+ T cells differentiate according to the problem at hand. They tend to differentiate into type 2 helper T cells (Th2) when extracellular parasites lurk, Th1 when the culprit is intracellular, Th17 cells after invasion by bacteria and fungi, or regulatory T (T reg) cells when an inflammatory response requires dampening. Gfi-1 helps control that differentiation decision, show Zhu et al. Or as senior author William Paul says, &#x0201c;It keeps cells on the straight and narrow.&#x0201d;</p><p>This team previously reported that Th2-inducing cytokines, such as interleukin (IL)-4, induce Gfi-1, which then amplifies the Th2 response by triggering proliferation. Now they find that Gfi-1 also dampens the cells' tendencies toward the Th17 and T reg cell lineages. Gfi-1 inhibited production of IL-17 and blocked the expression of CD103, which is found on certain T reg cells. In a model of autoimmunity, mice that lacked Gfi-1 developed a preponderance of CD103-expressing T reg cells, thus delaying the onset of disease.</p><p>The protein prevented gene expression by binding to loci in the genes encoding IL-17 and CD103. Gfi-1 binding triggered histone modifications&#x02014;most likely via its known interaction with the LSD1 histone demethylase&#x02014;thus turning off gene expression. Gfi-1 expression was repressed by the cytokine TGFb, which drives Th17 and T reg cell differentiation, allowing induction of those cells when needed.</p><p>Examining expression of Gfi-1 in various human infections may help explain why the balance of cell types can sometimes be tipped in the wrong direction.</p></body></article>