<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="rapid-communication" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Am Chem Soc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ja</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">jacsat</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of the American Chemical Society</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0002-7863</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1520-5126</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18593116</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2646756</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja800772p</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Detection and Relative Quantification of Proteinsby Surface Enhanced Raman Using Isotopic Labels</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>ShirshenduK.</given-names></name><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Brandon</given-names></name><xref rid="afn3" ref-type="author-notes">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>Giselle M.</given-names></name><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><name><surname>Gudihal</surname><given-names>Ravindra</given-names></name><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath5"><name><surname>Ben-Amotz</surname><given-names>Dor</given-names></name><xref rid="afn3" ref-type="author-notes">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath6"><name><surname>Davisson</surname><given-names>V. Jo</given-names></name><xref rid="ath6" ref-type="author">*</xref><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Medicinal Chemistry and Molecular Pharmacology,Bindley Bioscience Center, and Department of Chemistry, Purdue University,West Lafayette, Indiana 47907</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><email>davisson@purdue.edu</email></corresp><fn id="afn1"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Department of Medicinal Chemistryand Molecular Pharmacology.</p></fn><fn id="afn2"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>Bindley Bioscience Center.</p></fn><fn id="afn3"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p>Department of Chemistry.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>30</day><month>07</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>130</volume><issue>30</issue><fpage>9624</fpage><lpage>9625</lpage><history><date date-type="issue-pub"><day>30</day><month>07</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="asap"><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="xml-first-instance"><day>24</day><month>04</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>02</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 American Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>American Chemical Society</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org" license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the ACS AuthorChoice Terms &#x00026; Conditions.  Any use of this article, must conform to the terms of that license which are available at <uri xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org">http://pubs.acs.org</uri>.</license-p></license><license license-type="ccc-price"><license-p>40.75</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ja-2008-00772p_0001" id="tgr1"/></p><p>Accurate quantification of protein content and compositionhas been achieved using isotope-edited surface enhanced resonanceRaman spectroscopy. Synthesis of isotopomeric Rhodamine dye-linkedbioconjugation reagents enabled direct labeling of surface lysineson a variety of proteins. When separated in polyacrylamide gels andstained with silver nanoparticles. The spectral signatures reflectthe expected statistical distribution of isotopomeric labels on thelabeled proteins in the gel matrix format without interference fromprotein features.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement><funding-source>National Institutes of Health, United States</funding-source></funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>ja800772p</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>ja-2008-00772p</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Accurate and precise protein quantification remains an importantfundamental methodology and represents a critical component in identifyingbiomarkers and early detection of diseases.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>) The capacity to quantify relative changes in proteins from complexbiological samples is a central challenge to understanding the responseof protein expression to genomic or environmental factors. SurfaceEnhanced Resonance Raman Spectroscopy (SERRS) has proven to be a usefulspectroscopic tool for diagnostic applications,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> explosive detection,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>) monitoring eventsin enzyme catalysis,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>) detection of metabolites,(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>) and detection of bioanalytes during capillaryelectrophoresis.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>) However, SERRS suffersfrom variability in enhancement of Raman intensity depending uponthe nanomorphology of the substrate (typically silver colloids), therebyaffecting the reproducibility of the measurement. In our previouswork, we have demonstrated the improved reproducibility and accuracyof quantitative SERRS measurements obtained using isotopomeric rhodamine6G (R6G) probes over a useful analyte concentration range (picomolarto micromolar) of analytes.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>) Herein, wedemonstrate for the first time that these dyes may be transformedinto biomolecular labeling reagents and used for SERRS based quantificationof labeled proteins in a polyacrylamide matrix.</p><p>The sensitivity of SERRS can rival that of fluorescence, a standardfor optical detection and quantification of antibodies and nucleicacids.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>) Advantages of SERRS include thenarrow band widths and chemical fingerprint information of Raman spectrallines, as well as the improved quantification capability of the isotopicSERRS approach.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>) The SERRS of suitabledye probes such as R6G adsorbed on roughened metallic nanostructuresdominates over other Raman scattering processes and enables the detectionof dilute analytes in mixtures.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>) Thesechemical features provide suitable enhancements of the Raman signaturesfor the dye to allow detection in the background of matrix immobilizedprotein. By using isotope-encoded dyes for internal standardizationof SERRS one should be able to quantify protein concentration withunprecedented accuracy.</p><p>In order to establish the above strategy by incorporating isotope-encodedRaman labels into proteins, a method for synthesis of modified R6Gwas pursued through modification of the carboxylic functional group(Scheme <xref rid="sch1" ref-type="scheme">1</xref>). Previous efforts showed that thetetra-deuterio-R6G based upon 1A provided reliable differences inSERRS signature and enabled quantification.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup> Using this pattern of hydrogen substitution, the precursor d4-R6G-acid(1B) was obtained from condensation of 3-ethylamino 4-methylphenolwith d4-phthalic acid. R6G was hydrolyzed under basic conditions toobtain the corresponding acid (1A). Installation of a side chain linkerwas developed to enable efficient protein conjugation. The xanthenechromophore has a propensity for cyclization under basic conditions.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>) To ensure retention of the xanthene chromophore,a tertiary substituted amide linkage was selected to prevent cyclizationat the C7 position under basic conditions required for bioconjugationreactions. A linker was derived by basic hydrolysis of <italic>N</italic>-methyl caprolactam and subsequent esterification of the terminalcarboxyl moiety. Amidation of 1A (and 1B) with the linker was followedby ester interconversion by hydrolysis to the free acids and activationto the corresponding NHS esters (2A and 2B). Since lysine taggingis typically done at pH 8.5, we established that the dye linker wasstable in aqueous buffer at pH 9.0 for 2 d at room temperature.</p><fig id="sch1" position="float"><label>Scheme 1</label><caption><title><xref rid="sch1-fn1"/></title><p id="sch1-fn1">Reagents and conditions:(a) HATU/DIPEA/NHMe(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>Me/DMF,65%; (b) Ba(OH)<sub>2</sub>/MeOH&#x02212;H<sub>2</sub>O, 45%; (c) (iii)HATU/DIPEA/NHS/DMF, 80%. (NHS = <italic>N</italic>-hyrdoxysuccinimideester). The sites of deuterium are noted with an asterisk.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ja-2008-00772p_0002" id="gs1" position="float"/></fig><p>To test the feasibility of the bioconjugation approach, proteinsamples of lysozyme, glycogen phosphorylase, cytochrome c, casein,and ferritin were labeled with the isotopomeric R6G probes and subsequentlyquantified by SERRS detection: The labeling efficiency for reagents2A and 2B was first tested using UV&#x02212;vis spectra of the finaldye-labeled samples to standardize the protein and R6G content bythe relative absorbance&#x02019;s at 280 and 540 nm, respectively (<xref rid="si1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Protein labeling on the200 nmol dye per mg of protein scale gave a labeling efficiency ofapproximately 5 dye molecules per protein chain but ranged from 0.5to 10 for different proteins tested and depended upon lysine contentof the protein. Lysozyme labeling was further characterized by ESILC/MS and found to contain one (23% in the d0 sample or 29% in thed4 sample) or two labels (13% d0 or 12% d4).</p><p>Examples of the SERRS spectra of the d0/d4 labeled proteins areshown for lysozyme and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> in Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. In all cases, the R6G-labeled protein samplesshowed identical SERRS spectra to those of the parent R6G labelingreagents. The critical distinctions in the SERRS spectra of the isotopomericR6G-labeled proteins were also apparent. The Raman fine structureis dominated by the features of the R6G. These colloidal suspensionsdisplayed a limit of detection at an approximately 300 pM proteinconcentration, which was similar to the level of detection of R6Gdye alone. Despite the complexity of surface interactions, the reproducibleand predicted SERRS signatures in colloid suspensions with isotopomericmixtures of the R6G-labeled protein samples established a statisticalrepresentation of the dye populations. No features of the proteinwere observed in the Raman spectra, further supporting the dominantrole of the dye&#x02212;nanoparticle exchange interactions as a mechanismfor the enhancement.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>)</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>SERRSspectra of (left) 3 nM lysozyme-R6G-d0 (solid) and lysozyme-R6G-d4(dashed) and (right) cytochrome C-R6G-d0 (solid) and cytochrome-C-R6G-d4(dashed). The inset calibration curves show the relative amount ofd4 labeled protein determined from the ratio of peak areas of thed0 (611 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) peak and the d4 (600 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) peak compared to the known mixture ratio with 95% C.I. error bars.The solid line in the insets represents an ideal slope = 1.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ja-2008-00772p_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig><p>Polyacrylamide gel based protein separation and quantificationplay a central role in protein analysis, proteomics, and diagnostics.Spectral detection methods for proteins in gels have been limitedto fluorescence. No prior studies have focused on using SERRS detectionin gels or applications of isotopic variants for quantitative measurementsin such a matrix. To obtain SERRS in a gel matrix, <italic>in situ</italic> formation of silver nanoparticles using a protein silver stainingprotocol was pursued.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Ferritin samples labeled withd0- or d4-R6G were mixed in varied ratios and separated on SDS PAGE(Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The protein bands were imaged firstby fluorescence, followed by silver staining and SERRS spectral imagingagain using a 514.5 nm laser. The spectral shifts at 600 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were used to calculate the percent isotopic compositions for d0and d4 R6G corresponding to the relative amounts of the two ferritinsamples. The SERRS spectral signature reflects that of the isotopomericlabel as shown (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>E). The expected statisticaldistribution of the two labeled proteins in the PAGE gel format wasobserved.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>SDS-PAGEgel analysis of 0, 25, 50, 75, and 100% d4-R6G mixtures of isotopomericR6G-labeled ferritin, loaded with a total of 20 pmol of dye or 0.7&#x003bc;g protein per lane (see <xref rid="si1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref> for details of detection). Shown here is the 20 kDa protein bandimaged by silver stain (A), fluorescence (B), and SERRS intensitynormalized to the most intense signal in the image of the boxed regionin A and B (C). (D) A color coded representation of the percent ofR6G-d4 label (blue corresponds to 100% R6G-d4 label; red correspondsto 100% R6G-d0-label). (E) Fluorescence baseline subtracted SERRS-spectraof the five mixtures. The inset of E shows the percent d4 determinedby least-squares fitting of spectra from the ratio lanes. The errorbars represent the 95% C.I. for five measurements taken from eachratio lane.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ja-2008-00772p_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig><p>Standardization of SERRS measurements by use of isotopomers ofthe same dye class overcomes many limitations of surface enhancedspectroscopy.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>) Demonstrated here is thefeasibility of a bioconjugation approach for quantification of proteinsby SERRS detection enabled by isotopic substitution of a Raman activelabel. Protein Raman signals were not observed in the surface enhancedR6G spectra presumably due to larger SERRS enhancements for the dye&#x02212;surfaceinteractions. Equally important is the fact that spectra in the immobilizedlabeled protein accurately reflect the relative molecular content.Formation of an SERRS active silver nanoparticle enhancement agentwithin a polymeric matrix offers a practical approach to biomoleculardetection after capture or separation from biological mixtures. Optimizationof the methods to enhance SERRS intensity or minimize fluorescenceor other backgrounds offers additional promise.</p><p>Future applications of isotopic SERRS-based quantification includecomparative proteomics, which would take advantage of labeling proteinmixtures from a distinct origin with different isotopomer dye reagents.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>) Additional quantitative biomolecular analysessuch as antibody&#x02212;antigen complexes in semipermeable matricesalso represent promising applications for this detection strategy.Highest accuracy measurements are expected when the isotopic ratiosare near unity, but preliminary results indicate the method may beapplicable with ratios up to a factor of 10.</p></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work as supported in part by funds from NIH GM67195 (V.J.D.)and GM053155 (V.J.D.), NSF CHE-0455968 (Y.L.L. and D.B.A.), and NCIF32CA123662 (G.M.K.).</p></ack><notes id="si1" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>Experimental details and spectroscopicdata (PDF). This material is available free of charge via the Internetat <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org">http://pubs.acs.org</uri>.</p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ja800772p_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>ja800772p_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation id="cit1" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Unwin</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Whetton</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name> <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>31</volume>, 473&#x02013;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16815709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation id="cit2" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lyandres</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yonzon</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Glucksberg</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Van Duyne</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name> <source>Anal. Chem.</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>78</volume>, 7211&#x02013;7215.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17037923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation id="cit3" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grubisha</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lipert</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Driskell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name> <source>Anal. Chem.</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>75</volume>, 5936&#x02013;43.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14588035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation id="cit4" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thaxton</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mirkin</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name> <source>Science</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>301</volume>, 1884&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14512622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation id="cit5" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wabuyele</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vo-Dinh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> <source>Anal. Chem.</source> <year>2005</year>, <volume>77</volume>, 7810&#x02013;5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16316192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation id="cit6" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Keir</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name> <source>Chem. Commun.</source> <year>2002</year>, 580&#x02013;1.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation id="cit7" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Flitsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source> <year>2004</year>, <volume>22</volume>, 1133&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15300259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation id="cit8" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> <source>Anal. Chem.</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>78</volume>, 3379&#x02013;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16689540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation id="cit9" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arraez Roman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Efremov</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ariese</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Segura Carretero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gooijer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> <source>Anal. Bioanal. Chem.</source> <year>2005</year>, <volume>382</volume>, 180&#x02013;5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15900469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation id="cit10" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Davisson</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ben-Amotz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> <source>Anal. Chem.</source> <year>2005</year>, <volume>77</volume>, 3563&#x02013;3569.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15924390</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation id="cit11" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Faulds</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barbagallo</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Keer</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> <source>Analyst</source> <year>2004</year>, <volume>129</volume>, 567&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15213819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation id="cit12" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Littleford</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lundahl</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>McComb</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Laforest</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> <source>Faraday Discuss.</source> <year>2006</year>, <volume>132</volume>, 135&#x02013;45.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16833113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation id="cit13" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dieringer</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lettan</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Scheidt</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>VanDuyne</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name> <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source> <year>2007</year>, <volume>129</volume>, 16249&#x02013;16256.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18052068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation id="cit14" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name> <source>Org. Lett.</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>5</volume>, 3245&#x02013;3248.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12943398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation id="cit15" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garrell</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name> <source>Langmuir</source> <year>1988</year>, <volume>4</volume>, 1162&#x02013;1168.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation id="cit16" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shevchenko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wilm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vorm</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> <source>Anal. Chem.</source> <year>1996</year>, <volume>68</volume>, 850&#x02013;858.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8779443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation id="cit17" publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alban</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>David</surname><given-names>S. O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bjorkesten</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sloge</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name> <source>Proteomics</source> <year>2003</year>, <volume>3</volume>, 36&#x02013;44.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12548632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>