<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19247501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2646136</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PONE-RA-04915R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004633</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Ecology/Community Ecology and Biodiversity</subject><subject>Ecology/Marine and Freshwater Ecology</subject><subject>Ecology/Physiological Ecology</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology/Evolutionary Ecology</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology/Evolutionary and Comparative Genetics</subject><subject>Molecular Biology/Molecular Evolution</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular Adaptation of <italic>rbcL</italic> in the Heterophyllous Aquatic Plant <italic>Potamogeton</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">RbcL Adaptation in Aquatics</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>Satoko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1"><sup>&#x000a4;a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miyagi</surname><given-names>Atsuko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2"><sup>&#x000a4;b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>Seishiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Motomi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kadono</surname><given-names>Yasuro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kosuge</surname><given-names>Keiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Research Center for Environmental Genomics, Kobe University, Kobe, Hyogo, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, Kobe University, Kobe, Hyogo, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, The University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Tregenza</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Exeter, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>iida@kobe-u.ac.jp</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SI SA MI KK. Performed the experiments: SI AM. Analyzed the data: SI SA. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SI YK. Wrote the paper: SI KK.</p></fn><fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><label>&#x000a4;a</label><p>Current address: Research Center for Inland Seas, Kobe University, Awaji, Hyogo, Japan</p></fn><fn id="fn2" fn-type="current-aff"><label>&#x000a4;b</label><p>Current address: Institute of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences, The University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e4633</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Iida et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Heterophyllous aquatic plants show marked phenotypic plasticity. They adapt to environmental changes by producing different leaf types: submerged, floating and terrestrial leaves. By contrast, homophyllous plants produce only submerged leaves and grow entirely underwater. Heterophylly and submerged homophylly evolved under selective pressure modifying the species-specific optima for photosynthesis, but little is known about the evolutionary outcome of habit. Recent evolutionary analyses suggested that <italic>rbcL</italic>, a chloroplast gene that encodes a catalytic subunit of RuBisCO, evolves under positive selection in most land plant lineages. To examine the adaptive evolutionary process linked to heterophylly or homophylly, we analyzed positive selection in the <italic>rbcL</italic> sequences of ecologically diverse aquatic plants, Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Principal Findings</title><p>Phylogenetic and maximum likelihood analyses of codon substitution models indicated that <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic> has evolved under positive Darwinian selection. The positive selection has operated specifically in heterophyllous lineages but not in homophyllous ones in the branch-site models. This suggests that the selective pressure on this chloroplast gene was higher for heterophyllous lineages than for homophyllous lineages. The replacement of 12 amino acids occurred at structurally important sites in the quaternary structure of RbcL, two of which (residue 225 and 281) were identified as potentially under positive selection.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions/Significance</title><p>Our analysis did not show an exact relationship between the amino acid replacements and heterophylly or homophylly but revealed that lineage-specific positive selection acted on the <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic>. The contrasting ecological conditions between heterophyllous and homophyllous plants have imposed different selective pressures on the photosynthetic system. The increased amino acid replacement in RbcL may reflect the continuous fine-tuning of RuBisCO under varying ecological conditions.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Many aquatic plants exhibit marked developmental plasticity, known as heterophylly. Heterophylly occurs widely across distantly related taxa and is thought to have arisen via convergent evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Cook1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>. Heterophyllous species have broad, thick leaves with stomata on the water surface (floating leaves), as well as elongated, thin leaves without stomata within the water column growing from submerged shoots (submerged leaves). In addition, they sometimes produce terrestrial leaves from land shoots during droughts. In contrast, homophyllous aquatic plants produce only submerged leaves and grow entirely underwater. Each leaf type appears to be adapted to its environment morphologically and anatomically <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Arber1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Hutchinson1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. Moreover, the submerged and floating leaves have different photosynthetic properties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-FrostChristensen1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>. The degree of heterophylly (the shapes of the submerged, floating, and terrestrial leaves) varies from population to population, depending on the water level fluctuation in each habitat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Cook2">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Wooten1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. Therefore, heterophylly and submerged homophylly evolved under selective pressure modifying the species-specific optima for photosynthesis.</p><p><italic>Potamogeton</italic> L. (Potamogetonaceae), one of the largest genera of aquatic angiosperms, is ecologically diverse and distributed in various freshwater bodies (lakes, marshes, rivers, artificial ponds, etc.), as well as in brackish water <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Hutchinson1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kadono1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>. The genus includes both heterophyllous and homophyllous (strictly submerged) species. Recent molecular phylogenetic analyses of <italic>Potamogeton</italic> revealed that homophylly is the ancestral state and heterophylly has evolved several times in different lineages, possibly due to parallel evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Lindqvist1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>. Furthermore, we have reported that the degree of heterophylly in natural hybrids depends on the maternal type in reciprocal crosses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. The parental taxa of the hybrid are closely related but differ ecologically; <italic>P. malaianus</italic> Miq. can survive droughts by producing terrestrial shoots and is frequently distributed in shallow and inshore areas; <italic>P. perfoliatus</italic> L. generally lacks such phenotypic plasticity, grows in deeper water, and is more shade tolerant. Despite the high similarity of the <italic>trnT</italic>-<italic>trnL</italic> intergenic region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, all three substitutions between <italic>rbcL</italic> of the parental species are nonsynonymous <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. Even single amino acid replacements in RbcL could account for differences in the CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> specificity of ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (RuBisCO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Galms1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>. The maternal effect on survival under drought stress and the depth distribution of reciprocal hybrids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref> has led to speculation that the amino acid difference in RbcL plays an important role in ecological adaptation.</p><p>RbcL provides all the catalytically essential residues of RuBisCO, a critical enzyme for both the reductive and oxidative photosynthetic carbon cycles. The activity of RuBisCO is thought to be limited by environmental stresses, such as oxidative stress, heat, osmotic stress, and drought <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Moreno1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Parry1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. The holoenzyme consists of eight large catalytic subunits (RbcLs) and eight small subunits (RbcSs). The sequence of <italic>rbcL</italic> has great phylogenetic utility because of its conserved nature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Albert1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>, although substitutions occur in sites of known functional importance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kellogg1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Wolfe1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. The amino acid replacements in RbcL at the interface of subunits are correlated with the loss and gain of pyrenoids in the unicellular green alga lineage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Nozaki1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>. In addition, positive Darwinian selection of <italic>rbcL</italic> has been detected in cyanobacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Miller1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref> and various taxonomic groups of land plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kapralov1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Christin1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p><italic>Potamogeton</italic> is a representative example of the adaptive evolution of heterophylly. Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic> taxa are highly diversified in growth forms and leaf types and represent 11 of the 14 species groups in the genus <italic>Potamogeton</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Wiegleb1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>. In this study, to gain insight into whether an adaptive evolutionary process is linked to heterophylly or homophylly in Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic>, we tested whether there was positive selection in <italic>rbcL</italic> using phylogenetic and maximum likelihood analyses of codon substitution models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Yang1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Zhang1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>. We demonstrated that the evolution of ecologically divergent Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic> has involved the molecular adaptation of <italic>rbcL</italic>. In this article, abstract is also available in Japanese (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004633.s006">Text S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Evidence for positive selection in <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic></title><p>Three genes (<italic>rbcL</italic>, <italic>atpB</italic>, <italic>petA</italic>) were sequenced from 18 Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic>. All the nucleotide sequences determined in this study were deposited in GenBank (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004633.s001">Table S1</xref>). The phylogenetic trees based on individual chloroplast genes were consistent with each other and with a previous phylogenetic study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. A robust gene tree of chloroplast DNA is essential to conduct a maximum likelihood analysis in the molecular adaptation test. We combined all four datasets (1349 <italic>rbcL</italic>, 1467 <italic>atpB</italic>, 918 <italic>petA</italic>, and 660 <italic>trnT</italic>-<italic>trnL</italic> intergenic spacer sites) to obtain a well-resolved gene tree of the <italic>Potamogeton</italic> chloroplast DNA (cpDNA tree; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The basal branches of the cpDNA tree were congruent with those found in a previous study of the <italic>trnT</italic>-<italic>trnL</italic> intergenic spacer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. The Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic> species were divided into group I, with broad submerged leaves, and group II, with linear submerged leaves and subepidermal bundles. The latter was further divided into subgroups IIa and IIb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). In addition, newly resolved terminal branches identified several species groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), each of which was characterized by morphological features <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Wiegleb2">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kaplan1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. For example, subgroup Ia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) was characterized by the presence of overwintering subterranean turions.</p><fig id="pone-0004633-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004633.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Maximum likelihood <italic>Potamogeton</italic> cpDNA tree based on a combined 4394-bp chloroplast DNA dataset.</title><p>Approximate likelihood-ratio test measures (aLRT) are indicated as support for branches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Anisimova1">&#x0005b;52&#x0005d;</xref>. Amino acid replacements of RbcL reconstructed under the codon substitution model (M8) are also indicated. Branches with orange lines indicate three heterophyllous lineages, whereas the others were homophyllous lineages.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004633.g001"/></fig><p>To test the hypothesis of positive selection in <italic>rbcL</italic>, we examined the fit of the <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic> sequences to codon substitution models based on the cpDNA tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Table 1</xref> lists the parameter estimates and log-likelihood values for the eight codon substitution models of molecular evolution. In order to evaluate positive selection, we performed four likelihood ratio tests comparing M1A (nearly neutral) with M2A (positive selection), M7 (beta) with M8 (beta and &#x003c9;<sub>s</sub>&#x02265;1), M8A (beta and &#x003c9;<sub>s</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1) with M8 (beta and &#x003c9;<sub>s</sub>&#x02265;1), and branch-site model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1 fixed) with branch-site model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> estimated) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0004633-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004633.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Parameter estimates and log-likelihood values for <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic> under eight codon substitution models included in PAML.</title></caption><graphic id="pone-0004633-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0004633.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0004633-t001-1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Log-likelihood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Site-specific models</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M0 : one &#x003c9;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2182.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.129</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M1A : nearly neutral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2167.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>0</sub></italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.912, &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.088, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M2A : positive selection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2163.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>0</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.914, &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.082, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>2</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.004, &#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;11.494</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M7 : beta</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2167.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.005, <italic>q</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.0482</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M8 : beta &#x00026; &#x003c9;<sub>s</sub>&#x02265;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2163.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>0</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.963</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.010, <italic>q</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.314</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.037, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;3.825</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M8A : beta &#x00026; &#x003c9;<sub>s</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2167.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>0</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.912</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.005, <italic>q</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;99.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.088, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1.000</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Branch-site models</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Foreground: Heterophylly</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1 fixed)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2166.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>0</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.871, &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.064, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>2&#x0002b;</sub>p<sub>3</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.065 , &#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> estimated)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2162.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>0</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.920, &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.066, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>2&#x0002b;</sub>p<sub>3</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.013 , &#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;26.150</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Foreground: Homophylly</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1 fixed)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2166.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>0</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.850, &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.053, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>2&#x0002b;</sub>p<sub>3</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.097 , &#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> estimated)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2165.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>0</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.899, &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.055, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p<sub>2&#x0002b;</sub>p<sub>3</sub></italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.046 , &#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;2.575</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>the proportion (<italic>p<sub>i</sub></italic>) of codon sites with &#x003c9;<sub>i</sub>. In models M7, M8 and M8A, &#x003c9; was drawn from a beta distribution B(<italic>p</italic>, <italic>q</italic>) for a proportion (<italic>p<sub>0</sub></italic>) of sites.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0004633-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004633.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>LRT statistics for testing the hypothesis of positive selection in <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic>.</title></caption><graphic id="pone-0004633-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0004633.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0004633-t002-2"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test No.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test model</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Null model</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x00394;L<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M2A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M1A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4&#x0002a;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0&#x0002a;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M8A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8&#x0002a;&#x0002a;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branch-site model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> estimated)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branch-site model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1 fixed)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: Heterophylly</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2&#x0002a;&#x0002a;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: Homophylly</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label>a</label><p>The test statistic for the M8A-M8 comparison is compared with 50&#x02236;50 mixture of df&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0 and 1 according to Swansson et al. (2003).</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>b</label><p>&#x0002a;: <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;: <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The average &#x003c9; ratio of <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic> was 0.129 over all 449 codon sites and lineages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Table 1</xref>, M0). Assuming that the &#x003c9; ratio of all sites was either &#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0 or &#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1 and for the average of all the lineages in the tree, a majority of the sites (91.2&#x00025;) were under purifying selection with &#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0 in model M1A (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Table 1</xref>). The remaining sites (8.8&#x00025;) were under neutral evolution with &#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1, indicating the dominant role of purifying selection in the evolution of <italic>rbcL</italic>. In model M2A, the majority of the sites (91.4&#x00025;) were under purifying selection, 8.2&#x00025; of the sites were under neutral evolution, and 0.4&#x00025; of the sites experienced positive selection (&#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;11.494)(<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Table 1</xref>). The likelihood ratio test revealed that model M2A fit the data significantly better than the null model M1A (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>Model M7 assumed several codon site classes with values of &#x003c9; ranging from 0 to 1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Table 1</xref>). By contrast, 3.7&#x00025; of the codons had &#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;3.825 and experienced positive selection in model M8 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Table 1</xref>). Once again, the <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic> sequences fit model M8, which allowed positive selection better than the null model M7 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>In Model M8A, an additional category of sites with &#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1 was added to the null model M7 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Table 1</xref>). The hypothesis of positive selection on <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic> was also supported by a test comparing M8 against the null model M8A (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t002">Table 2</xref>), which may be more robust than M1A <italic>vs.</italic> M2A or M7 <italic>vs.</italic> M8 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Swanson1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>The branch-site models allow the &#x003c9; ratio to vary both among codon sites and among lineages. Heterophyllous lineages in the <italic>Potamogeton</italic> cpDNA tree were specified <italic>a priori</italic> as foreground branches that might be expected to be under positive selection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). In model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> estimated), a majority of the sites were under purifying selection (92.0&#x00025;), whereas 6.6&#x00025; of the codons were evolving neutrally throughout the tree. The remaining sites (1.34&#x00025;) were either purifying (1.25&#x00025;) or neutral (0.9&#x00025;) on the background branches, but came under positive selection on the foreground branches with &#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;26.150 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Table 1</xref>). Test model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> estimated) fit <italic>Potamogeton rbc</italic>L significantly better than null model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;1 fixed; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Table 1</xref>)(<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t002">Table 2</xref>). Conversely, when homophyllous lineages within the genus <italic>Potamogeton</italic> were specified as foreground branches, both the test and null models had similar log-likelihood values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t002">2</xref>).</p><p>The other chloroplast encoded genes, <italic>atpB</italic> and <italic>petA</italic>, have reported evolutionary rates similar to <italic>rbcL</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Wolfe2">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>. The average &#x003c9; ratios of <italic>Potamogeton atpB</italic> and <italic>petA</italic> were 0.098 and 0.174, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004633.s003">Tables S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004633.s004">S4</xref>). In both genes, positive selection was detected in the site-specific models analyses with a high posterior probability of evolving under positive selection for two <italic>atpB</italic> (sites 16 and 488) and one <italic>petA</italic> (site 239) residues but not in the branch-site models (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004633.s003">Tables S3</xref> to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004633.s005">S5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Features of amino acid replacement sites</title><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t003">Table 3</xref> shows the distribution of 12 variable amino acid sites in RbcLs from <italic>Potamogeton</italic> and the outgroup species. Amino acid replacements at residues 225 and 281 were identified as potentially under positive selection. Most of the replacements were implied to have occurred at terminal branches of the phylogenic tree, rather than at basal ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The replacement of residue 225 (Ile<sup>225</sup>&#x02192;Leu<sup>225</sup>, codon exchange ATT&#x02192;CTT) was thought to have occurred twice: once in subgroup Ia and again in subgroup IIa. Residue 281 was replaced five times: three parallel changes of Ser<sup>281</sup>&#x02192;Ala<sup>281</sup> (TCT&#x02192;GCT) and two of Ala<sup>281</sup>&#x02192;Ser<sup>281</sup> (GCT&#x02192;TCT).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0004633-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004633.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Amino acid replacement sites in 18 <italic>Potamogeton</italic> species and <italic>Stuckenia</italic> RbcL.</title></caption><graphic id="pone-0004633-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0004633.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0004633-t003-3"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amino acid site</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">279</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">281</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">282</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">309</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">328</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="13" align="left" rowspan="1">Species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. crispus</italic> (&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. maackianus</italic> (&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. gramineus</italic> (&#x0002b;&#x0002b;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. dentatus</italic> (&#x02212;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. distinctus</italic> (&#x0002b;&#x0002b;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. malaianus</italic> (&#x0002b;&#x0002b;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. perfoliatus</italic> (&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. alpinus</italic> (&#x0002b;), <italic>P. cristatus</italic> (&#x0002b;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. fryeri</italic> (&#x0002b;&#x0002b;), <italic>P. natans</italic> (&#x0002b;&#x0002b;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. praelongus</italic> (&#x02212;), <italic>P. oxyphyllus</italic> (&#x02212;), <italic>P. octandrus</italic> (&#x0002b;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. compressus</italic> (&#x02212;), <italic>P. obtusifolius</italic> (&#x02212;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. panormitanus</italic> (&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>), <italic>P. pusillus</italic> (&#x02212;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Stuckenia pectinata</italic> (&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Structural feature<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">i</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">i</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0002a;c</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0002a;c</td></tr><tr><td colspan="13" align="left" rowspan="1">Posterior probabilities of &#x003c9;&#x02265;1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site-specific model (M8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branch-site model A (estimated &#x003c9;<sub>2</sub>, Foreground: Heterophylly)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>.98</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>.98</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.68</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>Number corresponds to the amino acid position of spinach RbcL. (&#x02212;): homophyllous plant with submerged leaves, (&#x0002b;): heterophyllous plant with submerged and floating leaves, (&#x0002b;&#x0002b;): heterophyllous plant with submerged, floating and terrestrial leaves.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>a</label><p>the species is also distributed in brackish water.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>b</label><p>&#x0002a;: residues that are close to the active sites, c: residues that are buried in the interior of RbcL, D: residues at the intradimer interface of RbcL, i: residues at the interface between RbcL and RbcS.</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>c</label><p>probabilities above 0.95 are indicated in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In order to infer the possible effects of amino acid replacement sites, the structural motif of <italic>Spinacia oleracea</italic> RbcL <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Knight1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref> was used (1UPP and 1RCX were obtained from the RCSB Protein Data Bank) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t003">Table 3</xref>). Many amino acid replacements in <italic>Potamogeton</italic> RbcLs have occurred at the interface between subunits and near the active sites. Seven amino acids (76, 230, 245, 249, 279, 282, and 309) were located at the surface of the RbcL molecule. Two of them (76 and 230) were at the interface between RbcL and RbcS, whereas five (245, 249, 279, 282, and 309) were at the interface of the RbcL dimer. The remaining four (101, 225, 281, and 328) were buried within the molecule. Residue 270 was also located within the molecule, although it was not completely buried. Residues 270 and 328 were close to some of the active sites (Arg<sup>295</sup>, His<sup>298</sup>, and His<sup>327</sup>) in substrate-binding regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Knight1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>In <italic>Potamogeton</italic>, heterophyllous species are distributed in freshwater and sometimes on the shore, whereas homophyllous species live entirely underwater in fresh or brackish water. The contrasting ecological conditions between heterophyllous and homophyllous plants may have imposed different selective pressures on the photosynthetic system. Our molecular evolutionary analyses indicated that <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic> has evolved under positive selection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t002">2</xref>). Of 12 amino acid sites, two (sites 225 and 281) were potentially driven by positive selection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t003">Table 3</xref>). The replacement at site 281 appeared to have originated independently in different phylogenetic lineages of both heterophyllous and homophyllous species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>Contrary to our observations, positive selection was absent in the <italic>rbcL</italic> of two exclusively aquatic lineages: monocots-4 (Potamogetonaceae plus Zosteraceae) and monocots-9 (Hydrocharitaceae) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kapralov2">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>. Sample size may account for the differences. Compared to the enormous numbers and variety of land plant <italic>rbcL</italic>, nonsynonymous substitutions in each aquatic lineage were limited, so weak signals of positive selection could not be detected. Indeed, the presence of positive selection was shown in a combined <italic>rbcL</italic> dataset for both lineages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kapralov2">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>. The &#x003c9; (&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;<italic>dN</italic>/<italic>dS</italic>) ratio in <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic> (0.129) was approximately twice that found in seagrass <italic>Zostera</italic> (0.050). Ecological differences between aquatic and terrestrial habitats may account for this increase in nonsynonymous substitution in <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic>.</p><p>Most aquatic plants are thought to have originally thrived on land and adapted secondarily to an aquatic habitat. Therefore, the heterophyllous condition arose as the land became submerged. On the other hand, the phylogenetic tree of Alismatales <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Les1">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref> (Angiosperm Phylogeny Website, Version 9, June 2008 by Stevens PF &#x0005b;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mobot.org/MOBOT/research/APweb/">http://www.mobot.org/MOBOT/research/APweb/</ext-link>&#x0005d;) suggests that the Potamogetonaceae and its sister family Zosteraceae originated entirely from submerged seagrasses. Considering such secondary adaptation to the terrestrial environment, the heterophyllous taxa of <italic>Potamogeton</italic> are surmised to have been derived from homophyllous taxa.</p><p>Terrestrial plants are commonly exposed to temperatures of 40 to 50&#x000b0;C for several hours a day <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Larcher1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>. Heterophyllous taxa usually produce floating or terrestrial leaves in the summer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Sculthorpe1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Wiegleb3">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>. The temperature of the floating leaves can exceed 30&#x000b0;C <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Ikusima1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>. To improve their intrinsic thermal stability, proteins have more hydrophobic residues with branched side chains and more charged residues, at the expense of uncharged polar residues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kumar1">&#x0005b;37&#x0005d;</xref>. Molecular evolutionary analysis of cyanobacteria RbcL suggests that adaptive replacement, an increase in hydrophobic residues and a decrease in uncharged polar residues, occurred in a clade of hot spring strains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Miller1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>. In <italic>Potamogeton</italic> RbcL, the uncharged polar residue Ser was replaced with the hydrophobic residue Ala at site 281 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t003">Table 3</xref>). This amino acid replacement might increase the thermal stability of RbcL in the heterophyllous taxa. However, recent evolutionary analyses of RuBisCO suggested that amino acid site 281 underwent parallel genetic changes; the Ala in almost all C<sub>3</sub> photosynthesis species was replaced by Ser in the C<sub>4</sub> group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Christin1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. The replacement of Ala<sup>281</sup> by Ser<sup>281</sup> occurred in two homophyllous species (<italic>P. crispus</italic> and <italic>P. dentatus</italic>), and the reverse from Ser<sup>281</sup> to Ala<sup>281</sup> occurred in two independent heterophyllous lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). A significant correlation was found between the presence or absence of heterophylly and the amino acid at residue 281 (<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 by Fisher's exact test). The detection of positive selection in heterophyllous lineages suggested that selective pressure on this chloroplast gene was higher for heterophyllous lineages than for homophyllous lineages. In the evolutionary analyses of <italic>rbcL</italic> sequences from over 3000 species representing green plants and other phototroph lineages, the neighboring residues 279 and 282 in helix 4 were identified as evolving under positive selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kapralov2">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>. This suggests that a replacement at these amino acid sites could be involved in the adaptation of specificity or catalytic efficiency to widespread environmental variation in temperature and dryness in both terrestrial land plants (C<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>3</sub> plants) and <italic>Potamogeton</italic>.</p><p>Many aquatic plants have acquired carbon-concentrating mechanisms to overcome the potentially low, fluctuating supply of CO<sub>2</sub> for underwater photosynthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Maberly1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>. A strategy of C<sub>4</sub>-like carbon fixation operates in several freshwater homophyllous species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Maberly1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Magnin1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref> and seagrasses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Touchette1">&#x0005b;41&#x0005d;</xref>. The evolutionary analysis of the RuBisCO gene revealed that five amino acid sites in <italic>rbcL</italic> evolved under positive selection in terrestrial C<sub>4</sub> monocots <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Christin1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. At three amino acid sites, residues of the C<sub>4</sub>-like seagrass <italic>Zostera</italic> were fixed and shared with those of terrestrial C<sub>4</sub> monocots (Ile<sup>101</sup>, Ile<sup>270</sup>, and Ser<sup>281</sup>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kato1">&#x0005b;42&#x0005d;</xref>. In <italic>Potamogeton</italic>, some homophyllous plants share residues with C<sub>4</sub> monocots (Ile<sup>101</sup>, Ile<sup>270</sup>, Ser<sup>281</sup>, and Ile<sup>309</sup>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t003">Table 3</xref>). The homophyllous species <italic>P. perfoliatus</italic>, which is located terminally in the cpDNA tree, had Ile<sup>270</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004633-t003">Table 3</xref>). This plant tends to be shade tolerant and grows in deep fresh water and brackish water <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. Its sister species <italic>P. malaianus</italic> is heterophyllous, shade intolerant, and distributed mainly in shallow, inshore freshwater <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. Our ongoing studies indicate that underwater heat stress induces the transcription of key enzymes in C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis (phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase and pyruvate, orthophosphate dikinase) in submerged leaves of <italic>P. perfoliatus</italic> but not in those of <italic>P. malaianus</italic>. This suggests that amino acid replacement in <italic>P. perfoliatus</italic> RbcL could be involved in acquiring C<sub>4</sub>-like photosynthesis. However, the selective pressure involved appeared to be mild, as no positive selection specific to homophyllous lineages was detected.</p><sec id="s3a"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our analysis did not show an exact relationship between the amino acid replacements and heterophylly or homophylly but revealed that positive selection has affected the <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic>. Polyploidy and aneuploidy, major forces in diversification, are common within the genus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Les2">&#x0005b;43&#x0005d;</xref>. We are now conducting phylogenetic analyses of four nuclear genes to infer the polyploid history of Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic>. Our preliminary data suggest that heterophylly has evolved through allopolyploid formation. The increased amino acid replacement in <italic>rbcL</italic> may reflect the adaptive fine-tuning of RuBisCO in the alternation of growth forms (heterophyllous or homophyllous) and nuclear genome setsz.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic> species and the allied species <italic>Stuckenia pectinata</italic> (L.) B&#x000f6;rner were used in the analyses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004633.s001">Table S1</xref>). Total DNA was prepared previously for a phylogenetic analysis of Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic> based on the <italic>trnT</italic>-<italic>trnL</italic> region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. We categorized the <italic>Potamogeton</italic> species into three groups based on growth form and leaf type: homophyllous species (submerged leaves), floating-leaved heterophyllous species (submerged and floating leaves), and terrestrial-leaved heterophyllous species (submerged, floating, and terrestrial leaves), according to the descriptions of Kadono (1984) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kadono2">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>. The production of terrestrial leaves has been observed in some homophyllous species (<italic>P. dentatus</italic> and <italic>P. perfoliatus</italic>) under cultivation or on a few anomalous occasions in the field <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kadono2">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Amano1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref>. Nevertheless these species were treated as homophyllous, as their terrestrial leaves did not seem to contribute to persistent survival.</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Amplification and sequencing of chloroplast-encoded genes</title><p>The amplification and sequence analysis of chloroplast-encoded genes (<italic>rbcL</italic>, <italic>atpB</italic>, and <italic>petA</italic>) were performed as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. Twenty-five PCR cycles at 94&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 59&#x000b0;C for 40 s, and 72&#x000b0;C for 60 s were performed. The forward and reverse primers used for amplification are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004633.s002">Table S2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Molecular evolutionary analysis</title><p>Maximum likelihood (ML) trees were produced online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/">http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/</ext-link>) using the program PhyML <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Guindon1">&#x0005b;47&#x0005d;</xref>. Five starting trees (neighbor-joining and four equally parsimonious trees) were examined with the substitution model HKY85, and the phylogenetic tree with the largest likelihood was selected. <italic>Stuckenia pectinata</italic> was used as the outgroup. Two length mutations (a 9-bp deletion in <italic>P. gramineus</italic> and <italic>P. dentatus atpB</italic> and a 6-bp insertion in <italic>P. praelongus petA</italic>) were treated as missing data and excluded from the analysis.</p><p>Molecular adaptation tests on the <italic>Potamogeton rbcL</italic> codon sites and reconstruction of the ancestral <italic>rbcL</italic> sequences were performed using maximum-likelihood models and programs included in PAML ver. 4.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Yang1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Zhang1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Yang3">&#x0005b;48&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Yang4">&#x0005b;49&#x0005d;</xref>. The models used the nonsynonymous/synonymous substitution rate ratio (&#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;<italic>dN</italic>/<italic>dS</italic>) as an indicator of selective pressure and allowed the ratio to vary among codon sites. We used five site-specific codon substitution models: null models for testing positive selection (M1A, M7, and M8A) and models allowing for positive selection (M2A and M8) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Wong1">&#x0005b;50&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Yang5">&#x0005b;51&#x0005d;</xref>. The likelihood ratio test was used to compare these alternative models. Using model 0 included in the same program, the average nonsynonymous/synonymous substitution rate ratio (&#x003c9;&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;<italic>dN</italic>/<italic>dS</italic>) was also estimated.</p><p>In contrast to the site-specific models, which assume the same &#x003c9; ratio among all of the lineages in the tree, the branch-site models let the &#x003c9; ratio vary among both sites and lineages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Yang2">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Zhang1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>. To clarify whether positive selection is linked to the evolution of heterophylly or homophylly, the branch-site models implemented in PAML ver. 4.1 (the modified branch-site model A) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Zhang1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Yang3">&#x0005b;48&#x0005d;</xref> used heterophylly or homophylly to define branches tested for positive selection (foreground branches). As a single origin of heterophylly is more parsimonious than multiple origins, subgroup Ia was assigned as a heterophyllous lineage for the selection test, in addition to the other monophyletic lineages of heterophyllous species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004633-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Such a definition of heterophyllous lineage was considered logical, as the homophyllous species included in subgroup Ia (<italic>P. dentatus</italic> and <italic>P. perfoliatus</italic>) has been observed to produce anomalous terrestrial leaves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Iida2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Kadono2">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Amano1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>The posterior probabilities that a site was drawn from a given &#x003c9; site class were calculated using the parameter estimates from model M8 or branch-site model A (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> estimated, foreground: heterophylly) and a procedure called the Bayes empirical Bayes method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Yang5">&#x0005b;51&#x0005d;</xref>. A site was considered potentially under positive selection when it had probabilities above 0.95. All the above molecular evolutionary analyses were also carried out for the other chloroplast genes, <italic>atpB</italic> and <italic>petA</italic>.</p><p>To identify the amino acid position for the structural motif, the quaternary structure of RbcL was inferred from data for <italic>Spinacia oleracea</italic> L. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004633-Knight1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref> (1UPP and 1RCX obtained from the RCSB Protein Data Bank: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/pdb">http://www.rcsb.org/pdb</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004633.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>List of <italic>Potamogeton</italic> and <italic>Stuckenia</italic> species with GenBank accession numbers of chloroplast genes examined in the present study.</p><p>(0.05 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004633.s001.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004633.s002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>List of primers used for PCR.</p><p>(0.03 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004633.s002.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004633.s003"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p>Parameter estimates and log-likelihood values for <italic>Potamogeton atpB</italic> under eight codon substitution models included in PAML.</p><p>(0.05 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004633.s003.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004633.s004"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p>Parameter estimates and log-likelihood values for <italic>Potamogeton petA</italic> under eight codon substitution models included in PAML.</p><p>(0.05 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004633.s004.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004633.s005"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p>LRT statistics for testing the hypothesis of positive selection in <italic>Potamogeton</italic> chloroplast genes.</p><p>(0.05 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004633.s005.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004633.s006"><label>Text S1</label><caption><p>Abstract in Japanese.</p><p>(0.03 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004633.s006.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr. Hisayoshi Nozaki (The University of Tokyo) for discussion of the molecular evolution of <italic>rbcL</italic>.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0004633-Cook1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>CDK</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><source>Aquatic plant book</source><publisher-loc>The Hague</publisher-loc><publisher-name>SPB Academic Publishing</publisher-name><fpage>228</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Arber1"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1920</year><source>Water plants: a study of aquatic angiosperms</source><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>436</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Sculthorpe1"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sculthorpe</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1967</year><source>The biology of aquatic vascular plants</source><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Edward Arnold</publisher-name><fpage>610</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Hutchinson1"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1975</year><source>A treatise on limnology. 3. Limnological Botany</source><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><fpage>672</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-FrostChristensen1"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frost-Christensen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sand-Jensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Comparative kinetics of photosynthesis in floating and submerged <italic>Potamogeton</italic> leaves.</article-title><source>Aquat Bot</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1016/0304-3770(95)00455-9</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Cook2"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1968</year><article-title>Adaptation to heterogeneous environments. I. Variation in heterophylly in <italic>Ranunculus flammula</italic> L.</article-title><source>Evolution</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>516</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Wooten1"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wooten</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1970</year><article-title>Experimental investigations of the <italic>Sagittaria graminea</italic> complex: transplant studies and genecology.</article-title><source>J Ecol</source><volume>58</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>242</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Kadono1"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>1982</year><article-title>Distribution and habitat of Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic>.</article-title><source>Bot Mag Tokyo</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Iida1"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosuge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Molecular phylogeny of Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic> species in light of noncoding chloroplast sequences.</article-title><source>Aquat Bot</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1016/j.aquabot.2004.08.005</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Lindqvist1"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindqvist</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Laet</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Aagesen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Keener</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Molecular phylogenetics of an aquatic plant lineage, Potamogetonaceae.</article-title><source>Cladistics</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>568</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1111/j.1096-0031.2006.00124.x</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Iida2"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Inherited maternal effects on the drought tolerance of a natural hybrid aquatic plant, <italic>Potamogeton anguillanus</italic>.</article-title><source>J Pl Res</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1007/s10265-007-0087-y</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Galms1"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galm&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Flexas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Keys</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cifre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>RAC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Rubisco specificity factor tends to be larger in plant species from drier habitats and in species with persistent leaves.</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>579</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1111/j.1365-3040.2005.01300.x</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Moreno1"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Spreitzer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>C172S Substitution in the chloroplast-encoded large subunit affects stability and stress-induced turnover of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>274</volume><fpage>26789</fpage><lpage>26793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10480884</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Li1"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Association of heat-induced conformational change with activity loss of Rubisco.</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>290</volume><fpage>1128</fpage><lpage>1132</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1006/bbrc.2001.6322</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11798193</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Parry1"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>MAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Andralojc</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Keys</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Rubisco activity: effects of drought stress.</article-title><source>Ann Bot</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12102509</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Albert1"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Backlund</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Manhart</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Functional constraints and <italic>rbcL</italic> evidence for land plant phylogeny.</article-title><source>Ann Mo Bot Gard</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>534</fpage><lpage>567</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Kellogg1"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kellogg</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Juliano</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>The structure and function of RUBISCO and their implications for systematic studies.</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>428</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Wolfe1"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>dePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Alternate paths of evolution for the photosynthetic gene <italic>rbcL</italic> in four nonphotosynthetic species of <italic>Orobanche</italic>.</article-title><source>Pl Mol Biol</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>965</fpage><lpage>977</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1023/A:1005739223993</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Nozaki1"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nozaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Onishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Differences in pyrenoid morphology are correlated with differences in the <italic>rbcL</italic> genes of members of the <italic>Chloromonas</italic> lineage (Volvocales, Chlorophyceae).</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1007/s00239-002-2338-9</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12355262</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Miller1"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Evidence for the adaptive evolution of the carbon fixation gene <italic>rbcL</italic> during diversification in temperature tolerance of a clade of hot spring cyanobacteria.</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1237</fpage><lpage>1246</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1046/j.1365-294X.2003.01831.x</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12694287</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Kapralov1"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapralov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Filatov</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Molecular adaptation during adaptive radiation in the Hawaiian endemic genus <italic>Schiedea</italic>.</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>e8</fpage><comment>DOI 10.1371/journal.pone.0000008</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183712</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Kapralov2"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapralov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Filatov</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Widespread positive selection in the photosynthetic Rubisco enzyme.</article-title><source>BMC Evol Biol</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>73</fpage><comment>DOI 10.1186/1471-2148-7-73</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17498284</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Christin1"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christin</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Muasya</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roalson</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Russier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Evolutionary switch and genetic convergence on <italic>rbcL</italic> following the evolution of C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>2361</fpage><lpage>2368</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1093/molbev/msn178</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18695049</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Wiegleb1"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiegleb</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year><article-title>Notes on pondweeds: outlines for a monographical treatment of the genus <italic>Potamogeton</italic> L.</article-title><source>Feddes Repert</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>266</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Yang1"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>A-MK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Codon-substitution models for heterogeneous selection pressure at amino acid sites.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>155</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10790415</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Yang2"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Codon-substitution models for detecting molecular adaptation at individual sites along specific lineages.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>908</fpage><lpage>917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12032247</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Zhang1"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Evaluation of an improved branch-site likelihood method for detecting positive selection at the molecular level.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>2472</fpage><lpage>2479</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1093/molbev/msi237</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16107592</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Wiegleb2"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiegleb</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>An account of the species of <italic>Potamogeton</italic> L. (Potamogetonaceae).</article-title><source>Folia Geobot</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>316</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Kaplan1"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;t&#x0011b;p&#x000e1;nek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Genetic variation within and between populations of <italic>Potamogeton pusillus</italic> agg.</article-title><source>Plant Syst Evol</source><volume>239</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1007/s00606-002-0252-7</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Swanson1"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Pervasive adaptive evolution in mammalian fertilization proteins.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519901</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Wolfe2"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Rates of nucleotide substitution vary greatly among plant mitochondrial, chloroplast, and nuclear DNAs.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>9054</fpage><lpage>9058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3480529</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Knight1"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000e4;nd&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>C-I</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Crystallographic analysis of ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase from spinach at 2&#x000b7;4 &#x000c5; resolution subunit interactions and active site.</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>215</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80100-7</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2118958</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Les1"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Les</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Waycott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Phylogenetic studies in Alismatidae. II. Evolution of marine angiosperms (seagrasses) and hydrophily.</article-title><source>Syst Bot</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>463</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Larcher1"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larcher</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><source>&#x000d6;kophysiologie der Pflanzen, 5. Auflage</source><publisher-loc>Stuttgart</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Eugen Ulmer GmbH &#x00026; Co</publisher-name><fpage>408</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Wiegleb3"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiegleb</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Growth and development of <italic>Potamogeton malaianus</italic> in southwestern Japan.</article-title><source>Nord J Bot</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Ikusima1"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikusima</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year><source>Seitaigakukouza 7 Suikaishokubutsugunraku no butsushitsuseisan I &#x02013; Suiseishokubutsu- (Matter production in aquatic plant community I Aquatic plants) (In Japanese)</source><publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kyoritsu shuppan</publisher-name><fpage>98</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Kumar1"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussinov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>How do thermophilic proteins deal with heat?</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><volume>58</volume><fpage>1216</fpage><lpage>1233</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1007/PL00000935</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11577980</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Maberly1"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maberly</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Freshwater angiosperm carbon concentrating mechanisms: process and patterns.</article-title><source>Funct Plant Biol</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1071/PP01187</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Holaday1"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holaday</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><article-title>C<sub>4</sub> acid metabolism and dark CO<sub>2</sub> fixation in a submersed aquatic macrophyte (<italic>Hydrilla verticillata</italic>).</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16661184</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Magnin1"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magnin</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooley</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiskind</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Regulation and localization of key enzymes during the induction of kranz-less, C<sub>4</sub>-type photosynthesis in <italic>Hydrilla verticillata</italic>.</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>1681</fpage><lpage>1689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223888</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Touchette1"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Touchette</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkholder</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Overview of the physiological ecology of carbon metabolism in seagrasses.</article-title><source>J Exp Mar Bio Ecol</source><volume>250</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1016/S0022-0981(00)00196-9</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10969168</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Kato1"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Aioi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Omori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Satta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Phylogenetic analyses of <italic>Zostera</italic> species based on <italic>rbcL</italic> and <italic>matK</italic> nucleotide sequences: Implications for the origin and diversification of seagrasses in Japanese waters.</article-title><source>Genes Genet Syst</source><volume>78</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14676424</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Les2"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Les</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>Taxonomic implications of aneuploidy and polyploidy in <italic>Potamogeton</italic> (Potamogetonaceae).</article-title><source>Rhodora</source><volume>85</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>323</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Kadono2"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><article-title>Comparative ecology of Japanese <italic>Potamogeton</italic>: an extensive survey with special reference to growth form and life cycle.</article-title><source>Jpn J Ecol</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>172</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Kaplan2"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Phenotypic plasticity in <italic>Potamogeton</italic> (Potamogetonaceae).</article-title><source>Folia Geobot</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>170</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Amano1"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Origin and present status of <italic>Potamogeton</italic>&#x000d7;<italic>inbaensis</italic> in a natural population of Oitoike pond, Kitakyushu-city, Japan (in Japanese with English abstract).</article-title><source>Bunrui</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>139</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Guindon1"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood.</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1080/10635150390235520</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530136</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Yang3"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>PAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1586</fpage><lpage>1591</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1093/molbev/msm088</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483113</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Yang4"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielawski</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Statistical methods for detecting molecular adaptation.</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1016/S0169-5347(00)01994-7</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114436</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Wong1"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>WSW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Detecting selection in noncoding regions of nucleotide sequences.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>167</volume><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>958</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1534/genetics.102.010959</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15238543</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Yang5"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>WSW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Bayes empirical bayes inference of amino acid sites under positive selection.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>1118</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1093/molbev/msi097</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15689528</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004633-Anisimova1"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anisimova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Approximate likelihood-ratio test for branches: a fast, accurate, and powerful alternative.</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><comment>DOI 10.1080/10635150600755453</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16785212</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>The authors have no support or funding to report.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>