<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JO</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Oncology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1687-8450</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1687-8469</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19266089</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2648644</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2008/478325</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Clear Cell Adenocarcinoma Arising from   Abdominal Wall Endometriosis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Achach</surname><given-names>Thouraya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rammeh</surname><given-names>Soumaya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Trabelsi</surname><given-names>Amel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ltaief</surname><given-names>Rached</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ben Abdelkrim</surname><given-names>Soumaya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mokni</surname><given-names>Moncef</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Korbi</surname><given-names>Sadok</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Pathology, University Teaching Hospital Farhat Hached, Sousse 4000, Tunisia</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Surgery, University Teaching Hospital Farhat Hached, Sousse 4000, Tunisia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Soumaya Ben Abdelkrim: <email>benabdelkrims@voila.fr</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Recommended by Edward A. Copelan</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>2008</volume><elocation-id>478325</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Thouraya Achach et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Endometriosis is a frequent benign disorder. Malignancy arising in extraovarian endometriosis is a rare event. A 49-year-old woman is presented with a large painful abdominal wall mass. She underwent a myomectomy, 20 years before, for uterus leiomyoma. Computed tomography suggested that this was a desmoid tumor and she underwent surgery. Histological examination showed a clear cell adenocarcinoma associated with endometriosis foci. Pelvic ultrasound, computed tomography, and endometrial curettage did not show any malignancy or endometriosis in the uterus and ovaries. Adjuvant chemotherapy was recommended, but the patient was lost to follow up. Six months later, she returned with a recurrence of the abdominal wall mass. She was given chemotherapy and then she was reoperated.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="section" id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Endometriosis  isa frequent benign  disorder. Several observations of the coexistence of endometriosisand cancer have been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Malignancy arising in extraovarian endometriosisis a rare event [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Here, we report a case of clear cell adenocarcinoma derived frompathologically confirmed endometriosis in the abdominal wall. We discuss theepidemiological and clinicopathological features of malignancy arising inabdominal wall endometriosis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec2"><title>2. Case Report</title><p>A 49 year-old woman,gravida 3, para 0, underwent a myomectomy, 20 years before, for uterusleiomyoma through a midline incision. She is presented with a painful large abdominal wallmass. On physical examination, a firm indurated mass was palpated in the lowerabdominal wall. Abdominal and pelvic ultrasounds followed by computed tomography showed aheterogeneous intramuscular mass of 8.5 cm diameter without local extension (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). The clinical impression was of desmoid tumor and the patient taken tosurgery and the tumor was resected without rupture. The surgeon did not performany peritoneal washing or biopsies because of the absence of widespread tumorin the peritoneal cavity. The surgical specimen consisted of 11 cm cutaneous andmuscular tissues, occupied by ill-defined white tumor, which contained cysticcavities and abundant foci of necrosis. Surgical margins were positive. Microscopically, the tumor showed a predominant papillary and tubulocysticgrowth pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). The tumor cells were round or polygonal most withhobnail configuration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). The cytoplasm was clear, and the nuclei wereround with prominent nucleoli. Cellular atypia was moderate, and mitosis was rare. Benignendometriotic foci were observed in the proximity of the tumor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). Immunohistochemically,tumor cells showed diffuse and strong cytoplasmic positivity with vimentin,epithelial membrane antigen, and cytokeratin 7, but no staining for cytokeratin20 progesterone and estrogen receptor. Calretinin and mesothelin were negative. Pelvic ultrasound and computed tomography identified normal-sized ovaries anduterus. Endometrial curettage was negative for malignancy.</p><p>The diagnosis  ofclear cell adenocarcinoma arising from abdominal endometriosis foci wasretained. Adjuvant chemotherapy was indicated, but the patient was lost tofollow up. She returned six months after. At that time, ultrasound and computedtomography showed a recurrent mass at the abdominal wall with extension to thebladder. Three cycles of combination chemotherapy with cyclophosphamide and cisplatinwere given, but the tumor did not regress. She underwent surgery again with aresection of 5 cm encapsulated nodule. At that time, uterus, ovaries, and tubesdid not show any abnormalities. Histology demonstrated the same type of tumor. Margins were free of tumor. Three cycles of chemotherapy were also given butfailed to control the disease; the chemotherapy she got is not precised. Thecomputed tomography showed again a recurrent mass with extension to the bladderand pelvic bone, and adjuvant radiotherapy was indicated.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec3"><title>3. Discussion</title><p>Endometriosis,defined as the presence of endometrial-like tissue outside the uterine cavity,is usually located in the ovaries and pelvic peritoneum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Parietalendometriosis is very rare and constitutes 1 to 2% of endometriosis cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. It arises usually in a surgical scar of cesarean section or hysterectomy, andless frequently in a surgical scar of hernia or of appendicectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Casesof endometriosis without scar have been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The incidence of abdominal wall endometriomas is of 0.04% amongparturients undergoing cesarean section and it is more frequent thanendometriosis following conventional gynaecologic surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. In our case,abdominal wall endometriosis occurred in a surgical midline scar of myomectomy. The etiopathogenetic mechanism is more likely related to iatrogenictransplantation of endometrium during gynecological surgery rather than hematogenousdissemination or metaplasia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Clinical diagnosis remains difficult, and manypatients are asymptomatic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Symptoms related to pelvic endometriosis arenoted in 26% of cases. Ultrasound can show a cystic lesion in many cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Women with pelvic endometriosis have a higher frequency of malignancy, butmalignant change in extrapelvic endometriosis is a rare event [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Twenty percent of malignancy in endometriosis occurs in extragonadal site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. There is extensive clinicopathological, molecular, and genetic evidencesupporting the hypothesis that endometriosis is a neoplastic process with apotential for malignant transformation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The natural course of malignanttransformation of endometriosis is long and can be explained by estrogenicstimulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Malignanttransformation  in endometriosis was first described by Sympson in 1925 in   [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], whoproposed three criteria for diagnosis: demonstration of a clear example of theendometriosis in proximity to the tumor, no other primary site for the tumor,and histologic appearance consistent with an origin from endometriosis. Scottin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] recommended the presence of transitional area between endometriosis andcancer. Atypical endometriosis, a term first coined by LaGrenade and Silvergergin 1988 in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], is rare and is characterized by endometriotic glands with cytologicaland/or architectural atypia (hyperchromatic or pale nuclei with moderate to markedpleomorphism increased nuclear to cytoplasmic ratio, cellular crowding, stratification,or tufting). The rate of atypical endometriosis ranges from 1.7 to 3.6% in ovarian endometriosis[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Fukunaga et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] demonstrated that atypical endometriosis in ovary isoften associated with epithelial neoplasm and showed direct transition fromatypical epithelium to malignant tumor. In our case, the criteria of Sympsonwere fully satisfied. The demonstration of endometriosis might require theexamination of multiple levels and sections, that is why preoperative biopsy cannotmake the diagnosis of malignancy arising in endometriosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Tumors that canarise in endometriosis include in decreasing order: endometrio id carcinoma(75.9&#x02013;69.1%), sarcoma(25&#x02013;11.6%), clearcell carcinoma (13.5&#x02013;4.5%), andmucinous or serous carcinoma (4.6%&#x02013;1%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Inextrapelvic localization, clear cell carcinoma is the most common histologicalsubtype, followed by endometrioid carcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Due to the rarity of malignanttransformation of endometriosis at extragonadal sites, it is difficult toestablish a treatment protocol. First-line treatment is surgery, removing asmuch endometriosis as possible, staging at this point is also necessary. Second-line treatment, with chemotherapy, radiotherapy, and even hormonotherapymay be needed. Prognosis is variable from 10 to 100% five-year survival,depending on histological type and localization of the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec4"><title>4. Conclusion</title><p>Cutaneouslocalization of endometriosis is unusual and appears most frequently insurgical scars from obstetric or gynecological interventions. It is importantto recognize the possibility of tumors arising from endometriosis when thepathologist is confronted to an extraovarian tumor with endometrial appearance. Examination of multiple sections is required to demonstrate endometriosis foci.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sergent</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Cornec</surname><given-names>J-B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marpeau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title xml:lang="FR">Malignant transformation of abdominal wall endometriosis: a new case report</article-title><source><italic>Journal de Gynecologie Obstetrique et Biologie de la Reproduction</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>190</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Spar&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergqvist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endometriosis and the risk of cancer with special emphasis on ovarian cancer</article-title><source><italic>Human Reproduction</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1237</fpage><lpage>1242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16431901</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollason</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endometriosis and the neoplastic process</article-title><source><italic>Reproduction</italic></source><year>2004</year><volume>127</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15016949</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamblin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathevet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Buenerd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endom&#x000e9;triose pari&#x000e9;tale sur cicatrice abdominale. <italic>&#x000c0;</italic> propos de 3 observations</article-title><source><italic>Journal de Gynecologie Obstetrique et Biologie de la Reproduction</italic></source><year>1999</year><volume>28</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>274</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abdominal wall endometriomas</article-title><source><italic>International Journal of Gynecology and Obstetrics</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>90</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040035</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCluggage</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Toner</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvert</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clear cell adenocarcinoma of the colon arising in endometriosis: a rare variant of primary colonic adenocarcinoma</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Pathology</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11271795</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paillocher</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pessaux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Catala</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Malignant tumors arising in extra-ovarian endometriosis: a case report</article-title><source><italic>Journal de Gynecologie Obstetrique et Biologie de la Reproduction</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>503</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carcinosarcoma arising from atypical endometriosis in a cesarean section scar</article-title><source><italic>International Journal of Gynecological Cancer</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16445672</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kusaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikuni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A case of high-grade endometrial stromal sarcoma arising from endometriosis in the cul-de-sac</article-title><source><italic>International Journal of Gynecological Cancer</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16681780</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiserowitz</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumbs</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Oi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endometriosis-related malignancies</article-title><source><italic>International Journal of Gynecological Cancer</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12911723</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chene</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Darcha</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dechelotte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mage</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Canis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Malignant degeneration of perineal endometriosis in episiotomy scar, case report and review of the literature</article-title><source><italic>International Journal of Gynecological Cancer</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17300680</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Malignant transformation of residual endometriosis in women on unopposed oestrogen hormone replacement therapy</article-title><source><italic>British Journal of Obstetrics and Gynaecology</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1106</fpage><lpage>1107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11702846</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ushigome</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ovarian atypical endometriosis: its close association with malignant epithelial tumours</article-title><source><italic>Histopathology</italic></source><year>1997</year><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9088954</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Computed tomograms of the abdomen show a heterogeneous and ill-defined tumor in the abdominalwall.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JO2008-478325.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Tubulocystic andpapillary pattern (hematoxylineosin, original magnification &#x000d7;200).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JO2008-478325.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Tumorcells with hobnail configuration (hematoxylin eosin, original magnification  &#x000d7;400).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JO2008-478325.003"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Endometrial gland invaded by tumor cells (hematoxylin eosin, original magnification&#x000d7;400).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JO2008-478325.004"/></fig></floats-wrap></article>