<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Mol Signal</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Molecular Signaling</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1750-2187</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19055777</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2648954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1750-2187-3-20</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-2187-3-20</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Differential role of beta-arrestin ubiquitination in agonist-promoted down-regulation of M<sub>1 </sub><italic>vs </italic>M<sub>2 </sub>muscarinic acetylcholine receptors</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mosser</surname><given-names>Valerie A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>vamosser@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Kymry T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>kymry_j@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>Katie M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Katie.Hoffman@umontana.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCarty</surname><given-names>Nael A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>nael_mccarty@oz.ped.emory.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>Darrell A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>darrell.jackson@umontana.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Biomedical and Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Health Professions and Biomedical Science, Skaggs Building Room 376, The University of Montana, Missoula, MT 59812, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>School of Biology, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, 30332, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmolecularsignaling.com/content/3/1/20"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Mosser et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mosser et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Mosser               A               Valerie                              vamosser@yahoo.com            </dc:author><dc:title>            Differential role of beta-arrestin ubiquitination in agonist-promoted down-regulation of M1 vs M2 muscarinic acetylcholine receptors         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Molecular Signaling 3(1): 20-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1750-2187(2008)3:1&#x0003c;20&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1750-2187</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Sustained agonist-promoted ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin has been correlated with increased stability of the GPCR &#x02013; &#x003b2;-arrestin complex. Moreover, abrogation of &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination has been reported to inhibit receptor internalization with minimal effects on receptor degradation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Herein we report that agonist activation of M<sub>1 </sub>mAChRs produces a sustained &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination but no stable co-localization with &#x003b2;-arrestin. In contrast, sustained ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin by activation of M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs does result in stable co-localization between the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and &#x003b2;-arrestin. Internalization of receptors was unaffected by proteasome inhibitors, but down-regulation was significantly reduced, suggesting a role for the ubiquitination machinery in promoting down-regulation of the receptors. Given the ubiquitination status of &#x003b2;-arrestin following agonist treatment, we sought to determine the effects of &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination on M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR down-regulation. A constitutively ubiquitinated &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 chimera in which ubiquitin is fused to the C-terminus of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 (YFP-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2-Ub) significantly increased agonist-promoted down-regulation of both M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs, with the effect substantially higher on the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR. Based on this observation, we were interested in examining the effects of disruption of potential ubiquitination sites in the &#x003b2;-arrestin sequence on receptor down-regulation. Agonist-promoted internalization of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR was not affected by expression of &#x003b2;-arrestin lysine mutants lacking putative ubiquitination sites, &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>, while down-regulation and stable co-localiztion of the receptor with this &#x003b2;-arrestin lysine mutant were significantly reduced. Interestingly, expression of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>increased the agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR but did not result in a stable co-localiztion of the receptor with this &#x003b2;-arrestin lysine mutant.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>These findings indicate that ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin has a distinct role in the differential trafficking and degradation of M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>There are five subtypes of muscarinic acetylcholine receptors (M<sub>1 </sub>&#x02013; M<sub>5 </sub>mAChR) with distinct yet overlapping tissue distributions. Muscarinic receptors regulate a variety of physiological responses ranging from cardiac homeostasis to cholinergic signaling in the brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. A common feature of mAChRs, and in fact all GPCRs, is that both their expression and activation are tightly regulated. Agonist-promoted trafficking of mAChRs, and most other GPCRs can be broken down into five distinct phases: agonist-binding promotes G protein dissociation (I) from the receptor which allows phosphorylation of specific serine and threonine residues (II) on internal loops of the receptor by G protein receptor kinases (GRKs). This phosphorylation allows the binding of &#x003b2;-arrestins (III) which promotes homologous desensitization and subsequent internalization of the receptor into clathrin coated pits. Following internalization, the receptor can either be dephosphorylated and recycled (IV) to the cell surface or targeted for degradation (V) in proteasomes or lysosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>&#x003b2;-arrestins have emerged as a central control point in the trafficking of nearly all GPCRs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. In addition to mediating desensitization of GPCRs, &#x003b2;-arrestin also participates in clathrin-dependent endocytosis of activated receptors by directly interacting with clathrin and the clathrin-associated adaptor AP-2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Once internalized, &#x003b2;-arrestins are involved in regulation of post-endocytotic trafficking and recently have been shown to function as scaffolding proteins interacting with cellular trafficking machinery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p><p>Initial reports examining the role of &#x003b2;-arrestin, clathrin and dynamin indicated that agonist-promoted internalization of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR proceeded via both arrestin-dependent and -independent pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Later work, however, indicated the essential role of &#x003b2;-arrestin in M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR internalization, and suggested that all M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR internalization, like other mAChR subtypes, is dynamin-dependent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><p>Two classes of GPCRs have been identified with respect to kinetics of receptor recycling and interaction with &#x003b2;-arrestins. Class A receptors, such as the &#x003b2;<sub>2 </sub>adrenergic (&#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>AR), dopamine D1A and endothelin 1A receptors recycle rapidly and dissociate from &#x003b2;-arrestin prior to receptor internalization. Class B receptors, such as the vasopressin 2 (V2R), angiotensin 1a and neurotensin 1 receptors, recycle slowly and internalize in a stable association with &#x003b2;-arrestin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Recently, it has become clear that the classification of receptors as A or B directly correlates with patterns of &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination and deubiquitination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Stimulation of Class A &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>ARs leads to transient ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin with deubiquitination occurring shortly (minutes) after internalization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In contrast, stimulation of Class B V2Rs leads to a stable ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p><p>Ubiquitination of proteins is a signal for degradation that leads to delivery to and degradation of proteins in the 26S proteasome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. There are a number of examples where ubiquitination has been shown to be involved in the regulation of GPCRs, including the opiod receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], yeast pheromone receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], human immunodeficiency virus co-receptor CXCR4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], and &#x003b2;<sub>2 </sub>ARs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>Class A receptors, which do not internalize with &#x003b2;-arrestin, display a pattern of transient &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination. Class B receptors, on the other hand, do internalize with &#x003b2;-arrestin, and display a sustained &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination pattern [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Shenoy <italic>et al. </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] showed that agonist stimulation led to the ubiquitination of both &#x003b2;-arrestin and the &#x003b2;<sub>2 </sub>AR. Their data suggested that it was the ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin that was involved in the initial receptor internalization step whereas ubiquitination of the receptor itself was required for subsequent receptor degradation.</p><p>In the present study, we wanted to address several questions regarding the role of &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination in the agonist-promoted down-regulation of mAChRs. First we wanted to determine if there was a role for &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination in receptor down-regulation. Collectively, our data support a role for &#x003b2;-arrestin in differential targeting of mAChRs towards down-regulation. In addition, the data indicate that this differential targeting may be controlled by preferential interaction of mAChR subtypes with the different &#x003b2;-arrestin subtypes which in turn may be mediated by specific patterns of &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>For a number of years there has been some controversy as to the role of &#x003b2;-arrestin in M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR specific internalization and down-regulation. Our recent publication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] established the essential role of &#x003b2;-arrestin in the internalization of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR. The current study is a follow up which not only addresses the role of &#x003b2;-arrestin in agonist-promoted mAChR down-regulation, but also indicates a differential role for &#x003b2;-arrestin in M<sub>1 </sub>versus M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR down-regulation. As in the previous study, we performed our down-regulation experiments in mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) derived from &#x003b2;-arrestin 1/2 double knockout mice (MEF KO1/2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Experiments performed using this cell line offer a significant advantage over previous studies of the role of &#x003b2;-arrestin in GPCR internalization and down-regulation that used dominant-negative or knockdown strategies because they avoid any possible complications that could arise from the presence of low levels of endogenous arrestin proteins. These cells have been characterized to confirm the absence of mAChR expression using both PCR and radioligand binding assays [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><p>To determine whether or not MEF cells could be used in the current study, we performed agonist-promoted down-regulation time courses for both the M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR subtypes. Total receptor numbers were measured using the non-selective membrane permeable muscarinic antagonist quinuclidinyl benzilate (QNB), which binds to both surface and intracellular pools of mAChR. Wild-type MEF cells that were transfected with either eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR resulted in similar expression levels (~4000 fmol/mg). After 24 hr, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for the indicated time. Maximal down-regulation of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR occurred after 6 hr of stimulation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). In contrast, maximal down-regulation of the M<sub>1 </sub>subtype did not occur until after 12 hr of carbachol stimulation. In addition, M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs were maximally decreased by only 22% while the M<sub>1 </sub>subtype was decreased by 55%. These results demonstrate that exogenously expressed M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs undergo agonist-promoted down-regulation in MEFwt cells. The different time course and extent of down-regulation suggest the possibility that down-regulation of the two subtypes may involve distinct pathways. Despite the fact that M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs were maximally down-regulated by 6 hr of stimulation, subsequent single time point experiments used the 12 hr time point so that the M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>subtype experiments would be compared at a standardized time point.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Time-course of agonist-promoted down-regulation of mAChRs in MEF</bold>. MEF wt cells were transfected with eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>(&#x025c6;) or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>(&#x025a0;) mAChR. 24 hr following transfection, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for the indicated time. Down-regulation was determined using [<sup>3</sup>H]-QNB binding (fmol/mg protein) in crude membranes as described in methods. The M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR displays nearly threefold the down-regulation of the M<sub>2 </sub>subtype over the same time course. Data are expressed as percent down-regulation compared to t = 0 control and are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean for three independent experiments with duplicate data points. Total mAChR expressed (fmol/mg) at t = 0 was 4000 for both M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-1"/></fig><p>Several recent studies have reported that mAChR down-regulation occurs independently of agonist-promoted internalization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Recently, we demonstrated that agonist-promoted internalization of M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs in MEF cells was &#x003b2;-arrestin dependent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. To examine whether or not agonist-promoted down-regulation of M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs is &#x003b2;-arrestin dependent, we performed down-regulation studies in MEF &#x003b2;-arrestin double knockout cells transiently expressing either M<sub>1 </sub>or M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and either FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 1 or 2. After 24 hr, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 12 hr. In the absence of exogenous &#x003b2;-arrestin, there was no down-regulation in response to agonist stimulation in the double knockout cell line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A&#x02013;D</xref>). Expression of either &#x003b2;-arrestin 1 or &#x003b2;-arrestin 2, however, rescued down-regulation of both receptor subtypes in response to agonist (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A &#x02013; D</xref>). These results demonstrate that agonist-promoted down-regulation of M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs is &#x003b2;-arrestin dependent.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Rescue of mAChR down-regulation in MEF KO1/2 with &#x003b2;-arrestin 1 or 2</bold>. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR (<bold>A-B</bold>) or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR (<bold>C-D</bold>) and either FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 1 (<bold>top</bold>) or 2 (<bold>bottom</bold>). 24 hr following transfection, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 12 hr. Down-regulation was determined using [<sup>3</sup>H]-QNB binding (fmol/mg protein) in crude membranes as described in methods. No down-regulation occurs in the absence of &#x003b2;-arrestin and either isoform (&#x003b2;-arrestin 1 or 2) rescues both constitutive and agonist-promoted down-regulation. Data are expressed as percent of [<sup>3</sup>H]-QNB bound (fmol/mg total protein) compared to untreated, no &#x003b2;-arrestin control and are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean from three independent experiments with duplicate data points. Statistical analysis was performed using a paired t-test. *: p &#x02264; 0.05 versus the untreated, no &#x003b2;-arrestin control. Total M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR expressed (fmol/mg) at t = 0 was 400 &#x02013; 900 (M<sub>1</sub>) and 1000 &#x02013; 2000 (M<sub>2</sub>) for both the &#x003b2;-arrestin 1 and &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 rescue experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-2"/></fig><p>Recent studies have demonstrated that agonist stimulation of GPCRs results in ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. This group demonstrated receptor specific agonist-promoted ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 that was either transient (peaked at 1 min of agonist stimulation) or stable (still present after 15 min of agonist stimulation) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. We performed experiments in order to determine if agonist stimulation of M<sub>1 </sub>or M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs promoted the ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin and if so, examine whether the observed ubiquitination was transient or stable. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2 and eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and treated with carbachol for 0, 1, 3, 15 and 30 min. Stimulation of M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs significantly increased ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). This increase is clearly visible at both the 15 and 30 min time point for both mAChR subtypes. These results demonstrate that stimulation of M<sub>1 </sub>or M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs promotes a stable ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Agonist treatment promotes ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 in MEF KO1/2 cells expressing the mAChRs and &#x003b2;-arrestin 2</bold>. MEF KO1/2 cells transfected with FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2 and either eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR. 24 hr following transfection, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for the indicated times. Top panel: cells were lysed and immunoprecipitated (IP) with anti-FLAG MAb and blotted (IB) with anti-ubiquitin-MAb. There was an increase in ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 with increasing exposure to 1 mM carbachol. Each blot is representative of two independent experiments. <bold>Bottom panel</bold>: lysates blotted with anti-FLAG MAb to demonstrate &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 expression levels.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-3"/></fig><p>Having established that &#x003b2;-arrestin is required for mAChR down-regulation and that muscarinic stimulation leads to the ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin, we wanted to examine if there was a direct role for &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination in receptor down-regulation. Since ubiquitination is known to serve as a signal for protein degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] we were interested in determining whether disruption of the ubiquitin/proteasome pathway would affect the agonist-promoted down-regulation of the mAChRs. To confirm that &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 promotes down-regulation via a ubiquitin dependent pathway, we examined agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR in the presence of the proteosomal inhibitor lactacystin (impairs ubiquitin recycling). MEFwt cells were transfected with HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and after 24 hr cells were incubated for 20 min with or without 10 &#x003bc;M lactacystin prior to treatment with 1 mM carbachol for 4 hr. Lactacystin was able to completely block agonist-promoted down-regulation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>) suggesting that the ubiquitination machinery has a role in mediating agonist-promoted down-regulation of mAChRs.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>The proteosomal inhibitor lactacystin inhibits the &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 mediated agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR in MEFwt</bold>. MEFwt cells were transfected with HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and, after 24 hr cells were incubated for 20 min with or without 10 &#x003bc;M lactacystin then treated with 1 mM carbachol for 4 hr. Lactacystin inhibits the &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 mediated down-regulation of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR receptor in response to agonist. Down-regulation was determined using [<sup>3</sup>H]-QNB binding in crude membranes as described in methods. Data are expressed as [<sup>3</sup>H]-QNB bound (fmol/mg total protein) and are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from three independent experiments with duplicate data points. Statistical analysis was performed using a paired t-test, ** indicates p &#x02264; 0.001 (compared to paired untreated control), ns indicates not significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-4"/></fig><p>To determine whether or not the effects of lactacystin were occurring at the level of receptor internalization, we examined the effect of lactacystin on the agonist-promoted internalization of mAChRs using the membrane impermeable muscarinic antagonist <italic>N</italic>-methylscopolamine (NMS). MEFwt cells were transfected with HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR, and after 24 hr cells were incubated for 20 min in the absence or presence of 10 &#x003bc;M lactacystin prior to treatment with 1 mM carbachol for 30 min. Pretreatment with inhibitor had no effect on agonist-promoted internalization (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). These results indicate that agonist-promoted down-regulation of mAChRs involves receptor &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>The proteosomal inhibitor lactacystin does not affect agonist-promoted down-regulation internalization of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR in MEFwt</bold>. MEFwt cells were transfected with HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and, after 24 hr cells were incubated for 20 min with or without 10 &#x003bc;M lactacystin then treated with 1 mM carbachol for 30 min. Lactacystin has no effect on the internalization of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR receptor in response to agonist. Internalization was determined using [<sup>3</sup>H]-NMS binding in whole cells as described in methods. Data are [<sup>3</sup>H]-NMS bound per well (plated at 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>cells) and are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from three independent experiments with duplicate data points. Statistical analysis was performed using a paired t-test, * indicates p &#x02264; 0.05; (compared to paired untreated control), ns indicates not significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-5"/></fig><p>To examine the consequences of &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination on receptor down-regulation, we expressed a yellow fluorescent protein-tagged &#x003b2;-arrestin 2-ubiquitin chimera that cannot be deubiquitinated by cellular deubiquitinases (YFP-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2-Ub) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and either FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2 or YFP-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2-Ub. After 24 hr, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 12 hr. There was a 40% agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR by &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 alone which increased to 70% in the presence of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2-Ub (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). These values were 62 and 95%, respectively, for the M<sub>2 </sub>subtype (Figure7). &#x003b2;-arrestin 2-Ub also increased the constitutive receptor down-regulation, and again the effect was much larger for the M<sub>2 </sub>(90%) <italic>vs </italic>M<sub>1 </sub>(50%) subtype (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). It is clear from these data that ubiquitination enhanced the ability of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 to mediate both constitutive and agonist-promoted down-regulation of both the M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Expression of a chimeric ubiquitinated form of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 enhances the agonist-promoted down-regulation of M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs in MEF KO1/2</bold>. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>(<bold>A</bold>) or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>(<bold>B</bold>) mAChRs and either no &#x003b2;-arrestin, FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2 or YFP-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2-Ub. 24 hr following transfection, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 12 hr. Down-regulation was determined using [<sup>3</sup>H]-QNB binding (fmol/mg protein) in crude membranes as described in methods. Expression of the constitutively ubiquitinated form of &#x003b2;-arrestin (&#x003b2;-arrestin 2-Ub) had a greater effect on down-regulation of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR compared to the M<sub>1 </sub>subtype. Data are expressed as percent of [<sup>3</sup>H]-QNB bound compared to the untreated control with no &#x003b2;-arrestin and are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from two independent experiments with duplicate data points. Statistical analysis was performed using a repeated measures ANOVA with Bonferroni post test; * indicates p &#x02264; 0.05 and ** indicates p &#x02264; 0.001 (compared to untreated, no &#x003b2;-arrestin control), ns indicates not significant. Total mAChR expressed (fmol/mg) in the absence of &#x003b2;-arrestin was 1000 &#x02013; 2000 for both receptor subtypes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-6"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>differentially affects down-regulation of M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs in MEF KO1/2</bold>. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>(<bold>A</bold>) mAChR or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>(<bold>B</bold>) mAChR and either empty vector (control), FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2 (WT), FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>or FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R</sup>. 24 hr after transfection, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 12 hr. Down-regulation was determined in crude membranes (fmol/mg protein) as described in methods. All &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 constructs were able to mediate agonist-promoted down-regulation of mAChR with the exception of the &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>mutant when co-expressed with the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR. Data are expressed as percent of [<sup>3</sup>H]-QNB bound (compared to untreated, no &#x003b2;-arrestin control) and presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from three independent experiments with duplicate or quadruplicate data points. Statistical analysis was performed using a repeated measures ANOVA with Bonferroni post test; * indicates p &#x02264; 0.05 ** indicates p &#x02264; 0.001 (compared to untreated, no &#x003b2;-arrestin control), ns indicates not significant. Total M<sub>1 </sub>(300&#x02013;500 fmol/mg) and M<sub>2 </sub>(1500&#x02013;2500 fmol/mg) mAChR expressed in the absence of &#x003b2;-arrestin constructs was similar.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-7"/></fig><p>Having demonstrated a role for ubiquitin in agonist-promoted mAChR degradation, we were interested in the effects of disrupting &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 ubiquitination on receptor down-regulation. Several lysine residues on &#x003b2;-arrestin are known to be sites of ubiquitination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. To further confirm the essential role of ubiquitination in agonist-promoted down-regulation, we examined the ability of specific &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 lysine mutants to mediate agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and either empty vector (control), FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2 (wild-type), FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>or FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R</sup>. After 24 hr, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 12 hr. As shown previously, there was no down-regulation in the control cells in the absence of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). All three &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 constructs were able to rescue agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>1 </sub>subtype. We also noted a large constitutive effect on down-regulation with both mutant &#x003b2;-arrestins. In contrast, for the M<sub>2 </sub>subtype only wild-type &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 (24%) and &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R </sup>(27%) were able to rescue agonist-promoted down-regulation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>, had lost the ability to rescue agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>).</p><p>Since it was possible that the effect of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>on M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR down-regulation seen in the previous experiment was actually occurring at the receptor internalization step, we performed receptor internalization experiments with [<sup>3</sup>H]-NMS. Transfections were identical to the previous experiment. After 24 hr, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 1 hr. All &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 constructs (wild-type or lysine mutants) were able to rescue agonist-promoted internalization of M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs in MEF KO1/2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Agonist-promoted internalization of M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR is unaffected by &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 lysine mutants in MEF KO1/2</bold>. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and either empty vector (control), FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2 (WT), FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>or FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R</sup>. 24 hr after transfection, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 1 hr. Internalization was determined in whole cells (receptors/cell) as described in methods. All constructs were able to mediate agonist-promoted internalization. Data are expressed as percent of [<sup>3</sup>H]-NMS bound compared to untreated control and presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from three independent experiments with duplicate data points. Statistical analysis was performed using a repeated measures ANOVA with Bonferroni post test; * indicates p &#x02264; 0.05 (compared to untreated, no &#x003b2;-arrestin control), ns indicates not significant. Total receptor expressed in the presence of all four &#x003b2;-arrestin constructs was between 5 and 6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>receptor/cell.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-8"/></fig><p>Since &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>not only appears to interfere with the agonist promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR but also increased the constitutive down-regulation of the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR we examined the ability of this mutant to co-localize with the M<sub>1</sub>/M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR compared to wt and &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R </sup>following agonist stimulation. MEF KO1/2 were plated on cover slips in 6-well plates. 24 hrs after transfection with eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR or HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and FLAG tagged &#x003b2;-arrestin (wt or lysine mutants) cells were treated for 30 min or 12 hrs with 1 mM carbachol. Cells were fixed and processed for indirect immunofluorescence as described in methods. After 30 minutes of agonist exposure there is clear overlap of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR receptor and &#x003b2;-arrestin signal signified by the yellow puncta (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>) for the wt and &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11, K12R</sup>. This overlap is absent with &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>which indicates a disrupted or impaired interaction between this &#x003b2;-arrestin mutant and the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR. Surprisingly, despite our previous observation of the effects of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>on constitutive M<sub>1 </sub>down-regulation, no co-localization was observed between &#x003b2;-arrestin and the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><bold>&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>demonstrates impaired agonist-promoted co-localiztion with M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR in MEF KO1/2</bold>. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs (green) and either wild-type FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2, FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>or FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R </sup>(red). 24 hr after transfection, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 30 min. Cells were fixed, probed, and imaged as described in methods. Wild-type and &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R </sup>demonstrate co-localization with the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR which is significantly diminished with &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>. Image shown is representative of two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-9"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p><bold>&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>demonstrates no co-localization with M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR in MEF KO1/2</bold>. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with eGFP-M<sub>1 </sub>(A) mAChRs (green) and either wild-type FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2, FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>or FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R </sup>(red). 24 hr after transfection, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 30 min. Cells were fixed, probed, and imaged as described in methods. None of the &#x003b2;-arrestin constructs demonstrate co-localization with the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR. Image shown is representative of two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-10"/></fig><p>Finally we used immunocytochemistry with the lysosomal marker LAMP-1 to examine the effects of the &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>mutant on mAChR lysosomal targeting down-regulation. MEF KO1/2 were transfected with HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and either empty vector (control), FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2 (wild-type), FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R </sup>or FLAG&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>. After 24 hr, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 6 hr. There was significant co-localization of the receptor with LAMP-1 in the presence of wild-type &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 or &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R </sup>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>). It is clear, however, that &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>shows reduced co-localization of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR with LAMP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F11"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p><bold>&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>disrupts the co-localization of M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and LAMP-1 in MEF KO1/2</bold>. MEF KO1/2 cells were transfected with HA-M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and either wild-type FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2, FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>or FLAG-&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R</sup>. 24 hr after transfection, cells were treated with 1 mM carbachol for 6 hr. Cells were fixed, probed, and imaged as described in methods. &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>disrupts the co-localization of M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and LAMP-1 compared to wild-type and &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R</sup>. Image shown is representative of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1750-2187-3-20-11"/></fig><p>Collectively, these data indicate that the agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs involves differential sorting of the receptor by ubiquitinated &#x003b2;-arrestin.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Our recent work established the essential role of &#x003b2;-arrestin in the internalization of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The present study extends the observations of previous work and demonstrates that the agonist-promoted down-regulation of M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs is &#x003b2;-arrestin dependent, and that the ubiquitination pattern of &#x003b2;-arrestin has a critical role in the differential down-regulation for M<sub>1 </sub><italic>vs </italic>M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs.</p><p>It has been previously established in a variety of cell lines that a prolonged activation of M<sub>1 </sub>or M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs induces receptor down-regulation. In agreement with these findings, long-term stimulation of M<sub>1 </sub>or M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs induced receptor down-regulation with the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR showing significantly more down-regulation than M<sub>2 </sub>subtype. This observation suggests that the two subtypes are differentially regulated by endogenous &#x003b2;-arrestins. No down-regulation of either mAChR subtype occurred in the absence of &#x003b2;-arrestin and either &#x003b2;-arrestin subtype was able to rescue receptor down-regulation.</p><p>The observations of Shenoy and co-workers suggest that the ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin is a critical control point in the trafficking of different classes of GPCRs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. The time course of ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 in response to muscarinic stimulation in MEF KO1/2 cells transiently expressing the M<sub>1 </sub>or M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs was slow in onset and stable over time. This observation suggests that both M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs display a Class B &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination pattern despite the fact that the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR is known to recycle rapidly compared to M<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], and does not show a stable endocytotic co-localization with &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] &#x02013; both characteristics of Class A GPCRs. This observation suggests that there is some flexibility in the Class A <italic>vs </italic>B distinction. This same flexibility has been observed in the categorization of somatostatin receptor subtypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><p>To confirm that agonist-promoted down-regulation of mAChRs was ubiquitin-dependent we performed internalization/down-regulation experiments in the presence of the proteosomal inhibitor lactacystin. Lactacystin is a specific inhibitor of the 26S proteasome that functions by covalently modifying the active site and inhibiting the enzymatic activity of the proteasome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. This inhibition of the enzyme would inhibit recycling and thus deplete the available ubiquitin. Lactacystin was able to completely block agonist-promoted down-regulation with no effect on agonist-promoted internalization. These results suggested that the availability of free ubiquitin has a role in agonist-promoted down-regulation of the mAChRs. This effect is most likely due to effects on ubiquitin-dependent lysosomal sorting as evidenced by a later experiment that demonstrated the co-localization of the agonist-internalized M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR with the lysosomal membrane protein LAMP-1.</p><p>Having established that &#x003b2;-arrestin is ubiquitinated via mAChR activation, we then examined whether the ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin enhances its ability to mediate agonist-promoted down-regulation. M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR levels were reduced and M<sub>2 </sub>levels were nearly completely ablated in the presence of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2-Ub compared to wild-type &#x003b2;-arrestin. The effect was seen on both constitutive and agonist promoted down-regulation.</p><p>In order to examine the role of &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination in targeting mAChRs toward degradation, we used &#x003b2;-arrestin lysine mutants that have been previously shown to have a role in the endocytotic trafficking of other GPCRs. The constructs, generated by Shenoy and co-workers, contain mutations of potential ubiquitination sites near the amino terminus (&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R</sup>) and at five other sites in the protein (&#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. We were particularly interested in the possible differential effects of &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination patterns on M<sub>1 </sub><italic>vs </italic>M<sub>2 </sub>down-regulation given the fact that M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs did not fit neatly into the classical Class A <italic>vs </italic>B distinction.</p><p>Both of the &#x003b2;-arrestin lysine mutants were able to mediate agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR to the same extent as wild-type &#x003b2;-arrestin. While our data clearly indicates an essential role for &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination in M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR down-regulation, other lysine residues than the ones examined must be the targets for the necessary ubiquitination required for targeting the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChRs toward down-regulation. We did observe increased constitutive down-regulation of the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR with both mutant &#x003b2;-arrestin constructs. It is possible that the pattern of ubiquitination of these mutant &#x003b2;-arrestins altered the constitutive targeting of the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR toward lysosomal down-regulation. This observation is one of several in this study that suggests that the pattern of ubiquitination on &#x003b2;-arrestin is directly implicated in the downstream targeting of mAChRs. Previously it has been suggested that the only role for &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination is to promote the internalization of GPCRs.</p><p>We obtained surprisingly different results with the effects of the &#x003b2;-arrestin lysine mutants on the agonist-promoted down-regulation of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR subtype. Mutation of the two lysine residues in &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R </sup>had no effect on either agonist-promoted internalization or down-regulation of M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs. This result is similar to those seen with other Class B receptors such as the V2R and NK1R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. The results are different however from those seen with another Class B receptor, the AT1a receptor. When this receptor was co-expressed with &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R</sup>, agonist stimulation resulted in transient association of the receptor with &#x003b2;-arrestin 2, thus converting the receptor to a Class A type.</p><p>In contrast, the &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>mutant significantly reduced M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR degradation with no effect on receptor internalization. These results are similar to those seen with the Class B V2R, where &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>was shown to impair association of V2Rs with &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 on endosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p><p>The fact that &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>was able to internalize but not down-regulate the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR suggests that one or more of these lysines has a role in down-regulation but not internalization for this subtype. These data suggest a direct role for the ubiquitination state of &#x003b2;-arrestin in the lysosomal targeting of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR.</p><p>Unlike effects observed with the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR, &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>was able to mediate down-regulation of M<sub>1 </sub>mAChRs. This observation clearly demonstrates that the role of these lysines in down-regulation is subtype specific and that a specific pattern of ubiquitination on &#x003b2;-arrestin can differentially target the two mAChR subtypes for down-regulation.</p><p>Co-localization of wild-type and &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R </sup>with the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR, observed after 30 min of agonist treatment is absent with &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>which may indicate a disrupted or impaired interaction between this &#x003b2;-arrestin mutant and the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR. &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>was also shown to disrupt the co-localization of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR and the lysosomal marker LAMP-1 confirming our observation that &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>does not mediate the agonist-promoted degradation of the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR. Surprisingly, no co-localization of M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR was observed with any of the three &#x003b2;-arrestin constructs. Time points from 1 min to 12 hrs of carbachol treatment were performed to attempt to image co-localization between the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR and the &#x003b2;-arrestins (data not shown). This observation seems to indicate that the role of &#x003b2;-arrestin in M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR down-regulation may involve a transient interaction between &#x003b2;-arrestin and the receptor which fates the receptor toward degradation.</p><p>Our observations of M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR trafficking are different from the results of work with the Class A &#x003b2;<sub>2 </sub>AR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] which suggests that ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin is required for receptor internalization and that ubiquitination of the receptor itself is required for receptor degradation. Our data indicate that, for the M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR, the ubiquitination state of &#x003b2;-arrestin appears to have a role in the level of constitutive (agonist-independent) down-regulation and for the M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR the ubiquitination state of &#x003b2;-arrestin has a direct role in the agonist-promoted down-regulation of the receptor. Of the seven lysine residues we examined, at least one (or more) of the group 18, 107, 108, 207 and 296 are required for this M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR down-regulation. We also observed that M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR internalization was independent of &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination at these same lysine residues that have been shown to interfere with the association of &#x003b2;-arrestin with other Class B receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. The possibility that other lysine residues than those we examined are ubiquitinated in order to internalize the receptor would preserve the role for &#x003b2;-arrestin in receptor internalization. The absence of down-regulation of M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs with &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>however, clearly indicates a direct role for the ubiquitination of &#x003b2;-arrestin in receptor down-regulation.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We conclude that agonist-promoted down-regulation of both M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChRs is &#x003b2;-arrestin-dependent. We further conclude that this down-regulation is specifically modulated by the ubiquitination state of &#x003b2;-arrestin and that this &#x003b2;-arrestin ubiquitination differentially targets the receptor subtypes for degradation in lysosomes. Significantly, where it has been suggested that Class A GPCR down-regulation proceeds primarily via receptor ubiquitination, these data indicate that the ubiquitination state of &#x003b2;-arrestin 2 has an essential role in the differential targeting the M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR toward down-regulation. Future studies will examine the role of receptor ubiquitination in M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR down-regulation. Specifically, we will examine whether expression of wild type <italic>vs </italic>the &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>mutant differentially affects M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR ubiquitination and subsequent down-regulation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Reagents</title><p>[<sup>3</sup>H]-<italic>N</italic>-methylscopolamine -(81&#x02013;84 Ci/mmol) and [<sup>3</sup>H]-L-quinuclidinyl benzilate- (43 Ci/mmol) were purchased from Amersham Corporation (Buckinghamshire, England). LipofectAMINE 2000 and Protein A agarose were purchased from Invitrogen (Carlsbad, CA). Halt protease inhibitor and BCA protein assay kit were purchased from Pierce (Rockford, Il). Atropine, N-ethyl maleimide, carbamyl choline chloride, -anti-FLAG polyclonal antibody (F7425); polyclonal anti-LAMP1 antibody (L1418) and all other chemicals were purchased from Sigma Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). Anti-FLAG monoclonal antibody (200&#x02013;472) was purchased from Stratagene (La Jolla, CA). Monoclonal anti-HA antibody (MMS101R) was purchased from Covance (Berkeley, CA). Polyclonal anti-HA antibody (71&#x02013;5500) was purchased from Zymed (Carlsbad, CA). Monoclonal anti-Ub antibody P4D1 (sc 8017) was purchased from Santa Cruz Biotech (Santa Cruz, CA). Alexa 594 goat anti-mouse, Alexa 488 goat anti-Rabbit and Texas red goat anti-mouse (115-075-003) were purchased from Molecular Probes (Eugene, OR). FITC goat anti-rabbit (AP132F) was purchased from Chemicon (Temecula, CA). -HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies were purchased from Bio-Rad Laboratories (Hercules, CA). Prolong Gold Antifade (P36930) was purchased from Jackson Immuno Research (West Grove, PA.). pIRESeGFP were purchased from Clontech (Palo Alto CA).</p></sec><sec><title>Expression constructs and cell lines</title><p>Expression constructs and cell lines were generously provided by the following: MEF wild-type cells, &#x003b2;-arrestin 1 and 2 double knockout cells, FLAG-tagged &#x003b2;-arrestin 1 and 2, YFP-&#x003b2;-arrestin-2-Ub, &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R</sup>, and &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R </sup>(pcDNA3.1 FLAG &#x003b2;-arrestin 1 or 2, pEYFP &#x003b2;-Arr-Ub, pcDNA3.1 FLAG &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K11R, K12R</sup>, and pcDNA3.1 FLAG &#x003b2;-arrestin 2<sup>K18R, K107R, K108R, K207R, K296R</sup>) by Dr. Robert Lefkowitz (Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC); HA tagged human M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR (pRK HA M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR) by Dr. Audrey Claing (University of Montreal, Montreal Canada); eGFP tagged M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR (pCEP4eGFP M<sub>1 </sub>mAChR by Dr. Brigitte Ilien (University of Strasbourg, Strasbourg, France).</p></sec><sec><title>Cell culture and transient transfection</title><p>Mouse embryonic fibroblast (MEF) cells (wild-type and knockouts) were maintained in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium (DMEM). Media was supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 100 IU/mL penicillin, and 100 &#x003bc;g/mL streptomycin. All cells were maintained at 37&#x000b0;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. At 24 hr prior to transfection, cells were plated at 7.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>cells/well (12-well plate), 1.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>cells/well (6-well plate) and 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells/dish (100 mm dish). Cells were transfected using LipofectAMINE 2000 according to the manufacturer's protocol with 1.6, 5 or 25 &#x003bc;g total DNA per well/plate on a 12-well plate, 6-well plate and 100 mm dish, respectively. Transfection efficiencies of 40 &#x02013; 60% were routinely obtained [determined by including 10% of total DNA as eGFP construct (pIRESeGFP) and visualizing transfected cells using an Olympus 1X71 fluorescent microscope].</p></sec><sec><title>Crude membrane preparation</title><p>Two wells of a 6-well plate were rinsed twice with ice cold PBS and cells were scraped in 50 mM sodium phosphate pH 7.0, pooled and homogenized with 20 strokes through a Dounce homogenizer. Homogenate was spun at 10,000 rpm for 20 min at 4&#x000b0;C in a Sorvall Mach 1.6R fixed angle rotor. Pellet was resuspended in 50 mM sodium phosphate pH 7.0 and spun again. Pellet was resuspended in 0.55 mL 50 mM sodium phosphate pH 7.0 and used for protein assay and radioligand binding.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoprecipitation</title><p>At 24 hr post transfection, cells were lysed by sonication in HEPES lysis buffer (50 mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 1% Triton X-100, 10% glycerol, 10 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, 50 mM NaF, 10 mM N-ethyl maleimide, 1 &#x003bc;g/mL each leupeptin, aprotinin, and pepstatin A). Next, 500 &#x003bc;g (BCA) of lysate was precleared using Protein-A agarose beads for 4 hr at 4&#x000b0;C followed by incubation with 5 &#x003bc;g of monoclonal anti-FLAG antibody at 4&#x000b0;C overnight. The immunocomplex was incubated for 4 hr with 100 &#x003bc;L Protein-A beads (50% slurry) at 4&#x000b0;C with rotation. Beads were washed 3 &#x000d7; 500 &#x003bc;L in the same buffer and resuspended in 30 &#x003bc;l of Laemmli buffer and boiled for 5&#x02013;10 min. The immunocomplex was resolved on a 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) gradient gel.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoblotting</title><p>Lysates were prepared as described above and 10 &#x02013; 20 &#x003bc;g total protein was run on a 10% SDS-PAGE gel. Samples from immunoprecipitation or for direct immnuoblotting were transferred to nitrocellulose membranes, blocked with 5% powdered nonfat milk in Tris Buffered Saline, 0.1% Tween 20 (TBST) and probed with antibody as indicated. Immunoreactive bands were visualized with a Fuji imaging system using enhanced chemiluminescence after adding HRP conjugated secondary antibody.</p></sec><sec><title>Radioligand binding</title><sec><title>Internalization</title><p>Internalization was determined by measuring the binding of &#x02013; the membrane-impermeable muscarinic antagonist [<sup>3</sup>H]-<italic>N</italic>-methylscopolamine (NMS) to intact cells. Briefly, 24&#x02013;42 hr after transfection, MEF cells were treated or not treated with 1 mM carbachol for 30 min or 1 h at 37&#x000b0;C. Cultures were washed 3 &#x000d7; 1 mL with serum free media and incubated with 100 nM &#x02013; [<sup>3</sup>H]-NMS in 1 mL PBS for 30 min at 37&#x000b0;C or 4 hr at 4&#x000b0;C. Nonspecific binding was determined as the bound radioactivity in the presence of 1 &#x003bc;M atropine. Labeled cells were washed 3 &#x000d7; 1 mL with ice-cold PBS, solubilized in 0.5 mL 1% Triton-X-100, and combined with 3.5 mL scintillation fluid followed by measurement of radioactivity. Cpm were converted to receptors per well which were then corrected to receptors per cell by dividing by cells/well. Cells were counted using a standard haemocytometer. Receptor internalization is defined as percent of surface M<sub>2 </sub>mAChR not accessible to [<sup>3</sup>H]-NMS at each time relative to untreated or control cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Down-regulation</title><p>Down-regulation was determined by measuring the binding of the membrane permeable muscarinic antagonist [<sup>3</sup>H]-L-quinuclidinyl benzilate (QNB). Crude membranes (100 &#x003bc;L) were incubated with 30 nM [<sup>3</sup>H]-QNB in a total volume of 1 mL 50 mM sodium phosphate pH 7.0 for 2 hr at 25&#x000b0;C. Nonspecific binding was determined as the bound radioactivity in the presence of 1 &#x003bc;M atropine. Membranes were harvested on glass fiber filters using a Brandel cell harvester (Gaithersburg, MD) and washed 3 &#x000d7; 2 mL with ice cold 50 mM sodium phosphate pH 7.0. Filter discs were combined with 3.5 mL scintillation fluid followed by measurement of radioactivity.</p><p>Cpm per tube was converted to fmoles receptor, which was then corrected to mg of total protein per tube. Percent down-regulation was determined as percent of sites remaining compared to untreated control membranes.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Indirect immunofluorescence</title><sec><title>LAMP-1:M2 mAChR co-localization</title><p>Cells were fixed in 4% formaldehyde in PBS for 5 minutes, and rinsed with 10% fetal bovine serum and 0.02% azide in PBS (PBS/serum). Fixed cells were incubated with primary antibodies (1:1000 anti-LAMP1 and 1:500 anti-HA MAb) diluted in PBS/serum containing 0.2% saponin for 45 minutes, and then washed with PBS/serum (3 &#x000d7; 5 min.). The cells were then incubated with fluorescently labeled secondary antibodies (1:800 Alexa 488 goat anti-rabbit and Alexa 594 goat anti-mouse) in PBS-serum and 0.2% saponin for 45 minutes, washed with PBS/serum (3 &#x000d7; 5 min.) and once with PBS, and mounted on glass slides in prolong gold antifade.</p></sec><sec><title>FLAG-&#x003b2;-Arrestin 2:HA-M2 mAChR or eGFP-M1 mAChR co-localization</title><p>Cells were fixed in 4% formaldehyde in PBS for 5 minutes. Fixed cells were permeabilized for 5 minutes with 0.1% triton in PBS and washed 3 &#x000d7; with PBS and blocked in rabbit pre-immune sera (1:200 in PBS). Fixed cells were incubated with primary antibodies (1:500 anti HA PAb or 1:800 anti FLAG MAb) rinsed 3 &#x000d7; with PBS ad incubated with fluorescent secondary antibodies (1:1000 FITC goat anti-rabbit or 1:1000 Texas red goat anti-mouse). Coverslips were mounted on slides in prolong gold antifade. Images were acquired using an Olympus 1X71 inverted fluoresecent microscope equipped with a 60x oil immersion objective. Images were obtained with Olympus Image Manager (Center Valley, PA).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>AT1aR: angiotensin 1a receptor; &#x003b2;<sub>2 </sub>AR: &#x003b2;<sub>2 </sub>adrenergic receptor; CHO: Chinese hamster ovary cells; GPCR: G protein-coupled receptor; MAb: monoclonal antibody; mAChR: muscarinic acetylcholine receptor; MEF: mouse embryonic fibroblast; NK1R: neurokinin 1 receptor; NMS: <italic>N</italic>-methylscopolamine; PAb: polyclonal antibody; QNB: quinuclidinyl benzilate; V2R: vasopressin 2 receptor.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>VAM performed down-regulation, internalization, immunoblotting, participated in the design of the study and drafted the manuscript. KJTperformed down-regulation and immunocytochemistry. KMH performed immunocytochemistr. NAM was involved in critical revision of the manuscript. DAJ designed the study and participated in drafting and critical evaluation of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to acknowledge Sean M. Seagraves for technical assistance. This research was supported by National Institutes of Health Grants NS044164, P20 RR15583 and P20 RR017670</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Koppen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of muscarinic acetylcholine receptor signaling</article-title><source>Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2003</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12725869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0163-7258(03)00032-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Historical review: a brief history and personal retrospective of seven-transmembrane receptors</article-title><source>Trends Pharmacol Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15276710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tips.2004.06.006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>OB</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Krupnick</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Santini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Keen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Benovic</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beta-arrestin acts as a clathrin adaptor in endocytosis of the beta2-adrenergic receptor</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8837779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/383447a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laporte</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The beta2-adrenergic receptor/betaarrestin complex recruits the clathrin adaptor AP-2 during endocytosis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>3712</fpage><lpage>3717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10097102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.7.3712</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transduction of receptor signals by beta-arrestins</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>308</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1109237</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pals-Rylaarsdam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ptasienski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Benovic</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosey</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Internalization of the m2 muscarinic acetylcholine receptor. Arrestin-independent and -dependent pathways</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>23682</fpage><lpage>23689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9295310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.38.23682</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobs</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>van Koppen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of muscarinic acetylcholine receptor sequestration and function by beta-arrestin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>12333</fpage><lpage>12338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10212203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.18.12333</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werbonat</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleutges</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobs</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>van Koppen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential role of dynamin in internalization of M2 muscarinic acetylcholine and angiotensin AT1A receptors</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>21969</fpage><lpage>21974</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10801820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M001736200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Echeverry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosser</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agonist mediated internalization of M2 mAChR is beta-arrestin-dependent</article-title><source>J Mol Signal</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17224084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-2187-1-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Laporte</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of beta-arrestin with G protein-coupled receptors during clathrin-mediated endocytosis dictates the profile of receptor resensitization</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>32248</fpage><lpage>32257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10542263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.45.32248</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Anborgh</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Laporte</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular trafficking of G protein-coupled receptor/beta-arrestin endocytic complexes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>10999</fpage><lpage>11006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10196181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.16.10999</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trafficking patterns of beta-arrestin and G protein-coupled receptors determined by the kinetics of beta-arrestin deubiquitination</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>14498</fpage><lpage>14506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12574160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M209626200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hershko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciechanover</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ubiquitin system</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>1998</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9759494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.67.1.425</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Howells</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteasome involvement in agonist-induced down-regulation of mu and delta opioid receptors</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>12345</fpage><lpage>12355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M008054200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hicke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Riezman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitination of a yeast plasma membrane receptor signals its ligand-stimulated endocytosis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8565073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80982-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Benovic</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agonist-promoted ubiquitination of the G protein-coupled receptor CXCR4 mediates lysosomal sorting</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>45509</fpage><lpage>45512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C100527200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohout</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of receptor fate by ubiquitination of activated beta 2-adrenergic receptor and beta-arrestin</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>1307</fpage><lpage>1313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11588219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1063866</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohout</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>beta-Arrestin 1 and 2 differentially regulate heptahelical receptor signaling and trafficking</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>1601</fpage><lpage>1606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11171997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.041608198</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathanson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deletion analysis of the mouse m1 muscarinic acetylcholine receptor: effects on phosphoinositide metabolism and down-regulation</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1989</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>8946</fpage><lpage>8950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2557912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00448a039</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathanson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential role of the carboxyl-terminal tyrosine in down-regulation and sequestration of the m2 muscarinic acetylcholine receptor</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>15640</fpage><lpage>15645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8195213</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shockley</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Burford</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lameh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Residues specifically involved in down-regulation but not internalization of the m1 muscarinic acetylcholine receptor</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>1997</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9003046</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Receptor-specific ubiquitination of beta-arrestin directs assembly and targeting of seven-transmembrane receptor signalosomes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>15315</fpage><lpage>15324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15699045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M412418200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogatkewitsch</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wriske</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krummenerl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobs</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>van Koppen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Receptor subtype-specific regulation of muscarinic acetylcholine receptor sequestration by dynamin. Distinct sequestration of m2 receptors</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>12155</fpage><lpage>12160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9575162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.20.12155</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tulipano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stumm</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreienkamp</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential beta-arrestin trafficking and endosomal sorting of somatostatin receptor subtypes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>21374</fpage><lpage>21382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15001578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M313522200</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>