<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Adv Urol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AU</journal-id><journal-title>Advances in Urology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1687-6369</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1687-6377</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19255628</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2648052</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2009/960490</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Correlation of Hydronephrosis Index to Society of Fetal Urology Hydronephrosis Scale</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venkatesan</surname><given-names>Krishnan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>Steven R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3"><sup>3, 4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steinhardt</surname><given-names>George F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"><sup>1, 5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Urology, School of Medicine, Wayne State University, Detroit, MI 48201, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Surgery, College of Human Medicine, Michigan State University, Grand Rapids, MI 49503, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Section of Urology, Sutter Memorial Hospital, Sacramento, CA, 95819, USA</aff><aff id="I4"><sup>4</sup>Pediatric Urology Medical Group, Inc., Santa Monica, CA, 90403, USA</aff><aff id="I5"><sup>5</sup>Department of Pediatric Urology, Helen DeVos Children's Hospital, Grand Rapids, MI 49503, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*George F. Steinhardt: <email>gsteinhardt@urologic-consultants.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Recommended by Paddy Dewan</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>2009</volume><elocation-id>960490</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>3</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Krishnan Venkatesan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>					<italic>Purpose</italic>. We seek to correlate conventional hydronephrosis (HN) grade and hydronephrosis index (HI). <italic>Methods</italic>. We examined 1207 hydronephrotic kidneys by ultrasound.  HN was classified by Society of Fetal Urology guidelines. HN was then gauged using HI, a reproducible, standardized, and dimensionless measurement of renal area. We then calculated average HI for each HN grade. <italic>Results</italic>. Comparing HI to standard SFU HN grade, average HI is 89.3 for grade I; average HI is 83.9 for grade II; average HI is 73.0 for grade III; average HI is 54.6 for SFU grade IV. <italic>Conclusions</italic>. HI correlates well with SFU HN grade. The HI serves as a quantitative measure of HN.  HI can be used to track HN over time.  Versus conventional grading, HI may be more sensitive in defining severe (grades III and IV) HN, and in indicating resolving, stable, or worsening HN, thus providing more information for clinical decision-making and HN management.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="section" id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Ultrasound (US) has gainedwidespread acceptance and use in fetal and pediatric urology. Hydronephrosis (HN) has become the most common abnormality detected by prenatalUS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. HN had previously been characterized in a fairly subjective manner as mild, moderate, and severe. In 1993, theSociety for Fetal Urology (SFU) established a grading system based on renalsinus splitting patterns and dilation of the renal pelvis and calyces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Though the SFU grading system has been widelyaccepted, it does have certain deficiencies&#x02014;especially indifferentiation of severe (grades III and IV) HN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Serial assessment of HNby US, often used in clinical decision making, relies on this grading system tosuggest improving, stable, or worsening HN. Others have suggested improvementsor complementary approaches to the SFU grading system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]; none has gained widespreadpopularity of use.</p><p>Recently, a novel method to measureHN was suggested. The Hydronephrosis index (HI) has been shown to be aquantitative, reproducible, standardized measure of HN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. HI is calculated as a dimensionless numberthat represents renal area and can be used for serial examination of kidneyswith HN. The present work serves tocorrelate the SFU grading system with the HI system, to advance familiaritywith this new method of HN description.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec2"><title>2. Materials and Methods</title><p>An IRB approved prospective,computerized database accrued by the authors (George F. Steinhardt, Steven R. Shapiro) at their previous institution, was queried for all kidneys with thediagnosis of ureteropelvic junction obstruction (excluding kidneys withconcomitant vesicoureteral reflux or sonographic ureteral dilation). All of these 1207 kidneys were then assessedusing both the SFU grading system and the HI technique. The managing pediatricurologist (George F. Steinhardt) determined the SFU grade (I&#x02013;IV) of HN; thepediatric radiologists, supervising the sonographic technician, determined HI. Studies were performed using an Acuson Sequoia 512 system (Siemens MedicalSolutions, Malvern, Pa,USA).</p><p>Specifically, a single sagittal USimage was selected, where the kidney achieved its maximal longitudinal dimensions. The operator thenmarked the renal boundaries, traced an outline of the entire renal perimeterand then of the dilated renal pelvis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). The portion of the renal pelvis extendingbeyond the kidney was not included in the HI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The respective areas werethen computed with integrated software which is standard on most modernultrasound machines.</p><p>Data was entered into the databaseas patients were managed in the office.</p><p>HI is calculated as follows: HI(percentage) = 100  &#x000d7;  (total area of the kidney minus area of dilated pelvis)/(totalarea). The result is a quantitative,dimensionless measurement of renal mass. In essence, HI represents thepercentage of total kidney that is renal parenchyma.</p><p>For each grade of hydronephrosis,the average HI was calculated.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec3"><title>3. Results</title><p>The average HI was calculated foreach group of kidneys, in order to establish a correlation of HI to HN grade(<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>). The number of kidneys in each group is also listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>A normal nonhydronephrotic kidneywould have an HI of 100. Morehydronephrosis, or renal pelvis dilation, translates to a larger renal pelvicarea and thus, a lower HI. For the groupcomprised of kidneys with grade I hydronephrosis, the average HI was 89.3. The group of grade II hydronephrotic kidneyshad an average HI of 83.9. Kidneys withgrade III hydronephrosis averaged 73.0 for HI. Average HI for grade IVhydronephrotic kidneys was 54.6.</p><p>The objectivity and reproducibilityof HI measurements have been shown previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec4"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>Management of prenatal and infantHN relies heavily upon serial examination by US [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Currently, the main paradigm of HNdescription is the SFU grading system. The HI has been shown as a viable,alternate method of longitudinal HN monitoring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. It is an objective,reproducible, and standardized calculation. Because HI is quantitative anddimensionless, it allows easy portability of US interpretation across multiplelocations and over time. The medical application of dimensionless numbers hasbeen shown to be effective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>As one would expect, kidneys withmore significant HN on average had a lower HI. While the difference in HI between lower grades of HN was minor, meanHI is markedly different at higher grades (III &#x00026; IV) of HN. This end of thespectrum, differentiating between grades III and IV HN, is where the SFUgrading system lacks clarity and depends heavily on individual interpretation[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The value of HI over the SFUgrading system is the greatest in this regard. The subjective factor of visualinterpretation is removed for one observer over time, as are discrepancies betweenmultiple observers. In its place, anobjective, quantitative interpretation of HN is produced.</p><p>Serial measurement of HI may bemore sensitive to subtle changes in hydronephrosis, not discriminated orperceived by the SFU system. Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref> and<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref> demonstrate obvious changes in HN degree in a kidney with static SFU grade. This sensitivity also holds true for postoperative monitoring, where the SFUsystem may not detect results appropriately [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p><p>The quantified HI measurementserves as a &#x0201c;continuous&#x0201d; variable, in contrast to a discrete grade encompassinga wide range of pathology. This can affect better informed clinical decision makingfor a wide variety of hydronephrotic kidneys with diverse clinical settings. Accordingly, results of hydronephrosis management may improve as well. For example, earlier correction of UPJobstruction has been shown to give better drainage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Also, it is clear thatglomeruli are irreparably damaged prior to any evident loss of GFR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>],suggesting that waiting longer for loss of function to manifest beforeintervening would be less than ideal. Therefore, worsening hydronephrosisconstitutes a relative indication for surgery, and our technique betterdiscriminates subtle changes in HN.</p><p>This work reviews the HI of 1207 renal units with HN to facilitate establishment ofcontext for HI. Clinicians can now calculate and use HI with the confidencethat it provides an objective, quantifiable interpretation for the managementof HN. It correlates well with, and improves upon, the SFU grading system forHN and is especially valuable in management of high-grade HN.</p><p>The concept of quantification of HN has been addressed previously. Rodr&#x000ed;guez et al.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] described a series of 81 patients, in which they calculated renalparenchymal and pelvic areas, in a manner similar to our own. However, theirtechnique differs in that they propose a computation to derive a thresholdratio which predicts the need for a surgery. This work, on the other hand,emphasizes HI as a more sensitive indicator of HN over time, not necessarily asa singular criterion for, or prognosticator of, surgery.</p><p>HI does have its limitations. The data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>) shows that a wide HI rangerepresents each SFU grade. For example, the lowest HI for grade I HN is 42, which is obviously quitelow. One inherent problem in a dataset containing greater than 1200 renal unitsis the difficulty in accounting for data entry problems.</p><p>The standard deviation is calculated for each HI and bolsters the constructedframework. While there is minimal overlap of HI at lower grades of HN, on alarger spectrum, and the predicted trend is seen. While it may not be usedreliably to compare different patients with HN, the calculated average HI doesprovide a reference point for better informed individual HN management.</p><p>Also, it is possible that some HI measurements were made with a full bladder. As thiswork is extracted from a database, original imaging was unavailable for review. However, this should have been acknowledged and accounted by the clinician atthe time of HI review.</p></sec><sec sec-type="section" id="sec5"><title>5. Conclusion</title><p>HI correlates predictably with theSFU grading system for HN. Because it provides a quantitative measurement, itcan be used to predict the SFU HN grade. HI can also be employed forlongitudinal monitoring of HN by US, including pre- and postoperativeobservation. Because it is a more sensitive indicator of renal parenchymalstatus, HI allows for better informed clinical decision making, identifyingchanges in HN not discerned by the current SFU system.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blyth</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Retik</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Estroff</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Benacerraf</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural genitourinary defects detected in utero</article-title><source><italic>Radiology</italic></source><year>1991</year><volume>178</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1984303</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernbach</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Maizels</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasound grading of hydronephrosis: introduction to the system used by the Society for Fetal Urology</article-title><source><italic>Pediatric Radiology</italic></source><year>1993</year><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8255658</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Onen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An alternative grading system to refine the criteria for severity of hydronephrosis and optimal treatment guidelines in neonates with primary UPJ-type hydronephrosis</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Pediatric Urology</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18947735</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dairiki Shortliffe</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of sonographic renal parenchymal area in the management of hydronephrosis</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Urology</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>165</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11176432</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imaji</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calyx to parenchyma ratio in pelvi-ureteric junction obstruction</article-title><source><italic>BJU International</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>89</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11849165</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Silberstein</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinhardt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydronephrosis index: a new method to track patients with hydronephrosis quantitatively</article-title><source><italic>Urology</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>72</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18400271</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belarmino</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kogan</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of neonatal hydronephrosis</article-title><source><italic>Early Human Development</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>82</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16427220</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahdes-Vasama</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of bladder compliance can be standardized by a dimensionless number: clinical perspective</article-title><source><italic>BJU International</italic></source><year>2004</year><volume>94</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>898</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15476531</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chacko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boucat</surname><given-names>HAP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved drainage following early pyeloplasty for pelvi-ureteric junction obstruction</article-title><source><italic>Asian Journal of Surgery</italic></source><year>1997</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>259</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental determinants of recovery after relief of partial ureteral obstruction</article-title><source><italic>Kidney International</italic></source><year>1988</year><volume>33</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3386132</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Boundaries of hydronephrotic kidneymarked.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="AU2009-960490.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>SFU grade IV hydronephrosis; Calculated HI 58.5. The dotted line outlines the renal pelvis [black]  as used in calculating HI. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="AU2009-960490.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Same kidney 1.5 months later. SFU grade IV hydronephrosis; Calculated HI 27. The dotted line outlines the entire renal area, including renal pelvis [black] and parenchyma (dark gray). While the SFU grade remained the same, the HI has deteriorated significantly, indicating an actual worsening HN. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="AU2009-960490.003"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Correlation of HI to HN grade.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SFU grade</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean HI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range of HI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI std dev</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of kidneys</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42&#x02013;97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x02013;100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43&#x02013;97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-wrap></article>