<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Health Geogr</journal-id><journal-title>International Journal of Health Geographics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1476-072X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19154599</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2649061</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1476-072X-8-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-072X-8-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Traffic-related air pollution associated with prevalence of asthma and COPD/chronic bronchitis. A cross-sectional study in Southern Sweden</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>anna.lindgren@med.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stroh</surname><given-names>Emilie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>emilie.stroh@med.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Montn&#x000e9;mery</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>peter.montnemery@med.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nihl&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>Ulf</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>Ulf.Nihlen@med.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>Kristina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kristina.jakobsson@med.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Axmon</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>anna.axmon@med.lu.se</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Community Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Astra Zeneca R&#x00026;D, Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine and Allergology, Lund University, Lund, Sweden</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ij-healthgeographics.com/content/8/1/2"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Lindgren et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lindgren et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>               Lindgren               Anna                              anna.lindgren@med.lu.se            </dc:author><dc:title>            Traffic-related air pollution associated with prevalence of asthma and COPD/chronic bronchitis. A cross-sectional study in Southern Sweden         </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>International Journal of Health Geographics 8(1): 2-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1476-072X(2009)8:1&#x0003c;2&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1476-072X</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>There is growing evidence that air pollution from traffic has adverse long-term effects on chronic respiratory disease in children, but there are few studies and more inconclusive results in adults. We examined associations between residential traffic and asthma and COPD in adults in southern Sweden. A postal questionnaire in 2000 (n = 9319, 18&#x02013;77 years) provided disease status, and self-reported exposure to traffic. A Geographical Information System (GIS) was used to link geocoded residential addresses to a Swedish road database and an emission database for NOx.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Living within 100 m of a road with &#x0003e;10 cars/minute (compared with having no heavy road within this distance) was associated with prevalence of asthma diagnosis (OR = 1.40, 95% CI = 1.04&#x02013;1.89), and COPD diagnosis (OR = 1.64, 95%CI = 1.11&#x02013;2.4), as well as asthma and chronic bronchitis symptoms. Self-reported traffic exposure was associated with asthma diagnosis and COPD diagnosis, and with asthma symptoms. Annual average NOx was associated with COPD diagnosis and symptoms of asthma and chronic bronchitis.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Living close to traffic was associated with prevalence of asthma diagnosis, COPD diagnosis, and symptoms of asthma and bronchitis. This indicates that traffic-related air pollution has both long-term and short-term effects on chronic respiratory disease in adults, even in a region with overall low levels of air pollution.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Traffic-related air pollution is well known to have short-term effects on chronic respiratory disease, exacerbating symptoms and increasing hospital admissions for respiratory causes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Strong effects on symptoms have also been observed in areas with relatively low background pollution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Long-term effects have been disputed, but there is growing evidence that traffic-related air pollution is related, at least among children, to asthma incidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], decreased lung function development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], and incidence of bronchitic symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>In adults, studies of long-term effects from traffic-related air pollution have been few, and recent studies have found both positive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] and negative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] associations with asthma, as well as positive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] and negative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] associations with COPD. Overall, chronic respiratory disease in adults is heterogenous and involves major exposures, such as personal smoking and occupational exposure, which do not directly affect children. This larger variety of risk factors may complicate research and contribute to inconclusive results in adults.</p><p>Self-reported living close to traffic has been associated with prevalence of asthma, but not COPD, among adults in southern Sweden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. However, self-reports could be severely biased if people are more aware of (and hence over-report) exposures that are known to be potentially connected to disease, and may not be trustworthy if used as the only exposure estimate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>].</p><p>One way of obtaining objective exposure estimates is the use of Geographical Information Systems (GIS) to combine geocoded population data with external traffic exposure data, such as road networks and modeled or monitored traffic pollutants. Since the concentrations of many traffic pollutants decline to background levels within 30&#x02013;200 m of a road, the level of spatial aggregation may be just as important as the type of proxy when estimating exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Some studies have found that adverse effects on respiratory disease are best captured with simple variables of traffic density and proximity to roads [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], rather than more complex models of specific pollutants, which are difficult to model with a high resolution. However, air pollutant models do have a number of advantages; for example, they can account for total traffic density, and can also be validated against real measurements, providing more specific estimates of the level of pollution at which adverse effects from traffic can be seen.</p><p>In the present study, we made use of a high quality GIS-modeled pollutant database for nitrogen oxides (NO<sub>x </sub>and NO<sub>2</sub>) which has been developed and validated for southern Sweden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The high spatial variability of NO<sub>x </sub>(NO+NO<sub>2</sub>), with traffic as the dominating source, makes it a better proxy for exposure to traffic at the local level, compared with pollutants such as PM<sub>2.5 </sub>which have a more geographically homogenous spread [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. We also used GIS-based road data and self-reported living close to heavy traffic as proxies for exposure.</p><sec><title>Study aim</title><p>The aim of this study was to investigate the association between traffic-related air pollution and asthma and COPD in adults. The outcomes investigated were prevalence of; 1) asthma diagnosis 2) COPD diagnosis 3) asthma symptoms last 12 months, and 4) chronic bronchitis symptoms, in relation to residential traffic exposure.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study area</title><p>The study area was the most southwestern part of Sweden (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), the most populated part of the county of Scania. The study area contains 840 000 of Sweden's total population of 8.9 million, and has a population density of 170 inhabitants per km<sup>2 </sup>(data from 2000). The majority of the population live in six of the communities, the largest of which is Malm&#x000f6;, the third largest city in Sweden, with a population of 260 000. A detailed regional description has previously been given [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. In the geographical stratification of the present study, "Malm&#x000f6;" refers strictly to the city boundaries of Malm&#x000f6;, not the larger municipality.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Study area</bold>. Malm&#x000f6; is the largest city in the study region, which comprises the southwestern part of Sweden.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-072X-8-2-1"/></fig><p>The climate in the region is homogenous. Although pollutant levels in the region are low in an European context, they are higher than in the remainder of Sweden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], due to long-range transport of pollutants from the continent and extensive harbor and ferry traffic.</p></sec><sec><title>Study population &#x00026; questionnaire</title><p>In 2000, a questionnaire was sent to a total of 11933 individuals aged 18&#x02013;77, of whom 9319 (78%) answered. The study population originated from two different study populations, with 5039 (response rate: 71%) from a new random selection, and 4280 (response rate: 87%) constituting a follow-up group from an earlier selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p><p>The questionnaire dealt with respiratory symptoms, potential confounders such as smoking habits and occupation, and exposures such as living close to a road with heavy traffic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. An external exposure assessment was also obtained by geocoding the residential addresses (as of 2000) of both respondents and non-respondents. This was achieved by linking each individual's unique 10-digit personal identity codes to a registry containing the geographical coordinates of all residential addresses.</p><p>Non-respondents had a higher mean of NO<sub>x </sub>than respondents; 14.7 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3 </sup>versus 13.5 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>. To a large extent this was due to a lower response rate in the more polluted city of Malm&#x000f6; (73% vs. 80% in the remaining region).</p></sec><sec><title>Outcome measures</title><p>The following outcomes were investigated, as obtained by the postal questionnaires:</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Diagnosis of asthma</italic>. "Have you been diagnosed by a doctor as having asthma?"</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Diagnosis of COPD/CBE (Chronic Bronchitis Emphysema)</italic>. "Have you been diagnosed by a doctor as having chronic bronchitis, emphysema, or COPD?"</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Asthma symptoms during the last 12 months</italic>. "Have you had asthma symptoms during the last 12 months, i.e. intermittent breathlessness or attacks of breathlessness? The symptoms may exist with or without cough or wheezing."</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Chronic bronchitis symptoms</italic>. "Have you had periods of at least three months where you brought up phlegm when coughing on most days?", and if so, "Have you had such periods during at least two successive years?"</p><p>The questionnaire has been published previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. No information regarding year of disease onset was available.</p></sec><sec><title>Exposure assessment</title><p>Exposure to traffic-related air pollution was assessed at each participant's residential address in 2000, using three different proxies:</p><p>1. Self-reported exposure to traffic. This was obtained from the survey. Exposure was defined as a positive answer to the question "<italic>Do you live close to a road with heavy traffic?</italic>"</p><p>2. Traffic intensity on the heaviest road within 100 m. GIS-based registers from <italic>The Swedish National Road Database </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] provided information about traffic intensity for all major roads in the county (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). To assess exposure to traffic, we identified the road with the heaviest traffic intensity within 100 m of the residence. Traffic intensity was categorized as 0&#x02013;1 cars/min, 2&#x02013;5 cars/min, 6&#x02013;10 cars/min, and &#x0003e;10 cars/min, based upon 24-hour mean levels.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Regional road network</bold>. Data from the Swedish National Road Network. No heavy road means that no registered road was available in the database, but local traffic could exist. The traffic intensity categories of (0&#x02013;1, 2&#x02013;5, 6&#x02013;10, &#x0003e;10) cars/min corresponds to daily mean traffic counts of (0&#x02013;2880, 2880&#x02013;8640, 8640&#x02013;14400, &#x0003e;14400) cars/day.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-072X-8-2-2"/></fig><p>3. Modeled exposure to NO<sub>x </sub>(figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Annual mean concentrations of NO<sub>x </sub>were acquired from a pollutant database, based on the year 2001 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Emission sources included in the model were: road traffic, shipping, aviation, railroad, industries and larger energy and heat producers, small scale heating, working machines, working vehicles, and working tools. Meteorological data were also included. A modified Gaussian dispersion model (AERMOD) was used for dispersion calculations; a flat two-dimensional model which did not adjust for effects of street canyons or other terrain, but which did take the height of the emission sources into consideration. Concentrations of NO<sub>x </sub>were modeled as annual means on a grid with a spatial resolution of 250 &#x000d7; 250 m. Bilinear interpolation was used to adjust individual exposure with weighted values of neighboring area concentrations. Concentrations modeled with this spatial resolution have been validated and found to have a high correlation with measured values in the region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Modeled levels of NO<sub>x </sub>Dispersion modeled annual average of NO<sub>x</sub>, modeled with a resolution of 250 &#x000d7; 250 m</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-072X-8-2-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Statistics</title><p>A categorical classification of NO<sub>x </sub>was used in order to allow analysis of non-linear associations with outcomes. To determine the category limits, the subjects (n = 9274) were divided into NO<sub>x</sub>-quintiles. The five exposure groups used were 0&#x02013;8 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>, 8&#x02013;11 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>, 11&#x02013;14 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>, 14&#x02013;19 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>, and &#x0003e;19 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>.</p><p>For all measures of exposure, subgroup analyses were made for Malm&#x000f6; and the remaining region. Relative risk was not estimated in exposure groups with fewer than 50 individuals. As few individuals in Malm&#x000f6; had a low exposure to NO<sub>x</sub>, the middle exposure group was used as the reference category for NO<sub>x</sub>, in Malm&#x000f6;. Because of this, NO<sub>x </sub>was also used as a continuous variable for trend analysis using logistic regression. A p-value &#x0003c; 0.05 was regarded as evidence of a trend. Stratified analyses were performed for sex, age, smoking, geographical region (Malm&#x000f6; vs. remaining region), and study population (new random selection vs. follow-up group). Sensitivity analyses of the associations with traffic were also performed by restricting the groups to those with asthma but not COPD, and COPD but not asthma, to exclude confounding by comorbidity. This process was also followed for symptoms.</p><p>Relative risk was estimated using Odds Ratios (ORs) with 95% Confidence Intervals (CI). Odds Ratios and tests of trends were obtained by binary logistic regression, using version 13.0 of SPSS.</p><p>Sex, age (seven categories), and smoking (smokers/ex-smokers vs. non-smokers) are known risk factors for asthma, and were therefore adjusted for in the model. Socio-Economic Indices (SEI codes, based on occupational status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]) and occupational exposure (ALOHA JEM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]) were tested as confounders, using the "change-in-estimate" method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>], where a change in the OR of 10% would have motivated an inclusion in the model.</p><p>Neither occupational exposure nor Socio-Economic Indices fulfilled the predetermined confounder criteria, or had any noticeable impact on the risk estimates, and were thus not included in the model.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A description of the study population in terms sex, age, and smoking, along with the associations with the outcomes, is presented in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Description of study population. Disease prevalence in relation to sex, age, and smoking.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">Diagnosed asthma</td><td align="left">Asthma symptoms</td><td align="left">Diagnosed COPD</td><td align="left">Chronic b. symptoms</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Sex</td><td align="left">Men</td><td align="left">4341</td><td align="left">258(5.9%)</td><td align="left">429(9.9%)</td><td align="left">172(4.0%)</td><td align="left">308(7.1%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Women</td><td align="left">4975</td><td align="left">428(8.6%)</td><td align="left">686(13.8%)</td><td align="left">243(4.9%)</td><td align="left">327(6.6%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ever smoker</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">4306</td><td align="left">291(6.8%)</td><td align="left">431(10.0%)</td><td align="left">118(2.7%)</td><td align="left">217(5.0%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">5010</td><td align="left">395(7.9%)</td><td align="left">684(13.7%)</td><td align="left">297(5.9%)</td><td align="left">418(8.3%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age</td><td align="left">18&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">135</td><td align="left">15(11.1%)</td><td align="left">23(17%)</td><td align="left">3(2.2%)</td><td align="left">9(6.7%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">20&#x02013;29</td><td align="left">1062</td><td align="left">110(10.4%)</td><td align="left">141(13.3%)</td><td align="left">19(1.8%)</td><td align="left">41(3.9%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">30&#x02013;39</td><td align="left">2045</td><td align="left">158(7.7%)</td><td align="left">246(12.0%)</td><td align="left">61(3.0%)</td><td align="left">108(5.3%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">40&#x02013;49</td><td align="left">1887</td><td align="left">112(5.9%)</td><td align="left">217(11.5%)</td><td align="left">69(3.7%)</td><td align="left">101(5.4%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">50&#x02013;59</td><td align="left">2123</td><td align="left">142(6.7%)</td><td align="left">237(11.2%)</td><td align="left">106(5.0%)</td><td align="left">185(8.7%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">60&#x02013;69</td><td align="left">1586</td><td align="left">113(7.1%)</td><td align="left">178(11.2%)</td><td align="left">115(7.3%)</td><td align="left">139(8.8%)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">70&#x02013;77</td><td align="left">478</td><td align="left">36(7.5%)</td><td align="left">73(15.3%)</td><td align="left">42(8.8%)</td><td align="left">52(10.9%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec><title>Association with self-reported living close to traffic</title><p>Asthma diagnosis and asthma symptoms in the last 12 months were associated with self-reported traffic exposure (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). These results were consistent in a geographical stratification (tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Asthma diagnosis and asthma symptoms in relation to traffic.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="3">Asthma Diagnosis</td><td align="left" colspan="3">Asthma Symptoms</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">n (%)</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">n (%)</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup>,</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heavy traffic</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">6041</td><td align="left">400(6.6%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">6041</td><td align="left">668(11.1%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">3275</td><td align="left">286(8.7%)</td><td align="left">1.28(1.09&#x02013;1.50)</td><td align="left">3275</td><td align="left">447(13.6%)</td><td align="left">1.22(1.07&#x02013;1.39)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heaviest road within &#x0003c;100 m</td><td align="left">no heavy road</td><td align="left">3755</td><td align="left">269(7.2%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3755</td><td align="left">419(11.2%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003c;2 cars/min</td><td align="left">2235</td><td align="left">149(6.7%)</td><td align="left">0.92(0.75&#x02013;1.13)</td><td align="left">2235</td><td align="left">263(11.8%)</td><td align="left">1.05(0.89&#x02013;1.24)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">2&#x02013;5 cars/min</td><td align="left">1820</td><td align="left">134(7.4%)</td><td align="left">1.00(0.81&#x02013;1.25)</td><td align="left">1820</td><td align="left">216(11.9%)</td><td align="left">1.06(0.89&#x02013;1.26)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">6&#x02013;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">886</td><td align="left">69(7.8%)</td><td align="left">1.05(0.79&#x02013;1.38)</td><td align="left">886</td><td align="left">126(14.2%)</td><td align="left">1.25(1.01&#x02013;1.55)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">578</td><td align="left">61(10.6%)</td><td align="left">1.40(1.04&#x02013;1.89)</td><td align="left">578</td><td align="left">85(14.7%)</td><td align="left">1.29(1.00&#x02013;1.67)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NO<sub>x </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">140(7.5%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">217(11.7%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">146(7.9%)</td><td align="left">1.04(0.82&#x02013;1.32)</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">213(11.5%)</td><td align="left">0.97(0.80&#x02013;1.19)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">11&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">124(6.7%)</td><td align="left">0.85(0.66&#x02013;1.09)</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">208(11.2%)</td><td align="left">0.94(0.77&#x02013;1.15)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">14&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">1858</td><td align="left">115(6.2%)</td><td align="left">0.77(0.60&#x02013;1.00)</td><td align="left">1858</td><td align="left">206(11.1%)</td><td align="left">0.90(0.74&#x02013;1.11)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;19</td><td align="left">1851</td><td align="left">157(8.5%)</td><td align="left">1.05(0.83&#x02013;1.34)</td><td align="left">1851</td><td align="left">265(14.3%)</td><td align="left">1.21(0.99&#x02013;1.46)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.84</td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.026</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>Adjusted for age, sex, and smoking. [OR(95%CI)].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Geographical stratification. Asthma diagnosis in the city of Malm&#x000f6; and the area outside.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="3">Malm&#x000f6;</td><td align="left" colspan="3">Region outside Malm&#x000f6;</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">Asthma diagnosis</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">Asthma diagnosis</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heavy traffic</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1767</td><td align="left">109(6.2%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">4178</td><td align="left">283(6.8%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">1877</td><td align="left">161(8.6%)</td><td align="left">1.35(1.05&#x02013;1.75)</td><td align="left">1343</td><td align="left">119(8.9%)</td><td align="left">1.28(1.02&#x02013;1.61)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heaviest road within &#x0003c;100 m</td><td align="left">no heavy road</td><td align="left">586</td><td align="left">40(6.8%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3124</td><td align="left">224(7.2%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003c;2 cars/min</td><td align="left">1021</td><td align="left">66(6.5%)</td><td align="left">0.95(0.63&#x02013;1.43)</td><td align="left">1193</td><td align="left">82(6.9%)</td><td align="left">0.95(0.73&#x02013;1.23)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">2&#x02013;5 cars/min</td><td align="left">837</td><td align="left">57(6.8%)</td><td align="left">0.99(0.65&#x02013;1.51)</td><td align="left">961</td><td align="left">75(7.8%)</td><td align="left">1.07(0.81&#x02013;1.40)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">6&#x02013;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">663</td><td align="left">50(7.5%)</td><td align="left">1.12(0.72&#x02013;1.72)</td><td align="left">212</td><td align="left">19(9.0%)</td><td align="left">1.21(0.74&#x02013;1.99)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">537</td><td align="left">57(10.6%)</td><td align="left">1.50(0.98&#x02013;2.31)</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NO<sub>x </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1824</td><td align="left">138(7.6%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1792</td><td align="left">138(7.7%)</td><td align="left">1.01(0.79&#x02013;1.30)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">11&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">562</td><td align="left">39(6.9%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">1268</td><td align="left">83(6.5%)</td><td align="left">0.81(0.61&#x02013;1.08)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">14&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">1325</td><td align="left">76(5.7%)</td><td align="left">0.79(0.53&#x02013;1.18)</td><td align="left">510</td><td align="left">37(7.3%)</td><td align="left">0.93(0.64&#x02013;1.36)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;19</td><td align="left">1698</td><td align="left">149(8.8%)</td><td align="left">1.18(0.81&#x02013;1.71)</td><td align="left">127</td><td align="left">6(4.7%)</td><td align="left">0.58(0.25&#x02013;1.34)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.044</td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.079</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>Adjusted for age, sex, and smoking. [OR(95%CI)].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Geographical stratification. Asthma symptoms in the city of Malm&#x000f6; and the region outside.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="3">Malm&#x000f6;</td><td align="left" colspan="3">Region outside Malm&#x000f6;</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">Asthma symptoms</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">Asthma symptoms</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heavy traffic</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1767</td><td align="left">209(11.8%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">4178</td><td align="left">449(10.7%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">1877</td><td align="left">263(14.0%)</td><td align="left">1.17(0.96&#x02013;1.43)</td><td align="left">1343</td><td align="left">178(13.3%)</td><td align="left">1.23(1.02&#x02013;1.49)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heaviest road within &#x0003c;100 m</td><td align="left">No heavy road</td><td align="left">586</td><td align="left">74(12.6%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3124</td><td align="left">342(10.9%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003c;2 cars/min</td><td align="left">1021</td><td align="left">119(11.7%)</td><td align="left">0.93(0.68&#x02013;1.26)</td><td align="left">1193</td><td align="left">142(11.9%)</td><td align="left">1.09(0.88&#x02013;1.34)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">2&#x02013;5 cars/min</td><td align="left">837</td><td align="left">101(12.1%)</td><td align="left">0.97(0.70&#x02013;1.33)</td><td align="left">961</td><td align="left">112(11.7%)</td><td align="left">1.06(0.84&#x02013;1.33)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">6&#x02013;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">663</td><td align="left">97(14.6%)</td><td align="left">1.17(0.85&#x02013;1.63)</td><td align="left">212</td><td align="left">29(13.7%)</td><td align="left">1.24(0.82&#x02013;1.87)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">537</td><td align="left">81(15.1%)</td><td align="left">1.19(0.84&#x02013;1.68)</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NO<sub>x </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1824</td><td align="left">215(11.8%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1792</td><td align="left">205(11.4%)</td><td align="left">0.96(0.79&#x02013;1.18)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">11&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">562</td><td align="left">65(11.6%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">1268</td><td align="left">142(11.2%)</td><td align="left">0.93(0.74&#x02013;1.16)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">14&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">1325</td><td align="left">146(11.0%)</td><td align="left">0.90(0.66&#x02013;1.23)</td><td align="left">510</td><td align="left">57(11.2%)</td><td align="left">0.95(0.69&#x02013;1.29)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;19</td><td align="left">1698</td><td align="left">254(15.0%)</td><td align="left">1.28(0.95&#x02013;1.72)</td><td align="left">127</td><td align="left">8(6.3%)</td><td align="left">0.50(0.24&#x02013;1.04)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.344</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>Adjusted for age, sex, and smoking. [OR (95%CI)].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>COPD diagnosis was associated with self-reported traffic exposure, both for the whole region (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>) and when geographically stratified (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). Chronic bronchitis symptoms were not associated with self-reported traffic exposure (tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">7</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>COPD diagnosis and chronic bronchitis symptoms in relation to traffic.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">COPD Diagnosis</td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Chronic bronchitis symptoms</td><td></td><td></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">n, (%)</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">n, (%)</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heavy traffic</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">6041</td><td align="left">243(4.0%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">6041</td><td align="left">401(6.6%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">3275</td><td align="left">172(5.3%)</td><td align="left">1.36(1.10&#x02013;1.67)</td><td align="left">3275</td><td align="left">234(7.1%)</td><td align="left">1.11(0.94&#x02013;1.31)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heaviest road within &#x0003c;100 m</td><td align="left">no heavy road</td><td align="left">3755</td><td align="left">153(4.1%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3755</td><td align="left">222(5.9%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003c;2 cars/min</td><td align="left">2235</td><td align="left">95(4.3%)</td><td align="left">1.04(0.80&#x02013;1.35)</td><td align="left">2235</td><td align="left">159(7.1%)</td><td align="left">1.21(0.98&#x02013;1.50)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">2&#x02013;5 cars/min</td><td align="left">1820</td><td align="left">71(3.9%)</td><td align="left">0.96(0.72&#x02013;1.28)</td><td align="left">1820</td><td align="left">137(7.5%)</td><td align="left">1.30(1.04&#x02013;1.62)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">6&#x02013;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">886</td><td align="left">60(6.8%)</td><td align="left">1.57(1.15&#x02013;2.14)</td><td align="left">886</td><td align="left">67(7.6%)</td><td align="left">1.24(0.93&#x02013;1.65)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">578</td><td align="left">34(5.9%)</td><td align="left">1.64(1.11&#x02013;2.41)</td><td align="left">578</td><td align="left">48(8.3%)</td><td align="left">1.53(1.10&#x02013;2.13)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NO<sub>x </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">74(4.0%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">110(5.9%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">68(3.7%)</td><td align="left">0.89(0.63&#x02013;1.24)</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">118(6.4%)</td><td align="left">1.05(0.81&#x02013;1.38)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">11&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">87(4.7%)</td><td align="left">1.19(0.86&#x02013;1.64)</td><td align="left">1855</td><td align="left">121(6.5%)</td><td align="left">1.12(0.86&#x02013;1.46)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">14&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">1858</td><td align="left">83(4.5%)</td><td align="left">1.03(0.74&#x02013;1.42)</td><td align="left">1858</td><td align="left">122(6.6%)</td><td align="left">1.06(0.81&#x02013;1.39)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;19</td><td align="left">1851</td><td align="left">101(5.5%)</td><td align="left">1.43(1.04&#x02013;1.95)</td><td align="left">1851</td><td align="left">162(8.8%)</td><td align="left">1.55(1.21&#x02013;2.00)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.010</td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>Adjusted for age, sex, and smoking. [OR(95%CI)].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Geographical stratification. COPD diagnosis in Malm&#x000f6; and the region outside.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="3">Malm&#x000f6;</td><td align="left" colspan="3">Region outside Malm&#x000f6;</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">COPD</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">COPD</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heavy traffic</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1767</td><td align="left">85(4.8%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">4178</td><td align="left">152(3.6%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">1877</td><td align="left">103(5.5%)</td><td align="left">1.24(0.92&#x02013;1.67)</td><td align="left">1343</td><td align="left">69(5.1%)</td><td align="left">1.47(1.09&#x02013;1.97)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heaviest road within &#x0003c;100 m</td><td align="left">no heavy road</td><td align="left">586</td><td align="left">28(4.8%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3124</td><td align="left">124(4.0%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003c;2 cars/min</td><td align="left">1021</td><td align="left">44(4.3%)</td><td align="left">0.89(0.55&#x02013;146)</td><td align="left">1193</td><td align="left">49(4.1%)</td><td align="left">1.06(0.75&#x02013;1.49)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">2&#x02013;5 cars/min</td><td align="left">837</td><td align="left">35(4.2%)</td><td align="left">0.89(0.53&#x02013;1.48)</td><td align="left">961</td><td align="left">35(3.6%)</td><td align="left">0.93(0.64&#x02013;1.37)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">6&#x02013;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">663</td><td align="left">50(7.5%)</td><td align="left">1.53(0.95&#x02013;2.48)</td><td align="left">212</td><td align="left">10(4.7%)</td><td align="left">1.20(0.62&#x02013;2.35)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">537</td><td align="left">31(5.8%)</td><td align="left">1.34(0.79&#x02013;2.28)</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NO<sub>x </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1824</td><td align="left">72(3.9%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1792</td><td align="left">66(3.7%)</td><td align="left">0.90(0.64&#x02013;1.27)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">11&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">562</td><td align="left">27(4.8%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">1268</td><td align="left">60(4.7%)</td><td align="left">1.26(0.89&#x02013;1.80)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">14&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">1325</td><td align="left">64(4.8%)</td><td align="left">0.94(0.59&#x02013;1.49)</td><td align="left">510</td><td align="left">18(3.5%)</td><td align="left">0.91(0.54&#x02013;1.55)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;19</td><td align="left">1698</td><td align="left">95(5.6%)</td><td align="left">1.23(0.79&#x02013;1.92)</td><td align="left">127</td><td align="left">5(3.9%)</td><td align="left">1.19(0.47&#x02013;3.02)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.142</td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.421</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>Adjusted for age, sex, and smoking. [OR (95%CI)].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Geographical stratification. Chronic bronchitis symptoms in the city of Malm&#x000f6; and the area outside.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="3">Malm&#x000f6;</td><td align="left" colspan="3">Region outside Malm&#x000f6;</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">Chronic b. symptoms</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">Chronic b. symptoms</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heavy traffic</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1767</td><td align="left">150(8.5%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">4178</td><td align="left">246(5.9%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">1877</td><td align="left">140(7.5%)</td><td align="left">0.91(0.71&#x02013;1.16)</td><td align="left">1343</td><td align="left">92(6.9%)</td><td align="left">1.20(0.94&#x02013;1.54)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heaviest road within &#x0003c;100 m</td><td align="left">no heavy road</td><td align="left">586</td><td align="left">43(7.3%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3124</td><td align="left">179(5.7%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003c;2 cars/min</td><td align="left">1021</td><td align="left">89(8.7%)</td><td align="left">1.21(0.83&#x02013;1.77)</td><td align="left">1193</td><td align="left">68(5.7%)</td><td align="left">1.00(0.75&#x02013;1.34)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">2&#x02013;5 cars/min</td><td align="left">837</td><td align="left">66(7.9%)</td><td align="left">1.10(0.73&#x02013;1.64)</td><td align="left">961</td><td align="left">69(7.2%)</td><td align="left">1.30(0.98&#x02013;1.74)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">6&#x02013;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">663</td><td align="left">47(7.1%)</td><td align="left">0.94(0.61&#x02013;1.45)</td><td align="left">212</td><td align="left">19(9.0%)</td><td align="left">1.63(0.99&#x02013;2.69)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">537</td><td align="left">45(8.4%)</td><td align="left">1.22(0.78&#x02013;1.89)</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NO<sub>x </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1824</td><td align="left">109(6.0%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">1792</td><td align="left">113(6.3%)</td><td align="left">1.04(0.79&#x02013;1.37)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">11&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">562</td><td align="left">35(6.2%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">1268</td><td align="left">84(6.6%)</td><td align="left">1.17(0.87&#x02013;1.57)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">14&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">1325</td><td align="left">96(7.2%)</td><td align="left">1.13(0.76&#x02013;1.70)</td><td align="left">510</td><td align="left">26(5.1%)</td><td align="left">0.88(0.57&#x02013;1.37)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;19</td><td align="left">1698</td><td align="left">155(9.1%)</td><td align="left">1.57(1.06&#x02013;2.30)</td><td align="left">127</td><td align="left">6(4.7%)</td><td align="left">0.86(0.37&#x02013;2.01)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.017</td><td></td><td align="left">p-trend</td><td align="left">0.541</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>Adjusted for age, sex, and smoking. [OR(95%CI)].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Association with traffic intensity on heaviest road within 100 m</title><p>Asthma diagnosis and asthma symptoms were associated with traffic intensity (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), with higher prevalence of asthma symptoms among those living next to a road with at least 6 cars/minute, and higher prevalence of asthma diagnosis among those exposed to at least 10 cars/minute, compared with the group having no road within 100 m. The effects seemed consistent, although statistically non-significant, across geographical region (tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><p>COPD and chronic bronchitis symptoms were associated with traffic intensity (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). However, when stratified geographically, the effect estimates indicated that chronic bronchitis symptoms were not associated with traffic intensity in Malm&#x000f6; (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">7</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Association with NO<sub>x </sub>at residential address</title><p>Asthma symptoms, but not asthma diagnosis, were associated with NO<sub>x </sub>in the trend tests (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). However, effects were only seen in the highest quintile of &#x0003e;19 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>. A geographical stratification showed that it was only in Malm&#x000f6; that high exposure was associated with asthma; no association was found in the region outside (tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><p>COPD diagnosis and chronic bronchitis symptoms were associated with NO<sub>x</sub>(table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). After geographical stratification, associations were seen only in Malm&#x000f6;, and not in the region outside (tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">7</xref>).</p><sec><title>Stratification by smoking, sex, age, response group, and restricted analysis</title><p>In a stratified analysis, the effects of traffic exposure were more pronounced for smokers than for non-smokers, for both COPD (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T8">8</xref>) and bronchitis symptoms (data not shown). A test for interaction, however, showed no significance except for the interaction between smoking and road within 100 m for chronic bronchitis symptoms (p = 0.023). Asthma showed no indications of effect modification by smoking.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T8"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Stratification on smoking. COPD diagnosis in relation to traffic among smokers/ex-smokers and non-smokers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="3">Smokers/ex-smokers</td><td align="left" colspan="3">Non-smokers</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">COPD D</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">COPD D</td><td align="left">OR <sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heavy traffic</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">3149</td><td align="left">167(5.3%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">2892</td><td align="left">76(2.6%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">1861</td><td align="left">130(7.0%)</td><td align="left">1.43(1.13&#x02013;1.82)</td><td align="left">1414</td><td align="left">42(3.0%)</td><td align="left">1.19(0.81&#x02013;1.76)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heaviest road within &#x0003c;100 m</td><td align="left">no heavy road</td><td align="left">1951</td><td align="left">104(5.3%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">1804</td><td align="left">49(2.7%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003c;2 cars/min</td><td align="left">1185</td><td align="left">67(5.7%)</td><td align="left">1.06(0.77&#x02013;1.45)</td><td align="left">1050</td><td align="left">28(2.7%)</td><td align="left">0.99(0.62&#x02013;1.59)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">2&#x02013;5 cars/min</td><td align="left">992</td><td align="left">52(5.2%)</td><td align="left">0.99(0.70&#x02013;1.40)</td><td align="left">828</td><td align="left">19(2.3%)</td><td align="left">0.88(0.51&#x02013;1.51)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">6&#x02013;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">522</td><td align="left">44(8.4%)</td><td align="left">1.56(1.08&#x02013;2.26)</td><td align="left">364</td><td align="left">16(4.4%)</td><td align="left">1.64(0.92&#x02013;2.94)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">344</td><td align="left">28(8.1%)</td><td align="left">1.84(1.18&#x02013;2.86)</td><td align="left">234</td><td align="left">6(2.6%)</td><td align="left">1.15(0.48&#x02013;2.75)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NO<sub>x </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">969</td><td align="left">47(4.9%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">886</td><td align="left">27(3.0%)</td><td align="left">1.00</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="left">971</td><td align="left">47(4.8%)</td><td align="left">0.96(0.63&#x02013;1.46)</td><td align="left">884</td><td align="left">21(2.4%)</td><td align="left">0.77(0.43&#x02013;1.37)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">11&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">945</td><td align="left">63(6.7%)</td><td align="left">1.35(0.92&#x02013;2.00)</td><td align="left">910</td><td align="left">24(2.6%)</td><td align="left">0.92(0.52&#x02013;1.61)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">14&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">1037</td><td align="left">60(5.8%)</td><td align="left">1.14(0.92&#x02013;2.00)</td><td align="left">821</td><td align="left">23(2.8%)</td><td align="left">0.85(0.48&#x02013;1.50)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;19</td><td align="left">1072</td><td align="left">78(7.3%)</td><td align="left">1.61(1.11&#x02013;2.35)</td><td align="left">779</td><td align="left">23(3.0%)</td><td align="left">1.12(0.63&#x02013;1.98)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Test f&#x000f6;r</td><td align="left" colspan="3">Heavy traffic*eversmoker</td><td align="left">p = 0.47</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Interaction</td><td align="left" colspan="3">Heaviestroad100 m*eversmoker</td><td align="left">p = 0.89</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left" colspan="3">NOx*eversmoker</td><td align="left">p = 0.83</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>Adjusted for age and sex. [OR(95%CI)].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>No effect modifications were seen when the data were stratified by sex, age, or sample group (new participants vs. follow-up group). Restriction of analysis to asthmatics without COPD, and to those with COPD without asthma, was performed for both diagnoses and symptoms. The results showed similar effects in the restricted and non-restricted groups. The overlaps between the different disease outcome definitions are presented in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T9">9</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T9"><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Description of overlap between the different reported disease outcomes. Percentage within row. The first row shows that 70% of those with asthma diagnosis had asthma symptoms, 20% of those with asthma diagnosis had COPD diagnosis, and 21% of those with asthma diagnosis had chronic bronchitis symptoms.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left">Total n</td><td align="left">Asthma diagnosis n (%)</td><td align="left">Asthma symptoms n (%)</td><td align="left">COPD diagnosis n (%)</td><td align="left">Chronic b. Symptoms (n %)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Asthma diagnosis</td><td align="left">686</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">483 (70%)</td><td align="left">139 (20%)</td><td align="left">145 (21%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Asthma symptoms</td><td align="left">1115</td><td align="left">483 (43%)</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">219 (20%)</td><td align="left">277 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">COPD diagnosis</td><td align="left">415</td><td align="left">139 (34%)</td><td align="left">219 (53%)</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">152 (37%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chronic bronchitis symptoms</td><td align="left">635</td><td align="left">145 (23%)</td><td align="left">277 (44%)</td><td align="left">152 (24%)</td><td align="left">-</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Overall, residential traffic was associated with a higher prevalence of both asthma diagnosis and asthma symptoms in the last 12 months, as well as COPD diagnosis and chronic bronchitis symptoms. Traffic intensity on the heaviest road within 100 m showed effects at a traffic intensity of &#x0003e;6 cars/min. Effects from NO<sub>x </sub>were seen in the highest exposure quintile of &#x0003e;19 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>, but only in Malm&#x000f6;, not in the region outside.</p><sec><title>Discussion of exposure assessment</title><p>The major strength of this study was the use of three different proxies of exposure, which may have different intrinsic strengths and weaknesses. The strengths of the NO<sub>x </sub>model are firstly that it reflects total traffic density in the area, and secondly the fact that the dispersion model has been validated, with a resolution of 250 &#x000d7; 250 m showing a high correlation with measured background concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Nevertheless, street-level concentrations may vary on a much smaller scale. High peak concentrations are often found in so-called "street canyons" in urban areas, where pollutants are trapped between high buildings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Since the dispersion model did not take account of this kind of accumulation effect, the true exposure among people living in these surroundings might have been underestimated. This may partly explain why effects from NO<sub>x </sub>were seen in the urban city of Malm&#x000f6; but not in the surrounding area.</p><p>The proportion of NO<sub>x </sub>that originates from traffic is also dependent on geographical area. In urban areas of southern Sweden, local traffic contributes approximately 50&#x02013;60% of total NO<sub>x</sub>, while in the countryside such traffic is responsible for only 10&#x02013;30% of total NO<sub>x </sub>(S. Gustafsson, personal communication, 2007-10-17). This difference was also reported by the SAPALDIA study, which found that local traffic accounted for the majority of NO<sub>x </sub>in urban but not rural areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. This indicates that our model of NO<sub>x </sub>is a good proxy for exposure to traffic-related air pollution in an urban area, but may not be sensitive enough to capture individual risk in the countryside, where traffic contributes to a lower proportion of total concentrations.</p><p>Self-reported living close to a road with heavy traffic, and traffic intensity on the heaviest road within 100 m, are simple proxies; they do not reflect, for example, whether someone lives at a junction. Still, they have the advantage that they are less limited by aggregation in space than the NO<sub>x </sub>model. In the present study, both of these variables showed fairly consistent associations, at least with asthma, despite large differences in the level of NO<sub>x </sub>that they corresponded to in Malm&#x000f6; and the region outside (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T10">10</xref>); this may indicate that adverse effects from traffic pollutants are mainly seen in close proximity to traffic. High traffic intensity, however, may not only correlate with high total number of vehicles, but also with a higher proportion of heavy vehicles, an additional factor which could affect the outcome, since diesel exhaust from heavy vehicles might have more adverse respiratory effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T10"><label>Table 10</label><caption><p>Relation between the exposure proxies and modeled NO<sub>x </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>) as a continuous variable.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="4">Malm&#x000f6; NO<sub>x</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="4">Region outside Malm&#x000f6; NO<sub>x</sub></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">Mean</td><td align="left">SD</td><td align="left">Median</td><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">Mean</td><td align="left">SD</td><td align="left">Median</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heavy traffic</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1507</td><td align="left">18.0</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">17.4</td><td align="left">4502</td><td align="left">10.2</td><td align="left">3.5</td><td align="left">9.6</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">1772</td><td align="left">19.6</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">19.6</td><td align="left">1495</td><td align="left">12.1</td><td align="left">4.5</td><td align="left">11.4</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heaviest road within &#x0003c;100 m</td><td align="left">no heavy road</td><td align="left">488</td><td align="left">17.6</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">17.2</td><td align="left">3267</td><td align="left">10.1</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">9.6</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003c;2 cars/min</td><td align="left">855</td><td align="left">18.0</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">17.8</td><td align="left">1380</td><td align="left">9.8</td><td align="left">4.3</td><td align="left">8.1</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">2&#x02013;5 cars/min</td><td align="left">746</td><td align="left">18.9</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">19.4</td><td align="left">1074</td><td align="left">12.6</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">11.5</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">6&#x02013;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">627</td><td align="left">18.1</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">17.4</td><td align="left">259</td><td align="left">13.8</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">14.03</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;10 cars/min</td><td align="left">561</td><td align="left">21.9</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">22.0</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">19.2</td><td align="left">4.4</td><td align="left">21.6</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NO<sub>x </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">6.8</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">6.8</td><td align="left">1824</td><td align="left">6.7</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">6.8</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">10.4</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">9.6</td><td align="left">1792</td><td align="left">9.9</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">10.0</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">11&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">562</td><td align="left">13.5</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">13.7</td><td align="left">1268</td><td align="left">12.8</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">12.7</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">14&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">1325</td><td align="left">16.7</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">15.9</td><td align="left">510</td><td align="left">15.7</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">15.3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">&#x0003e;19</td><td align="left">1698</td><td align="left">21.7</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">21.5</td><td align="left">127</td><td align="left">21.9</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">21.2</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left">3644</td><td align="left">18.4</td><td align="left">3.6</td><td align="left">18.5</td><td align="left">5521</td><td align="left">10.31</td><td align="left">3.6</td><td align="left">10.04</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>It should be noted that the distribution of exposure is not comparable between the proxies. While NO<sub>x </sub>was divided into quintiles, with 20% in the highest exposure category, only 6% of the population lay in the highest traffic intensity category. Thus, the different proxies are complementary rather than comparable in this study.</p><p>One limitation of all three proxies of exposure was that traffic-related air pollution was only estimated by residential address. Lack of individual data about work address and time spent commuting could have biased the exposure assessments, particularly for people living in areas with low exposure to traffic-related air pollution, where individual differences in daily activities outside the residential area translate to a large proportion of total exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. In Los Angeles, 1 h commuting/day contributes approximately 10&#x02013;50% of people's daily exposure to ultrafine particles from traffic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. While only 20% of the working population living in Malm&#x000f6; commute to work outside Malm&#x000f6;, the majority of the population in smaller municipalities in the remaining region commute to work outside their own municipality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>].</p><p>Another limitation was the cross-sectional nature of the study; we had no information about disease onset or years living at current address, making it hard to establish a temporal relationship between cause and effect. However, since asthma and COPD are known to be exacerbated by traffic-related air pollution, subjects with disease may have been more likely to move away from traffic, rather than towards it, and so a migrational bias would mainly be expected to dilute the effects.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion of potential confounding</title><p>Areas with high levels of exposure to traffic-related air pollution were mainly located in the city of Malm&#x000f6; (table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>), while low exposure was found in more sparsely populated areas. It is a well recognized problem that the different exposure levels in rural and urban environments are also accompanied by large differences in lifestyle factors, and even if confounders are controlled for, unmeasured factors may remain. Since NO<sub>x </sub>was limited by its spatial resolution, it is also the measure that was most susceptible to ecological bias. The lack of association seen with NO<sub>x</sub>, in the region outside Malm&#x000f6; might thus reflect that the individual risk from traffic is being overridden by some other factor correlating with low exposure levels. The existence of independent risk factors correlating with low exposure is given some support by a Swedish study which found a tendency to higher adult asthma incidence in rural areas, after adjustment for exposure to traffic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><p>The most important risk factors from a validity standpoint, however, are factors that could correlate with high exposure to traffic-related air pollution, and thus cause a false positive relationship, such as socio-economic and occupational risk factors. However, the present study, which used individual-level data, found no confounding effects for either socio-economic status or occupational exposure. A recently developed and validated JEM was used to adjust for occupational exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. In a JEM, people are assigned the statistically average level of exposure in their occupation; this is an aggregated form of exposure assessment that can suffer from misclassification bias, although non-differential to disease. Since we only had information on the participants' current occupations, we cannot rule out the possibility of a "healthy worker effect". Lack of information about occupational history may be a limitation, especially in relation to the prevalence of COPD/chronic bronchitis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results discussion</title><p>Although asthma and COPD have many risk factors in common and often coexist in clinical settings, and there is some evidence that asthma may be a risk factor for the development of COPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>], they are distinct conditions, with differing clinical course and pathological features. Thus, inconsistencies between studies in the relation between air pollution and asthma/COPD could depend both on the presence of different competing risk factors, and on geographically different pollution mixtures acting on different regions of the respiratory tract. It is therefore important to consider local pollution characteristics as thoroughly as possible (tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T12">12</xref>). When using traffic intensity or self-reported traffic exposure as a proxy, there is a lack of knowledge of the exact pollution compounds that this exposure represents. One known characteristic of traffic-related pollution in the study region is a large amount of wear particles from road-tire interaction. These particles have been shown to be potent inducers of local inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>], and their levels are high in the Scandinavian countries due to the use of traction sand and studded tires.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T11"><label>Table 11</label><caption><p>Urban background. Descriptive data of regional air pollution at a monitoring station in Malm&#x000f6;. Annual mean concentrations of traffic-related pollutants measured at R&#x000e5;dhuset Malm&#x000f6; 1980&#x02013;2006. Data source: IVL Swedish Environmental Research Institute Ltd. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ivl.se/miljo/"/></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Year</td><td align="left">SO<sub>2 </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">NO<sub>2 </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">O<sub>3 </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">PM<sub>10 </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">PM<sub>2.5 </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1980*</td><td align="left">49</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1981</td><td align="left">50</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1982</td><td align="left">43</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1983</td><td align="left">33,1</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1984</td><td align="left">22,9</td><td align="left">42</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1985</td><td align="left">20,3</td><td align="left">39</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1986</td><td align="left">16,7</td><td align="left">31</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1987</td><td align="left">20,3</td><td align="left">32</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1988</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">30.5</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1989</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">26.9</td><td align="left">46</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1990</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">21.3</td><td align="left">39</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1991</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">19.6</td><td align="left">41</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1992</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">22.4</td><td align="left">43</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1993</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">25.6</td><td align="left">40</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1994</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">21.4</td><td align="left">43</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1995</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">50</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1996</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">24.6</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">17.4</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1997</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">26.2</td><td align="left">48</td><td align="left">17.6</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1998</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">21.8</td><td align="left">47</td><td align="left">15.2</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1999</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">23.5</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">15.8</td><td align="left">12.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2000</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">22.9</td><td align="left">49</td><td align="left">16.5</td><td align="left">13.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2001</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">21.1</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">18.7</td><td align="left">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2002</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">20.3</td><td align="left">52</td><td align="left">18.1</td><td align="left">11.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2003</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">20.8</td><td align="left">49</td><td align="left">21.6</td><td align="left">13.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2004</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">19.5</td><td align="left">54</td><td align="left">15.9</td><td align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2005</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">20.6</td><td align="left">49</td><td align="left">17.5</td><td align="left">11.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2006</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">19.3</td><td align="left">52</td><td align="left">18.2</td><td align="left">12.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T12"><label>Table 12</label><caption><p>Rural background. Descriptive data of regional air pollution at a monitoring station in a rural area. Annual mean concentrations of traffic-related pollutants measured at Vavihill 1985&#x02013;2006. Data source: IVL Swedish Environmental Research Institute Ltd. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ivl.se/miljo/"/></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Year</td><td align="left">SO<sub>2 </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">NO<sub>2 </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">O<sub>3' </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">PM<sub>10 </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td align="left">PM<sub>2.5 </sub>(&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1985</td><td align="left">5.14</td><td align="left">2.36</td><td align="left">60.2</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1986</td><td></td><td align="left">2.27</td><td align="left">59.9</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1987</td><td align="left">5.47</td><td align="left">2.11</td><td align="left">55.1</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1988</td><td align="left">3.90</td><td align="left">1.84</td><td align="left">57.7</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1989</td><td align="left">3.93</td><td align="left">2.66</td><td align="left">56.5</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1990</td><td align="left">2.98</td><td align="left">2.36</td><td align="left">55.0</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1991</td><td align="left">2.64</td><td align="left">2.08</td><td align="left">51.3</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1992</td><td align="left">2.06</td><td align="left">1.72</td><td align="left">56.0</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1993</td><td align="left">1.70</td><td align="left">1.98</td><td align="left">57.4</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1994</td><td align="left">1.17</td><td align="left">1.78</td><td align="left">58.6</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1995</td><td align="left">1.35</td><td align="left">1.92</td><td align="left">59.3</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1996</td><td align="left">1.31</td><td align="left">1.77</td><td align="left">63.0</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1997</td><td align="left">0.67</td><td align="left">2.05</td><td align="left">58.8</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1998</td><td align="left">0.74</td><td align="left">1.87</td><td align="left">54.6</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1999</td><td align="left">0.55</td><td align="left">1.66</td><td align="left">59.1</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2000</td><td align="left">0.45</td><td align="left">1.70</td><td align="left">57.6</td><td align="left">16.0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2001</td><td align="left">0.42</td><td align="left">1.37</td><td align="left">60.2</td><td align="left">15.4</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2002</td><td align="left">0.37</td><td align="left">1.39</td><td align="left">66.6</td><td align="left">16.3</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2003</td><td align="left">0.52</td><td align="left">1.54</td><td align="left">62.9</td><td align="left">18.6</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2004</td><td align="left">0.37</td><td align="left">1.48</td><td align="left">58.5</td><td align="left">13.8</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2005</td><td align="left">0.49</td><td align="left">1.47</td><td align="left">61.0</td><td align="left">15.2</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2006</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">1.59</td><td align="left">64.3</td><td align="left">17.3</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Although levels of traffic pollution in Sweden are lower than those found in most other countries, the results for asthma are basically supported by some European studies with higher exposure levels. An Italian study reported an association between symptom exaggeration of adult asthma and NO<sub>2 </sub>exposure levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], and the Swiss SAPALDIA study observed an increase of asthma-related symptoms, although not current asthma, in relation to NO<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. The European ECRHS study found a positive association between NO<sub>2 </sub>(modeled with a resolution of 1 km) and asthma incidence, but effect estimates seemed very heterogenous among the Swedish centers (although overall heterogeneity tested was non-significant). [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Most relevantly, a Swedish study found a non-significant tendency to increased asthma incidence among adults living close to traffic flows, and measured NO<sub>2 </sub>levels comparable to those found in the present study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Another study of asthma symptoms in Sweden found a significant but weak relation to NO<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>], although a stronger relation was found with self-reported measures of traffic. The findings in the present study, support the existence of a relation between exposure to traffic-related air pollution and asthma in adults at relatively low levels of traffic-related air pollution.</p><p>For COPD, a German study restricted to women found that COPD as defined by the GOLD criteria was 1.79 times more likely (95% CI 1.06&#x02013;3.02) for those living less than 100 m from a road with 10 000 cars/day, than for those living farther away [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. This is in agreement with our results, which found effects for living less than 100 m from a road with 6 cars/min (8 640 cars/day).</p><p>The European ECRHS study found that new onset of chronic bronchitis, as defined by chronic phlegm, was related among females to both self-reported traffic intensity (constant traffic vs. none, OR = 1.86; 95% CI 1.24 to 2.77) and home outdoor NO<sub>2 </sub>(OR = 50 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3 </sup>vs. 20 &#x003bc;g/m<sup>3 </sup>= 2.71; 95% CI 1.03 to 7.16) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. The higher levels of NO<sub>2 </sub>seen in the ECRHS study may partly stem from truly higher concentrations, but may also have been affected by the use of home outdoor measurements, which are better than our models at capturing locally high peak exposures. Other studies have suggested an effect modification for sex, with women being at higher risk, but this was not observed in our study. Our results did indicate effect modification by smoking, but tests for interaction were mainly non-significant. No interaction with smoking was found in any of the abovementioned studies of the effects of air pollution on prevalence/incidence of COPD in adults.</p><p>Overall, our results show that traffic-related air pollution is associated with the prevalence of COPD/chronic bronchitis in adults, but there is still a need for further investigation of the reasons behind the inconsistencies seen when the data were stratified by region.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Residential traffic is associated with both current symptoms and prevalence of diagnosis of asthma and COPD/chronic bronchitis, among adults in southern Sweden. This may indicate that traffic has not only short-term but also long-term effects on adult chronic respiratory disease, even in a region with low overall levels of traffic pollution.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>AL: Conducted the statistical analyses and wrote the main part of the manuscript. ES: Performed GIS analyses and wrote part of the manuscript. PM: Designed and conducted the survey and made revisions on drafts. UN: Designed and conducted the survey and made revisions on drafts. KJ: Designed the study and made revisions on drafts. AA: Wrote part of the manuscript and made major revisions of drafts. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to acknowledge Susanna Gustafsson and H&#x000e5;kan Tinnerberg, for providing valuable comments. Hans Kromhout provided the ALOHA job-exposure matrix. The study was supported by grants from the Swedish Environmental Protection Agency, the Swedish Emission Research Program, and the Faculty of Medicine at Lund University.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halonen</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yli-Tuomi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulmala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiittanen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pekkanen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urban Air Pollution And Asthma And Copd Hospital Emergency Room Visits</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2008</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18267984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2007.091371</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smorodinsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoats</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipsett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Residential traffic and children's respiratory health</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2008</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>1274</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18795175</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Vliet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Meliefste</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koopman</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Neijens</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerritsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerkhof</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellander</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunekreef</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution from traffic and the development of respiratory infections and asthmatic and allergic symptoms in children</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>1092</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12379553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200108-007OC</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Zutavern</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cyrys</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockow</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Koletzko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhardt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wichmann</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory health and individual estimated exposure to traffic-related air pollutants in a cohort of young children</article-title><source>Occup Environ Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16912084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oem.2006.028241</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jongste</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerritsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerkhof</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunekreef</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution and development of asthma, allergy and infections in a birth cohort</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2007</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>879</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17251230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00083406</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Zutavern</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cyrys</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockow</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Koletzko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000e4;mer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Behrendt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbarth</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>von Berg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wichmann</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><collab>GINI Study Group; LISA Study Group</collab></person-group><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>1331</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18337595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200701-036OC</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jerrett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shankardass</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Berhane</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauderman</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;nzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Avol</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lurmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Molitor</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Molitor</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McConnell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traffic-related air pollution and asthma onset in children: a prospective cohort study with individual exposure measurement</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2008</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>1433</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18941591</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gauderman</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vora</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>McConnell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Berhane</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lurmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Avol</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerrett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of exposure to traffic on lung development from 10 to 18 years of age: a cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2007</year><volume>369</volume><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17307103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)60037-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oftedal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunekreef</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nystad</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nafstad</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Residential outdoor air pollution and lung function in schoolchildren</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18091005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viegi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Maio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldacci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: health effects of air pollution</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16916323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2006.00886.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Modig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000e4;rvholm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;nnmark</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nystr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundb&#x000e4;ck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vehicle exhaust exposure in an incident case-control study of adult asthma</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2006</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16540504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.06.00071505</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Marco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Poli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Accordini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Giammanco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bugiani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Villani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponzio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bono</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavallini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cazzoletti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dallari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginesu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauriola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandrioli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Perfetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pignato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirina</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Struzzo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><collab>ISAYA study group</collab></person-group><article-title>Italian Study on Asthma in Young Adults, The impact of climate and traffic-related NO2 on the prevalence of asthma and allergic rhinitis in Italy</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>2002</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12372117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2745.2002.01466.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cesaroni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Badaloni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Porta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Forastiere</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Perucci</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison between several indices of exposure to traffic-related air pollution and their respiratory health impact in adults</article-title><source>Occup Environ Med</source><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18203803</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montn&#x000e9;mery</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindholm</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f6;fdahl</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of obstructive lung diseases and respiratory symptoms in relation to living environment and socio-economic group</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11575896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/rmed.2001.1129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacquemin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilera</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Esteban</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;tschi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000e4;rvholm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vienneau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;nzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Home Outdoor NO2 and New Onset of Self-Reported Asthma in Adults</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>2008</year><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Topp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Thefeld</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traffic at residential address, respiratory health, and atopy in adults: the National German Health Survey 1998</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15820731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2004.08.004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun-Fahrl&#x000e4;nder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;nzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackermann-Liebrich</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Perruchoud</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Leuenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000fc;thrich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to motor vehicle traffic and allergic sensitization. The Swiss Study on Air Pollution and Lung Diseases in Adults (SAPALDIA) Team</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10874554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001648-200007000-00015</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zemp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsasser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;nzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Perruchoud</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Domenighetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Medici</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackermann-Liebrich</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Leuenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Monn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolognini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongard</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000e4;ndli</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Karrer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;ni</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschopp</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Villiger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zellweger</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term ambient air pollution and respiratory symptoms in adults (SAPALDIA study). The SAPALDIA Team</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>1257</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10194174</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schikowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranft</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wichmann</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000e4;mer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term air pollution exposure and living close to busy roads are associated with COPD in women</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>152</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16372913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1465-9921-6-152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sunyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotschi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Esteban</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquemin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilera</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>de Marco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gislason</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Norb&#x000e4;ck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Villani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;nzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic bronchitis and urban air pollution in an international study</article-title><source>Occup Environ Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16847030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oem.2006.027995</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forastiere</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Galassi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self report and GIS based modelling as indicators of air pollution exposure: is there a gold standard?</article-title><source>Occup Environ Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16046601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oem.2005.020560</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing the spatial extent of mobile source air pollution impacts: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>89</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17519039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-7-89</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Greig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Drye</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal and Spatial Variations in Nitrogen Dioxide Concentrations Across an Urban Landscape: Cambridge, UK</article-title><source>Environmental Monitoring and Assessment</source><year>1998</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1005856916308</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salam</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent evidence for adverse effects of residential proximity to traffic sources on asthma</article-title><source>Curr Opin Pulm Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18043269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCP.0b013e3282f1987a</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uppbyggnad och validering av emissionsdatabas avseende luftf&#x000f6;roreningar f&#x000f6;r Sk&#x000e5;ne med bas&#x000e5;r 2001 [A geographical and temporal high resolution emission database for dispersion modelling of environmental NOX in Southern Sweden.]</article-title><source>The Department of Physical Geography and Ecosystem Analysis In Swedish, english summary</source><year>2007</year><publisher-name>Lund University: Lund</publisher-name><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.med.lu.se/content/download/27330/192790/file/Susanna_Gustafsson_lic.pdf"/></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tager</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term health effects of particulate and other ambient air pollution: research can progress faster if we want it to</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2000</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>915</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11049809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3435048</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stroh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Oudin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilesj&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Str&#x000f6;mberg</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are associations between socio-economic characteristics and exposure to air pollution a question of study area size? An example from Scania, Sweden</article-title><source>Int J Health Geogr</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16288656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-072X-4-30</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="other"><source>Sj&#x000f6;berg, Luftkvalitet i t&#x000e4;torter 2005 IVL [Swedish Environmental Research Institute]: Stockholm</source><year>2006</year></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nihl&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Montn&#x000e9;mery</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f6;fdahl</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Greiff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specific nasal symptoms and symptom-provoking factors may predict increased risk of developing COPD</article-title><source>Clin Physiol Funct Imaging</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18331572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1475-097X.2008.00800.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>V&#x000e4;gverket, NVDB Nationell v&#x000e4;gdatabas [The Swedish national road database]</article-title><year>2007</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vv.se/nvdb/"/></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stroh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>The use of GIS in Exposure-Response Studies, in The Department of Physical Geography and Ecosystem Analysis</source><year>2006</year><publisher-name>Lund University: Lund</publisher-name><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.med.lu.se/content/download/27331/192793/file/Emilie_Stroh_lic.pdf"/></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Statistics-Sweden, The Socio-economic Classification of Occupation. Stockholm</article-title><year>1982</year></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Benke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kromhout</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermeulen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological dust exposure in the workplace is a risk factor for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2005</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16061705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2004.035170</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names/></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling and variable selection in epidemiologic analysis</article-title><source>American Journal of Public Health</source><year>1989</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2916724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.79.3.340</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SL-JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Keidel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Heldstab</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fb;nzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer-Oglesby</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackermann-Liebrich</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><collab>the SAPALDIA team</collab></person-group><article-title>Characterization of Source-Specific Air Pollution Exposure for a Large Population-Based Swiss Cohort (SAPALDIA)</article-title><source>Environmental Health Perspectives</source><year>2007</year><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunekreef</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Hartog</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harssema</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Knape</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Vliet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution from truck traffic and lung function in children living near motorways</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>1997</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9115026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001648-199705000-00012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berhane</surname><given-names>KGW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stram</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical Issues in Strudies of the Long-Term Effects of Air Pollution: The Southern California Children's Health Study</article-title><source>Statistical Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/088342304000000413</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Eiguren-Fernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Miguel</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In-cabin commuter exposure to ultrafine particles on Los Angeles freeways</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><year>2007</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>2138</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17438754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es0618797</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Statistics-Sweden</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scb.se/Pages/TableAndChart____23020.aspx"/></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mannino</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global burden of COPD: risk factors, prevalence, and future trends</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2007</year><volume>370</volume><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17765526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)61380-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindbom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blomqvist</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gudmundsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Swietlicki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljungman</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wear particles generated from studded tires and pavement induces inflammatory reactions in mouse macrophage cells</article-title><source>Chem Res Toxicol</source><year>2007</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17516662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/tx700018z</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blomqvist</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gudmundsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Swietlicki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohgard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindbom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljungman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Properties and toxicological effects of particles from the interaction between tyres, road pavement and winter traction material</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>2008</year><volume>393</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18258284</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayer-Oglesby</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazenkamp-von Arx</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun-Fahrl&#x000e4;nder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Keidel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;nzli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Braendli</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Burdet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sally Liu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leuenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackermann-Liebrich</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><collab>SAPALDIA Team</collab></person-group><article-title>Living near main streets and respiratory symptoms in adults: the Swiss Cohort Study on Air Pollution and Lung Diseases in Adults</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwj338</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Modig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perceived annoyance and asthmatic symptoms in relation to vehicle exhaust levels outside home: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Environ Health</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>29</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17903240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-069X-6-29</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>